<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>

    <rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-oauth-assertions-03" ipr="trust200902">

    <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <front>
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Assertion Profile</title>

    <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." role="editor"
            surname="Mortimore">
      <organization abbrev="Salesforce">Salesforce.com</organization>

      <address>
        <email>cmortimore@salesforce.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael B. Jones" initials="M.B." surname="Jones">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>

      <address>
        <email>mbj@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brian Campbell" initials="B." surname="Campbell">
      <organization abbrev="Ping">Ping Identity Corp.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>brian.d.campbell@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yaron Y. Goland" initials="Y.Y." surname="Goland">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">Microsoft</organization>

      <address>
        <email>yarong@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="2" month="May" year="2012" />


	        <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

	        <area>Internet</area>

	        <workgroup>&nbsp;</workgroup> 

	        <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
	IETF is fine for individual submissions.
	If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
	which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

	        <keyword>OAuth</keyword>
	        <keyword>SAML</keyword>
	        <keyword>Assertion</keyword>



    <abstract>
      <t>This specification provides a general framework for the use of
      assertions as client credentials and/or authorization grants with OAuth
      2.0. It includes a generic mechanism for transporting assertions during
      interactions with a token endpoint, as wells as rules for the content
      and processing of those assertions. The intent is to provide an enhanced
      security profile by using derived values such as signatures or HMACs, as
      well as facilitate the use of OAuth 2.0 in client-server integration
      scenarios where the end-user may not be present.</t>

      <t>This specification only defines abstract message flow and assertion
      content. Actual use requires implementation of a companion protocol
      binding specification. Additional profile documents provide standard
      representations in formats such as SAML and JWT.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="rnc" title="Requirements Notation and Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref> .</t>

      <t>Throughout this document, values are quoted to indicate that they are
      to be taken literally. When using these values in protocol messages, the
      quotes MUST NOT be used as part of the value.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Protocol
      </xref> provides a method for making authenticated HTTP requests to a
      resource using an access token. Access tokens are issued to clients by
      an authorization server with the (sometimes implicit) approval of the
      resource owner. These access tokens are typically obtained by exchanging
      an authorization grant representing authorization by the resource owner
      or privileged administrator. Several authorization grant types are
      defined to support a wide range of client types and user experiences.
      OAuth also allows for the definition of new extension grant types to
      support additional clients or to provide a bridge between OAuth and
      other trust frameworks. Finally, OAuth allows the definition of
      additional authentication mechanisms to be used by clients when
      interacting with the authorization server.</t>

      <t>In scenarios where security is at a premium one wants to avoid
      sending secrets across the Internet, even on encrypted connections.
      Instead one wants to send values derived from the secret that prove to
      the receiver that the sender is in possession of the secret without
      actually sending the secret. Typically the way derived values are
      created is by generating an assertion that is then either HMAC&rsquo;ed
      or digitally signed using an agreed upon secret. By validating the HMAC
      or digital signature on the assertion, the receiver can prove to
      themselves that the entity that generated the assertion was in
      possession of the secret without actually communicating the secret
      directly.</t>

      <t>This specification provides a general framework for the use of
      assertions as client credentials and/or authorization grants with OAuth
      2.0. It includes a generic mechanism for transporting assertions during
      interactions with a token endpoint, as wells as rules for the content
      and processing of those assertions. The intent is to provide an enhanced
      security profile by using derived values such as signatures or HMACs, as
      well as facilitate the use of OAuth 2.0 in client-server integration
      scenarios where the end-user may not be present.</t>

      <t>This specification only defines abstract message flow and assertion
      content. Actual use requires implementation of a companion protocol
      binding specification. Additional profile documents provide standard
      representations in formats such as SAML and JWT.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Authentication vs. Authorization">
      <t>This specification provides a model for using assertions for
      authentication of an OAuth client during interactions with an
      Authorization Server, as well as the use of assertions as authorization
      grants. It is important to note that the use of assertions for client
      authentication is orthogonal and separable from using assertions as an
      authorization grant and can be used either in combination or in
      isolation. In addition, in scenarios when assertion based authentication
      and authorization are used in combination, the assertion format and
      processing may be redundant; under such circumstances, the protocol may
      be optimized to present a single assertion.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transporting Assertions" anchor="transporting">
      <t>This section defines generic HTTP parameters for transporting
      assertions during interactions with a token endpoint.</t>

      <section title="Using Assertions for Client Authentication" anchor="clientauth">
        <t>In scenarios where one wants to avoid sending secrets, one wants to
        send values derived from the secret that prove to the receiver that
        the sender is in possession of the secret without actually sending the
        secret.</t>

        <t>For example, a client can establish a secret using an out-of-band
        mechanism with a resource server. As part of this out-of-band
        communication the client and resource server agree that the client
        will authenticate itself using an assertion with agreed upon
        parameters that will be signed by the provisioned secret. Later on,
        the client might send an access token request to the token endpoint
        for the resource server that includes an authorization code, as well
        as a <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx> that is signed with the previously agreed key
        and parameters. The <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx> proves to the token endpoint the
        identity of the client and the authorization code provides the link to
        the end-user authorization.</t>

        <t>The following section defines the use of assertions as client
        credentials as an extension of Section 2.3 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>. When using
        assertions as client credentials, the client includes the assertion
        and related information using the following HTTP request parameters:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="client_id">OPTIONAL. The client identifier as
            described in Section 2.2 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth
            2.0</xref>. When present, the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx> MUST identify the client to the authorization server.</t>

            <t hangText="client_assertion_type">REQUIRED. The format of the
            assertion as defined by the authorization server. The value MUST
            be an absolute URI.</t>

            <t hangText="client_assertion">REQUIRED. The assertion being used
            to authenticate the client. Specific serialization of the
            assertion is defined by profile documents. The serialization MUST
            be encoded for transport within HTTP forms. It is RECOMMENDED that
            base64url be used.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following non-normative example demonstrates a client
        authenticating using an assertion during an Authorization Code Access
        Token Request as defined in Section 4.1.3 of
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>
	(with line breaks for display purposes only):</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[POST /token HTTP/1.1 
Host: server.example.com 
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

grant_type=authorization_code&
code=i1WsRn1uB1&
client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&
client_assertion_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth
%3Aclient-assertion-type%3Asaml2-bearer&
client_assertion=PHNhbW...[omitted for brevity]...ZT]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Token endpoints can differentiate between assertion based
      credentials and other client credential types by looking for the
      presence of the <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx> and
      <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx> parameters,
      which will only be present when using assertions for client
      authentication.</t>




       <section title="Error Responses">


      <t>If an assertion is invalid for any reason or if more than one client authentication mechanism is used, the Authorization
      Server MUST construct an error response as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>. The value of the <spanx style='verb'>error</spanx>
      parameter MUST be the <spanx style='verb'>invalid_client</spanx> error code. The
      authorization server MAY include additional information regarding the
      reasons the client assertion was considered invalid using the <spanx style='verb'>error_description</spanx>
      or <spanx style='verb'>error_uri</spanx> parameters.</t>

      <t>For example:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 400 Bad Request
Content-Type: application/json
Cache-Control: no-store

{
  "error":"invalid_client"
  "error_description":"Multiple Credentials Not Allowed"
}]]></artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>

      </section>

      <section title="Using Assertions as Authorization Grants" anchor="authgrants">
        <t>An assertion can be used to request an access token when a client
        wishes to utilize an existing trust relationship. This may be done
        through the semantics of (and a digital signature/HMAC calculated
        over) the assertion, and expressed to the authorization server
 		through an extension authorization grant type.
        The processes by which authorization is previously granted, and by
        which the client obtains the assertion prior to exchanging it with the
        authorization server, are out of scope.</t>

        <t>The following defines the use of assertions as authorization grants
        as an extension of <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>,
        Section 4.5. When using assertions as authorization grants, the client
        includes the assertion and related information using the following HTTP request
        parameters:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="grant_type">REQUIRED. The format of the assertion as
            defined by the authorization server. The value MUST be an absolute
            URI.</t>

            <t hangText="assertion">REQUIRED. The assertion being used as an
            authorization grant. Specific serialization of the assertion is
            defined by profile documents. The serialization MUST be encoded
            for transport within HTTP forms. It is RECOMMENDED that base64url
            be used.</t>

            <t hangText="scope">OPTIONAL. The requested scope as
            described in Section 3.3 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth
            2.0</xref>. When
            exchanging assertions for access tokens, the authorization for the
            token has been previously granted through some other mechanism. As
            such, the requested scope SHOULD be equal or lesser than the scope
            originally granted to the authorized accessor. If the scope
            parameter and/or value is omitted, the scope SHOULD be treated as
            equal to the scope originally granted to the authorized accessor.
            The Authorization Server SHOULD limit the scope of the issued
            access token to be equal or lesser than the scope originally
            granted to the authorized accessor.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following non-normative example demonstrates an assertion being
        used as an authorization grant
	(with line breaks for display purposes only):</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[POST /token HTTP/1.1 
Host: server.example.com 
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&
grant_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth%3Agrant-type%3Asaml2-bearer&
assertion=PHNhbWxwOl...[omitted for brevity]...ZT4]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>An assertion used in this context is generally a short lived representation
          of the authorization grant and authorization servers SHOULD NOT issue tokens
          that exceed that lifetime by a significant period. In practice, that will
          usually mean that refresh tokens are not issued in response to assertion
          grant requests and access tokens will be issued with a reasonably limited lifetime.
          Clients can refresh an expired access token by requesting a new one using the same
          assertion, if it is still valid, or with a new assertion.
        </t>

        <section title="Error Responses">
            <t>If an assertion is not valid or has expired, the Authorization Server
          MUST construct an error response as defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>. The value of the <spanx style='verb'>error</spanx>
          parameter MUST be the <spanx style='verb'>invalid_grant</spanx> error code. The authorization
          server MAY include additional information regarding the reasons the
          assertion was considered invalid using the <spanx style='verb'>error_description</spanx> or
          <spanx style='verb'>error_uri</spanx> parameters.</t>


      <t>For example:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 400 Bad Request
Content-Type: application/json
Cache-Control: no-store

{
  "error":"invalid_grant",
  "error_description":"Audience validation failed"
}]]></artwork>
      </figure>

             </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Assertion Content and Processing" anchor="contentprocessing">
      <t>This section provides a general content and processing model for the
      use of assertions in <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth
      2.0</xref>.</t>

      <section title="Assertion Metamodel">
        <t>The following are entities and metadata involved in the issuance,
        exchange and processing of assertions in OAuth 2.0. These are general
        terms, abstract from any particular assertion format. Mappings of
        these terms into specific representations are provided by profiles of
        this specification.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Issuer">The unique identifier for the entity that
            issued the assertion. Generally this is the entity that holds the
            keying material used to generate the assertion. In some use cases
            Issuers may be either OAuth Clients (when assertions are
            self-asserted) or a Security Token Service (STS) (an entity capable of
            issuing, renewing, transforming and validating of security
            tokens).</t>

            <t hangText="Principal">A unique identifier for the subject of the
            assertion. When using assertions for client authentication, the
            Principal SHOULD be the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx> of the OAuth client. When using
            assertions as an authorization grant, the Principal MUST identify
            an authorized accessor for whom the access token is being
            requested (typically the resource owner, or an authorized
            delegate).</t>

            <t hangText="Audience">A URI that identifies the party intended to 
			      process the assertion.  The audience SHOULD be the URL of
            the Token Endpoint as defined in Section 3.2 of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>.</t>

            <t hangText="Issued At ">The time at which the assertion was
            issued. While the serialization may differ by assertion format,
            this is always expressed in UTC with no time zone component.</t>

            <t hangText="Expires At ">The time at which the assertion expires.
            While the serialization may differ by assertion format, this is
            always expressed in UTC with no time zone component.</t>

            <t hangText="Assertion ID">A nonce or unique identifier for the
            assertion. The Assertion ID may be used by implementations
            requiring message de-duplication for one-time use assertions. Any
            entity that assigns an identifier MUST ensure that there is
            negligible probability that that entity or any other entity will
            accidentally assign the same identifier to a different data
            object.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="General Assertion Format and Processing Rules">
        <t>The following are general format and processing rules for the use
        of assertions in OAuth:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The assertion MUST contain an Issuer. The Issuer MUST identify
            the entity that issued the assertion as recognized by the
            Authorization Server. If an assertion is self-asserted, the Issuer
            SHOULD be the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>.</t>

            <t>The assertion SHOULD contain a Principal. The Principal MUST
            identify an authorized accessor for whom the access token is being
            requested (typically the resource owner, or an authorized
            delegate).  When the client is acting on behalf of itself, the
            Principal SHOULD be the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>.</t>

            <t>The assertion MUST contain an Audience that identifies the
            Authorization Server as the intended audience. The Authorization
            Server MUST verify that it is an intended audience for the
            assertion. The Audience SHOULD be the URL of the Authorization
            Server's Token Endpoint.</t>

            <t>The assertion MUST contain an Expires At entity that limits the
            time window during which the assertion can be used. The
            authorization server MUST verify that the expiration time has not
            passed, subject to allowable clock skew between systems. The
            authorization server SHOULD reject assertions with an Expires At
            attribute value that is unreasonably far in the future.</t>

            <t>The assertion MAY contain an Issued At entity containing the
            UTC time at which the assertion was issued.</t>

            <t>The assertion MAY contain an Assertion ID. An Authorization
            Server MAY dictate that Assertion ID is mandatory.</t>

            <t>The Authorization Server MUST validate the assertion's signature
            in order to verify the Issuer of the assertion. The algorithm used to validate the
            assertion, and the mechanism for designating the secret used to
            generate the assertion, are beyond the scope of this specification.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Specific Assertion Format and Processing Rules">
      <t>The following clarifies the format and processing rules defined in
      <xref target="transporting" /> and <xref target="contentprocessing" />
      for a number of common use cases:</t>

      <section title="Client Authentication">
        <t>When a client authenticates to a token service using an assertion,
        it SHOULD do so according to <xref target="clientauth" />. The following format and
        processing rules apply.<list style="symbols">

            <t>The <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx> HTTP parameter MUST identify the
            assertion format being used for authentication.</t>

            <t>The <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx> HTTP parameter MUST contain the serialized
            assertion in a format indicated by the <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx>
            parameter.</t>

            <t>The Principal SHOULD be the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>.</t>

            <t>The Issuer of the assertion MUST identify the entity that issued
               the assertion as recognized by the Authorization Server.  If the
               assertion is self-asserted, the Issuer SHOULD be the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>.</t> 

            <t>The Audience of the assertion MUST identify the Authorization
            Server and SHOULD be the URL of the Token Endpoint.</t>

            <t>The Authorization Server MUST validate the assertion's signature in order to verify the Issuer of the assertion.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following non-normative example demonstrates the use of a
        client authentication using an assertion during an Authorization Code
        Access Token Request as defined in Section 4.1.3 of
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>
	(with line breaks for display purposes only):</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[POST /token HTTP/1.1 
Host: server.example.com 
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

grant_type=authorization_code&
code=i1WsRn1uB1&
client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&
client_assertion_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth
%3Aclient-assertion-type%3Asaml2-bearer&
client_assertion=PHNhb...[omitted for brevity]...ZT4]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Client Acting on Behalf of Itself">
        <t>When a client is accessing resources on behalf of itself, it SHOULD
        do so in a manner analogous to the Client Credentials flow defined in
        Section 4.4 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>. This
        is a special case that combines both the authentication and
        authorization grant usage patterns. In this case, the interactions
        with the authorization server SHOULD be treated as using an assertion
        for Client Authentication according to <xref target="clientauth" />, with the addition
        of a grant_type parameter. The following format and processing rules
        apply.<list style="symbols">

            <t>The grant_type HTTP request parameter MUST be
            <spanx style='verb'>client_credentials</spanx>.</t>

            <t>The <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx> HTTP parameter MUST identify the
            assertion format.</t>

            <t>The <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx> HTTP parameter MUST contain the serialized
            assertion as in a format indicated by the <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx>
            parameter.</t>

            <t>The Issuer of the assertion MUST identify the entity that
            issued the assertion as recognized by the Authorization Server. If
            the assertion is self-asserted, the Issuer SHOULD be the
            <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>. If the assertion was issued by a Security Token
            Service (STS), the Issuer SHOULD identify the STS as recognized by the
            Authorization Server.</t>

            <t>The Principal SHOULD be the <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>.</t>

            <t>The Audience of the assertion MUST identify the Authorization
            Server and SHOULD be the URL of the Token Endpoint.</t>

            <t>The Authorization Server MUST validate the assertion's signature in order to verify the Issuer of the assertion.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following non-normative example demonstrates the use of a
        sample assertion being used for a Client Credentials Access Token
        Request as defined in Section 4.4.2 of
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>
	(with line breaks for display purposes only):</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[POST /token HTTP/1.1 
Host: server.example.com 
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&
grant_type=client_credentials&
client_assertion_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth
%3Aclient-assertion-type%3Asaml2-bearer&
client_assertion=PHNhbW...[omitted for brevity]...ZT]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Client Acting on Behalf of a User ">
        <t>When a client is accessing resources on behalf of a user, it SHOULD
        be treated as using an assertion as an Authorization Grant according
        to <xref target="authgrants" />. The following format and processing rules apply.<list style="symbols">

            <t>The grant_type HTTP request parameter MUST indicate the
            assertion format.</t>

            <t>The assertion HTTP parameter MUST contain the serialized
            assertion as in a format indicated by the grant_type
            parameter.</t>

            <t>The Issuer of the assertion MUST identify the entity that
            issued the assertion as recognized by the Authorization Server. If
            the assertion is self-asserted, the Issuer SHOULD be the
            <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>. If the assertion was issued by a
	    Security Token Service (STS), the Issuer SHOULD
            identify the STS as recognized by the Authorization Server.</t>

            <t>The Principal MUST identify an authorized accessor for whom the
            access token is being requested (typically the resource owner, or
            an authorized delegate).</t>

            <t>The Audience of the assertion MUST identify the Authorization
            Server and MAY be the URL of the Token Endpoint.</t>

            <t>The Authorization Server MUST validate the assertion's signature in order to verify the Issuer of the assertion.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following non-normative example demonstrates the use of a
        client authenticating using an assertion during an Authorization Code
        Access Token Request as defined in Section 4.1.3 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>
	(with line breaks for display purposes only):</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[POST /token HTTP/1.1 
Host: server.example.com 
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&
grant_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth%3Agrant-type%3Asaml2-bearer&
assertion=PHNhbWxwOl...[omitted for brevity]...ZT]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Client Acting on Behalf of an Anonymous User">
        <t>When a client is accessing resources on behalf of an anonymous
        user, the following format and processing rules apply.<list style="symbols">

            <t>The grant_type HTTP request parameter MUST indicate the
            assertion format.</t>

            <t>The assertion HTTP parameter MUST contain the serialized
            assertion as in a format indicated by the grant_type
            parameter.</t>

            <t>The Issuer of the assertion MUST identify the entity that
            issued the assertion as recognized by the Authorization Server. If
            the assertion is self-asserted, the Issuer SHOULD be the
            <spanx style='verb'>client_id</spanx>. If the assertion was issued by a Security Token
            Service (STS), the Issuer SHOULD identify the STS as recognized by the
            Authorization Server.</t>

            <t>The Principal SHOULD indicate to the Authorization Server that
            the client is acting on-behalf of an anonymous user as defined by
            the Authorization Server. It is implied that authorization is based
            upon additional criteria, such as additional attributes or claims
            provided in the assertion. For example, a client may present an
            assertion from a trusted issuer asserting that the bearer is over
            18 via an included claim. In this case, no additional information
            about the user's identity is included yet all the data needed to
            issue an access token is present.</t>

            <t>The Audience of the assertion MUST identify the Authorization
            Server and MAY be the URL of the Token Endpoint.</t>

            <t>The Authorization Server MUST validate the assertion's signature in order to verify the Issuer of the assertion.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>Authorization Providers concerned with preventing replay attacks may choose to implement using replay detection using a combination of the Assertion ID and Issued At/Expires At attributes.  Previously processed assertions MAY be de-duped and rejected based on the Assertion ID.  The addition of the validity window relieves the authorization server from maintaining an infinite state table of processed assertion IDs.</t>

      <t>Authorization Servers SHOULD consider the amount of information exposed in error responses, and the risk associated with exposing details of specific processing errors.   In addition, Authorization Servers SHOULD prevent timing attacks related to cryptographic processing of the assertion.</t>

      <t>There are no additional security considerations beyond those described within
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">OAuth 2.0</xref>, Section 11.</t>

    </section>


	        <section title='IANA Considerations'>
	          <section title='assertion Parameter Registration'>
	            <t>
	              The following is the parameter registration request, as
	defined in The OAuth Parameters Registry of <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">The OAuth 2.0 Authorization
	Protocol</xref>, for the
	              <spanx style='verb'>assertion</spanx> parameter:

	              <list style='symbols'>
	                <t>Parameter name: assertion</t>
	                <t>Parameter usage location: client authentication, token request
	                </t>
	                <t>Change controller: IETF</t>
	                <t>Specification document(s): [[this document]]</t>
	              </list>
	            </t>
	          </section>
	
	          <section title='client_assertion Parameter Registration'>
	            <t>
	              The following is the parameter registration request, as
	defined in The OAuth Parameters Registry of <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">The OAuth 2.0 Authorization
	Protocol</xref>, for the
	              <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx> parameter:

	              <list style='symbols'>
	                <t>Parameter name: <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion</spanx></t>
	                <t>Parameter usage location: client authentication, token request
	                </t>
	                <t>Change controller: IETF</t>
	                <t>Specification document(s): [[this document]]</t>
	              </list>
	            </t>
	          </section>
	
	          <section title='client_assertion_type Parameter Registration'>
	            <t>
	              The following is the parameter registration request, as
	defined in The OAuth Parameters Registry of <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2">The OAuth 2.0 Authorization
	Protocol</xref>, for the
	              <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx> parameter:

	              <list style='symbols'>
	                <t>Parameter name: <spanx style='verb'>client_assertion_type</spanx></t>
	                <t>Parameter usage location: client authentication, token request
	                </t>
	                <t>Change controller: IETF</t>
	                <t>Specification document(s): [[this document]]</t>
	              </list>
	            </t>
	          </section>

	        </section>

  </middle>

  <back>                                                                                        
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-oauth-v2-26.xml' ?>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors wish to thank the following people that have influenced
      or contributed this specification: Paul Madsen, Eric Sachs, Jian Cai,
      Tony Nadalin, the authors of OAuth WRAP, and those in the OAuth working group.</t>
    </section>

    <section title='Document History'>
      <t>
	[[ to be removed by RFC editor before publication as an RFC ]]
      </t>
       <t>
        draft-ietf-oauth-assertions-03
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>updated reference to draft-ietf-oauth-v2 from -25 to -26</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
	draft-ietf-oauth-assertions-02
	<list style='symbols'>
	  <t>Added text about limited lifetime ATs and RTs per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08298.html.</t>
	  <t>Changed the line breaks in some examples to avoid awkward rendering to text format. Also removed encoded '=' padding from a few examples because both known derivative specs, SAML and JWT, omit the padding char in serialization/encoding.</t>
	  <t>Remove section 7 on error responses and move that (somewhat modified) content into subsections of section 4 broken up by authn/authz per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08735.html.</t>
	  <t>Rework the text about "MUST validate ... in order to establish a mapping between ..." per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08872.html and http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08749.html.</t>
	  <t>Change "The Principal MUST identify an authorized accessor.  If the
	  assertion is self-issued, the Principal SHOULD be the client_id" in 6.1 per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08873.html.</t>
	  <t>Update reference in 4.1 to point to 2.3 (rather than 3.2) of oauth-v2 (rather than self) http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08874.html.</t>
	  <t>Move the "Section 3 of" out of the xref to hopefully fix the link in 4.1 and remove the client_id bullet from 4.2 per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08875.html.</t>
	  <t>Add ref to Section 3.3 of oauth-v2 for scope definition and remove some then redundant text per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08890.html.</t>
	  <t>Change "The following format and processing rules SHOULD be applied" to "The following format and processing rules apply" in sections 6.x to remove conflicting normative qualification of other normative statements per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08892.html.</t>
	  <t>Add text the client_id must id the client to 4.1 and remove similar text from other places per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08893.html.</t>
	  <t>Remove the MUST from the text prior to the HTTP parameter definitions per http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/oauth/current/msg08920.html.</t>
	  <t>Updated examples to use grant_type and client_assertion_type values from the OAuth SAML Assertion Profiles spec.</t>
	</list>
      </t>

    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
