<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5012   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5012.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6442 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6442.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5962 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5962.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5491 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5491.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3841   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3841.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5069   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5069.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5031   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4119   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4119.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-trustworthy-location PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-trustworthy-location.xml">
]>

<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?> 
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-rosen-ecrit-ecall-07.txt">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IP-based In-Vehicle Emergency Call">Internet Protocol-based In-Vehicle Emergency Call</title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Rosen" fullname="Brian Rosen">
      <organization>NeuStar, Inc. </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>470 Conrad Dr</street>
          <city>Mars</city>
          <region> PA </region>
          <code>16046 </code>
          <country>US </country>
        </postal>
        <phone> </phone>
        <email>br@brianrosen.net
        </email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Gellens" fullname="Randall Gellens">
      <organization>QUALCOMM Incorporated</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5775 Morehouse Drive</street>
          <city>San Diego</city>
          <code>92651</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>rg+ietf@qualcomm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2012"/>
    <area>Real-Time Applications and Infrastructure</area>
    <workgroup>ECRIT</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes how to use a subset of the IETF-based emergency call framework for
        accomplishing emergency calling support in vehicles. Simplifications are possible due to the
        nature of the functionality that is going to be provided in vehicles with the usage of GPS.
        Additionally, further profiling needs to be done regarding the encoding of location
        information.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Emergency calls made from vehicles can assist with the objective of significantly reducing
        road deaths and injuries. Unfortunately, drivers often have a poor location-awareness,
        especially on urban roads (also during night) and abroad. In the most crucial cases, the
        victim(s) may not be able to call because they have been injured or trapped.</t>

      <t>In Europe the European Commission has launched the eCall initiative that may best be
        described as a user initiated or automatically triggered system to provide notifications to
        Public Safety Answering Point's (PSAP), by means of cellular communications, that a vehicle
        has crashed, and to provide geodetic location information and where possible a voice channel
        to the PSAP. At the time of writing the suppor for eCall are focused on legacy technology.
         This document details how emergency calls triggered by vehicles can be accomplished in an Internet Protocol-based environment. </t>

      <t>This document is organized as follows: <xref target="terminology"/> defines the
        terminology, <xref target="protocol-profile"/> illustrates the required protocol
        functionality, <xref target="data-profile"/> indicates the required data that has to be
        transmitted within a PIDF-LO and <xref target="example"/> shows an example message exchange.
        This document concludes with the security considerations in <xref target="security"/> and
        IANA considerations in <xref target="iana"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
      <t>This document re-uses a lot of the terminology defined in Section 3 of <xref
          target="RFC5012"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="protocol-profile" title="Protocol Profile">
      <t>The usage of in-vehicular emergency calls does not require the usage of a Location
        Configuration Protocol since GPS is used. Furthermore, since the GPS receiver is permanently
        turned on it can even provide useful information in cases where the car entered a tunnel.
        Consequently, there is no need to discover any Location Information Server (LIS).</t>

      <t>Since the emergency call within the car is either triggered by a button or, in most cases,
        automatically thanks to sensors mounted in the car there is no need to learn a dial string.
        This document registers a separate service URN, namely 'urn:service:sos.ecall', used
        specifically for emergency calls that are initiated from vehicles. This URN comes with two sub-services to indicate how the emergency call was triggered, namely 'automatic' for cases when the emergency call was triggered due to a crash automatically without any user involvement and 'manual' for cases where a driver or a passenger triggered the emergency call. If the device initiating the emergency call does not allow to differentiate these two cases then the Service URN 'urn:service:sos.ecall' is used.</t>

      <t>The following list provides information about the sections and requires of <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> that are relevant to this specification: <list
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Identifying an emergency call:">Emergency calls are detected at the end
            device, i.e., by the vehicle, and the service URN 'urn:service:sos.ecall', 'urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic', or 'urn:service:sos.ecall.manual' MUST be implemented by the end device. The requirements listed in Section 5 of
              <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> related to identifying an emergency call based on dial strings are not applicable to this
            specification. </t>
          <t hangText="Location:">The encoding of the PIDF-LO <xref target="RFC4119"/> is described
            in <xref target="data-profile"/>. In an emergency, the end point adds the available
            location information to the initial SIP INVITE emergency call message. In special cases
            a location update may be provided, using the procedure described in requirement ED-38 of
            Section 6.8 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>; all other aspects of Section
            6.8 from that document are not applicable to this specification. Section 6.2.1, 6.2.2,
            6.2.4, 6.4, 6.5 and 6.6 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> are not applicable
            to this document. For location conveyance in SIP <xref
              target="RFC6442"/> MUST be used. Further aspects that are not
            relevant for this document are multiple locations (Section 6.9 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>), location validation (Section 6.10 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>), default location (Section 6.11 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>) </t>
          <t hangText="LoST:">Emergency call routing support, for example utilizing LoST, is
            provided by VSP. As such, the description in Section 8 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is applicable to this document, except for
            requirement SP-25 and SP-26 regarding legacy devices.</t>

          <t hangText="Signaling of emergency calls:">Section 9 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is applicable to this document with the following
            exception: ED-60/AN-25 is
            not applicable as HELD is not used. 
            Video and real-time text may be supported by end device in the future, although currently not envisioned.
            The corresponding text paragraphs are relevant from Section 9 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> when support is being provided.
            Additionally, ED-62 dealing with "SIP signaling
            requirements for User Agents" is simplified as follows. The initial SIP signaling method
            is an INVITE request with the following setting: <list style="numbers">
              <t>The Request URI MUST be the service URN 'urn:service:sos.ecall' or one of the sub-services. </t>
              <t>The To header MUST be a service URN 'urn:service:sos.ecall' or one of the sub-services. </t>
              <t> The From header MUST be present and SHOULD be the AoR of the caller.</t>
              <t>A Via header MUST be present.</t>
              <t>A Contact header MUST be present which MUST be globally routable to permit an
                immediate call-back to the specific device which placed the emergency call.</t>
              <t>Other headers MAY be included as per normal SIP behavior. </t>
              <t>A Supported header MUST be included with the 'geolocation' option tag <xref
                  target="RFC6442"/>. </t>
              <t>The device MUST include location by-value into the call. </t>
              <t>A normal SDP offer SHOULD be included in the INVITE. If voice is supported the
                offer SHOULD include the G.711 codec, if a voice channel can be established based on
                the equipment in the car.</t>
              <t>If the device includes location-by-value, the UA MUST support multipart message
                bodies, since SDP will likely be also in the INVITE.</t>
             <!--  <t>The UAC MUST include a "inserted-by=endpoint" header parameter on all Geolocation
                headers. This informs downstream elements which device entered the location at this
                URI (either cid-URL or location-by-reference URI).</t> -->
              <t>SIP Caller Preferences <xref target="RFC3841"/> MAY be used to signal how the PSAP
                should handle the call. For example, a language preference expressed in an
                Accept-Language header may be used as a hint to cause the PSAP to route the call to
                a call taker who speaks the requested language. SIP Caller Preferences may also be
                used to indicate a need to invoke a relay service for communication with people with
                disabilities in the call. </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t hangText="Call backs:"> The description in Section 10 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is relevant for this document. </t>
          <t hangText="Mid-call behavior:"> The description in Section 11 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is fully applicable to this document. </t>
          <t hangText="Call termination:">The description in Section 12 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is fully applicable to this document. </t>
          <t hangText="Disabling of features:"> The description in Section 13 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is fully applicable to this document. </t>
            <t hangText="Media:">If hardware and software for real-time text, voice, and video is available in the end device then the requirements regarding multi-media support described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> are applicable. </t>
          <t hangText="Testing:"> The description in Section 15 of <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> is fully applicable to this document. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="data-profile" title="Data Profile">
      <t>Due to the requirement for a built-in GPS receiver only geodetic location information will
        be sent within an emergency call. Furthermore, the number of location shapes is is
        restricted. Hence, the following location shapes of <xref
          target="RFC5491"/> MUST be implemented: 2d and 3d Point (see
        Section 5.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5491"/>), Circle (see Section
        5.2.3 of <xref target="RFC5491"/>), and Ellipsoid (see Section
        5.2.7 of <xref target="RFC5491"/>). The coordinate reference
        systems (CRS) specified in <xref target="RFC5491"/> are also
        mandatory for this document. Furthermore, the direction of travel of the vehicle is
        important for dispatch and hence it MUST be included in the PIDF-LO. The
        &lt;heading&gt; element specified in <xref
          target="RFC5962"/> MUST be supported. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example" title="Example">
      <t>
        <xref target="fig1"/> shows an emergency call placed from a vehicle whereby location
        information information is directly attached to the SIP INVITE message itself. The call is
        marked as an emergency call using the 'urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic' service URN and the PSAP of the
        VoIP provider determines which PSAP to contact based on the provided location information.
        As shown in the figure, this route determination may be based on LoST. Then, the emergency
        call continues towards the PSAP and in this example it hits the ESRP, as the entry point to
        the PSAP operators emergency services network. Finally, the emergency call will be received
        by a call taker and first reponders will be dispatched. </t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig1" title="Example of In-Vehicular Emergency Call Message Flow">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                 +--------+
                 | LoST   |
                 | Server |
                 +--------+
                     ^                         +-------+
                     |                         | PSAP2 |
                     |                         +-------+
                     v
                 +-------+     +------+     +-------+
  Vehicle ------>| Proxy |---->| ESRP |---->| PSAP1 |-----> Call-Taker
                 +-------+     +------+     +-------+

                                               +-------+
                                               | PSAP3 |
                                               +-------+
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t> The following example, in <xref target="fig2"/>, shows the SIP INVITE and location information encoded in a
        PIDF-LO that is being conveyed in such an emergency call.</t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig2" title="SIP INVITE indicating an In-Vehicular Emergency Call">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   INVITE urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic SIP/2.0
   To: <sip:intermediate-psap@example.com>
   From: <sip:+13145551111@example.com>;tag=9fxced76sl
   Call-ID: 3848276298220188511@atlanta.example.com
   Geolocation: <cid:target123@example.com>
   Geolocation-Routing: no
   Accept: application/sdp, application/pidf+xml
   CSeq: 31862 INVITE
   Content-Type: multipart/mixed; boundary=boundary1
   Content-Length: ...

   --boundary1

   Content-Type: application/sdp

   ...Session Description Protocol (SDP) goes here

   --boundary1

Content-Type: application/pidf+xml
Content-ID: <target123@atlanta.example.com>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<presence
       xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf"
       xmlns:dm="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:data-model"
       xmlns:gp="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10"
       xmlns:dyn="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:pidf:geopriv10:dynamic"
       xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml"
       xmlns:gs="http://www.opengis.net/pidflo/1.0"
       entity="sip:+13145551111@example.com">
       <dm:device id="123">
           <gp:geopriv>
               <gp:location-info>
                   <gml:Point srsName="urn:ogc:def:crs:EPSG::4326">
                      <gml:pos>-34.407 150.883</gml:pos>
                   </gml:Point>
                    <dyn:Dynamic>
                       <dyn:heading>278</dyn:heading>
                    </dyn:Dynamic>
               </gp:location-info>
               <gp:usage-rules/>
               <method>gps</method>
           </gp:geopriv>
           <timestamp>2012-04-5T10:18:29Z</timestamp>
           <dm:deviceID>vehicle-number</dm:deviceID>
       </dm:device>
</presence>
   --boundary1--
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not raise security considerations beyond those described in <xref
          target="RFC5069"/>. As with emergency service systems with end host provided location
        information there is the possibility that that location is incorrect, either intentially (in
        case of an a denial of service attack against the emergency services infrastructure) or due
        to a malfunctioning devices. The reader is referred to <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-trustworthy-location"/> for a discussion of some of these
        vulnerabilities. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to register the URN 'urn:service:sos.ecall' under the sub-services 'sos'
        registry defined in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC5031"/>.</t>
      
          <t>This service identifier reaches a public safety answering
            point (PSAP), which in turn dispatches aid appropriate to the emergency related to
            accidents of vehicles. Two sub-services are registered as well, namely 
            
            <list style='hanging'> 
            <t hangText="urn:service:sos.ecall.manual">This service URN indicates that an eCall had been triggered based on the manual interaction of the driver or a passenger.</t>
            <t hangText="urn:service:sos.ecall.automatic">This service URN indicates that an eCall had been triggered automatically, for example, due to a crash. No human involvement was detected.</t>
             
            </list> 
            </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>We would like to thank Ulrich Dietz for his help with earlier versions of the document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Michael Montag, Arnoud van Wijk, and Gunnar Hellström for their feedback.</t>
    </section>

<!-- 
    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t>While working on this document a few aspects where discovered that require further
        discussion:</t>
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Today's work on the eCall system does not necessarily require a voice call to be
            established; a voice call may be established whenever possible by the functionality
            offered by the device. From a protocol mechanims, however, the design for establishing
            an emergency call including voice and without voice support are somewhat different.
            Further discussion on the design aspects are needed to align this aspect. </t>
          <t>This document currently defines a new service URN to differentiate it from ordinary
            calls as in-vehicular emergency calls are, in some countries, routed to different PSAPs
            than regular emergency calls. More thoughts are needed to determine whether this is the
            best approach. </t>
          <t>The current version of the document assumes the usage of LoST at the VSP to perform
            call routing of the in-vehicular emergency call. This is useful when there are no dial
            strings need to be learned nor any other service URNs need to be discovered. Further
            discussion is needed whether additional service URNs might be made available to the
            vehicle, for example to request roadside assistance or similar services. In that case
            the option might be provided to run LoST at the end host as well as on the VSP.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
--> 
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC4119;
      &RFC5491; &I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp;
      &RFC6442; &RFC3841; &RFC5962;
      &RFC5031; </references>
    <references title="Informative references"> &RFC5012; &RFC5069;
      &I-D.ietf-ecrit-trustworthy-location; </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
