<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3325 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3325.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3966 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3966.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3969 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3969.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4474 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4484 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4484.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5012 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5012.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5031 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5627 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5627.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-sip-saml PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sip-saml.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.holmberg-emergency-callback-id PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.holmberg-emergency-callback-id.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6444 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6444.xml">
]>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-ecrit-psap-callback-06.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
       
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
  <?rfc compact="no"?>
  <?rfc strict="no"?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PSAP Callback">Public Safety Answering Point (PSAP)
    Callback</title>

    <author fullname="Henning Schulzrinne" initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne">
      <organization>Columbia University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>

          <street>450 Computer Science Building</street>

          <city>New York</city>

          <region>NY</region>

          <code>10027</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 212 939 7004</phone>

        <email>hgs+ecrit@cs.columbia.edu</email>

        <uri>http://www.cs.columbia.edu</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>

          <city>Espoo</city>

          <code>02600</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>

        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
   <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Milan Patel" initials="M." surname="Patel">
      <organization>InterDigital Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>Milan.Patel@interdigital.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>    
    <date year="2012" />

    <workgroup>ECRIT</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>After an emergency call is completed (either prematurely terminated
      by the emergency caller or normally by the call taker) it is possible
      that the call taker feels the need for further communication. 
      For example, the call may have been dropped by accident
      without the call taker having sufficient information about the current
      situation of a wounded person. A call taker may trigger a callback
      towards the emergency caller using the contact information provided with
      the initial emergency call. This callback could, under certain
      circumstances, be treated like any other call and as a consequence
      it may get blocked by authorization policies or may get forwarded to an
      answering machine.</t>

      <t>The IETF emergency services architecture specification already 
      offers a solution approach for allowing PSAP callbacks to 
      bypass authorization policies to reach the caller without
      unnecessary delays. Unfortunately, the specified mechanism only supports limited scenarios. This document
      discusses shortcomings of the current mechanisms and illustrates additional scenarios where better-than-normal
      call treatment behavior would be desirable.</t>
      
      <t>Note that this version of the document does not yet specify a solution due to the lack of the working group 
      participants agreeing on the requirements.</t> 
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Summoning police, the fire department or an ambulance in emergencies
      is one of the fundamental and most-valued functions of the telephone. As
      telephone functionality moves from circuit-switched telephony to
      Internet telephony, its users rightfully expect that this core
      functionality will continue to work at least as well as it has for the
      legacy technology. New devices and services are being made available
      that could be used to make a request for help, which are not traditional
      telephones, and users are increasingly expecting them to be used to
      place emergency calls.</t>

      <t>An overview of the protocol interactions for emergency calling using the IETF emergency services architecture are described in <xref target="RFC6444"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> specifies the technical details. As part of the emergency call setup procedure two important identifiers are conveyed to the PSAP call taker's user agent, namely the Address-Of-Record (AoR), and, if available, the Globally Routable User Agent (UA) URIs (GRUU). RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/> defines the AoR as: 
<list style="empty"> 
<t>      
         'An address-of-record (AOR) is a SIP or SIPS URI
         that points to a domain with a location service that can map
         the URI to another URI where the user might be available.
         Typically, the location service is populated through
         registrations.  An AOR is frequently thought of as the "public
         address" of the user.'
</t>
</list> 
</t>
<t>
   In SIP systems a single user can have a number of user agents (handsets,
   softphones, voicemail accounts, etc.) which are all referenced by the
   same AOR.  There are a number of cases in which it is desirable to
   have an identifier which addresses a single user agent rather than
   the group of user agents indicated by an AOR. The GRUU is such a unique user-
   agent identifier, which is still globally routable. RFC 5627 <xref target="RFC5627"/> specifies how to obtain and use GRUUs.
   <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> also makes use of the GRUU for emergency calls.
</t>
      
<t>Regulatory requirements demand that the emergency call setup procedure itself 
provides enough information to allow the call taker to initiate a call back to the 
emergency caller. This is desirable in those cases where the call got dropped 
prematurely or when further communication need arises. 
The AoR and the GRUU serve this purpose.</t>
<t>The communication attempt by the PSAP call taker back to the emergency caller is called 'PSAP callback'. 
</t> 

<t>A PSAP callback may, 
      however,
      be blocked by user configured authorization policies or may be forwarded to an answering machine since SIP entities (SIP
      proxies as well as the SIP user equipment itself) cannot differentiate the PSAP callback from any other SIP call.
      "Call barring", "do not disturb", or "call diversion"(aka call forwarding) are features that prevent delivery of a call. It is important to note that these features may be implemented by SIP intermediaries as well as by the user agent. </t>

      <t>Among the emergency services community there is the desire to offer PSAP callbacks a treatment such that chances are 
      increased that it reaches the emergency caller. At the same time a design must deal with the negative side-effects of allowing certain calls to bypass call forwarding or other authorization policies. Ideally, the PSAP callback has to relate to an earlier emergency call that was made "not too long ago". An exact time interval is difficult to define in a global IETF standard due to the variety of national regulatory requirements.</t> 
      
      <t>To nevertheless meet the needs from the emergency services community a basic mechanism for preferential treatment of PSAP callbacks was defined in Section 13 of <xref
      target="RFC6444"></xref>. The specification says:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>'A UA may be able to determine a PSAP call back by examining the
          domain of incoming calls after placing an emergency call and
          comparing that to the domain of the answering PSAP from the
          emergency call. Any call from the same domain and directed to the
          supplied Contact header or AoR after an emergency call should be
          accepted as a callback from the PSAP if it occurs within a
          reasonable time after an emergency call was placed.'</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This approach mimics a stateful packet filtering firewall and is
      indeed helpful in a number of cases. It is also relatively simple to
      implement even though it requires state to be maintained by the user agent as well as by SIP intermediaries. Unfortunately, the solution does not work in all deployment scenarios. 
      In <xref target="scenarios"/> we describe cases where the currently 
      standardized approach is insufficient.</t>
      
      <t><!-- In <xref target="solution"/> a solution is described. --> 
      </t> 

</section> 


    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Emergency services related terminology is borrowed from <xref
      target="RFC5012"></xref>. This includes terminology like emergency caller, user equipment, and call taker. 
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="scenarios" title="Callback Scenarios">
   
     <t>This section illustrates a number of scenarios where the currently specified solution, as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>, for preferential treatment of callbacks fails. As explained in <xref target="intro"/> a SIP entity examines an incoming PSAP call back by comparing the domain of the PSAP with the destination domain of the emergency call.</t> 
     
      <section title="Routing Asymmetry">
        <t>In some deployment environments it is common to have incoming and
        outgoing SIP messaging routed through different SIP entities. <xref target="asymmetry"/> shows this graphically whereby a VoIP provider uses different SIP proxies for inbound and for outbound call handling. Unless they two devices are state synchronized the callback hitting the inbound proxy would get treated like any other call since the emergency call established state information at the outbound proxy only. </t>

        <t><figure anchor="asymmetry" title="Example for Routing Asymmetry">
            <artwork>

              <![CDATA[
                                                ,-------.
                                              ,'         `.
                   ,-------.                 /  Emergency  \
                 ,'         `.              |   Services    |
                /  VoIP       \      I      |   Network     |
               |   Provider    |     n      |               |
               |               |     t      |               |
               |               |     e      |               |
               |   +-------+   |     r      |               |
            +--+---|Inbound|<--+-----m      |               |
            |  |   |Proxy  |   |     e      |   +------+    |
            |  |   +-------+   |     d      |   |PSAP  |    |
            |  |               |     i      |   +--+---+    |
  +----+    |  |               |     a-+    |      |        |
  | UA |<---+  |               |     t |    |      |        |
  |    |----+  |               |     e |    |      |        |
  +----+    |  |               |       |    |      |        |
            |  |               |     P  |   |      |        |
            |  |               |     r  |   |      |        |
            |  |   +--------+  |     o   |  |      |        |
            +--+-->|Outbound|--+---->v   |  |   +--+---+    |
               |   |Proxy   |  |     i    | | +-+ESRP  |    |
               |   +--------+  |     d    | | | +------+    |
               |               |     e     || |             |
               |               |     r     |+-+             |
                \             /             |               |
                 `.         ,'               \             /
                   '-------'                  `.         ,'
                                                '-------'
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="multistage" title="Multi-Stage Routing">
        <t>Consider the following emergency call routing scenario shown in
        <xref target="stages"></xref> where routing towards the PSAP occurs in
        several stages. In this scenario we consider a SIP UA that uses LoST to learn 
        the next hop destination closer to the PSAP. This call is then sent to the user's VoIP provider. 
        The user's VoIP provider
        receives the emergency call and creates state based on the destination domain, namely state.com. 
        It then routes it to the indicated ESRP. 
        When the ESRP receives it it needs to decide what the next hop is to get it closer to the PSAP. 
        In our example the next hop is the PSAP with the URI psap@town.com.</t>
        
        <t>When a callback is sent from psap@town.com towards the emergency caller the call 
        will get normal treatment by the VoIP providers inbound proxy since the domain of the PSAP 
        does not match the stored state information.</t>
        
        <t><figure anchor="stages" title="Example for Multi-Stage Routing">
            <artwork><![CDATA[

                                      ,-------.
    +----+                          ,'         `.
    | UA |--- esrp1@foobar.com     /  Emergency  \
    +----+   \                    |   Services    |
              \  ,-------.        |   Network     |
               ,'         `.      |               |
              /   VoIP      \     |   +------+    |
             (    Provider   )    |   |PSAP  |    |
              \             /     |   +--+---+    |
               `.         ,'      |      |
                 '---+---'        |      |        |
                     |            |psap@town.com  |
             esrp@state.com       |      |        |
                     |            |      |        |
                     |            |      |        |
                     |            |   +--+---+    |
                     +------------+---+ESRP  |    |
                                  |   +------+    |
                                  |               |
                                   \             /
                                    `.         ,'
                                      '-------'
                              ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Call Forwarding">
        <t>Imagine the following case where an emergency call enters an
        emergency network (state.org) via an ERSP but then gets forwarded to a
        different emergency services network (in our example to
        police-town.org, fire-town.org or medic-town.org). The same
        considerations apply when the police, fire and ambulance networks
        are part of the state.org sub-domains (e.g., police.state.org).</t>
    
        <t>Similarly to the previous scenario the problem here is with the 
        wrong state information being established during the emergency call 
        setup procedure. A callback would originate in the police-town.org, fire-town.org or medic-town.org
        domain whereas the emergency caller's SIP UA or the VoIP outbound proxy has 
        stored state.org.</t>
        
        
        <t><figure anchor="fwd" title="Example for Call Forwarding">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                                ,-------.
                              ,'         `.
                             /  Emergency  \
                            |   Services    |
                            |   Network     |
                            |   (state.org) |
                            |               |
                            |               |
                            |   +------+    |
                            |   |PSAP  +--+ |
                            |   +--+---+  | |
                            |      |      | |
                            |      |      | |
                            |      |      | |
                            |      |      | |
                            |      |      | |
                            |   +--+---+  | |
          ------------------+---+ESRP  |  | |
          esrp-a@state.org  |   +------+  | |
                            |             | |
                            |    Call Fwd | |
                            |     +-+-+---+ |
                             \    | | |    /
                              `.  | | |  ,'
                                '-|-|-|-'           ,-------.
                         Police   | | | Fire      ,'         `.
                     +------------+ | +----+     /  Emergency  \
      ,-------.      |              |      |    |   Services    |
    ,'         `.    |              |      |    |   Network     |
   /  Emergency  \   |          Ambulance  |    | fire-town.org |
  |   Services    |  |              |      |    |               |
  |   Network     |  |              +----+ |    |   +------+    |
  |police-town.org|  |     ,-------.     | +----+---+PSAP  |    |
  |               |  |   ,'         `.   |      |   +------+    |
  |   +------+    |  |  /  Emergency  \  |      |               |
  |   |PSAP  +----+--+ |   Services    | |      |               ,
  |   +------+    |    |   Network     | |      `~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
  |               |    |medic-town.org | |
  |               ,    |               | |
  `~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~     |   +------+    | |
                       |   |PSAP  +----+ +
                       |   +------+    |
                       |               |
                       |               ,
                       `~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
                              ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Network-based Service URN Resolution">
       

        <t>The IETF emergency services architecture also considers
        cases where the resolution from the Service URN to the PSAP URI
        does not only happen at the SIP UA itself but at intermediate SIP entities, 
        such as the user's VoIP provider.</t>

        <t><xref target="late-binding"></xref> shows this message exchange
        of the outgoing emergency call and the incoming PSAP graphically.
        While the state information stored at the VoIP provider is correct 
        the state allocated at the SIP UA is not. </t>

        <t><figure anchor="late-binding"
            title="Example for Network-based Service URN Resolution">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
     ,-------.
   ,'         `.
  /  Emergency  \
 |   Services    |
 |   Network     |
 |police-town.org|
 |               |
 |   +------+    |    Invite to police.example.com
 |   |PSAP  +<---+------------------------+
 |   |      +----+------------------+     ^
 |   +------+    |Invite from       |     |
 |               ,police.example.com|     |
 `~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~                   v     |
 +--------+                        ++-----+-+
 |        |            query       |VoIP    |
 | LoST   |<-----------------------|Service |
 | Server |   police.example.com   |Provider|
 |        |----------------------->|        |
 +--------+                        +--------+
                                    |     ^
                              Invite|     | Invite
                                from|     | to
                  police.example.com|     | urn:service:sos
                                    V     |
                                   +-------+
                                   | SIP   |
                                   | UA    |
                                   | Alice |
                                   +-------+
                              ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
      
      
      <section title="PSTN Interworking">
        <t>In case an emergency call enters the PSTN, as shown in <xref
        target="pstn"></xref>, there is no guarantee that the callback some
        time later does leave the same PSTN/VoIP gateway or that the same end
        point identifier is used in the forward as well as in the backward
        direction making it difficult to reliably detect PSAP callbacks.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="pstn" title="Example for PSTN Interworking">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  +-----------+
  | PSTN      |-------------+
  | Calltaker |             |
  | Bob       |<--------+   |
  +-----------+         |   v
             -------------------
         ////                   \\\\      +------------+
        |                           |     |PSTN / VoIP |
        |             PSTN          |---->|Gateway     |
         \\\\                   ////      |            |
             -------------------          +----+-------+
                        ^                      |
                        |                      |
                  +-------------+              |  +--------+
                  |             |              |  |VoIP    |
                  | PSTN / VoIP |              +->|Service |
                  | Gateway     |                 |Provider|
                  |             |<------Invite----|   Y    |
                  +-------------+                 +--------+
                                                   |     ^
                                                   |     |
                                                 Invite Invite
                                                   |     |
                                                   V     |
                                                  +-------+
                                                  | SIP   |
                                                  | UA    |
                                                  | Alice |
                                                  +-------+
                              ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
          
          <t>Note: This scenario is considered outside the scope of this 
          document. The specified solution does not support this use case.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->
 
    <section anchor="solution" title="SIP PSAP Callback Indicator">
		<section title="General">
			<t>
				This section defines a new header field value, called "psap-callback", for the SIP Priority header 
				field defined in <xref target="RFC3261"/>. The value is used to inform 
				SIP entities that the request is associated with a PSAP callback SIP session. 
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Usage">
			<t>
				SIP entities that receive the header field value within an initial request for a SIP session can, 
				depending on local policies, apply PSAP callback specific procedures for the session or request.
			</t>
			<t>
				The PSAP callback specific procedures may be applied by SIP-based network entities and by the callee. 
				The specific procedures taken when receiving such a PSAP callback marked call, such as bypassing 
				services and barring procedures, are outside the scope of this document.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Syntax">
			<section title="General">
				<t>
					This section defines the ABNF for the new SIP Priority header field value "psap-callback".
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="ABNF">
				<t><figure anchor="abnf" title="ABNF">
				<artwork><![CDATA[
	priority-value  /=  "psap-callback"
			]]></artwork>
				</figure></t>
			</section>
		</section>
    </section>

    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    
    <section title="Security Threat">
      
	  <t>
      The PSAP callback functionality described in this document allows 
      marked calls to bypass blacklists, ignore call forwarding procedures
      and similar features to contact emergency callers and to raise their
      attention.  Regarding the latter aspect a callback, if understood 
      by the SIP UA would allow to override user interface configurations, 
	  such as vibrate-only mode, to alert the caller of the incoming call.  
	  </t>
    </section> 
	
   <section title="Security Requirements">
    
	<t>
	  The requirement is to ensure that the
      mechanisms described in this document can not be used for
      malicious purposes, including telemarketing.
    </t>
	<t>
      Furthermore, if the newly defined extension is not recognized, not
      verified adequately, or not obeyed by SIP intermediaries or SIP 
	  endpoints then it must not lead to a failure of the call handling 
	  procedure. Such call must be treated like a call that does not have
      any marking attached.
	</t>  
   </section> 
   
   <section title="Security Solution">
   
   <t>
   <xref target="identity-authz"/> shows the architecture that utilizes the identity of the PSAP 
   to decide whether a preferential treatment of callbacks should be
   provided. To make this policy decision the identity of the PSAP is 
   compared with a whitelist of valid PSAPs available to the SIP entity.  
   The identity assurance in SIP can come in different forms,
   such as SIP Identity <xref target="RFC4474"/> or with P-Asserted-Identity <xref target="RFC3325"/>.
   The former technique relies on a cryptographic assurance and the
   latter on a chain of trust. Also the usage of TLS between neighboring
   SIP entities may provide useful identity information.
   </t>   

      <t><figure anchor="identity-authz" title="Identity-based Authorization">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                    +----------+
                    | List of  |+
                    | valid    ||
                    | PSAPs    ||
                    +----------+|
                     +----------+
                         *
                         * whitelist
                         *
                         V
      Incoming      +----------+    Normal
      SIP Msg       | SIP      |+   Treatment
     -------------->| Entity   ||======================>
      + Identity    |          ||(if not in whitelist)
        Info        +----------+|
                    +----------+
                         ||
                         ||
                         || Preferential
                         || Treatment
                         ++========================>
                           (if successfully verified)
			]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
   <t>
   An important aspect from a security point of view is the relationship
   between the emergency services network (containing PSAPs) and the VSP 
   (assuming that the emergency call travels via the VSP and not directly 
   between the SIP UA and the PSAP).  
   </t>
   <t>
   If there is some form of relationship between the
   emergency services operator and the VSP then the identification of a
   PSAP call back is less problematic than in the case where the two
   entities have not entered in some form of relationship that would
   allow the VSP to verify whether the marked callback message indeed
   came from a legitimate source.
   </t>
   <t>
   The establishment of a whitelist with PSAP identities maybe be
   operationally complex.  When there is a local relationship between 
   the VSP/ASP and the PSAP then populating the whitelist is fairly simple. 
   For SIP UAs there is no need to maintain a list of PSAPs. Instead 
   SIP UAs are assumed to trust the correct processing of their VSP/ASP, i.e., 
   the VSP/ASP processes the PSAP callback marking and, if it cannot be 
   verified, the PSAP callback marking is removed. If it is left untouched 
   then the SIP UA should assume that it has been verified successfully by the 
   VSP/ASP and it should therefore be obeyed. 
   </t>
    </section>
	</section> 
	

    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
    
    <t>[Editor's Note: There is currently no registry available for the SIP Priority header. 
    A registry needs to be created and the value defined in this document needs to be added.]</t>
    
    </section>

    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank members from the ECRIT working group, in
      particular Brian Rosen, for their discussions around PSAP callbacks. The
      working group discussed the topic of callbacks at their virtual interim
      meeting in February 2010 and the following persons provided valuable
      input: John Elwell, Bernard Aboba, Cullen Jennings, Keith Drage, Marc
      Linsner, Roger Marshall, Dan Romascanu, Geoff Thompson, Janet Gunn.</t>
      
      <t>At IETF#81 a small group of people got to together to continue the 
      discussions started at the working group meeting to explore a 
      GRUU-based solution approach. Martin Thomson, Marc Linsner, Andrew Allen, 
      Brian Rosen, Martin Dolly, and Atle Monrad participated at this 
      side-meeting.</t>
      
	  <t>We would like to thank the following persons for their feedback on the solution 
	  discussion in 2012: Paul Kyzivat, Martin Thomson, Robert Sparks, Keith Drage, Brian Rosen, Roger Marshall, Martin Dolly, Bernard Aboba, Andrew Allen, John-Luc Bakker, James Polk, John Medland, Hadriel Kaplan, Kenneth Carlberg, Timothy Dwight, Janet Gunn</t>
	  
    </section>

    <!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC3261;

      &RFC3325;

      &RFC3966;

      &RFC3969;
      
      &RFC5627; 

	  <!-- 
      <reference anchor="RFC5341">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet Assigned Number Authority (IANA) tel Uniform
          Resource Identifier (URI) Parameter Registry</title>

          <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C" surname="Jennings">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Vijay K. Gurbani" initials="V. K. "
                  surname="Gurbani">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>
       --> 
	   
      &RFC4474;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC6444;

       &I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp;
      <!-- &I-D.ietf-sip-saml;
      &I-D.holmberg-emergency-callback-id; 
	  --> 
	  
      &RFC4484;

      &RFC5012;

      &RFC5031;

      &RFC5234;
    </references>
  
    </back>

   
</rfc>
