<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-aaa-diameter-cms-sec PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-aaa-diameter-cms-sec.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6733 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6733.xml">
]>

<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?> 
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>


<rfc category='std' ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-tschofenig-dime-e2e-sec-req-00.txt'>


  <front>
    <title abbrev="Diameter AVP Level Security">Diameter AVP Level Security: Requirements and Architecture</title>

    <author role="editor" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
 
   <author initials='J.' surname="Korhonen" fullname='Jouni Korhonen'>
           <organization></organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street></street>
                    <code></code>
                    <country>FINLAND</country>
                </postal>
                <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
             </address>
        </author>
		
		  <author initials='G.' surname="Zorn" fullname='Glen Zorn'>
           <organization abbrev="Network Zen">Network Zen</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>227/358 Thanon Sanphawut</street>
					<city> Bang Na</city>
                    <code>Bangkok 10260</code>
                    <country>Thailand</country>
                </postal>
                <email>glenzorn@gmail.com</email>
             </address>
        </author>
    <date year='2013'/>
    <area>OPS</area>
    <workgroup>DIME</workgroup>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>Diameter</keyword>
    <keyword>End-to-End Security</keyword>


    <abstract>
      <t>This specification discusses requirements and architectural aspect for providing Diameter end-to-end security at the level of individual Attribute Value Pairs.</t>
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
  
 
    <section title='Introduction'>
    
	<t>The Diameter Base specification <xref target="RFC6733"/> offers security protection between neighboring Diameter peers and mandates that either TLS (for TCP), DTLS (for SCTP), or IPsec is used. These security protocols offer a wide range of security properties, including entity authentication, data-origin authentication, integrity, confidentiality protection and replay protection. They also support a large number of cryptographic algorithms, algorithm negotiation, and different types of credentials.</t>

<t>The need to also offer additional security protection of AVPs between non-neighboring Diameter nodes was recognized very early in the work on Diameter. This lead to investigations on a Diameter security extension using Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) <xref target="I-D.ietf-aaa-diameter-cms-sec"/>. Due to lack of deployment interest at that time the specification was, however, never completed.</t>

<t>In the meanwhile Diameter had received a lot of deployment interest and due to the sophistication of those deployments the need for protecting Diameter AVPs between non-neighboring nodes re-surfaced. Since early 2000 when the work on <xref target="I-D.ietf-aaa-diameter-cms-sec"/> was discontinued the community had seen advances in cryptography and new requirements emerged.</t>

<t>This document collects requirements for protecting Diameter AVPs.</t>

  </section>
	  
      <section title='Terminology'>
        <t>
          The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL', 'SHALL NOT', 'SHOULD',
          'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this specification are to be
          interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
        </t>
      </section>

	  
	  <section title="Use Case"> 

	  <t>Consider the following use case shown in <xref target="example"/>. A Diameter client interacts with a Diameter server through two Diameter proxies. The Diameter client and the Diameter Proxy A belong to the same realm, example.com.

<figure title="Example Diameter Deployment Setup." anchor="example">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
****************************
                           *
   Realm: Example.com      *
+--------+      +--------+ *      +--------+        +--------+
|Diameter|      |Diameter| *      |Diameter|        |Diameter|
|Client  +------+Proxy A +-*------+Proxy B +--------+Server  |
+--------+      +--------+ *      +--------+        +--------+
    ^                      *                             ^
    .           End-to-End * Security Protection         .
    +......................*.............................+
                           *
****************************
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          </t>
		  
		  <t>The Diameter AVPs are protected end-to-end, from the Diameter client to the Diameter server, as shown in Figure 1 with the dotted line.</t>

<t>Other use cases are possible as well. For example, Diameter Proxy A could act on behalf of the Diameter clients in the example.com realm. In a general case, however, encryption of AVPs between arbitrary Diameter nodes can be challenging since it is upfront not know what Diameter nodes a message will traverse.</t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>QUESTION: Should the scope of the work be limited to provide data origin authentication, integrity, and optionally confidentially protection between of selected Diameter AVPs sent by the Diameter client to the Diameter server, and vice versa?</t>
</list>
</t>

	  </section> 
	  
      <section title='Requirements'>
	 
<t>Solutions MUST support an extensible set of cryptographic algorithms.
<list style="empty">
<t>Motivation: Crypto-agility is the ability of a protocol to adapt to evolving cryptographic algorithms and security requirements. This may include the provision of a modular mechanism to allow cryptographic algorithms to be updated without substantial disruption to deployed implementations.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>Solutions MUST support replay protection.</t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>QUESTION: Should replay protection be based on time-stamps assuming synchronized clocks?</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>Solutions MUST support confidentiality, integrity, and data-origin authentication.</t>

<t>Solutions MUST be able to selectively apply their cryptographic protection to certain Diameter AVPs.</t>

<t>Solutions MUST recommend a mandatory-to-implement cryptographic algorithm.</t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>QUESTION: Should solutions for integrity protection work in a backwards-compatible way with existing Diameter applications? Should the list of integrity protected AVP be indicated in the protected payload itself?</t>
</list>
</t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>QUESTION: Should we support symmetric keys and / or also asymmetric keys?</t>
</list>
</t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>QUESTION: Should statically provisioned keys be supported? Should requirements for dynamic key management be included here as well?</t>
</list>
</t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>QUESTION: Should the specification be written in such a way that it allows the provisioning of long-term shared symmetric credentials via a command-line interface / text file in an interoperable way? This would allow simplified configuration.</t>
</list>
</t>
 
    </section>



    <section title='Security Considerations' anchor='Security'>
  <t>This entire document focused on the discussion of new functionality for securing Diameter AVPs end-to-end.</t> 
    </section>

    <section title='IANA Considerations' anchor='IANA'>
	 <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title='Acknowledgments'>
	     <t>Add your name here.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>
   &RFC2119; 
   
   &RFC6733;
   
    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>
   &I-D.ietf-aaa-diameter-cms-sec;  
    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>
