<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-iab-smart-object-architecture-06.txt">

  <front>
  <title abbrev="Smart Object Architectural Considerations">Architectural Considerations in Smart Object Networking</title>   

    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <code></code>
          <country>Austria</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="J" surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Jorvas</city> <code>02420</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="D." surname="Thaler" fullname="Dave Thaler">
        <organization/>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
                <city>Redmond</city>
                <region>WA</region>
                <code>98052</code>
                <country>US</country>
            </postal>
            <email>dthaler@microsoft.com</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="D." surname="McPherson" fullname="Danny McPherson">
        <organization/>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street></street>
                <city></city>
                <region></region>
                <code></code>
                <country>US</country>
            </postal>
            <email>danny@tcb.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>
        
    <date year="2014"/>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>IAB Statement</keyword>
    <keyword>Smart Objects</keyword>
    <abstract>

      <t>The term "Internet of Things" (IoT) denotes a trend where a large number of
         embedded devices employ communication services offered by the Internet
         protocols.  Many of these devices, often called "smart objects" are
         not directly operated by humans, but exist as components in buildings
         or vehicles, or are spread out in the environment.

     Following the theme "Everything that can be connected will be
     connected", engineers and researchers designing smart object networks
     need to decide how to achieve this in practice.</t> 

<!-- 
     <t>How can different
     forms of embedded and constrained devices be interconnected to the Internet? How can
     they employ and interact with the currently deployed Internet? This
     memo discusses architectural design patterns for connecting smart objects to the 
     Internet. 
  </t>

--> 

  <t>This document offers guidance to engineers designing Internet connected smart objects.</t> 

</abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

  <t>RFC 6574 <xref target="RFC6574"/> refers to smart objects as 
   devices with constraints on energy, bandwidth, memory, size, cost, etc.  
     This is a fuzzy definition, as there is clearly a
     continuum in device capabilities and there is no hard line to draw
     between devices that can run Internet Protocols and those
     that can't.
  </t>
  

  <!-- and attempts to be more specific based on a device
       classification, as done in Section 2.1 of <xref
       target="I-D.ietf-lwig-guidance"/>, may not be suitable in
       all cases either. Clearly. Understanding this unclear boundary
       between "regular" Internet devices (like laptops, netbooks,
       phones, routers, home gateways, or desktops) connected to the
       Internet and other forms of devices (like sensors) is important
       to understand our line of argument.-->
  <!-- 
  <t>Following the theme "Everything that can be connected will be
     connected", engineers and researchers designing smart object networks
     need to address a number of questions.  How can different
     forms of embedded and constrained devices be interconnected? How can
     they employ and interact with the currently deployed Internet?
  </t>
      
  <t>These questions have been discussed at length. For instance, when
  the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) scheduled a workshop on Smart
  Objects, the community was asked to develop views on how
    Internet protocols can be utilized by smart objects. A report of the
  discussions and the position papers received for this workshop have
  been published <xref target="RFC6574"/>.
  </t>
  --> 

  <t>Interconnecting smart objects with the Internet enables exciting new 
    use cases and products. An increasing number of products put 
    the Internet Protocol suite on smaller and smaller devices and offer the 
    ability to process, visualize, and gain insight from the collected 
    sensor data. The network effect can be increased if the data collected 
    from many different devices can be combined.</t>

  <t>Developing embedded systems is a complex task, and designers must
     make a number of design decisions such as:
    <list style="symbols"> 
      <t>How long is the device designed to operate?
      </t>
      <t>How does it interact with the physical world? Is it a sensor or actuator or both?
      </t>
      <t>How many "owners" does it have? One? Many? Is the owner likely to change over the lifetime of the device?
      </t>
      <t>Is it continuously powered?  Intermittently powered?  Does it sleep?
      </t>
      <t>Is it connected to a network, and if so, how?
      </t>
      <t>Will it be physically accessible for direct maintenance after deployment? 
         How does that affect the security model?
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>
    
  <t>While developing embedded systems is itself a complex task, designing Internet-connected
    smart objects is even harder since it requires expertise with 
    Internet protocols in addition to software programming 
    and hardware skills. To simplify the development task, and thereby to 
    lower the cost of developing new products and prototypes, we believe 
    that re-use of prior work is essential. Therefore, we provide high-level 
    guidance on the use of Internet technology for the development of smart 
    objects, and connected systems in general.</t> 

   <t>
     <list style="hanging"> 

     <t hangText="Utilize Existing Design Patterns"><vspace blankLines="1"/>Design 
        patterns are generally reusable solutions to a commonly occurring 
        design problem (see <xref target="Gamma"/> for more discussion). 
        Existing smart object deployments show communication patterns 
        that can be re-used by engineers with the benefit of lowering the 
        design effort. As discussed in the sections below, individual patterns also have an implication on the 
        required interoperability between the different entities. Depending 
        on the desired functionality, already existing patterns can be re-used 
        and adjusted. <xref target="patterns"/> talks about various 
        communication patterns.
     </t> 

     <t hangText="Re-Use Internet Protocols"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Most
        smart object deployments can make use of the already 
        standardized Internet protocol suite. The Internet protocols can be 
        applied to almost any environment due to their generic design, and 
        typically offer plenty of potential for re-configuration, 
        which allows them to be tailored for the specific needs.
        <xref target="reuse"/> discusses this topic. 
     </t>

     <t hangText="The Deployed Internet matters"><vspace blankLines="1"/>When 
        connecting smart objects to the Internet, take existing deployment 
        into consideration to avoid unpleasant surprises.  Assuming an ideal, 
        clean-slate deployments is, in many cases, far too optimistic since 
        the already deployed infrastructure is convenient to use. In 
        <xref target="deployed"/> we highlight the importance of this topic. 
     </t> 

     <t hangText="Design for Change"><vspace blankLines="1"/>The Internet 
        infrastructure, the applications and preferred building blocks evolve 
        over time. Especially long-lived smart object deployments need to take 
        this change into account and <xref target="change"/> is dedicated to 
        that topic.</t> 

<!-- 
     <t hangText="Design for Tomorrow"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Understanding 
        the cost and limitations of todays systems is important in the design 
        of embedded systems and the constrained nature of smart objects invites 
        to optimize protocols for special use cases.  While some of these 
        optimizations may be necessary but they also come at a cost. 
     </t>
--> 
     </list> 
  </t> 

  <!-- 

  <t>Leasons learned from the design of the Internet help is guide the development of smart objects and the 
    following observations are made.

    <list style='numbers'> 
      <t>Connecting things to the Internet does not require a re-design of the Internet.</t.
      <t>Re-use of standardized protocols is important since it lowers costs and improves
        time-to-market.</t>
      <t>A completely standarized protocol stack may be desirable but is not necessarily required.</t>
      <t>The need for interoperability can be shifted to different parties.</t>
      <t>Providing end-to-end IP connectivity removes the need for special application layer gateways.</t>
    </list> 
  </t> 
   --> 

  <!-- 
  <t>This memo discusses smart objects and some of the architectural
  choices involved in designing smart object networks and protocols
  that they use. The main issues that we focus on are interaction with
  the Internet, the use of Internet protocols for these applications,
  models of interoperability, and approach to standardization. Many of
  the issues discussed in this memo are common to any communications
  system design or protocol development. However, given the high
  interest for smart object networks, their somewhat specific
  requirements, and commonly occurring requests for very different
  communications tools prompted the IAB to discuss these issues in
  this specific context.
  </t>

--> 

</section> 

<!-- /////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// --> 

<section anchor="patterns" title="Smart Object Communication Patterns"> 

<t>This section illustrates a number of communication patterns utilized in the smart object 
  environment. It is possible that more than one pattern can be applied at the same time in a product. 
  Developers re-using those patterns will benefit from the experience of others as well 
  as from documentation, source code, and available products.</t> 
  
<section title="Device-to-Device Communication Pattern"> 

  <t><xref target="d2d"/> illustrates a communication pattern where two devices developed 
  by different manufacturers are desired to interoperate and communicate directly. To pick an example from 
  <xref target="RFC6574"/>, consider a light switch that talks to a light 
  bulb with the requirement that each may be manufactured by a different company, 
  represented as manufacturer A and B. Other cases can be found with fitness 
  equipment, such as heart-rate monitors and cadence sensors.</t>

  <t>
          <figure anchor="d2d" title="Device-to-Device Communication Pattern">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
                     _,,,,    ,,,,                       
                    /     -'``    \                      
                   |  Wireless    |                     
                   \  Network     |                     
                   /               \                     
 ,''''''''|       /                 .       ,''''''''|   
 | Light  | ------|------------------\------| Light  |   
 | Bulb   |        .                 |      | Switch |   
 |........'         `'-              /      |........'   
                       \      _-...-`                    
 Manufacturer           `. ,.'              Manufacturer  
     A                    `                      B                                                                      
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
  </t>
  <t>In order to fulfill the promise that devices from different manufacturers are able to communicate out-of-the-box,
  these vendors need to agree on the protocol stack. They need to make decisions about the following protocol design
  aspects:</t>

  <t>
  <list style="symbols"> 
   <t>Which physical layer(s) should be supported? Does it use low power radio technologies (e.g., Bluetooth Smart, IEEE 802.15.4)? </t>
   <t>Can devices be IPv6-only, or
      must they also support IPv4 for legacy/backward compatibility reasons? What IPv4-IPv6 transition technologies are needed?</t>
   <t>Which IP address configuration mechanism(s) are integrated into the device?</t>
   <t>Which communication architectures shall be supported? Which devices are constrained 
    and what are those constraints? Is there a classical client-server model or rather a 
    peer-to-peer model?</t>
   <t>Is there a need for a service discovery mechanism to allow users to discover 
    light bulbs they have in their home or office?</t>
   <t>Which transport-layer protocol is used for conveying the sensor readings/sensor 
    commands? (e.g., UDP)</t>
   <t>Which application-layer protocol is used? (for example, CoAP <xref target="RFC7252"/>)</t>
   <t>What information model is used for expressing the different light levels?</t>
   <t>What data model is used to encode information? (See RFC 3444 <xref target="RFC3444"/>) for a discussion about the difference between data models and information models.)?</t>
   <t>
   Finally, security and privacy require careful thought.
    This includes questions like: what are the security threats? What security 
    services need to be provided to deal with the identified threats? Where do the 
    security credentials come from? At what layer(s) in the protocol stack should 
    the security mechanism(s) reside? What privacy implications are caused by various design decisions?</t> 
  </list> 
  </t> 
  
  <t>This list is not meant to be exhaustive but aims to illustrate that for every 
    usage scenario many design decisions will have to be made in order to accommodate 
    the constrained nature of a specific device in a certain usage scenario. 
    Standardizing such a complete solution to accomplish a full level of interoperability 
    between two devices manufactured by different vendors takes time but there are 
    obvious rewards for end customers and vendors.</t> 
<!-- 
  <t>An example of a non-IP-based communication pattern can be found with the Bluetooth Smart 
    profiles.</t>  --> 
</section> 

<section anchor="d2c" title="Device-to-Cloud Communication Pattern">

  <t><xref target="cloud"/> shows a communication pattern for uploading sensor data to an application service provider. Often 
  the application service provider (example.com in our illustration) also sells smart objects. In that case 
  the entire communication happens internal to the provider and no need for interoperability arises. Still, it is
  useful for example.com to re-use existing specifications to lower the design, implementation, testing and
  development effort.
  </t> 

  <t>While this pattern allows using IP-based communication end-to-end it may still lead to silos. To prevent silos,
  example.com may allow third party device vendors to connect to their server infrastructure as well. For those cases,
  the protocol interface used to communicate with the server infrastructure needs to be made available, and various
  standards are available, such as CoAP, DTLS <xref target="RFC6347"/>, UDP, IP, etc. as shown in
  <xref target="cloud"/>. A frequent concern from end users is that a change in the business model (or bankruptcy) 
  of the IoT device/service provide might make the hardware become unusable. Companies might consider the possibility
  to release their source code for the IoT device, or to allow other IoT operating systems (plus application software)
  to be installed on the IoT device.
  </t>

  <!-- Added following paragraph to address ticket 372 -->
  <t>Similarly, in many situations it is desirable to change which cloud service a device connects to, such
  as when an application service provider changes its hosting provider.  Again, standard Internet protocols
  are needed.
  </t>
  
  <t>Since the access networks to which various smart objects are connected are typically not under the control of
  the application service provider, commonly used radio technologies (such as WLAN, wired Ethernet, and cellular
  radio) together with the network access authentication technology have to be re-used. The same applies to standards
  used for IP address configuration. 
  </t> 

  <t>
    <figure anchor="cloud" title="Device-to-Cloud Communication Pattern">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
         .................                       
         |  Application  |                       
         |  Service      |                       
         |  Provider     |                       
         |  example.com  |                       
         |_______________|                       
             _,   .                              
  HTTP    ,'      `.        CoAP          
  TLS   _,'          `.     DTLS              
  TCP ,'               `._  UDP
  IP-'                    - IP                      
 ,'''''''''''''|       ,'''''''''''''''''|  
 | Device with |       | Device with     |  
 | Temperature |       | Carbon Monoxide |
 | Sensor      |       | Sensor          |       
 |.............'       |.................'               
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
  </t>
</section> 

<section title="Device-to-Gateway Communication Pattern"> 
  <t>The device-to-cloud communication pattern, described in <xref target="d2c"/>, is convenient for vendors of smart
  objects and works well if they choose a radio technology that is widely deployed in the targeted market, such as
  IEEE 802.11-based Wifi for smart home use cases. Sometimes less widely available radio technologies are needed (such
  as IEEE 802.15.4) or special application layer functionality (e.g., local authentication and authorization) has
  to be provided, or interoperability is needed with legacy, non-IP-based devices. In those cases some form of gateway has to be 
  introduced into the communication architecture that bridges
  between the different technologies and performs other networking and security
  functionality. <xref target="gateway"/> shows this pattern graphically. Often, these gateways are provided by the
  same vendor that offers the IoT product, for example because of the use of proprietary protocols, to lower the
  dependency on other vendors, or to avoid potential interoperability problems. It is expected that in the future
  more generic gateways will be deployed to lower cost and infrastructure complexity for end consumers, enterprises,
  and industrial environments.  Such generic gateways are more likely to exist if IoT device designs make use of generic Internet protocols and not require application layer gateways that translate one application layer protocol to another one. The use of application layer gateways will in general lead to a more fragile deployment, as it had been observed in the past already with RFC 3724 <xref target="RFC3724"/> and RFC 3238 <xref target="RFC3238"/>.</t>

  <t>This communication pattern can frequently be found with smart object deployments that require remote configuration 
  capabilities and real-time interactions. The gateway is thereby assumed to be always connected to the Internet.</t> 
  <t>
    <figure anchor="gateway" title="Device-to-Gateway Communication Pattern">
<artwork>
              <![CDATA[
             .................
             |  Application  |
             |  Service      |
             |  Provider     |
             |  example.com  |
             |_______________|
                    |
                    | 
                    | IPv4/IPv6
             .................
             |    Local      |
             |   Gateway     |
             |               |
             |_______________|
               _,         .                              
  HTTP      ,'              `.         CoAP          
  TLS     _,' Bluetooth Smart  `.      DTLS              
  TCP   ,'     IEEE 802.11       `._   UDP
  IPv6-'       IEEE 802.15.4         - IPv6/6lo                      
 ,'''''''''''''|          ,'''''''''''''''''|
 | Device with |          | Device with     |
 | Temperature |          | Carbon Monoxide |
 | Sensor      |          | Sensor          |
 |.............'          |.................'
]]></artwork>
   </figure>
  </t>

  <t>
  <!-- Replaced this with the next sentence, per ticket 375: 
  A variation of this model is the case where the gateway role is incorporated into a smartphone. Of 
  course, if the smartphone is not connected to smart objects, for example because the phone moved out of range, 
  they are not connected with the Internet anymore. 
    -->
  If the gateway is mobile, such as when the gateway is a smartphone, connectivity between the devices and
  the Internet may be intermittent.

  This limits the applicability of such a communication pattern but is 
  nevertheless very common with wearables and other IoT devices that do not need always-on Internet or real-time 
  Internet connectivity. From an interoperability point of view it is worth noting that smartphones with their 
  sophisticated software update mechanism via app stores allow new functionality to be updated regularly at the 
  smartphone and sometimes even at the IoT device. With special apps that are tailored to each specific IoT device 
  interoperability is mainly a concern with regard to the lower layers of the protocol stack, such as the radio 
  interface, and less so at the application layer (if users are willing to download a new app for each IoT device).</t>

  <t>It is also worth pointing out that a gateway allows supporting both IPv6 and IPv4 (for compatibility
  with legacy application service providers) externally, while allowing devices to be IPv6-only to reduce
  footprint requirements. If devices do not have the resources to support both IPv4 and IPv6 themselves,
  being IPv6-only (rather than IPv4-only) with a gateway enables the most flexibility, avoiding the
  need to update devices to support IPv6 later, whereas IPv4 address exhaustion makes it ill-suited to
  scale to smart object networks.  See <xref target="RFC6540"/> for further discussion.</t>
  
</section> 

<section title="Back-end Data Sharing Pattern"> 
  <t>The device-to-cloud pattern often leads to silos; IoT devices upload data only to a single application service
  provider. However, users often demand the ability to export and to analyze data in combination with data from other
  sources. Hence, the desire for granting access to the uploaded sensor data to third parties arises. This design is
  shown in <xref target="backend"/>. This pattern is known from the Web in case of mashups and is therefore re-applied
  to the smart object context. To offer familiarity for developers, typically a RESTful API design in combination
  with a federated authentication and authorization technology (like OAuth 2.0 <xref target="RFC6749"/>) is re-used. 
  While this offers re-use at the level of building blocks, the entire protocol stack (including the information/data model and RESTful Web APIs) is often not standardized.</t>

  <t>
          <figure anchor="backend" title="Backend Data Sharing Pattern">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
                                           .................
                                           |  Application  |
                                          .|  Service      |
                                       ,-` |  Provider     |
                                     .`    | b-example.com |
                                  ,-`      |_______________|
                                .`                          
          .................  ,-`   
          |  Application  |-` HTTPS
          |  Service      |   OAuth 2.0
          |  Provider     |   JSON
          |  example.com  |-,    
          |_______________|  '.            
               _,              `',                          
             ,'                   '.                      
          _,' CoAP or               `',    .................
        ,'   HTTP                      '.  |  Application  |
      -'                                 `'|  Service      |
   ,''''''''|                              |  Provider     |
   | Light  |                              | c-example.com |
   | Sensor |                              |_______________|
   |........'                                                                                                           
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
  </t>

</section> 

</section> 

<!-- /////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// --> 


<section anchor="reuse" title="Re-Use Internet Protocols">

   <t>When discussing the need for re-use of available standards vs. 
    extending or re-designing protocols, it is useful to look back at 
    the criteria for success of the Internet.</t>

    <t>RFC 1958 <xref target="RFC1958"/> provides lessons from the early days
    of the Internet and says:</t>
    
     <t>
     <list style="empty"> 
     <t>"The Internet and its architecture have grown in evolutionary 
        fashion from modest beginnings, rather than from a Grand Plan",
     </t>
     </list>
     </t>
     
     <t>and adds:</t>
     
     <t>
     <list style="empty">
     <t>"A good analogy for the development of the Internet is that of 
        constantly renewing the individual streets and buildings of a 
        city, rather than razing the city and rebuilding it."</t>
     </list> 
  </t>

  <t><!-- Due to network effects, the case for using the Internet Protocol(s)
    and other generic technology in smart object development is
    compelling. -->Yet because building very small, battery-powered
    devices is challenging, it may be difficult to resist
    the temptation to build solutions tailored to specific
    applications, or even to re-design networks from scratch to suit 
    a particular application. 
  </t>

  <t>While developing consensus-based standards in an open and
    transparent process takes longer than developing proprietary
    solutions, the resulting solutions often remain relevant over a
    longer period of time.</t>
     
  <t>RFC 1263 <xref target="RFC1263"/> considers protocol design strategy 
    and the decision to design new protocols or to use existing protocols 
    in a non-backward compatible way:
  </t>
  
  <t>
     <list style="empty"> 
     <t>"We hope to be
        able to design and distribute protocols in less time than it takes a
        standards committee to agree on an acceptable meeting time.  This is
        inevitable because the basic problem with networking is the
        standardization process. Over the last several years, there has been
        a push in the research community for lightweight protocols, when in
        fact what is needed are lightweight standards.  Also note that we
        have not proposed to implement some entirely new set of 'superior'
        communications protocols, we have simply proposed a system for making
        necessary changes to the existing protocol suites fast enough to keep
        up with the underlying change in the network.  In fact, the first
        standards organization that realizes that the primary impediment to
        standardization is poor logistical support will probably win."</t>
     </list> 
  </t>

  <t>While <xref target="RFC1263"/> 
    was written in 1991 when the standardization process was
    more lightweight than today, these thoughts remain relevant
    in smart object development. <!-- <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-post-standardization"/> <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-hourglass"/>.--> </t>
     
     
     <!-- We will discuss this topic in more detail later in this 
     document.
     <cref>DT: Much of this isn't specific to smart objects and might be
           better done in a generic document rather than hidden in one that's
           smart object specific.
           JA: See new section 1.
     </cref>

  <t>While RFC 1263 <xref target="RFC1263"/> certainly provides good food for 
     thought, it also gives recommendations that may not always be appropriate 
     for the smart object space, such as the preference for a so-called 
     evolutionary protocol design where new versions of the protocols are 
     allowed to be non-backwards compatible and all run independently on the 
     same device.  RFC 1263 adds: 
</t>
<t>
     <list style="empty"> 
     <t>"... the only real disadvantage of protocol evolution is the amount of
        memory required to run several versions of the same protocol.
        Fortunately, memory is not the scarcest resource in modern
        workstations (it may, however, be at a premium in the BSD kernel and
        its derivatives).  Since old versions may rarely if ever be executed,
        the old versions can be swapped out to disk with little performance
        loss.  Finally, since this cost is explicit, there is a huge incentive
        to eliminate old protocol versions from the network."
     </t>
     </list> 
  </t>

  <t>Even though it is common practice today to run many different software 
     applications that have similar functionality (for example, multiple 
     Instant Messaging clients) in parallel it may indeed not be the most preferred 
     approach for smart objects, which may have severe limitations regarding RAM,
     flash memory, and also power constraints.
     For example, a smart object that supports only one IP protocol (IPv4 or IPv6) may be preferred over one that
     supports both, at least from a complexity and cost point of view.
  </t>

  <t>To deal with exactly this problem, profiles have been suggested in many cases. Saying "no" 
     to a new protocol stack that only differs in minor ways may be appropriate 
     but could be interpreted as blocking innovation and, as 
     RFC 1263 <xref target="RFC1263"/> describes it nicely, 
     "In the long term, we envision protocols being designed on an application 
     by application basis, without the need for central approval." "Central 
     approval" here refers to the approval process that happens in a respective standards 
     developing organization.
  </t> 
 


  <t>Since many Internet protocols are used as building blocks by other
     organizations or in deployments that may have never been envisioned
     by the original designs, one can argue that this approach has
     been fairly successful.  It may, however, not lead to the level of
     interoperability many desire: they want interoperability of the entire
     system rather than interoperability at a specific protocol level.
     Consequently, an important architectural question arises, namely "What
     level of interoperability should Internet protocol engineers aim
     for?"
  </t>

  <t>In the diagrams below, we illustrate a few interoperability scenarios 
     with different interoperability needs.  Note that these are highly 
     simplified versions of what protocol architects are facing, 
     since there are often more parties involved in a sequence of required 
     protocol exchanges, and the entire protocol stack has to be 
     considered - not just a single protocol layer.  As such, the required coordination 
     and agreement between the different stakeholders is likely to be far 
     more challenging than illustrated.  We do, however, believe 
     that these figures illustrate that the desired level of interoperability 
     needs to be carefully chosen.
  </t>

--> 
  <t>Interestingly, a large number of already standardized protocols are relevant 
    for smart object deployments. RFC 6272  <xref target="RFC6272"/>, for example, 
    made the attempt to identify relevant IETF specifications for use in smart 
    grids.</t>

<!-- 
  <t>Of course, there are also many protocols that are unlikely to be
  needed or even suitable for the smart object environments. For
  instance, it would difficult to imagine inter-domain routing being a
  necessary feature in these objects; there are other devices in the
  network that would normally be responsible for this
  functionality. But the wide range of protocols listed in RFC 6272
  illustrates the view of the IETF about how readily Internet technology
  can be used in these applications, and indeed Internet communications
  have been incorporated into various smart object deployments.</t>
--> 
  <t>Still, many commercial products contain proprietary or industry-specific 
    protocol mechanisms and researchers have made several attempts to design 
    new architectures for the entire Internet system. There are several 
    architectural concerns that deserve to be highlighted:

  <list style="hanging">

  <t hangText="Vertical Profiles"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The discussions at the IAB
     workshop (see Section 3.1.2 of <xref target="RFC6574"/>) revealed the 
     preference of many participants to develop domain-specific profiles that 
     select a minimum subset of protocols needed for a specific operating 
     environment.  Various standardization organizations and industry fora 
     are currently engaged in activities of defining their preferred 
     profile(s).  Ultimately, however, the number of domains 
     where smart objects can be used is essentially unbounded. There is also
     an ever-evolving set of protocols and protocol extensions. <!-- Profiles, particularly, 
     full-stack profiles are common, for instance, in areas where existing legacy technology is being migrated to
     IP.--> 

     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     However, merely changing the networking protocol to IP does not
     necessarily bring the kinds of benefits that industries are
     looking for in their evolving smart object deployments. In particular,
     a profile is rigid, and leaves little room for interoperability among
     slightly differing, or competing technology variations. As an example,
     layer 1 through 7 type profiles do not account for the possibility that
     some devices may use different physical media than others, and that in such
     situations a simple router could still provide an ability to communicate
     between the parties.</t>

  <t hangText="Industry-Specific Solutions"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The Internet Protocol suite is more extensive than merely the use of
     IP. Often significant benefits can be gained from using additional, widely
     available, generic technologies, such as the Web. Benefits from using
     these kinds of tools include access to a large available workforce, 
     software, and education already geared towards employing the technology.</t>

  <t hangText="Tight Coupling"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
     Many applications are built around a specific set of servers, devices,
     and users. However, often the same data and devices could be useful for
     many purposes, some of which may not be easily identifiable at the time
     the devices are deployed.</t>

  </list></t>

  <t>In addition to the architectural concerns, developing new protocols
  and mechanisms is generally more risky and expensive than reusing
  existing standards, due to the additional costs involved in design,
  implementation, testing, and deployment. Secondary costs, such as training of technical staff and, in the worst case, training of end users, can be substantial. 
  
  </t>

  <t>As a result, 
  <!-- the following recommendations can be made. First, -->
  while there are some cases where specific solutions are needed, the
  benefits of general-purpose technology are often compelling, be it
  choosing IP over some more specific communication mechanism, a
  widely deployed link-layer (such as wireless LAN) over a more
  specific one, web technology over application specific protocols,
  and so on.</t>

  <t>However, when employing these technologies, it is important to
  embrace them in their entirety, allowing for the architectural
  flexibility that is built into them.  As an example, it rarely makes
  sense to limit communications to on-link or to specific media.
  Design your applications so that the participating devices can 
  easily interact with multiple other applications.</t>

</section>

<!-- /////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// --> 


<section anchor="deployed" title="The Deployed Internet Matters"> 

  <t>Despite the applicability of the Internet Protocols for smart
  objects, picking the specific protocols for a particular use case
  can be tricky.  As the Internet has evolved, certain
  protocols and protocol extensions have become the norm and others
  have become difficult to use in all circumstances.</t>

  <t>Taking into account these constraints is particularly important
  for smart objects, as there is often a desire to employ specific
  features to support smart object communication. For instance, from a
  pure protocol specification perspective, some transport protocols
  may be more desirable than others.  These constraints apply both to
  the use of existing protocols as well as designing new ones on top
  of the Internet Protocol stack.</t>

  <t>The following list illustrates a few of those constraints, 
    but every communication protocol comes with its own challenges.</t>
 
  <t>In 2005, Fonseca, et al. <xref target="IPoptions"/> studied the usage of IP 
        options-enabled packets in the Internet and found that overall, 
        approximately half of Internet paths drop packets with options, 
        making extensions using IP options "less ideal" for extending IP.
  </t>

  <t>In 2010, Honda, et al. <xref target="HomeGateway"/> tested 34 different home gateways 
        regarding their packet dropping policy of UDP, TCP, DCCP, SCTP, ICMP, 
        and various timeout behavior.  For example, more than half of the 
        tested devices do not conform to the IETF recommended timeouts for 
        UDP, and for TCP the measured timeouts are highly variable, ranging 
        from less than 4 minutes to longer than 25 hours.  For NAT traversal 
        of DCCP and SCTP, the situation is poor.  None of the tested devices,
        for example, allowed establishing a DCCP connection.
  </t>

  <t>In 2011, <xref target="TCPextensions"/> tested the behavior of 
        networks with regard to various TCP extensions: "From our results 
        we conclude the middleboxes implementing layer 4 functionality are 
        very common -- at least 25% of paths interfered with TCP in some 
        way beyond basic firewalling."
  </t>

<!-- 
  <t>As it can be seen from the examples above the question about extensibility 
     and incremental deployment is not only about how well protocol developers 
     anticipate future use cases.  In fact, the IAB publication RFC 5218 on 
     "What Makes For a Successful Protocol?" <xref target="RFC5218"/> defines 
     the ultimate goal to develop protocols that are deployed beyond their 
     envisioned use cases.
  </t> 
--> 

  <t>Extending protocols to fulfill new uses and to add new functionality may 
     range from very easy to difficult, as <xref target="RFC6709"/> explains 
     in great detail.  A challenge many protocol designers are facing is to ensure 
     incremental deployability and interoperability with incumbent elements in 
     a number of areas.  In various cases, the effort it takes to design 
     incrementally deployable protocols has not been taken seriously enough at 
     the outset. RFC 5218 on "What Makes For a Successful Protocol?" 
     <xref target="RFC5218"/> defines wildly successful protocols as protocols 
     that are widely deployed beyond their envisioned use cases.
  </t>

  <t>As these examples illustrate, protocol architects have to take 
     developments in the greater Internet into account, as not all features 
     can be expected to be usable in all environments.  For instance, 
     middleboxes <xref target="RFC3234"/> complicate the use of extensions 
     in the basic IP protocols and transport-layers.
  </t>   

  <t>RFC 1958 <xref target="RFC1958"/> considers this aspect and says "... the 
     community believes that the goal is connectivity, the tool is the Internet 
     Protocol, and the intelligence is end to end rather than hidden in the 
     network."  This statement is challenged more than ever with the perceived
     need to develop intermediaries interacting with less intelligent end devices.
     However, RFC 3724 <xref target="RFC3724"/> has this to say about this 
     crucial aspect: "One desirable consequence of the end-to-end principle 
     is protection of innovation.  Requiring modification in the network in 
     order to deploy new services is still typically more difficult than 
     modifying end nodes." Even this statement will become challenged, as 
     large numbers of devices are deployed and it indeed might be the case
     that changing those devices is hard. But RFC 4924 <xref target="RFC4924"/> 
     adds that a network that does not filter or transform the data that it 
     carries may be said to be "transparent" or "oblivious" to the content 
     of packets.  Networks that provide oblivious transport enable the 
     deployment of new services without requiring changes to the core.  It 
     is this flexibility that is perhaps both the Internet's most essential 
     characteristic as well as one of the most important contributors to 
     its success.
  </t>

</section> 

<!-- /////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// --> 

<section anchor="change" title="Design for Change">
  <t>How to embrace rapid innovation and at the same time accomplish a high 
    level of interoperability is one of the key aspects for competing in the 
    market place. RFC 1263 <xref target="RFC1263"/> points out that 
    "protocol change happens and is currently happening at a very respectable 
    clip. We simply propose [for engineers developing the technology] to 
    explicitly deal with the changes rather keep trying to hold back the 
    flood.".</t>

  <t>In <xref target="Tussels"/> Clark, et al. suggest to "design for variation 
    in outcome, so that the outcome can be different in different places, and 
    the tussle takes place within the design, not by distorting or violating it.  
    Do not design so as to dictate the outcome.  Rigid designs will be broken; 
    designs that permit variation will flex under pressure and survive.". The 
    term tussle refers to the process whereby different parties, which are part 
    of the Internet milieu and have interests that may be adverse to each other, 
    adapt their mix of mechanisms to try to achieve their conflicting goals, and 
    others respond by adapting the mechanisms to push back.</t>

   <t>In order to accomplish this, Clark, et al. suggest to 
     <list style="numbers"> 
        <t>Break complex systems into modular parts, so that
          one tussle does not spill over and distort unrelated
          issues.</t>
        <t>Design for choice to permit the different players to
          express their preferences. Choice often requires open interfaces.</t>
     </list> 
  </t>

<!--  <t>These are valid guidelines, and many protocols standardized in the 
     IETF have taken exactly this approach, namely to identify building 
     blocks that can be used in a wide variety of deployments providing 
     modularity and offer choice for those who deploy. Others then put 
     the building blocks together in a way that suits their 
     needs and business goals.</t> 
--> 
  <t>The main challenge with the suggested approach is to predict how 
    conflicts among the different players will evolve. Since tussles 
    evolve over time, there will be changes to the architecture too. 
    It is certainly difficult to pick the right set of building blocks 
    and to develop a communication architecture that will last a long 
    time, and many smart object deployments are envisioned to be rather
    long-lived.</t>
  <t>Luckily, the design of the system does not need to be cast in 
    stone during the design phase. It may adjust dynamically since many 
    of the protocols allow for configurability and dynamic discovery. 
    But ultimately software update mechanisms may provide the flexibility
    needed to deal with more substantial changes. </t>
<!-- 
    re are, however, limits to this approach.  Certain 
     building blocks are only useful in a limited set of architectural 
     variants and producing generic building blocks requires a good 
     understanding of different deployment strategies. Generic designs
     often make it hard to optimize. Sometimes the value of an individual 
     building block is hard for others to understand without providing 
     the larger context, which requires at least to illustrate one 
     deployment variant that comes with a specific architectural setup.  
     That said, it is also critical to consider systemic interdependencies 
     between the set of elements that constitute a system, or else they 
     impose constraints that weren't envisioned at the outset.
  </t>

  <t>To "design for varation in outcome", as postulated by <xref
     target="Tussels"/>, 
     </t>--> 
  
  <t>A solid software update mechanism is needed not only for dealing 
     with the changing Internet communication environment and for 
     interoperability improvements but also for adding new features and 
     for fixing security bugs. This approach may appear to be in conflict 
     with classes of severely restricted devices since, in addition to a 
     software update mechanism, spare flash and RAM capacity is needed. 
     It is, however, a tradeoff worth thinking about since better product
     support comes with a price.</t>
     
 <t>As technology keeps advancing, the constraints that the technology
 places on devices evolve as well. Microelectronics became more
 capable as time goes by, often making it possible for new
 devices to be both less expensive and more capable than their
 predecessors. This trend can, however, be in some cases offset by the
 desire to embed communications technology in even smaller and cheaper
 objects. But it is important to design communications technology not
 just for today's constraints, but also tomorrow's. This is particularly important 
 since the cost of a product is not only determined by the cost of hardware but also by the cost of  
not reusing already available protocol stacks and software library by developing custom solutions.
</t>

     <t>Software updates are common in operating systems and application 
      programs today. Without them, most devices would pose a latent 
      risk to the Internet at large. Arguably, the JavaScript-based web 
      employs a very rapid software update mechanism with code being
      provided by many different parties (e.g., by websites loaded into
      the browser or by smartphone apps).</t>

</section> 

<!-- /////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// --> 


<!-- DT 7/3/12: Commented this out because it is not needed when we have
                Table of Contents.  Prior to my edit here, it was half-commented
                out so that it only covered the latter half of the doc anyway.

  <t>The rest of this document is structured as follows.  <xref
     target="related"/> points to related work on this topic. <xref
     target="issues"/> discusses the architectural challenges. <xref
     target="issue-internet"/> highlights the desire to integrate smart
     object networks with Internet technology, <xref
     target="issue-interop"/> discusses the different models of
     interoperability, and <xref target="issue-standards"/> discusses the
     varying approaches to standardization of smart object networking
     technology.  Finally, <xref target="recs"/> provides some
     recommendations from the IAB on how to approach these challenges,
     <xref target="SecurityConsiderations"/> discusses general security issues,
     and privacy issues are discussed in <xref
     target="PrivacyConsiderations"/>.
  </t>

  <t>The
  document is being discussed at
  https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/architecture-discuss.</t>
-->


<!-- 

  <t>The rest of the document is organized as follows. <xref
  target="gen"/> discusses the problems associated with vertically
  integrated industry-specific solutions, and motivates the use of
  generic technologies and a more flexible architecture as a way to
  reduce these problems. <xref target="re-use"/> discusses the
  problems associated with attempting to use options and communication
  patterns other than those in current widespread use in the
  Internet. Often middleboxes and assumptions built into existing
  devices makes such usage problematic. <xref target="issue-interop"/>
  discusses different levels of interoperability, and the different
  level of effort required to achieve them. Finally, <xref
  target="SecurityConsiderations"/> presents some of the relevant
  security issues, <xref target="PrivacyConsiderations"/> discusses
  privacy, and <xref target="Summary"/> summarizes the
  recommendations.</t>
--> 

<!-- /////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// --> 


<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="SecurityConsiderations" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>Security is often even more important for smart objects than for more
     traditional computing systems, since interacting directly with the physical
     world can present greater dangers and smart objects often operate autonomously without any human interaction for a long time period.   The problem is compounded by the fact
     that there are often fewer resources available in constrained devices to
     actually implement security (e.g., see the discussion of "Class 0 devices" in Section 3 of
     <xref target="RFC7228"/>).  As such, it is critical to design for security,
     taking into account a number of key considerations:

     <list style="symbols"> 
     <t>A key part of any smart object design is the problem of how to establish trust
        for a smart object.  Typically, bootstrapping trust involves giving the device the credentials it needs
        to operate within a larger network of devices or services.
     </t>
     <t>Smart objects will in many cases be deployed in places where additional
        physical security is difficult or impossible.  Designers should
        take into account that any such device can and will be compromised by an attacker with direct
        physical access.  Thus, trust models should distinguish between devices
        susceptible to physical compromise and devices with some level of
        physical security. Physical attacks, such as timing, power analysis, and glitching, are commonly applied to extract secrets <xref target="PhysicalAttacks"/>. 
     </t>
     <t>Smart objects will in many cases be deployed as collections of identical or
        near identical devices.  Protocols should be designed so that a compromise
        of a single device does not result in compromise of the entire collection,
        especially since the compromise of a large number of devices can enable
        additional attacks such as a distributed denial of service.
		Sharing secret keys across an entire product family is therefore also problematic 
		since compromise of a single device might leave all devices from that product family 
		vulnerable. 			
     </t>
     <t>Smart objects will in many cases be deployed in ways that the designer
        never considered.  Designers should either seek to minimize the impact of misuse of their systems 
        and devices, or implement controls to prevent such misuse where applicable.
     </t>
     <t>It is anticipated that smart objects will be deployed with a long (e.g., 5-40 years) life-cycle.
        Any security mechanism chosen at the outset may not be "good enough" for the full lifespan of the device.
        Thus, long-lived devices should start with good security and provide a path to deploy
        new security mechanisms over the lifetime of the device.
     </t>
	 <t>Security protocols often rely on random numbers and offering randomness in embedded devices is challenging. For this reason, it is important to consider the use of hardware-based random number generators during early states of the design process. </t>
     </list> 
  </t>

  <t>A more detailed security discussion can be found in the report from 
     the "Smart Object Security" workshop <xref target="I-D.gilger-smart-object-security-workshop"/> that was
     held prior to the IETF meeting in Paris, March 2012, and in the report from the
     National Science Foundation's "Cybersecurity Ideas Lab" workshop <xref target="NSF"/>
     that was held in February 2014.
     For example, <xref target="NSF"/> includes, among other recommendations,
     these recommendations specific to the Internet of Things:
     <list style="empty"> 
     <t>"Enhance the Security of the Internet of Things by Identifying Enclaves:
        The security challenges posed by the emerging Internet of Things should be
        addressed now, to prepare before it is fully upon us. By identifying specific
        use segments, or enclaves, Internet of Things infrastructure stakeholders can
        address the security requirements and devise event remediations for that
        enclave."
     </t>
     <t>"Create a Framework for Managing Software Updates:
        The Internet of Things will challenge our current channels for distributing
        security updates. An environment must be developed for distributing security
        patches that scales to a world where almost everything is connected to the
        Internet and many things are largely unattended."
     </t> 
     </list> 
  </t>

  <t>Finally, we reiterate that use of standards that have gotten wide review can often avoid a number
     of security issues that could otherwise arise.
     Section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC6574"/> reminds us about the IETF 
     work style regarding security: 

     <list style="empty"> 
     <t>"In the development of smart object applications, as with any other
        protocol application solution, security must be considered early in
        the design process.  As such, the recommendations currently provided
        to IETF protocol architects, such as RFC 3552 <xref target="RFC3552"/>,
        and RFC 4101 <xref target="RFC4101"/>, apply also to the smart object 
        space."
     </t> 
     </list> 
  </t> 
   
  <t>In the IETF, security functionality is incorporated into each 
     <!-- DT 7/3/12: removed since it's not true that every protocol includes
                     security functionality.
     and every --> 
     protocol as appropriate, to deal with threats that are specific to 
     them.  It is extremely unlikely that there is a one-size-fits-all 
     security solution given the large number of choices for the 'right' 
     protocol architecture (particularly at the application layer).  For 
     this purpose, <xref target="RFC6272"/> offers a survey of IETF 
     security mechanisms instead of suggesting a preferred one.
  </t> 
    <!--
      As current attacks against embedded systems demonstrate, many of the security vulnerabilities are quite basic and 
      remind us about the lessons we should have learned by at least the late 90's: software has to be tested properly,
      it has to be shipped with a secure default configuration (which includes no default accounts, no debugging
      interfaces enabled, etc.), and software and processes need to be available to provide updates. While these aspects
      are typically outside the realm of standardization, they are nevertheless important.</t>
     -->
</section>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="PrivacyConsiderations" title="Privacy Considerations">

<t>This document mainly focuses on an engineering audience, i.e., those 
  who are designing smart object protocols and architecture. Since there is 
  no value-free design, privacy-related decisions also have to be made, even 
  if they are just implicit in the re-use of certain technologies. RFC 6973 
  <xref target="RFC6973"/> and the threat model in 
  <xref target="I-D.iab-privsec-confidentiality-threat"/>
  were written as guidance specifically for that 
  audience and are also applicable to the smart object context.</t> 

<t>For those looking at privacy from a deployment point of view, the following 
  additional guidelines are suggested: 

     <list style="hanging"> 

     <t hangText="Transparency:"> Transparency of data collection and processing
     is key to avoid unpleasant surprises for owners and users of smart objects.  
     Users and impacted parties must be put in a position 
     to understand what items of personal data concerning them are collected and
     stored, as well for what purposes they are sought.
     </t>

     <t hangText="Data Collection/Use Limitation:">Smart objects should only store personal 
        data that is adequate, relevant and not excessive in relation 
        to the purpose(s) for which they are processed.  The use of 
        anonymized data should be preferred wherever possible.
     </t>

     <t hangText="Data Access:">Before deployment starts, it is necessary 
        to consider who can access personal data collected by smart 
        objects and under which conditions.  Appropriate and clear 
        procedures should be established in order to allow data subjects 
        to properly exercise their rights. 
     </t>

     <t hangText="Data Security: ">
        Standardized data security measures to prevent unlawful access, 
        alteration or loss of smart object data need to be defined and 
        deployed. Robust cryptographic techniques and proper 
        authentication frameworks have to be used to limit the risk of 
        unintended data transfers or unauthorized access.
     </t>
     </list> 
  </t> 
 <t>
 A more detailed treatment of privacy considerations that extend beyond engineering can be found in a publication from the Article 29 Working Party <xref target="WP223"/>. </t>
</section>

    
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
</section>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
    
<section title="Acknowledgements">
  <t>We would like to thank the participants of the IAB Smart Object 
     workshop for their input to the overall discussion about smart 
     objects.
  </t>
  <t>Furthermore, we would like to thank Mike St. Johns, Jan Holler, Patrick Wetterwald, Atte Lansisalmi, Hannu Flinck, 
     Bernard Aboba, Markku Tuohino, Wes George, Robert Sparks, S. Moonsesamy, Dave Crocker, and Steve Crocker
     in particular for their review comments.
  </t>
  <!-- It is custom to not acknowledge IAB members, since their names are already on the document
       in the IAB Members section.  Prior to adding the "IAB Members" section, Joel Halpern and
       Mary Barnes were acknowledged.
    -->
</section>

<section title="IAB Members at the Time of This Writing">
  <figure>
    <artwork>
Jari Arkko
Mary Barnes
Marc Blanchet
Joel Halpern
Ted Hardie
Joe Hildebrand
Russ Housley
Eliot Lear
Xing Li
Erik Nordmark
Andrew Sullivan
Dave Thaler
Brian Trammell
    </artwork>
  </figure>
</section>

  </middle>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
  <back>

<!-- DT: this document really has no Normative references. JA: Done.
    <references title="Normative References"> 
    </references> 
-->
    
    <references title="Informative References"> 
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6574"?>
        <!--  <?rfc include="reference.I-D.tschofenig-post-standardization"?> --> 
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6709"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6973"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1263"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6272"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1958"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4924"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3234"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5218"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3552"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4101"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3724"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6540"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3238"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3444"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7228"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7252"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>
<!--          <?rfc include="reference.I-D.arkko-core-sleepy-sensors"?> 

         <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-core-coap"?>
         <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-lwig-guidance"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.tschofenig-hourglass"?> 
         <?rfc include="reference.I-D.jennings-senml"?>--> 
		 <?rfc include="reference.I-D.gilger-smart-object-security-workshop"?>
		 <?rfc include="reference.I-D.iab-privsec-confidentiality-threat"?>
		 
		 <reference anchor="PhysicalAttacks">
        <front>
          <title>A Tutorial on Physical Security and Side-Channel Attacks, in Foundations of Security Analysis and Design III: FOSAD 2004/2005 Tutorial Lectures, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 3655, pp 78-108</title>
            <author initials="F." surname="Koeune" fullname="F. Koeune">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="F.-X." surname="Standaert" fullname="F.-X. Standaert">
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date month="September" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
        target='http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007%2F11554578_3' />
      </reference>
      
    <reference anchor="WP223">
        <front>
          <title>Opinion 8/2014 on the on  Recent Developments on the Internet of Things</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Article 29 Working Party</organization>
            </author>
          <date month="September" year="2014"/>
        </front>
        <format type='PDF'
        target='http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/article-29/documentation/opinion-recommendation/files/2014/wp223_en.pdf' />
      </reference>
		 
      <reference anchor="IPoptions">
        <front>
          <title>IP options are not an option, Technical Report UCB/EECS</title>
            <author initials="R." surname="Fonseca" fullname="R. Fonseca">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="G." surname="Porter" fullname="G. Porter">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Katz" fullname="R. Katz">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="S." surname="Shenker" fullname="S. Shenker">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="I." surname="Stoica" fullname="I. Stoica">
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
        target='http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.123.4251' />
      </reference>
      
      <!-- 
         <reference anchor="Laws">
        <front>
          <title>The 10 Laws of Smart Object Security Design, In Proc. of IAB Workshop on 'Interconnecting Smart Objects with the Internet', Prague, Czech Repulic</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="Bernard Aboba">
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date month="March" year="2011"/>
        </front>
        <format type='PDF'
        target='http://www.iab.org/wp-content/IAB-uploads/2011/03/Tschofenig.pdf' />
      </reference>
      --> 
      <reference anchor="TCPextensions">
        <front>
          <title>Is it Still Possible to Extend TCP? In Proc. ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), Berlin, Germany</title>
            <author initials="M." surname="Honda" fullname="M. Honda">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="Y." surname="Nishida" fullname="Y. Nishida">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Greenhalgh" fullname="A. Greenhalgh">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="M." surname="Handley" fullname="M. Handley">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="H." surname="Tokuda" fullname="H. Tokuda">
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date month="Nov" year="2011"/>
        </front>
        <format type='PDF'
        target='http://conferences.sigcomm.org/imc/2011/docs/p181.pdf' />
      </reference>
      
      <!-- 
      
      <reference anchor="eLua">
        <front>
          <title>Embedded Lua Project</title>
            <author>
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
        target='http://www.eluaproject.net/' />
      </reference>

      --> 
      <reference anchor="HomeGateway">
        <front>
          <title>An experimental study of home gateway characteristics, In Proceedings of the '10th annual conference on Internet measurement'</title>
            <author initials="L." surname="Eggert" fullname="Lars Eggert">
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <format type='PDF'
        target='http://eggert.org/papers/2010-imc-hgw-study.pdf' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Gamma">
        <front>
          <title>Design Patterns: Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented Software</title>
          <author initials="E." surname="Gamma" fullname="Erich Gamma">
              <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="1995"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NSF">
        <front>
          <title>Interdisciplinary Pathwards towards a More Secure Internet: A report on the NSF-sponsored
                 Cybersecurity Ideas Lab held in Arlington, Virginia on February 10-12, 2014</title>
          <author initials="" surname="" fullname="">
              <organization>National Science Foundation</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2014"/>
        </front>
        <format type='PDF'
        target='http://www.nsf.gov/cise/news/CybersecurityIdeasLab_July2014.pdf' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Tussels">
        <front>
          <title>Tussle in Cyberspace: Defining Tomorrow's Internet, In
              Proc. ACM SIGCOMM</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="Clark" fullname="D. Clark">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Wroslawski" fullname="J. Wroslawski">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="K." surname="Sollins" fullname="K. Sollins">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Braden" fullname="R. Braden">
              <organization/>
            </author>
          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
        target='http://www.acm.org/sigcomm/sigcomm2002/papers/tussle.html' />
      </reference>

      <!-- 
      <reference anchor="OECD">
        <front>
          <title>OECD Guidelines on the Protection of Privacy and Transborder Flows of Personal Data</title>
          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1980"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="available at (September 2010)"
          value=", http://www.oecd.org/EN/document/0,,EN-document-0-nodirectorate-no-24-10255-0,00.html"/>
        <format target="http://www.oecd.org/EN/document/0,,EN-document-0-nodirectorate-no-24-10255-0,00.html" type="HTML"/>
      </reference>
      --> 

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
