<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.36 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc text-list-symbols="-o*+"?>
<?rfc docmapping="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-moore-iot-security-bcp-00.txt" category="bcp">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IoT Security BCP">Best Current Practices for Securing Internet of Things (IoT) Devices</title>

<author fullname="Keith Moore" initials="K." surname="Moore">
<organization></organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>moore@network-heretics.com</email>
</address>
</author>


    <author initials="R." surname="Barnes" fullname="Richard Barnes">
      <organization>Mozilla</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rbarnes@mozilla.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>ARM Limited</organization>
      <address>
        <email>hannes.tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft, Security, Internet of Things</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>Vendors of embedded devices have started to connect their devices to the Internet and the weak security of those devices has been a challenge for the Internet infrastructure. This document lists a number of minimum requirements vendors of Internet of Things (IoT) devices need to take into account before selling those devices to avoid security problems or, in case of security incidents, to have ways to mitigate them.</t> 


 
    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>The weak security of Internet of Things devices has resulted in many press releases 
over the last few years and unfortunately very few lessons have been learned from those 
incidents. The rate at which IoT devices get compromised is increasing and the event of 
distributed denial of service attacks illustrated that not only users of IoT devices 
and their data is at risk but also the wider Internet infrastructure itself. This document 
aims to recommend a small number of minimum security requirements to avoid security 
problems. 
</t> 

<t>The scope of these recommendations is as follows: 

<list style="symbols"> 

<t>These measures described in this document are intended to impede network-based attacks.
Other kinds of attacks, e.g. those requiring physical access to the device, are generally 
not considered in these requirements. The requirements do, however, reduce the implications 
of such physical attacks.</t> 

<t>In principle these requirements apply to all hosts that connect to the
   Internet, but this list of requirements is
   specifically targeted at devices that are constrained in their capabilities, more
   than general-purpose programmable hosts (PCs, servers, laptops,
   tablets, etc.), routers, middleboxes, etc. While this is a fuzzy boundary it reflects 
   the current understanding of IoT. A more detailed treatment of some of the constraints 
   of IoT devices can be found in [[RFC of LWIG terminology]].</t> 

<t>These are MINIMUM requirements that apply to all devices. They are
   unlikely to be sufficient by themselves, to ensure security of hosts
   from attack. Because IoT devices are used in a large number of different domains with 
   different needs device will have its own unique security
   considerations. It is not feasible to completely list all security
   requirements in a document such as this. Vendors will have to do their threat assessment 
   to determine which additional security considerations are applicable for use in a given 
   application domain.</t> 

<t>It is expected that this list of requirements will be revised from time
   to time as new threats are identified and/or new security techniques
   become feasible.</t>

<t>A companion document may be produced with suggestions for design choices
   and implementations that may aid in meeting these requirements. This document does not 
   make recommendations for solutions.</t> 

</list> 
</t> 

<t>We expect that many of the requirements can easily be met by the largest majority 
of vendors but may require additional documentation and transparency of those 
practices to improve crediability of their security practices in the market place.</t> 

</section> 

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

<t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”,
“SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “NOT RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this
document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

</section> 

<section title="Credentials"> 

<t>Vendors MUST provision devices with credentials either during manufacturing 
or to let those credentials be provisioned by humans at the time when those are 
deployed.</t> 

<t>Each devices MUST be provisioned with a unique credential. These credentials 
MUST be sufficiently strong and contain high entrophy inline with state-of-the-art 
crypto recommendations.</t> 
 
<t>Note: An entire product family of devices MAY share the same vendor credentials 
for attestation purposes in addition to a unique device credential.</t> 
 
<section title="Firmware Update"> 

<t>Vendors MUST offer an automatic firmware update mechanism. A discussion about 
the firmware update mechanisms can be found in [[I-D.iab-iotsu-report]]. 
The firmware update mechanism may require consent from the user if features are changed
in addition to bug fixes. To prevent widespread simultaneous failure of all instances of a
   particular kind of device due to a bug in a new firmware release,
   automatic firmware updates SHOULD be phased-in over a short time
   interval rather than updating all devices at once.
</t> 

<t>Devices SHOULD be configured to either poll the manufacturer's firmware update server 
at irregular intervals or use a push mechanism.</t> 

<t>Firmware updates MUST be authenticated; unauthenticated updates or updates where 
the authentication failes MUST be rejected.</t> 

</section> 

<section title="Bug Reporting"> 

<t>Vendors MUST provide an easy to find way for reporting of security bugs,
which is free of charge.</t> 

</section> 

<section title="Software Development Practices">

<t>Vendors are encouraged to use modern software development practices, including 
<list style="symbols"> 
<t>periodic checking of bug databases for reported security bugs associated
   with product</t>
<t>periodic checking of third party-provided source code for security bugs</t>
<t>periodic interaction with third parties where code is provided as a binary</t> 
</t> 

<t>All known security bugs MUST be fixed prior to shipping code.</t>

</section> 

<section title="Support Commitment"> 

<t>Vendors MUST be transparent about their commitment to supply devices 
with updates before selling products to their customers and what happens
with those devices after the support period finishes. </t> 

</section> 

<section title="Randomness"> 

<t>Vendors MUST include a solution for generating random numbers in their 
products. Randomness is an important component in security protocols and 
without such randomness many of today's security protocols offer weak 
or no security protection. The use of hardware-based random number 
generators SHOULD be preferred. </t> 

<t>A discussion about randomness can be found in [[RFC 4086]]. </t> 

</section> 

<section title="Operating Systems Concepts"> 

<t>Vendors SHOULD consider using (real-time) operating systems that offer 
memory compartmentalization techniques. Such mechanisms reduce the impact 
of a software bug, such as a buffer overflow vulnerability. Operating 
systems, or even software running bare metal, that do not provide such a
separation allow an attacker to gain access to the complete address space. 
While these concepts are available in hardware for a long time already they
often are not utilized by real-time operating systems.</t> 

<t>Vendors that do not make use of such features must document their design 
rational.</t> 

</section> 

<section title="Labeling"> 

<t>Vendors MUST have a manufacturer, model number and hardware
   revision numberlegibly printed on the device. This attempts to help 
   customers with bug reporting.</t> 

<t>There SHOULD be a documented means of querying a device for its
   firmware revision number via its network interface and/or via
   any manual input and display.</t> 

</section> 

<section title="Use of Standards"> 

<t>Designing cryptographic algorithms, and security protocols is known to be 
difficult and error prone. We strongly RECOMMEND that vendors make use of 
standardized security algorithms and protocols conforming with state-of-the-art 
key length recommendations. 

<t>Vendors MUST provide a way for crypto agility. The concept of crypto agility 
is described in [[CRYPTO-AGILITY]].</t> 

</section> 

<section title="Documentation">

<t>Vendors MUST offer documentation about their products so that security experts 
are able to assess the design choices. While such a document will not directly help
end customers since they will almost always lack the expertise to judge these 
design decisions but they help security experts to assess liability and independent 
third parties to compare products without spending an unproportional amount of time.</t> 

<t>This form of public documentation will help transparency similar to other 
documentation requirements found in other industries. It will also help to evolve
the best practices described in this document.</t> 
</section> 

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>This entire document is about security.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document does not contain any requests to IANA.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>Add acknowledgements here.</t>
</section>



  </middle>

  <back>


    <references title='Informative References'>



<reference anchor="SNMP-DDOS" target="https://www.bitag.org/documents/SNMP-Reflected-Amplification-DDoS-Attack-Mitigation.pdf">
  <front>
	<title>SNMP Reflected Amplification DDoS Attack Mitigation</title>

<author> <organization>BITAG</organization> </author>

	<date year="2012" month="August"/>
  </front>
</reference>



<reference anchor="DDOS-KREBS" target="http://arstechnica.com/security/2016/09/botnet-of-145k-cameras-reportedly-deliver-internets-biggest-ddos-ever/">
  <front>
	<title>Record-breaking DDoS reportedly delivered by >145k hacked cameras</title>

<author initials="D." surname="Goodin"> <organization></organization> </author>

	<date year="2016" month="September"/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>

