<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1964 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1964.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2203 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2203.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2743 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2743.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3748 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4462 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4462.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4422 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4282 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5056 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5056.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3645 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3645.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4072 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4072.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5801 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5801.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5849 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5849.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2904 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2904.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3579 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4017 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4017.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5106 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5106.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2138 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2138.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.nir-tls-eap SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nir-tls-eap.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-oauth-v2 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-v2.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.morris-privacy-considerations SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.morris-privacy-considerations.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology.xml">
<!ENTITY SAML20 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml2/reference.OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os.xml">
]>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-abfab-arch-00.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ABFAB Architecture">Application Bridging for Federated Access Beyond Web (ABFAB) Architecture</title>

    <author initials="J." surname="Howlett" fullname="Josh Howlett">
      <organization>JANET(UK)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Lumen House, Library Avenue, Harwell</street>
          <city>Oxford</city>
          <code>OX11 0SG</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+44 1235 822363</phone>
        <email>Josh.Howlett@ja.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Hartman" fullname="Sam Hartman">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> </street>
          <city> </city>
          <code> </code>
          <country> </country>
        </postal>
        <phone> </phone>
        <email>hartmans-ietf@mit.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Eliot Lear" initials="E." surname="Lear">
      <organization>Cisco Systems GmbH</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Richtistrasse 7</street>
          <city>Wallisellen</city>
          <code>CH-8304</code>
          <region>ZH</region>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+41 44 878 9200</phone>
        <email>lear@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>ABFAB</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>Federated Authentication</keyword>
    <keyword>AAA</keyword>
    <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
    <keyword>Diameter</keyword>
    <keyword>GSS-API</keyword>
    <keyword>EAP</keyword>
    <keyword>SASL</keyword>
    <abstract>
  <t>
    Over the last decade a substantial amount of work has occurred in
    the space of federated access management.  Most of
    this effort has focused on two use-cases: network and
    web-based access. However, the solutions to these use-cases that
    have been proposed and deployed tend to have few common building blocks in common.
  </t>
  <t>
    This memo describes an architecture that makes use of
    extensions to the commonly used security mechanisms for both federated and
    non-federated access management, including
    RADIUS, Diameter, GSS, GS2, EAP and SAML. The architecture addresses 
    the problem of federated access management to primarily non-web-based
    services, in a manner that will scale to large numbers of identity providers, relying parties, and 
    federations.
  </t>
</abstract>
</front>
<middle>
    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
  <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
    <t>
      The Internet uses numerous security mechanisms to manage
      access to various resources.  These mechanisms have been generalized
      and scaled over the last decade through mechanisms such as
      <xref target="RFC5801">SASL/GS2</xref>, <xref target="OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os">Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML)</xref>, 
      RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"/>, and Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      A Relying Party (RP) is the entity that manages access to some
      resource.  The actor that is requesting access to that resource
      is often described as the Subject.  Many security
      mechanisms are manifested as an exchange of information between
      these actors.  The RP is therefore able to decide whether
      the Subject is authorised, or not.  
    </t>
    <t>
      Some security mechanisms allow the RP to delegate aspects 
      of the access management decision to an actor called the
      Identity Provider (IdP).
      This delegation requires technical signalling, trust and a common understanding of
      semantics between the RP and IdP. These aspects are generally managed within a 
      relationship known as a 'federation'. This style of access management is accordingly
      described as 'federated access management'.
    </t>
    <t>
      Federated access management has evolved over
      the last decade through such standards as SAML <xref target="OASIS.saml-core-2.0-os"/>,
      <eref target="http://www.openid.net">OpenID</eref>, and OAuth <xref target="RFC5849"/>, <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/>. The benefits of federated access management include:
      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Single or Simplified sign-on:"> 
          <vspace blankLines="1"/> An Internet service can delegate access management, 
          and the associated responsibilities such as identity management and credentialing,
          to an organisation that already has a long-term relationship with the Subject.
          This is often attractive for Relying Parties who frequently do not want these responsibilities.
          The Subject may also therefore require fewer credentials, which is often desirable.
        </t>
	<t hangText="Privacy:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> 
	Often a Relying Party does not need to know the identity of a Subject to
          reach an access management decision. It is frequently only necessary for the
          Relying Party to establish, for example, that the Subject is affiliated with
          a particular organisation or has a certain role or entitlement. Sometimes the 
          RP does require an identifier for the Subject (for example, so that it can recognise
          the Subject subsequently); in this case, it is common practise for the IdP to only
          release a pseudonym that is specific to that particular Relying Party.
          Federated access management therefore provides various strategies for protecting
          the Subject's privacy. Other privacy aspects typically of concern are the policy for releasing 
          personal data about the Subjectfrom the IdP to the RP, the purpose of the usage, the retention period
          of the data, and many more. 
        </t>
        <t hangText="Provisioning"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
          Sometimes a Relying Party needs, or would like, to know more about
          a subject that an affiliation or pseudonym. For example, a Relying Party may want
          the Subject's email address or name. Some federated access management technologies 
          provide the ability for the IdP to provision this information, either on request by
          by the RP or unsolicited.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">

      <t>This document uses identity management and privacy
      terminology from
      <xref target="I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology"/>. 
      In particular, this document uses the terms pseudonymity, unlinkability, anonymity, and identity management.</t> 

      <t>We make one note about the IdP: in this architecture, the IdP
      consists of the following components: an EAP server, a radius
      server, and optionally a SAML Assertion service.  The IdP is
      also responsible for authentication, even though it may rely
      upon other components within a domain for such an operation.
      The reader is advised that for succinctness, in most cases the
      term IdP is used, except where additional clarity seems
      appropriate.
      </t>
    </section>

  <section title="An Overview of Federation">
    <t>
      In the previous section we introduced the following actors:
    </t>
    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>the Subject,</t>
        <t>the Identity Provider, and </t>
        <t>the Relying Party.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>
      These entities and their relationships are illustrated graphically in <xref
      target="framework"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      <figure title="General federation framework model" anchor="framework">
        <artwork><![CDATA[

 ,----------\                        ,---------\
 | Identity |       Federation       | Relying |
 | Provider +  <-------------------> + Party   |
 `----------'                        '---------'
         <                                
          \                              
           \ Identity                   
            \ management               
             \                         
              \                      
               \                    
                \  +------------+  
                 \ |            | 
                  v|  Subject   |
                   |            |
                   +------------+
                   ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>
      A federation typically this relationship encompasses
      operational specifications and legal rules:
    </t>
    <t>
      <list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Operational Specifications:"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        This includes the technical specifications (e.g. protocols used to communicate between the three parties), 
        process standards, policies, identity proofing, credential and authentication algorithm requirements, performance requirements, assessment and audit criteria, etc. The goal of these specifications to make the system work and to accomplish interoperability.</t>
        <t hangText="Legal Rules:"> <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        The legal rules take existing laws into consideration and provide contractual obligations to provide further clarification and define responsibilities. These legal rules regulate the operational specifications, make operational specifications legally binding to the participants, define and govern the rights and responsibilities of the participants. 
These legal rules may, for example, describe liability for losses, termination rights, enforcement mechanisms, measures of damage, dispute resolution, warranties, etc.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>
      The nature of federation dictates that there is some 
      form of relationship between the identity provider and the relying party.
      This is particularly important when the relying party wants to use 
      information obtained from the identity provider for access management
      decisions and when the identity provider does not want to release
      information to every relying party (or only under certain conditions).
    </t>
    <t>
      While it is possible to have a bilateral agreement between every
      IdP and every RP; on an Internet scale this setup requires the introduction of the
      multi-lateral federation concept, as the management of such pair-wise
      relationships would otherwise prove burdensome.
    </t>
    <t>
      While many of the non-technical aspects of federation, such as business practices and legal arrangements, are outside the
      scope of the IETF they still impact the architectural setup on how to ensure the dynamic establishment of trust.
    </t>
    <t>
      Some deployments are sometimes required to deploy complex technical
      infrastructure, including message routing intermediaries, to offer the 
      required technical functionality, while in other deployments those are missing.
    </t>
    <t>
      <xref target="framework"/> also shows the relationship between
      the IdP and the Subject. Often a real world entity is associated with the Subject; for example, a person
      or some software.
    </t>
    <t>
      The IdP will typically have a long-term relationship with the Subject. This relationship
      would typically involve the IdP positively identifying and credentialling the Subject
      (for example, at time of enrollment in the context of employment within an organisation).
      The relationship will often be instantiated within an agreement between the IdP and the
      Subject (for example, within an employment contract or terms of use that stipulates the
      appropriate use of credentials and so forth).
    </t>
    <t>
      While federation is often discussed within the context of relatively formal relationships, 
      such as between an enterprise and an employee or a government and a citizen, federation does
      not in any way require this; nor, indeed, does it require any particular level of formality.
      It is, for example, entirely compatible with a relationship between the IdP and Subject 
      that is only as weak as completing a web form and confirming the verification email.
    </t>
    <t>
      However, the nature and quality of the relationship between the Subject and the IdP is
      an important contributor to the level of trust that an RP may attribute to an
      assertion describing a Subject made by an IdP. This is sometimes described
      as the Level of Assurance.
    </t>
    <t>
      Similarly it is also important to note that, in the general case, there
      is no requirement of a long-term relationship betweem the RP and the Subject. This is a property
      of federation that yields many of its benefits. However, federation does not
      preclude the possibility relationship between the RP and the Subject,
      should needs dictate.
    </t>
    <t>
      Finally, it is important to reiterate that in some
      scenarios there might indeed be a human behind the device denoted as Subject and in other
      cases there is no human involved in the actual protocol execution.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Challenges to Contemporary Federation">
<!--      <t>
        JH: Much more content needed!
      </t>
-->      <t>
         As the number of such federated services has proliferated, however,
         the role of the individual has become ambiguous in certain
         circumstances.  For example, a school might provide online access to
         grades to a parent who is also a teacher.  She must
         clearly distinguish her role upon access.  After all, she is
         probably not allowed to edit her own child's grades.
       </t>
       <t>
         Similarly, as the number of federations proliferates, it becomes
         increasingly difficult to discover which identity provider a user is
         associated with.  This is true for both the web and non-web case,
         but particularly acute for the latter ans many non-web
         authentication systems are not semantically rich enough on their own
         to allow for such ambiguities.  For instance, in the case of an
         email provider, the use of SMTP and IMAP protocols does not on its
         own provide for a way to select a federation.  However, the building
         blocks do exist to add this functionality.
       </t>
    </section>

  <section title="An Overview of ABFAB-based Federation">
    <t>
      The previous section described the general model of federation, 
      and its the application of federated access management. This section provides
      a brief overview of ABFAB in the context of this model.
    </t>
    <t>
      The steps taken generally in an ABFAB federated authentication/authorization
      exchange are as follows:
    </t>
    <t>
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>Principal provides NAI to Application: Somehow the client is
           configured with at least the realm portion of 
           an NAI, which represents the IdP to be discovered.</t>
        <t>
          Authentication mechanism selection: this is the step necessary to
          indicate that the GSS-EAP SASL/GS2 mechanism will be used for
          authentication/authorization.
        </t>
        <t>
          Client Application provides NAI to RP: At the conclusion of mechanism
          selection the NAI must be provided to the RP for discovery.
        </t>
        <t>
          Discovery of federated IdP: 
          This is discussed in detail below.  Either the RP is configured with
          authorized IdPs, or it makes use of a federation proxy.
        </t>
        <t>
          Request from Relying Party to IdP: Once the RP knows who the IdP is,
          it or its agent will forward RADIUS 
          request that encapsulates a GSS/EAP access request to an IdP.  This
          may or may not contain a SAML request as a series of attributes.. At
          this stage, the RP will likely  have no idea who the principal is.
          The RP claims its identity to the IdP in AAA attributes, and
          it makes whatever SAML Attribute Requests through a
          AAA attribute. XXX- Check order of SAML attribute request.
        </t>
        <t>
          IdP informs the principal of which EAP method to use: The available
          and appropriate methods are discussed below in this memo.
        </t>
        <t>
          A bunch of EAP messages happen between the endpoints: Messages are
          exchanged between the principal and the IdP until a 
          result is determined.  The number and content of those messages will
          depend on the EAP method.  If the IdP is unable to authenticate the
          principal, the process concludes here.  As part of this process, the
          principal will, under protection of EAP, assert the identity of the
          RP to which it intends to authenticate.
        </t>
        <t>
          Successful Authentication: At the very least the IdP (its
          EAP server) and EAP peer / subject have authenticated one another.
          As a result 
          of this step, the subject and the IdP hold two cryptographic
          keys- a Master Session Key (MSK), and an Extended MSK (EMSK).  If the
          asserted identity of the RP by the principal matches the identity the
          RP itself asserted, there is some confidence that the RP is now
          authenticated to the IdP.
          </t>
          <t> 
          Local IdP Policy Check: At this stage, the IdP checks local policy to
          determine whether the RP and subject are authorized
          for a given transaction/service, and if so, what if any,
          attributes will be released to the RP.  Additional
          policy checks will likely have been made earlier just through the
          process of discovery.
          </t>
          <t>
          Response from the IdP to the Relying Party: Once the IdP has made a
          determination of whether and how to 
          authenticate or authorize the principal to the RP, it
          returns either a negative AAA result to the RP, or it
          returns a positive result to the RP, along with an optional
          set of AAA attributes associated with the principal that
          could include one or more SAML assertions.  In addition, an
          EAP MSK is returned to the subject.
          </t>
	  <t>RP Processes Results.  When the RP receives the result
	  from the IdP, it should have enough information to either
	  grant or refuse a resource access request.  It may have
	  information that leads it to make additional attribute
	  queries.  It may have information that associates the
	  principal with specific authorization identies.  It will
	  apply these results in an application-specific way.</t>
          <t>
          RP returns results to principal: Once the RP has a response it must inform
          the client application of 
          the result.  If all has gone well, all are authenticated, and the
          application proceeds with appropriate authorization levels.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    <t>
      An example communication flow is given below:
    </t>
    <t>
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
    Relying Party    Client App       IdP

       |              (1)             | Client App gets NAI (somehow)
       |               |              |
       |<-----(2)----->|              | Mechanism Selection
       |               |              |
       |<-----(3)-----<|              | NAI transmitted to RP
       |               |              |
       |<=====(4)====================>| Discovery
       |               |              |
       |>=====(5)====================>| Access request from RP to IdP
       |               |              |
       |               |< - - (6) - -<| EAP method to Principal
       |               |              |
       |               |< - - (7) - ->| EAP Exchange to authenticate
       |               |              | Principal
       |               |              |
       |               |           (8 & 9) Local Policy Check
       |               |              |
       |<====(10)====================<| IdP Assertion to RP
       |               |              |
       |               |              | (11) RP Processes results.
       |               |              |
       |>----(12)----->|              | Results to client app.



     ----- = Between Client App and RP
     ===== = Between RP and IdP
     - - - = Between Client App and IdP

]]>

        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
  </section>
<section title="Design Goals">
<t>Our key design goals are as follows:</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Each party of a transaction will be authenticated, and the
  principal will be authorized for access to a specific resource .</t>
<t>Means of authentication is decoupled so as to allow for multiple
  authentication methods.</t>
<t>Hence, the architecture requires no sharing of long term private
  keys.</t>
<t>The system will scale to large numbers of identity providers,
  relying parties, and users.</t>
<t>The system will be designed primarily for non-Web-based
  authentication.</t>
<t>The system will build upon existing standards, components, and
  operational practices.
</t>
</list>
</t>
      <t>Designing new three party authentication and authorization
        protocols is hard and frought with risk of cryptographic
        flaws. Achieving widespead deployment is even more
        difficult. A lot of attention on federated access has been devoted to the Web. This document instead
        focuses on a non-Web-based environment and focuses on those protocols where HTTP is not
        used. Despite the increased excitement for layering every protocol on top of HTTP there are
        still a number of protocols available that do not use HTTP-based transports. Many of these
        protocols are lacking a native authentication and authorization framework of the style shown in
          <xref target="framework"/>.</t>
</section>
<section title="Use of AAA">
      <t>Interestingly, for network access authentication the usage of the AAA framework with RADIUS
          <xref target="RFC2865"/> and Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/> was quite successful from a
        deployment point of view. To map the terminology used in <xref target="framework"/> to the
        AAA framework the IdP corresponds to the AAA server, the RP
        corresponds to the AAA client, and the technical building blocks of a federation are AAA proxies, relays
        and redirect agents
        (particularly if they are operated by third parties, such as AAA brokers and clearing
        houses). The front-end, i.e. the end host to AAA client communication, is in case of network
        access authentication offered by link layer protocols that forward authentication protocol
        exchanges back-and-forth.  An example of a large scale
          RADIUS-based federation
          is <eref target="http://www.eduroam.org">EDUROAM</eref>.</t>

      <t>Is it possible to design a system that builds on top of successful protocols to offer
        non-Web-based protocols with a solid starting point for authentication and authorization in
        a distributed system? </t>
</section>



    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
  </section>
    <section title="Architecture">


      <t><xref target="introduction"/> already introduced the federated access architecture, with the illustration
       of the different actors that need to interact, but it did not expand on the specifics of providing support for non-Web based applications. This section details this aspect and motivates
      design decisions. The main theme of the work described in this document is focused on re-using existing building blocks that have been deployed already and to re-arrange them in a novel way.</t>


      <t>
        Although this architecture assumes updates to both the relying party as well as to the end host for application integration, those changes
        are kept at a minimum.  A mechanism that can
        demonstrate deployment benefits (based on ease of update of existing
        software, low implementation effort, etc.)is preferred and there may be a need
        to specify multiple mechanisms to support the range of different
        deployment scenarios.
        </t>

      <t>There are a number of ways for encapsulating EAP into an application protocol. For ease of integration with a wide range of non-Web based application protocols the usage of the GSS-API was chosen. Encapsulating EAP into the GSS-API also allows EAP to be used in SASL. A description of the technical specification can be found in <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap"/>. Other alternatives exist as well and may be considered later, such as "TLS using EAP Authentication" <xref target="I-D.nir-tls-eap"/>.</t>
      <t>There are several architectural layers in the system; this section discusses the individual layers.</t>
      <section title="Federation Substrate">
	<t>The federation substrate is responsible for the connunication between the relying party and the identity provider. This layer is responsible for the inter-domain communication and for the technical mechanisms necessary to establish inter-domain trust.</t>
      <t>A key design goal is the re-use of an existing infrastructure,
      we build upon the AAA framework as utilized by RADIUS
      <xref target="RFC2138"/> and Diameter
      <xref target="RFC3588"/>. Since this document does not aim to
      re-describe the AAA framework the interested reader is referred
      to <xref target="RFC2904"/>. Building on the AAA infrastructure,
      and RADIUS and Diameter as protocols, modifications to that
      infrastructure is to be avoided. Also, modifications to AAA
      servers should be kept at a minimum.</t>

<t>The astute reader will notice that RADIUS and Diameter have
  substantially similar characteristics.  Why not pick one?  A key
  difference is that today RADIUS is largely transported upon UDP, and
  its use is largely, though not exclusively, intra-domain.  Diameter
  itself was designed to scale to broader uses.  We leave as a
  deployment decision, which protocol will be appropriate.
</t>
	<t>Through the integrity protection mechanisms in the AAA framework, the relying party can establish technical trust that messages are being sent by the appropriate relying party. Any given interaction will be associated with one federation at the policy level. The legal or business relationship defines what statements the identity provider is trusted to make and how these statements are interpreted by the relying party. The AAA framework also permits the relying party or elements between the relying party and identity provider to make statements about the relying party. </t>
	<t>The AAA framework provides transport for attributes. Statements made about the subject by the identity provider, statements made about the relying party and other information is transported as attributes.</t>

<section title="Discovery, Rules Determination, and Technical Trust">
<t>One demand that the AAA substrate must make of the upper
  layers is that they must properly identify the end points of the
  communication.  That is-  it must be possible for the AAA 
  client at
  the RP to determine where to send each RADIUS or Diameter message.
  Without this requirement, it would be  the RP's responsibility to determine the identity
  of the principal on its own, without the assistance of an IdP.  This
  architecture makes use of the Network Access Identifier (NAI), where
  the IdP is indicated in the realm component <xref target="RFC4282"
  />.  The NAI is represented and consumed by the GSS-API
  layer as GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME as specified in <xref target="RFC2743"
  />. The GSS-API EAp mechanism includes the NAI in the EAP Response/Identity message.
</t>
	  <t>The RP needs to discover which federation will be used to
	  contact the IDP. As part of this process, the RP determines
	  the set of business rules and technical policies governing
	  the relationship; this is called rules determination. The RP
	  also needs to establish technical trust in the
	  communications with the IDP.</t>
	  <t>Rules determination covers  a broad range of decisions
	  about the exchange. One of these is whether the given RP is
	  permitted to talk to the IDP using a given federation at
	  all, so rules determination encompasses the basic
	  authorization decision. Other factors are included, such as
	  what policies govern release of information about the
	  principal to the RP and what policies govern the RP's use of
	  this information. While rules determination is ultimately a
	  business function, it has significant impact on the
	  technical exchanges. The protocols need to communicate the
	  result of authorization. When multiple sets of rules are
	  possible, the protocol must disambiguate which set of rules
	  are in play. Some rules have technical enforcement
	  mechanisms; for example in some federations intermediates
	  validate information that is being communicated within the federation.</t>
	  <t>Several deployment approaches are possible. These can
	  most easily be classified based on the mechanism for
	  technical trust that is used. The choice of technical trust
	  mechanism constrains how rules determination is
	  implemented. Regardless of what deployment strategy is
	  chosen, it is important that the technical trust mechanism
	  constrain the names of both parties to the exchange. The
	  trust mechanism ought to ensure that the entity acting as
	  IDP for a given NAI is permitted to be the IDP for that
	  realm, and that any service name claimed by the RP is
	  permitted to be claimed by that entity. Here are the categories of technical trust
	  determination:<list style="hanging">
	      <t hangText="AAA Proxy:">The simplest model is that an
	  RP supports a request directly to an AAA proxy. The
	  hop-by-hop integrity protection of the AAA fabric provides
	  technical trust. An RP can submit a request directly to a
	  federation. Alternatively, a federation disambiguation
	  fabric can be used. Such a fabric takes information about
	  what federations the RP is part of and what federations the
	  IDP is part of and routes a message to the appropriate
	  federation. The routing of messages across the fabric plus
	  attributes added to requests and responses provides rules
	  determination. For example, when a disambiguation fabric
	  routes a message to a given federation, that federation's
	  rules are chosen. Naming is enforced as messages travel
	  across the fabric. The entities near the RP confirm its
	  identity and validate names it claims. The fabric routes the
	  message towards the appropriate IDP, validating the IDP's
	  name in the process. The routing can be statically
	  configured. Alternatively a routing protocol could be
	  developed to exchange reachability information about given
	  IDPs and to apply policy across the AAA fabric. Such a
	  routing protocol could flood naming constraints to the
	  appropriate points in the fabric.</t>
	      <t hangText="Trust Broker:">Instead of routing messages
	  through AAA proxies, some trust broker could establish keys
	  between entities near the RP and entities near the IDP. The
	  advantage of this approach is efficiency of message
	  handling. Fewer entities are needed to be involved for each
	  message. Security may be improved by sending individual
	  messages over fewer hops. Rules determination involves
	  decisions made by trust brokers about what keys to
	  grant. Also, associated with each credential is context
	  about rules and about other aspects of technical trust
	  including names that may be claimed. A routing protocol
	  similar to the one for AAA proxies is likely to be useful to
	  trust brokers in flooding rules and naming constraints.</t>
	      <t hangText="Global Credential:">A global credential
	  such as a public key and certificate in a public key
	  infrastructure can be used to establish technical trust. A
	  directory or distributed database such as the Domain Name
	  System is needed for an RP to discover what endpoint to
	  contact for a given NAI. Certificates provide a place to
	  store information about rules determination and naming
	  constraints. Provided that no intermediates are required and
	  that the RP and IDP are sufficient to enforce and determine
	  rules, rules determination is reasonably simple. However
	  applying certain rules is likely to be quite complex. For
	  example if multiple sets of rules are possible between an
	  IDP and RP, confirming the correct set is used may be
	  difficult. This is particularly true if intermediates are
	  involved in making the decision. Also, to the extent that
	  directory information needs to be trusted, rules
	  determination may be more complex.</t>
	    </list>
</t>
	  <t>Real-world deployments are likely to be mixtures of these
	  basic approaches. For example, it will be quite common for
	  an RP to route traffic to a AAA proxy within an
	  organization. That proxy MAY use any of the three methods to
	  get closer to the IDP. It is also likely that rather than
	  being directly reachable, an IDP may have a proxy within its
	  organization. Federations MAY provide a traditional AAA
	  proxy interface even if they also provide another mechanism
	  for increased efficiency or security.</t>
</section>

      </section>
      <section title="Subject To Identity Provider">
	<t>Traditional web federation does not describe how a subject
	communicates with an identity provider. As a result, this
	communication is not standardized. There are several
	disadvantages to this approach. It is difficult to have
	subjects that are machines rather than humans that use some
	sort of programatic credential. In addition, use of browsers
	for authentication restricts the deployment of more secure
	forms of authentication beyond plaintext username and password
	known by the server. In a number of cases the authentication
	interface may be presented before the subject has adequately
	validated they are talking to the intended server. By giving
	control of the authentication interface to a potential
	attacker, then the security of the system may be reduced and
	phishing opportunities introduced.</t>
	<t>As a result, it is desirable to choose some standardized
	approach for communication between the subject's end-host and
	the identity provider. There are a number of requirements this
	approach must meet.</t>
      <t>Experience has taught us one key security and scalability requirement:
        it is important that the relying party not get in possession of the
        long-term secret of the entity being authenticated by the AAA
        server. Aside from a valuable secret being exposed, a
        synchronization problem can also often develop.
Since there is
        no single authentication mechanism that will be used everywhere there is another associated
        requirement: The authentication framework must allow for the flexible integration of
        authentication mechanisms. For instance, some identity
        providers may require hardware tokens while others may use
        passwords.  A service provider would want to support both
        sorts of federations, and others.</t>

      <t>Fortunately, these requirements can be met by utilizing standardized and successfully deployed technology, namely by the Extensible Authentication
            Protocol (EAP) framework
            <xref target="RFC3748"/>.
      <xref
          target="abfab-arch"/> illustrates the integration graphically.</t>

<t>  EAP is an end-to-end framework; it provides for two-way
            communication between a peer (i.e,service client or
            principal) through the
            authenticator (i.e., service provider) to the back-end (i.e.,
            identity provider).  Conveniently, this is precisely the
            communication path that is needed for federated identity.
        Although EAP support is already integrated in AAA systems (see
            <xref target="RFC3579"/> and <xref target="RFC4072"/>)
            several challenges remain: one is to carry EAP payloads
            from the end host to the relying party. Another is to
            verify statements the relying party has made to the
            subject, confirm these statements are consistent with
            statements made to the identity provider and confirm all
            the above are consistent with the federation and any
            federation-specific policy or configuration. Another
            challenge is choosing which identity provider to use for
            which service.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="Application to Service">
	<t>One of the remaining layers is responsible for integration
	of federated authentication into the application. There are a
	number of approaches that applications have adopted for
	security. So, there may need to be multiple strategies for
	integration of federated authentication into
	applications. However, we have started with a strategy that
	provides integration to a large number of application
	protocols.</t>
	<t>Many applications such as SSH <xref target="RFC4462"/>, NFS
	<xref target="RFC2203"/>, DNS <xref target="RFC3645"/> and
	several non-IETF applications support the Generic Security
	Services Application Programming Interface <xref
	target="RFC2743"/>. Many applications such as IMAP, SMTP, XMPP
	and LDAP support e Simple Authentication and Security Layer
	(SASL) <xref target="RFC4422"/> framework. These two
	approaches work together nicely: by creating a GSS-API
	mechanism, SASL integration is also addressed. In effect,
	using a GSS-API mechanism with 
	SASL simply requires placing some headers on the front of the
	mechanism and constraining certain GSS-API options.</t>
	<t>GSS-API is specified in terms of an abstract set of
	operations which can be mapped into a programming language to
	form an API. When people are first introduced to GSS-API, they
	focus on it as an API. However, from the prospective of
	authentication for non-web applications, GSS-API should be
	thought of as a protocol not an API. It consists of some
	abstract operations such as the initial context exchange,
	which includes two sub-operations (gss_init_sec_context and
	gss_accept_sec_context). An application defines which abstract
	operations it is going to use and where messages produced by
	these operations fit into the application architecture. A
	GSS-API mechanism will define what actual protocol messages
	result from that abstract message for a given abstract
	operation. So, since this work is focusing on a particular
	GSS-API mechanism, we generally focus on protocol elements
	rather than the API view of GSS-API.</t>
	<t>The API view has significant value. Since the abstract
	operations are well defined, the set of information that a
	mechanism gets from the application is well defined. Also, the
	set of assumptions the application is permitted to make  is
	generally well defined. As a result, an application protocol
	that supports GSS-API or SASL is very likely to be usable with
	a new approach to authentication including this one with no
	required modifications. In some cases, support for a new
	authentication mechanism has been added using plugin
	interfaces to applications without the application being
	modified at all. Even when modifications are required, they
	can often be limited to supporting a new naming and
	authorization model. For example, this work focuses on
	privacy; an application that assumes it will always obtain an
	identifier for the principal will need to be modified to
	support anonymity, unlinkability or pseudonymity.</t>
	<t>So, we use GSS-API and SASL because a number of the
	application protocols we wish to federate support these
	strategies for security integration. What does this mean from
	a protocol standpoint and how does this relate to other
	layers? This means we need to design a concrete GSS-API
	mechanism. We have chosen to use a GSS-API mechanism that
	encapsulates EAP authentication. So, GSS-API (and SASL)
	encapsulate EAP between the end-host and the service. The AAA
	framework encapsulates EAP between the relying party and the
	identity provider. The GSS-API mechanism includes rules about
	how principals and services are named as well as per-message
	security and other facilities required by the applications we
	wish to support.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Personalization Layer">
	<t>The AAA framework provides a way to transport statements
	from the identity provider to the relying party. However, we
	also need to say more about the content of these
	statements. In simple cases, attributes particular to the AAA
	protocol can be defined. However in more complicated
	situations it is strongly desirable to re-use an existing
	protocol for asking questions and receiving information about
	subjects. SAML is used for this. </t>
	<t>SAML usage may be as simple as the identity provider
	including a SAML Response message in the AAA
	response. Alternatively the relying party may generate a SAML
	request XXX to whom, how, and at what point? (see above XXX).</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Tieing Layers Together">
       <t>
        <figure title="Architecture for Federated Access of non-Web based Applications" anchor="abfab-arch">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                 +--------------+
                                 |  AAA Server  |
                                 |  (Identity   |
                                 |  Provider)   |
                                 +-^----------^-+
                                   * EAP      | RADIUS/
                                   *          | Diameter
                                 --v----------v--
                              ///                \\\
                            //                      \\   ***
                           |        Federation        |  back-
                           |                          |  end
                            \\                      //   ***
                              \\\                ///
                                 --^----------^--
                                   * EAP      | RADIUS/
                 Application       *          | Diameter
+-------------+  Data            +-v----------v--+
|             |<---------------->|               |
| Client      |  EAP/EAP Method  | Server Side   |
| Application |<****************>| Application   |
| @ End Host  |  GSS-API         |(Relying Party)|
|             |<---------------->|               |
|             |  Application     |               |
|             |  Protocol        |               |
|             |<================>|               |
+-------------+                  +---------------+
               *** front-end ***

Legend:

 <****>: End-to-end exchange
 <---->: Hop-by-hop exchange
 <====>: Protocol through which GSS-API/GS2 exchanges are tunnelled
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section title="Application Security Services">
      <t>One of the key goals is to integrate federated authentication
      into existing application protocols and where possible, existing
      implementations of these protocols. Another goal is to perform
      this integration while meeting the best security practices of
      the technologies used to perform the integration. This section
      describes security services and properties required by the EAP
      GSS-API mechanism in order to meet these goals. This information
      could be viewed as specific to that mechanism. However, other
      future application integration strategies are very likely to
      need similar services. So, it is likely that these services will
      be expanded across application integration strategies if new
      application integration strategies are adopted.</t>
      <section title="Server (Mutual) Authentication">
	<t>GSS-API provides an optional security service called mutual
	authentication. This service means that in addition to the
	initiator providing (potentially anonymous or pseudonymous)
	identity to the acceptor, the acceptor confirms its identity
	to the initiator. Especially for the ABFAB context, this
	service is confusingly named. We still say that mutual
	authentication is provided when the identity of an acceptor is
	strongly authenticated to an anonymous initiator.</t>
	<t>RFC 2743 does not explicitly talk about what mutual
	authentication means. Within the GSS-API community successful mutual
	authentication has come to mean:<list style="symbols">
	    <t>If a target name is supplied by the initiator, then the
	initiator trusts that the supplied target name describes the
	acceptor. This implies both that appropriate cryptographic
	exchanges took place for the initiator to make such a trust
	decision, and that after evaluating the results of these
	exchanges, the initiator's policy trusts that the target name
	is accurate.</t>
	    <t>The initiator trusts that its idea of the acceptor name
	correctly names the entity it is communicating with.</t>
	    <t>Both the initiator and acceptor have the same key
	material for per-message keys and both parties have confirmed
	they actually have the key material. In EAP terms, there is a
	protected indication of success.</t>
	  </list></t>
	<t>Mutual authentication is an important defense against
	certain aspects of phishing. Intuitively, users would like to
	assume that if some party asks for their credentials as part
	of authentication, successfully gaining access to the resource
	means that they are talking to the expected party. Without
	mutual authentication, the acceptor could "grant access"
	regardless of what credentials are supplied. Mutual
	authentication better matches this user intuition.</t>
	<t>It is important, therefore, that the GSS-EAP mechanism implement mutual
	authentication. That is, an initiator needs to be able to
	request mutual authentication. When mutual authentication is
	requested, only EAP methods capabale of providing the
	necessary service can be used, and appropriate steps need to
	be taken to provide mutual authentication. A broader set of
	EAP methods could be supported when a particular application
	does not request mutual authentication. It is an open question
	whether the mechanism will permit this.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="GSS-API Channel Binding">
	<t><xref target="RFC5056"/> defines a concept of channel
	binding to prevent man-in-the-middle attacks. It is common to
	provide SASL and GSS-API with another layer to provide
	transport security; Transport Layer Security (TLS) is the most
	common such layer. TLS provides its own server
	authentication. However there are a variety of situations
	where this authentication is not checked for policy or
	usability reasons. Even when it is checked, if the trust
	infrastructure behind the TLS authentication is different from
	the trust infrastructure behind the GSS-API mutual
	authentication. If the endpoints of the GSS-API authentication
	are different than the endpoints of the lower layer, this is a
	strong indication of a problem such as a man-in-the-middle
	attack. Channel binding provides a facility to determine
	whether these endpoints are the same.</t>
	<t>The GSS-EAP mechanism needs to support channel
	binding. When an application provides channel binding data,
	the mechanism needs to confirm this is the same on both sides
	consistent with the GSS-API specification. XXXThere is an open
	question here as to the details; today RFC 5554 governs. We
	could use that and the current draft assumes we will. However
	in Beijing we became aware of some changes to these details
	that would make life much better for GSS authentication of
	HTTP. We should resolve this with kitten and replace this note
	with a reference to the spec we're actually following.</t>
	<t>Typically when considering channel binding, people think of
	channel binding in combination with mutual
	authentication. This is sufficiently common that without
	additional qualification channel binding should be assumed to
	imply mutual authentication. Without mutual authentication, only one party
	knows that the endpoints are correct. That's sometimes
	useful. Consider for example a user who wishes to access a
	protected resource from a shared whiteboard in a conference
	room. The whiteboard is the initiator; it does not need to
	actually authenticate that it is talking to the correct
	resource because the user will be able to recognize whether
	the displayed content is correct. If channel binding were used
	without mutual authentication, it would in effect be a request
	to only disclose the resource in the context of a particular
	channel. Such an authentication would be similar in concept to
	a holder-of-key SAML assertion. However, also note that while
	it is not happening in the protocol, mutual authentication is
	happening in the overall system: the user is able to visually
	authenticate the content. This is consistent with all uses of
	channel binding without protocol level mutual authentication
	found so far.</t>
	<t>RFC 5056 channel binding (also called GSS-API channel
	binding when GSS-API is involved) is not the same thing as EAP
	channel binding. EAP channel binding is also used in the ABFAB
	context in order to implement acceptor naming and mutual
	authentication. Details are discussed in the mechanisms
	specification <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Host-Based Service Names">
	<t>IETF security mechanisms typically take the name of a
	service entered by a user and make some trust decision about
	whether the remote party in an interaction is the intended
	party. GSS-API has a relatively flexible naming
	architecture. However most of the IETF applications that use
	GSS-API, including SSH, NFS, IMAP, LDAP and XMPP, have chosen
	to use host-based service names when they use GSS-API. In this
	model, the initiator names an acceptor based on a service such
	as "imap" or "host" (for login services such as SSH) and a
	host name.</t>
	<t>Using host-based service names leads to a challenging trust
	delegation problem. Who is allowed to decide whether a
	particular hostname maps to an entity. The public-key
	infrastructure (PKI) used by the web has chosen to have a
	number of trust anchors (root certificate authorities) each of
	wich can map any name to a public key. A number of GSS-API
	mechanisms suchs as Kerberos <xref target="RFC1964"/> split
	the problem into two parts. A new concept called a realm is
	introduced. Then the mechanism decides what realm is
	responsible for a given name. That realm is responsible for
	deciding if the acceptor entity is allowed to claim the
	name. ABFAB needs to adopt this approach.</t>
	<t>Host-based service names do not work ideally when different
	instances of a service are running on different ports. Also,
	these do not work ideally when SRV record or other insecure
	referrals are used.</t>
	<t>The GSS-EAP mechanism needs to support host-based service
	names in order to work with existing IETF protocols.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Per-Message Tokens">
	<t>GSS-API provides per-message security services that can
	provide confidentiality and integrity. Some IETF protocols
	such as NFS and SSH take advantage of these services. As a
	result GSS-EAP needs to support these services. As with mutual
	authentication, per-message services will limit the set of EAP
	methods that are available. Any method that produces a Master
	Session Key (MSK) should be able to support per-message
	security services.</t>
	<t>GSS-API provides a pseudo-random function. While the
	pseudo-random function does not involve sending data over the
	wire, it provides an algorithm that both the initiator and
	acceptor can run in order to arrive at the same key
	value. This is useful for designs where a successful
	authentication is used to key some other function. This is
	similar in concept to the TLS extractor. No current IETF
	protocols require this. However GSS-EAP supports this service
	because it is valuable for the future and easy to do given
	per-message services. Non-IETF protocols are expected to take
	advantage of this in the near future.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="attribute-providers" title="Future Work:
	Attribute Providers">
      <t>
	This architecture provides for a federated authentication and
	authorization framework between IdPs, RPs, principals, and
	subjects.  It does not at this time provide for a means to
	retrieve attributes from 3rd parties.  However, it envisions
	such a possibility.  We note that in any extension to the
	model, an attribute provider must be authorized to release
	specific attributes to a specific RP for a specific
	principal.  In addition, we note that it is an open question
	beyond this architecture as to how the RP should know to trust
	a particular attribute provider.
</t>
<t>There are a number of possible technical means to provide 
  attribute provider capabilities.  One possible approach is for the
  IdP to provide a signed attribute request to RP that it in turn
  will provide to the attribute authority.  Another approach  would be
  for the  IdP to provide a URI to the RP that contains a token of
  some form.  The form of communications between the IdP and attribute
  provider as well as other considerations are left for the future.
  One thing we can say now is that the IdP would merely be asserting
  who the attribute authority is, and not the contents of what the
  attribute authority would return.  (Otherwise, the IdP might as well
  make the query to the attribute authority and then resign it.)
</t>
</section>
  
    <section anchor="privacy-cons" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>Sharing identity information raises privacy violations and as described throughout this document an existing architecture is re-used for a different usage environment. As such, a discussion about the privacy properties has to take these pre-conditions into consideration. We use the approach suggested in <xref target="I-D.morris-privacy-considerations"/> to shed light into what data is collected and used by which entity, what the relationship between these entities and the end user is, what data about the user is likely needed to be collected, and what the identification level of the data is.</t>
     

<section title="What entities collect and use data?">

<t><xref target="abfab-arch"/> shows the architecture with the involved entities. Message exchanges are exchanged between the client application, via the relying part to the AAA server. There will likely be intermediaries between the relying party and the AAA server, labeled generically as "federation".
</t>

<t>In order for the relying party to route messages to the AAA server it is necessary for the client application to provide enough information to enable the identification of the AAA server's domain. While often the username is attached to the domain (in the form of a Network Access Identity (NAI) this is not necessary for the actual protocol operation. The EAP server component within the AAA server needs to authenticate the user and therefore needs to execute the respective authentication protocol. Once the authentication exchange is complete authorization information needs to be conveyed to the relying party to grant the user the necessary application rights. Information about resource consumption may be delivered as part of the accounting exchange during the lifetime of the granted application session.</t>

<t>The authentication exchange may reveal an identifier that can be linked to a user. Additionally, a sequence of authentication protocol exchanges may be linked together. Depending on the chosen authentication protocol information at varying degrees may be revealed to all parties along the communication path. This authorization information exchange may disclose identity information about the user. While accounting information is created by the relying party it is likely to needed by intermediaries in the federation for financial settlement purposes and will be stored for billing, fraud detection, statistical purposes, and for service improvement by the AAA server operator.</t>
</section>

<section title="Relationship between User's and other Entities">
<t>The AAA server is a first-party site the user typically has a relationship with. This relationship will be created at the time when the security credentials are exchange and provisioned. The relying party and potential intermediares in the federation are typically operate under the contract of the first-party site. The user typically does not know about the intermediaries in the federation nor does he have any relationship with them. The protocol interaction triggered by the client application happens with the relying party at the time of application access. The relying party does not have a direct contractual relationship with the user but depending on the application the interaction may expose the brand of the application running by the relying party to the end user via some user interface.</t> 
</section> 

<section title="What Data about the User is likely Needed to be Collected?">
<t>The data that is likely going to be collected as part of a protocol exchange with application access at the relying party is accounting information and authorization information. This information is likely to be kept beyond the terminated application usage for trouble shooting, statistical purposes, etc. There is also like to be additional data collected to to improve application service usage by the relying party that is not conveyed to the AAA server as part of the accounting stream. 
</t>
</section> 

<section title="What is the Identification Level of the Data?">
<t>With regard to identification there are several protocol layers that need to be considered separately. First, there is the EAP method exchange, which as an authentication and key exchange protocol has properties related to identification and protocol linkage. Second, there is identification at the EAP layer for routing of messages. Then, in the exchange between the client application and the relying party the identification depends on the underlying application layer protocol the EAP/GSS-API exchange is tunneled over. Finally, there is the backend exchange via the AAA infrastructure, which involves a range of RADIUS and Diameter extensions and yet to be defined extensions, such as encoding authorization information inside SAML assertions.</t> 
<t>Since this document does not attempt to define any of these exchanges but rather re-uses existing mechanisms the level of identification heavily depends on the selected mechanisms. The following two examples aim to illustrate the amount of existing work with respect to decrease exposure of personal data. 
</t>
<t><list style="numbers">
<t>When designing EAP methods a number of different requirements may need to get considered; some of them are conflicting. RFC 4017 <xref target="RFC4017"/>, for example, tried to list requirements for EAP methods utilized for network access over Wireless LANs. It also recommends the end-user identity hiding requirement, which is privacy-relevant. Some EAP methods, such as EAP-IKEv2 <xref target="RFC5106"/>, also fulfill this requirement.</t>
<t>EAP, as the layer encapsulating EAP method specific information, needs identity information to allow routing requests towards the user's home AAA server. This information is carried within the Network Access Identifier (NAI) and the username part of the NAI (as supported by RFC 4282 <xref target="RFC4282"/>) can be obfuscated.</t>
</list> 
</t>
</section> 

<section title="Privacy Challenges"> 
<t>While a lot of standarization work was done to avoid leakage of identity information to intermediaries (such as eavesdroppers on the communication path between the client application and the relying party) in the area of authentication and key exchange protocols. However, from current deployments the weak aspects with respect to security are: 
<list style="numbers"> 
<t>Today business contracts are used to create federations between identity providers and relying parties. These contracts are not only financial agreements but they also define the rules about what information is exchanged between the AAA server and the relying party and the potential involvement of AAA proxies and brokers as intermediaries. While these contracts are openly available for university federations they are not public in case of commercial deployments. Quite naturally, there is a lack of transparency for external parties.</t>
<t>In today's deployments the ability for users to determine the amount of information exchanged with other parties over time, as well as the possibility to control the amount of information exposed via an explict consent is limited. This is partially due the nature of application capabilities at the time of network access authentication. However, with the envisioned extension of the usage, as described in this document, it is desirable to offer these capabilities.</t>
</list> 
</t> 
</section> 

</section>

<!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section title="Deployment Considerations">
      <section title="EAP Channel Binding">
	<t>Discuss the implications of needing EAP channel
	binding.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="AAA Proxy Behavior">
	<t>Discuss deployment implications of our proxy requirements.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-cons" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This entire document is about security. A future version of the document will highlight some important security concepts.</t>
    </section>


    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
<!--      <t>The author would like to thank Sam Hartman for a discussion about all aspects of the
        "Federated Authentication Beyond The Web" effort when he was visiting MIT in June 2010.</t>-->
      <t>We would like to thank Mayutan Arumaithurai and        Klaas Wierenga for their feedback. Additionally, we would like to
      thank Eve Maler, Nicolas Williams, Bob Morgan, Scott Cantor, Jim Fenton, and Luke Howard for their feedback on the
      federation terminology question.</t>
      <t>Furthermore, we would like to thank Klaas Wierenga for his review of the pre-00 draft version.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
  </middle>

  <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2743;
      &RFC2865; &RFC3588;
      &RFC3748;  &RFC3579; &RFC4072; &RFC4282; 
      &I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology;
      &I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &I-D.nir-tls-eap;
      &I-D.ietf-oauth-v2;
      &I-D.morris-privacy-considerations;
      &RFC4017;
      &RFC5106;
      &RFC1964;
      &RFC2203;
      &RFC3645;
      &RFC2138;
      &RFC4462;
      &RFC4422;
      &RFC5056;
      &RFC5801; 
      &RFC5849;
      &SAML20;
      &RFC2904;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
