<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5246 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5226 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>	
  <!ENTITY RFC3874 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3874.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC1321 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6066 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6066.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6574 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6574.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7250 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7250.xml'>
	]>
	
	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
	<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-tls-cached-info-18.txt">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="TLS Cached Information Extension"> Transport Layer Security (TLS) Cached Information Extension </title>

        <author initials="S." surname="Santesson" fullname="Stefan Santesson">
            <organization>3xA Security AB</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Scheelev. 17</street>
					<city>Lund</city>
                    <code>223 70</code>
                    <country>Sweden</country>
                </postal>
                <email>sts@aaa-sec.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

    <author initials="H.T." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig ">
      <organization>ARM Ltd.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Hall in Tirol</city>
          <code> 6060 </code>
          <country>Austria</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Hannes.tschofenig@gmx.net </email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>


        <date year="2015"/>
        <area>Security</area>
        <workgroup>TLS</workgroup>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
		
        <abstract>
		 <t>Transport Layer Security (TLS) handshakes often include fairly 
		 static information, such as the server
   certificate and a list of trusted Certification Authorities (CAs).
   This information can be of considerable size, particularly if the server
   certificate is bundled with a complete certificate chain 
   (i.e., the certificates of intermediate CAs up to the root CA).</t>
   
   <t>This document defines an extension that allows a TLS client to inform a server of cached information, 
   allowing the server to omit already available information.</t>
        </abstract>

    </front>
    <middle>

        <section title="Introduction">

<!-- 
  <t>Transport Layer Security (TLS) handshakes often include fairly 
		 static information, such as the server
   certificate and a list of trusted Certification Authorities (CAs).
   This information can be of considerable size, particularly if the server
   certificate is bundled with a complete certificate chain 
   (i.e., the certificates of intermediate CAs up to the root CA).</t>
--> 

   <t>Reducing the amount of information exchanged during a Transport Layer Security handshake to a minimum helps to 
   improve performance in environments where devices are connected to a 
   network with a low bandwidth, and lossy radio technology. 
   With Internet of Things such environments exist, for example, when smart objects 
   are connected using a low power IEEE 802.15.4 radio or via Bluetooth Smart. For more information 
   about the challenges with smart object deployments please see 
   <xref target="RFC6574"/>.</t>

   <t>This specification defines a TLS extension that allows a client and a 
   server to exclude transmission information cached in an earlier TLS handshake.
   </t>
   
   <t>A typical example exchange may therefore look as follows. First, the client and the server executes the usual TLS handshake. The client may, for example, decide to cache the certificate provided by the server. When the TLS client connects to the TLS server some time in the future, without using session resumption, it then attaches the cached_info extension defined in this document to the client hello message to indicate that it had cached the certificate, and it provides the fingerprint of it. If the server's certificate has not changed then the TLS server does not need to send its' certificate and the corresponding certificate list again. In case information has changed, which can be seen from the fingerprint provided by the client, the certificate payload is transmitted to the client to allow the client to update the cache.</t>

   </section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

        <section title="Terminology">

		<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "MUST", "MUST NOT",   
		"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
		document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
		</t>
		 
		<t>This document refers to the TLS protocol but the description is equally applicable to DTLS as well.</t>  
		</section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

		<section anchor="cached-info" title="Cached Information Extension">
<t>This document defines a new extension type (cached_info(TBD)), which is used in
   client hello and server hello messages. The extension type
   is specified as follows.</t>
        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      enum {
           cached_info(TBD), (65535)
      } ExtensionType;
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>
The extension_data field of this extension, when included in the
client hello, MUST contain the CachedInformation structure. The client 
MUST NOT send multiple CachedObjects with the same CachedInformationType. 
</t>
        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      enum {
           certificate_list(1), certificate_authorities(2) (255)
      } CachedInformationType;

      struct {
           select (type) {
             case client: 
               CachedInformationType type;
               HashAlgorithm hash;
               opaque hash_value<1..255>;
             case server: 
               CachedInformationType type; 
           } body; 
      } CachedObject;

      struct {
           CachedObject cached_info<1..2^16-1>;
      } CachedInformation;
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>This document establishes a registry for CachedInformationType types; additional values can be added following the policy described in <xref target="IANA"/>.
</t>

<section title="Certificate_list Fingerprint">
		  <t>
   When the CachedInformationType identifies a certificate_list, then
   the hash_value field MUST include the hash calculated over the certificate_list
   element of the Certificate payload provided by the TLS server in an earlier exchange, excluding the three
   length bytes of the certificate_list vector.</t>

</section> 

<section title="Certificate_authorities Fingerprint"> 
<t>When the CachedInformationType identifies a certificate_authorities, then the hash_value
   MUST include a hash calculated over <!-- the certificate_authorities
   element of the--> CertificateRequest payload provided by the TLS server in an earlier exchange, excluding the msg_type and length field. <!-- excluding the
   two length bytes of the certificate_authorities vector.--> 
</t>
</section> 

<section title="Fingerprint Hash Algorithm"> 
<t>The hash algorithm used to calculate hash values is conveyed in the 'hash' field of the CachedObject element. The list of registered hash algorithms can be found in the TLS HashAlgorithm Registry, which was created by RFC 5246 <xref target="RFC5246"/>. The value zero (0) for 'none' and one (1) for 'md5' is not an allowed choice for a hash algorithm and MUST NOT be used.</t>
</section> 
   </section> 

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

<section title="Exchange Specification">

<t>Clients supporting this extension MAY include the "cached_info" extension in the
   (extended) client hello. If the client includes the extension then it MUST contain one or more CachedObject attributes. 
Clients and servers MUST NOT include more than one CachedObject attribute per info type.
</t>
<t>
A server supporting this extension MAY include the "cached_info" extension 
in the (extended) server hello. By returning the "cached_info" extension the server indicates that it
supports the cached info types. For each indicated cached info type the server MUST alters the transmission of respective payloads, as specified for each type. If the server includes the extension it MUST only include CachedObjects of a type also supported by the client (as expressed in the client hello).

<!-- By returning the "cached_info" extension the server indicates that it
supports caching of each present CachedObject that matches the specified hash value. 
 The server MAY support other cached objects that are not present in the extension.--> 
</t>

<t>Note that the client includes a fingerprint of the cached information to give the server enough information to determine whether cached information is stale. If the server supports this specification and notices a mismatch between the data cached by the client and its own information then the server MUST include the information in full and MUST NOT list the respective item in the "cached_info" extension.</t>

<t>Note: Clients may cache 
multiple data items for a single server if those servers are part of a hosting environment. 
To allow the client to select the appropriate information from the cached it is RECOMMENDED that the client uses information 
from the Server Name Indication <xref target="RFC6066"/>. </t>

<t>Following a successful exchange of the "cached_info" extensions in the client and server hello,
   the server alters sending the corresponding handshake message. How information is altered from the handshake messages is defined per cached info type. <xref target="certificate_list"/> and <xref target="certificate_authorities"/> defines the syntax of the fingerprinted information.</t>

   <!-- 
<t>The handshake protocol MUST proceed using the information as
   if it was provided in the handshake protocol. The Finished message
   MUST be calculated over the actual data exchanged in the handshake
   protocol. That is, the Finished message will not be calculated over the
   information that was omitted from transmission.</t>
--> 

<t>The handshake protocol MUST proceed using the information as if it was
provided in the handshake protocol. Since the Finished message is calculated over the 
exchanged data it will also include the hash of the cached data. <!-- The Finished message MUST be
calculated over the actual data exchanged in the handshake protocol. That
is, the Finished message will be calculated over the information that was
omitted from transmission by means of its present hash in the client hello
and not through its presence in the handshake exchange.--> 
</t>

<!-- <t>The server MUST NOT include more than one fingerprint for a single information element, i.e., at maximum only one CachedObject structure per replaced information is provided.</t>--> 




<section anchor="certificate_list" title="Omitting the Certificate List">

<t>When an object of type 'certificate_list' is provided in the client hello, the server MAY replace the list of
certificates with an empty sequence with an actual length field of zero (=empty vector).</t>

<t>The original handshake message syntax is defined in RFC 5246 <xref target="RFC5246"/> and has the following 
structure:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      opaque ASN.1Cert<1..2^24-1>;

      struct {
          ASN.1Cert certificate_list<0..2^24-1>;
      } Certificate;
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
	</t>

 <t>Note that <xref target="RFC7250"/> allows the certificate payload to contain only the SubjectPublicKeyInfo instead of the full information typically found in a certificate. Hence, when this specification is used in combination with <xref target="RFC7250"/> and the negotiated certificate type is a raw public key then the TLS server omits sending a Certificate payload that contains an ASN.1 Certificate structure with the included SubjectPublicKeyInfo.</t>
   
   </section> 

<section anchor="certificate_authorities" title="Omitting the Trusted Certificate Authorities">

<!-- 
<t>When a fingerprint for an object of type 'certificate_authorities' is provided in the
client hello, the server MAY send a DistinguishedName in the Certificate
Request message with an actual length field of zero (=empty vector).</t>
--> 

<t>When a fingerprint for an object of type 'certificate_authorities' is provided in the
client hello, the server MAY replace the CertificateRequest message with an empty sequence with an actual length field of zero.</t>

<t>The original handshake message syntax is defined in RFC 5246 <xref target="RFC5246"/> and has the following 
structure:</t>

           <t><figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      opaque DistinguishedName<1..2^16-1>;

      struct {
          ClientCertificateType certificate_types<1..2^8-1>;
          SignatureAndHashAlgorithm
            supported_signature_algorithms<2^16-1>;
          DistinguishedName certificate_authorities<0..2^16-1>;
      } CertificateRequest;
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
		  </t>
 </section>
</section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->
   
        <section title="Example">

<t><xref target="example"/> illustrates an example exchange using the TLS cached info extension. 
In the normal TLS handshake exchange shown in flow (A) the TLS server provides its certificate 
in the Certificate payload to the client, see step [1]. This allows the client to store the certificate 
for future use. After some time the TLS client again interacts with the same TLS server and makes use of the
TLS cached info extension, as shown in flow (B). The TLS client indicates support for this specification 
via the "cached_info" extension, see [2], and indicates that it has stored the 'certificate_list' from the earlier 
exchange. With [3] the TLS server acknowledges the supports of this specification and informs the client that 
it alterned the content of the certificate payload (see [4], as described in <xref target="certificate_list"/>).
</t>

           <t><figure anchor="example" title="Example Message Exchange">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
(A) Initial (full) Exchange 

ClientHello  ->
                       <-  ServerHello
                           Certificate* // [1]
                           ServerKeyExchange*
                           CertificateRequest*
                           ServerHelloDone 

Certificate*
ClientKeyExchange
CertificateVerify*
[ChangeCipherSpec]
Finished                  ->

                       <- [ChangeCipherSpec]
                          Finished

Application Data        <------->     Application Data


(B) TLS Cached Extension Usage

ClientHello 
cached_info=(certificate_list)   -> // [2]
                       <-  ServerHello
                           cached_info= 
                           (certificate_list) // [3]
                           Certificate* // [4]
                           ServerKeyExchange*
                           CertificateRequest*
                           ServerHelloDone 

Certificate*
ClientKeyExchange
CertificateVerify*
[ChangeCipherSpec]
Finished                  ->

                       <- [ChangeCipherSpec]
                          Finished

Application Data        <------->     Application Data
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        </section> 
		  
        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->
   
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>This specification defines a mechanism to reference stored state using a fingerprint.
		Sending a fingerprint of cached information in an
   unencrypted handshake, as the client and server hello is, may allow an attacker or observer to 
   correlate independent TLS exchanges. While some information elements used in this specification,
   such as server certificates, are public objects and usually not
   sensitive in this regard, others may be. Those who implement and deploy this specification should therefore 
   make an informed decision whether the cached information is inline with their security and privacy goals. 
   In case of concerns, it is advised to avoid sending the fingerprint of the data objects in clear.</t>

             
            <t>The hash algorithm used in this specification is required to have
  have strong collision resistance. <!-- However, since
   the hash algorithm is used to represent data in the finished
   calculation, the security properties of the finished calculation will
   change if a weaker hash algorithm is used to represent cached
   information compared with the hash algorithm used to calculate the
   finished message.--> </t>

   
        </section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

        <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<section title="New Entry to the TLS ExtensionType Registry"> 
<t>IANA is requested to add an entry to the existing TLS ExtensionType registry, 
defined in RFC 5246 <xref target="RFC5246"/>, for cached_info(TBD) defined in this document.</t>
</section> 

<section title="New Registry for CachedInformationType">
      <t>IANA is requested to establish a registry for TLS CachedInformationType values.  The
      first entries in the registry are <list style="symbols"> 
	    <t>certificate_list(1)</t> 
      	<t>certificate_authorities(2)</t>
      </list> 
      </t>
      <t>The policy for adding new values to this registry, following the terminology defined in RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226"/>, is as follows:
	  <list style="symbols"> 
	    <t>0-63 (decimal): Standards Action</t>
	    <t>64-223 (decimal): Specification Required</t>
        <t>224-255 (decimal): reserved for Private Use</t>
	  </list> 
	  </t>
</section>

</section> 

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

        <section title="Acknowledgments">

   <t>We would like to thank the following persons for your detailed document reviews:
   <list style="symbols"> 
   <t>Paul Wouters and Nikos Mavrogiannopoulos (December 2011)</t> 
   <t>Rob Stradling (February 2012)</t> 
   <t>Ondrej Mikle (in March 2012)</t>
   <t>Ilari Liusvaara, Adam Langley, and Eric Rescorla (in July 2014)</t>
   </list> 
   </t> 
   
   <t>Additionally, we would like to thank the TLS working group chairs, Sean Turner and Joe Salowey, as well as the responsible security area director, Stephen Farrell, for his support. </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

    </middle>
    <back>



        <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC5246; &RFC6066;  

<!-- 
           <reference anchor="SHA">
                <front>
                    <title>Federal Information Processing Standards Publication (FIPS PUB) 180-3, Secure Hash Standard (SHS)</title>
                    <author initials="" surname="" fullname="NIST">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="October" year="2008"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
     --> 
            
			&RFC3874; 
<!--			&RFC1321; --> 
			
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References"> &RFC5226; &RFC6574; &RFC7250; </references>

<section title="Example"> 

<t>The example TLS exchange shown in <xref target="example-TLS-exchange2"/> illustrates the use of a ECC ciphersuite with a 256 bit key. The use of ECC already ensures a small certificate size compared to RSA with equivalent security strength. The Certificate message provided by the server is with 550 bytes one of the largest message even though it only contains a single certificate (i.e., no intermediate CA certificates). The DistinguishedName field in the Certificate Request sent by the server has a length of 66 bytes. The client-provided Certificate message has a length of 566 bytes.</t>

       <t><figure anchor="example-TLS-exchange2" title="Example TLS Exchange">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
Client --> Server: 

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Client Hello
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 121
        Handshake Protocol: Client Hello
            Handshake Type: Client Hello (1)
            Length: 117
            Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
            Random
                gmt_unix_time: Jan 14, 2015 12:43:58.000000000 CET
                random_bytes: c61b966bba2781c50b07c3278c43f5892b3d...
            Session ID Length: 0
            Cipher Suites Length: 10
            Cipher Suites (5 suites)
            Compression Methods Length: 1
            Compression Methods (1 method)
            Extensions Length: 66
            Extension: server_name
            Extension: signature_algorithms
            Extension: elliptic_curves
            Extension: ec_point_formats

Client <-- Server: 

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Server Hello
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 87
        Handshake Protocol: Server Hello
            Handshake Type: Server Hello (2)
            Length: 83
            Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
            Random
                gmt_unix_time: Jan 14, 2015 12:43:58.000000000 CET
                random_bytes: 82d3d09b44149d738b7002da4ff5a986fe11...
            Session ID Length: 32
            Session ID: d069a74661088676b98db8346070278a7475b617a0...
            Cipher Suite: Unknown (0xc0ad)
            Compression Method: null (0)
            Extensions Length: 11
            Extension: renegotiation_info
            Extension: ec_point_formats

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 557
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate
            Handshake Type: Certificate (11)
            Length: 553
            Certificates Length: 550
            Certificates (550 bytes)
                Certificate Length: 547
                Certificate (id-at-commonName=localhost,
                id-at-organizationName=PolarSSL,id-at-countryName=NL)
                    signedCertificate
                    algorithmIdentifier (iso.2.840.10045.4.3.2)
                    Padding: 0
                    encrypted: 30650231009a2c5cd7a6dba2e5640df0b94ed...

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Server Key Exchange
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 215
        Handshake Protocol: Server Key Exchange
            Handshake Type: Server Key Exchange (12)
            Length: 211

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate Request
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 78
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate Request
            Handshake Type: Certificate Request (13)
            Length: 74
            Certificate types count: 1
            Certificate types (1 type)
            Signature Hash Algorithms Length: 2
            Signature Hash Algorithms (1 algorithm)
            Distinguished Names Length: 66
            Distinguished Names (66 bytes)

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Server Hello Done
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 4
        Handshake Protocol: Server Hello Done
            Handshake Type: Server Hello Done (14)
            Length: 0

Client --> Server: 

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 570
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate
            Handshake Type: Certificate (11)
            Length: 566
            Certificates Length: 563
            Certificates (563 bytes)
                Certificate Length: 560
                Certificate (id-at-commonName=PolarSSL Test Client 2,
                id-at-organizationName=PolarSSL,id-at-countryName=NL)
                    signedCertificate
                    algorithmIdentifier (iso.2.840.10045.4.3.2)
                    Padding: 0
                    encrypted: 306502304a650d7b2083a299b9a80ffc8dee8...

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Client Key Exchange
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 138
        Handshake Protocol: Client Key Exchange
            Handshake Type: Client Key Exchange (16)
            Length: 134

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate Verify
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 80
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate Verify
            Handshake Type: Certificate Verify (15)
            Length: 76

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Change Cipher Spec Protocol
        Content Type: Change Cipher Spec (20)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 1
        Change Cipher Spec Message

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: 
        Encrypted Handshake Message (TLS Finished)
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 40
        Handshake Protocol: Encrypted Handshake Message

Client <-- Server:

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Change Cipher Spec Protocol
        Content Type: Change Cipher Spec (20)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 1
        Change Cipher Spec Message

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol
        Encrypted Handshake Message (TLS Finished)
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 40
        Handshake Protocol: Encrypted Handshake Message
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>The TLS cached extension defined in this document allows the server to send an empty Certificate message and an empty CertificateRequest message. To accomplish further on-the-wire handshake size message reductions the Certificate message sent by the client can be reduced in size by using the Client Certificate URL extension. The resulting message exchange is shown in <xref target="example-TLS-exchange-optimized"/>. As it can be seen, this extension leads to an on-the-wire improvement of 640 bytes.</t> 

       <t><figure anchor="example-TLS-exchange-optimized" title="Example TLS Exchange with TLS Cached Info Extension">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
Client --> Server: 

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Client Hello
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 121 + 23
        Handshake Protocol: Client Hello
            Handshake Type: Client Hello (1)
            Length: 117 + 23
            Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
            Random
                gmt_unix_time: Jan 14, 2015 12:43:58.000000000 CET
                random_bytes: c61b966bba2781c50b07c3278c43f5892b3d...
            Session ID Length: 0
            Cipher Suites Length: 10
            Cipher Suites (5 suites)
            Compression Methods Length: 1
            Compression Methods (1 method)
            Extensions Length: 66
            Extension: server_name
            Extension: signature_algorithms
            Extension: elliptic_curves
            Extension: ec_point_formats
            Extension: cached_info

Client <-- Server: 

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Server Hello
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 87
        Handshake Protocol: Server Hello
            Handshake Type: Server Hello (2)
            Length: 83
            Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
            Random
                gmt_unix_time: Jan 14, 2015 12:43:58.000000000 CET
                random_bytes: 82d3d09b44149d738b7002da4ff5a986fe11...
            Session ID Length: 32
            Session ID: d069a74661088676b98db8346070278a7475b617a0...
            Cipher Suite: Unknown (0xc0ad)
            Compression Method: null (0)
            Extensions Length: 11
            Extension: renegotiation_info
            Extension: ec_point_formats

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 4
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate
            Handshake Type: Certificate (11)
            Length: 0
 
    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Server Key Exchange
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 215
        Handshake Protocol: Server Key Exchange
            Handshake Type: Server Key Exchange (12)
            Length: 211

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate Request
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 4
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate Request
            Handshake Type: Certificate Request (13)
            Length: 0

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Server Hello Done
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 4
        Handshake Protocol: Server Hello Done
            Handshake Type: Server Hello Done (14)
            Length: 0

Client --> Server: 

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 570
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate
            Handshake Type: Certificate (11)
            Length: 566
            Certificates Length: 563
            Certificates (563 bytes)
                Certificate Length: 560
                Certificate (id-at-commonName=PolarSSL Test Client 2,
                id-at-organizationName=PolarSSL,id-at-countryName=NL)
                    signedCertificate
                    algorithmIdentifier (iso.2.840.10045.4.3.2)
                    Padding: 0
                    encrypted: 306502304a650d7b2083a299b9a80ffc8dee8...

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Client Key Exchange
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 138
        Handshake Protocol: Client Key Exchange
            Handshake Type: Client Key Exchange (16)
            Length: 134

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: Certificate Verify
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 80
        Handshake Protocol: Certificate Verify
            Handshake Type: Certificate Verify (15)
            Length: 76

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Change Cipher Spec Protocol
        Content Type: Change Cipher Spec (20)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 1
        Change Cipher Spec Message

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol: 
        Encrypted Handshake Message (TLS Finished)
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 40
        Handshake Protocol: Encrypted Handshake Message

Client <-- Server:

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Change Cipher Spec Protocol
        Content Type: Change Cipher Spec (20)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 1
        Change Cipher Spec Message

    TLSv1.2 Record Layer: Handshake Protocol
        Encrypted Handshake Message (TLS Finished)
        Content Type: Handshake (22)
        Version: TLS 1.2 (0x0303)
        Length: 40
        Handshake Protocol: Encrypted Handshake Message
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>


</section> 

    </back>
</rfc>
