<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5246 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5226 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>	
  <!ENTITY RFC1321 PUBLIC ''  
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6066 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6066.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6574 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6574.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7250 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7250.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6234 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6234.xml'>
]>
	
	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
	<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-tls-cached-info-24.txt">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="TLS Cached Information Extension"> Transport Layer Security (TLS) Cached Information Extension </title>

        <author initials="S." surname="Santesson" fullname="Stefan Santesson">
            <organization>3xA Security AB</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Scheelev. 17</street>
					<city>Lund</city>
                    <code>223 70</code>
                    <country>Sweden</country>
                </postal>
                <email>sts@aaa-sec.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

       <author initials="H.T." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig ">
        <organization>ARM Ltd.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Hall in Tirol</city>
          <code> 6060 </code>
          <country>Austria</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Hannes.tschofenig@gmx.net </email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

        <date year="2016"/>
        <area>Security</area>
        <workgroup>TLS</workgroup>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
		
        <abstract>
		 <t>Transport Layer Security (TLS) handshakes often include fairly 
		 static information, such as the server
   certificate and a list of trusted certification authorities (CAs).
   This information can be of considerable size, particularly if the server
   certificate is bundled with a complete certificate chain 
   (i.e., the certificates of intermediate CAs up to the root CA).</t>
   
   <t>This document defines an extension that allows a TLS client to inform a server of cached information, 
   allowing the server to omit already available information.</t>
        </abstract>

    </front>
    <middle>

        <section title="Introduction">

   <t>Reducing the amount of information exchanged during a Transport Layer Security handshake to a minimum helps to 
   improve performance in environments where devices are connected to a 
   network with a low bandwidth, and lossy radio technology. 
   With Internet of Things such environments exist, for example, when devices
   use IEEE 802.15.4, Bluetooth Low Energy, or low power wide area networks. For more information 
   about the challenges with smart object deployments please see 
   <xref target="RFC6574"/>.</t>

   <t>This specification defines a TLS extension that allows a client and a 
   server to exclude information cached in an earlier TLS handshake.
   </t>
   
   <t>A typical example exchange may therefore look as follows. First, the client and the server executes the full TLS handshake. The client then caches the certificate provided by the server. When the TLS client connects to the TLS server again, some time in the future (without using session resumption), it attaches the cached_info extension defined in this document to the client hello message to indicate that it had cached the certificate, and it provides the fingerprint of it. If the server's certificate has not changed then the TLS server does not need to send its certificate and the corresponding certificate chain again. In case information has changed, which can be seen from the fingerprint provided by the client, the certificate payload is transmitted to the client to allow the client to update the cache.</t>

   </section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

        <section title="Terminology">

		<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "MUST", "MUST NOT",   
		"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
		document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
		</t>
		 
		<t>This document refers to the TLS protocol but the description is equally applicable to DTLS as well.</t>  
	</section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

		<section anchor="cached-info" title="Cached Information Extension">
<t>This document defines a new extension type (cached_info(TBD)), which is used in
   client hello and server hello messages. The extension type
   is specified as follows.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      enum {
           cached_info(TBD), (65535)
      } ExtensionType;
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>The extension_data field of this extension, when included in the
client hello, MUST contain the CachedInformation structure. The client 
MAY send multiple CachedObjects of the same CachedInformationType. This may, for example, 
be the case when the client has cached multiple certificates from a server. 
</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      enum {
           cert(1), cert_req(2) (255)
      } CachedInformationType;

      struct {
           select (type) {
             case client: 
               CachedInformationType type;
               opaque hash_value<1..255>;
             case server: 
               CachedInformationType type; 
           } body;
      } CachedObject;

      struct {
           CachedObject cached_info<1..2^16-1>;
      } CachedInformation;
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>This document defines the following two types: 
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="'cert' Type for not sending the complete Server Certificate Message:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> 
With the type field set to 'cert', the client MUST include the fingerprint of the Certificate message in the hash_value field. For this type the fingerprint MUST be calculated using the procedure described in <xref target="fingerprint"/> with the Certificate message as input data.</t>
<t hangText="'cert_req' Type for not sending the complete CertificateRequest Message:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> 
With the type set to 'cert_req', the client MUST include the fingerprint of the CertificateRequest message in the hash_value field. For this type the fingerprint MUST be calculated using the procedure described in <xref target="fingerprint"/> with the CertificateRequest message as input data.</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>New cached info types can be added following the policy described in the IANA considerations section, see <xref target="IANA"/>. These new cached info types must indicate what message digest algorithm is used with these newly defined types. For practical reasons we recommend to re-use hash algorithms already available with TLS implementations to avoid additional code. To keep the collision probably low new hash algorithms MUST NOT have a collision resistance worse than SHA-256.</t>

</section> 

<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

<section title="Exchange Specification">

<t>Clients supporting this extension MAY include the "cached_info" extension in the (extended) client hello. If the client includes the extension then it MUST contain one or more CachedObject attributes.</t>

<t>A server supporting this extension MAY include the "cached_info" extension in the (extended) server hello. By returning the "cached_info" extension the server indicates what cached info types it supports. For each indicated cached info type the server MAY alter the transmission of respective payloads, according to the rules outlined with each type. Whether the server actually alters the transmission of the payload depends on outcome of the comparison  between the fingerprint provided by the client and the information the server would normally send. In any case, if the server includes the "cached_info" extension it MUST only include CachedObjects of a type also supported by the client (as expressed in the client hello). For example, if a client indicates support for 'cert' and 'cert_req' then the server cannot respond with a "cached_info" attribute containing support for ('foo-bar').</t>

<t>Since the client includes a fingerprint of information it cached (for each indicated type) the server is able to determine whether cached information is stale. If the server supports a specific cached info type and notices a mismatch between the data cached by the client and its own information for this cached info type then the server MUST include the information in full of this cached info type.</t>

<t>Note: If a server is part of a hosting environment then the client may have cached multiple data items for a single server. To allow the client to select the appropriate information from the cache it is RECOMMENDED that the client utilizes the Server Name Indication extension <xref target="RFC6066"/>.</t>

<t>Following a successful exchange of the "cached_info" extension in the client and server hello, the server alters sending the corresponding handshake message. How information is altered from the handshake messages is defined in <xref target="cert"/>, and in <xref target="cert_req"/> for the types defined in this specification.</t>

<t>A client needs to distinguish a message that contains a fingerprint from one that contains the full, unaltered payload. This can be accomplished by utilizing the length field of the message. Shorter payloads contain hashes whereas longer payloads contain the unaltered payloads. For example, a server may send a fingerprint in a Certificate message (as explained in <xref target="cert"/>) rather than the full certificate payload.</t> 

<t><xref target="example-hash"/> shows an example hash calculation and <xref target="example-exchange"/> illustrates an example protocol exchange.</t>

<section anchor="cert" title="Server Certificate Message">

<t>When a ClientHello message contains the "cached_info" extension with a type set to 'cert' then the server MAY send the Certificate message shown in <xref target="cert-structure-modified"/> under the following conditions:

<list style="symbols">
<t>The server software implements the "cached_info" extension defined in this specification.</t>
<t>The 'cert' cached info extension is enabled (for example, a policy allows the use of this extension).</t>
<t>The server compared the value in the hash_value field of the client-provided "cached_info" extension with the fingerprint of the Certificate message it normally sends to clients. This check ensures that the information cached by the client is current. The procedure for calculating the fingerprint is described in <xref target="fingerprint"/>.</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>Note that an implementation may choose to return a ServerHello message already before constructing the Certificate message.</t>

<t>The original Certificate handshake message syntax is defined in  <xref target="RFC5246"/> and has been extended with <xref target="RFC7250"/>. RFC 7250 allows the certificate payload to contain only the SubjectPublicKeyInfo instead of the full information typically found in a certificate. Hence, when this specification is used in combination with <xref target="RFC7250"/> and the negotiated certificate type is a raw public key then the TLS server omits sending a Certificate payload that contains an ASN.1 Certificate structure with the included SubjectPublicKeyInfo rather than the full certificate chain. As such, this extension is compatible with the raw public key extension defined in RFC 7250.</t> 

<t>Note that we assume that the server implementation is able to select the appropriate certificate or SubjectPublicKeyInfo from the received hash value. If the SNI extension is used by the client then the server has additional information to guide the selection of the appropriate cached info. </t>

<t>When the cached info specification is used (and the client has cached the certificate already) then a modified version of the Certificate message is exchanged. The modified structure is shown in <xref target="cert-structure-modified"/>.</t>

           <t><figure anchor="cert-structure-modified" title="Cached Info Certificate Message.">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
      struct {
          opaque hash_value<1..255>;
      } Certificate;
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
		  </t>
   </section> 

<section anchor="cert_req" title="CertificateRequest Message">

<t>When a fingerprint for an object of type 'cert_req' is provided in the client hello, the server MAY send the CertificateRequest message shown in <xref target="certreq-structure-modified"/> under the following conditions:

<list style="symbols">
<t>The server software implements the "cached_info" extension defined in this specification.</t>
<t>The 'cert_req' cached info extension is enabled (for example, a policy allows the use of this extension).</t>
<t>The server compared the value in the hash_value field of the client-provided "cached_info" extension with the fingerprint of the CertificateRequest message it normally sends to clients. This check ensures that the information cached by the client is current. The procedure for calculating the fingerprint is described in <xref target="fingerprint"/>.</t>
<t>The server wants to request a certificate from the client.</t> 
</list> 
</t>

<t>The original CertificateRequest handshake message syntax is defined in <xref target="RFC5246"/>. The modified structure of the CertificateRequest message is shown in <xref target="certreq-structure-modified"/>.</t>

<t><figure anchor="certreq-structure-modified" title="Cached Info CertificateRequest Message.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[
      struct {
          opaque hash_value<1..255>;
      } CertificateRequest;
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</t>

<t>The CertificateRequest payload is the input parameter to the fingerprint calculation described in <xref target="fingerprint"/>.</t>

</section>

</section> 

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

<section anchor="fingerprint" title="Fingerprint Calculation"> 

<t>The fingerprint for the two cached info objects defined in this document MUST be computed as follows:
<list style="numbers"> 
<t>Compute the SHA-256 <xref target="RFC6234"/> hash of the input data. The input data depends on the cached info type. This document defines two cached info types, described in 
<xref target="cert"/> and in <xref target="cert_req"/>. Note that the computed hash only covers the input data structure (and not any type and length information of the record layer). <xref target="example-hash"/> shows an example. </t> 
<t>Use the output of the SHA-256 hash.</t> 
</list> 
</t> 

<t>The purpose of the fingerprint provided by the client is to help the server select the correct information. For example, in case of the certificate message the fingerprint identifies the server certificate (and consequently the corresponding private key) for use with the rest of the handshake. Servers may have, for example, more than one certificate and therefore the fingerprint needs to be long enough to keep the probably of hash collisions low. On the other hand, the cached info design aims to reduce the amount of data being exchanged. The security of the handshake depends on the private key and not on the size of the fingerprint. Hence, the fingerprint is a way to prevent the server from accidentally selecting the wrong information. If an attacker injects an incorrect fingerprint then two outcomes are possible: <list style='hanging'> 
<t>(1) The fingerprint does not relate to any cached state and the server has to fall back to a full exchange.</t> 
<t>(2) If the attacker manages to inject a fingerprint that refers to data the client has not cached then the exchange will fail later when the client continues with the handshake and aims to verify the digital signature. The signature verification will fail since the public key cached by the client will not correspond to the private key that was used by server to sign the message.</t> 
</list> 
</t> 

</section> 

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->
   
        <section anchor="example-exchange" title="Example">

<t>In the regular, full TLS handshake exchange, shown in <xref target="exampleA"/>, the TLS server provides its certificate 
in the Certificate payload to the client, see step (1). This allows the client to store the certificate 
for future use. After some time the TLS client again interacts with the same TLS server and makes use of the
TLS cached info extension, as shown in <xref target="exampleB"/>. The TLS client indicates support for this specification 
via the "cached_info" extension, see step (2), and indicates that it has stored the certificate from the earlier 
exchange (by indicating the 'cert' type). With step (3) the TLS server acknowledges the supports of the 'cert' type and by including the value in the server hello informs the client that the content of the certificate payload contains the fingerprint of the certificate instead of the RFC 5246 defined payload of the certificate message in step (4).</t>

           <t><figure anchor="exampleA" title="Example Message Exchange: Initial (full) Exchange.">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
ClientHello            ->
                       <-  ServerHello
                           Certificate* // (1)
                           ServerKeyExchange*
                           CertificateRequest*
                           ServerHelloDone 

Certificate*
ClientKeyExchange
CertificateVerify*
[ChangeCipherSpec]
Finished               ->

                       <- [ChangeCipherSpec]
                          Finished

Application Data <-------> Application Data
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>


           <t><figure anchor="exampleB" title="Example Message Exchange: TLS Cached Extension Usage.">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
ClientHello 
cached_info=(cert)     -> // (2)
                       <-  ServerHello
                           cached_info=(cert) (3) 
                           Certificate (4)
                           ServerKeyExchange*
                           ServerHelloDone 

ClientKeyExchange
CertificateVerify*
[ChangeCipherSpec]
Finished               ->

                       <- [ChangeCipherSpec]
                          Finished

Application Data <-------> Application Data
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        </section> 
		  
        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->
   
        <section title="Security Considerations">

            <t>This specification defines a mechanism to reference stored state using a fingerprint.
		Sending a fingerprint of cached information in an
   unencrypted handshake, as the client and server hello is, may allow an attacker or observer to 
   correlate independent TLS exchanges. While some information elements used in this specification,
   such as server certificates, are public objects and usually do not contain 
   sensitive information, other not yet defined types may. Those who implement and deploy this specification should therefore 
   make an informed decision whether the cached information is inline with their security and privacy goals. 
   In case of concerns, it is advised to avoid sending the fingerprint of the data objects in clear.</t>

   <t>The use of the cached info extension allows the server to send significantly smaller TLS messages. Consequently, these omitted parts of the messages are not included in the transcript of the handshake in the TLS Finish message. However, since the client and the server communicate the hash values of the cached data in the initial handshake messages the fingerprints are included in the TLS Finish message. </t>

<t>Clients MUST ensure that they only cache information from legitimate sources. For example, when the client populates the cache from a TLS exchange then it must only cache information after the successful completion of a TLS exchange to ensure that an attacker does not inject incorrect information into the cache. Failure to do so allows for man-in-the-middle attacks.</t> 
   
<t>Security considerations for the fingerprint calculation are discussed in <xref target="fingerprint"/>.</t> 
        </section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

        <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

<section title="New Entry to the TLS ExtensionType Registry"> 
<t>IANA is requested to add an entry to the existing TLS ExtensionType registry, 
defined in <xref target="RFC5246"/>, for cached_info(TBD) defined in this document.</t>
</section> 

<section title="New Registry for CachedInformationType">
      <t>IANA is requested to establish a registry for TLS CachedInformationType values.  The
      first entries in the registry are 
        <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>reserved(0)</t>
	    <t>cert(1)</t> 
      	    <t>cert_req(2)</t>
         </list> 
      </t>

      <t>The policy for adding new values to this registry, following the terminology defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, is as follows:
	  <list style="symbols"> 
	    <t>0-63 (decimal): Standards Action</t>
	    <t>64-223 (decimal): Specification Required</t>
            <t>224-255 (decimal): reserved for Private Use</t>
	  </list> 
      </t>
</section>

</section> 

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

        <section title="Acknowledgments">

   <t>We would like to thank the following persons for your detailed document reviews:
   <list style="symbols"> 
     <t>Paul Wouters and Nikos Mavrogiannopoulos (December 2011)</t> 
     <t>Rob Stradling (February 2012)</t> 
     <t>Ondrej Mikle (March 2012)</t>
     <t>Ilari Liusvaara, Adam Langley, and Eric Rescorla (July 2014)</t>
     <t>Sean Turner (August 2014)</t>
     <t>Martin Thomson (August 2015)</t>
     <t>Jouni Korhonen (November 2015)</t>
     <t>Matt Miller (December 2015)</t>
     <t>Dave Garrett (December 2015)</t>
     <t>Anirudh Ramachandran (March 2016)</t> 
   </list> 
   </t> 
  
   <t>We would also to thank Martin Thomson, Karthikeyan Bhargavan, Sankalp Bagaria and Eric Rescorla for their feedback regarding the fingerprint calculation.</t> 

   <t>Finally, we would like to thank the TLS working group chairs, Sean Turner and Joe Salowey, as well as the responsible security area director, Stephen Farrell, for their support and their reviews.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->

    </middle>
    <back>



        <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC5246; &RFC6066; 

<!-- 
           <reference anchor="SHA">
                <front>
                    <title>Federal Information Processing Standards Publication (FIPS PUB) 180-3, Secure Hash Standard (SHS)</title>
                    <author initials="" surname="" fullname="NIST">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="October" year="2008"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
     --> 
            
&RFC6234; 

<!--			&RFC1321; --> 
			
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References"> &RFC5226; &RFC6574; &RFC7250; 

    <reference anchor='ASN.1-Dump' target='http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/'>
       <front>
       <title>ASN.1 Object Dump Program</title>
       <author initials='P.' surname='Gutmann' fullname='Peter Gutmann'>
       <organization /></author>
       <date year='2013' month='February' />
       </front>
       <format type='HTML' target='http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/' />
    </reference>
    
    


</references>

<section anchor="example-hash" title="Example">

<t>Consider a certificate containing an NIST P256 elliptic curve public key displayed using Peter
Gutmann's ASN.1 decoder <xref target="ASN.1-Dump"/> in <xref target="example-certificate"/>.</t>

 <t><figure anchor="example-certificate" title="ASN.1-based Certificate: Example.">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
  0 556: SEQUENCE {
  4 434:   SEQUENCE {
  8   3:     [0] {
 10   1:       INTEGER 2
       :       }
 13   1:     INTEGER 13
 16  10:     SEQUENCE {
 18   8:      OBJECT IDENTIFIER ecdsaWithSHA256 (1 2 840 10045 4 3 2)
       :       }
 28  62:     SEQUENCE {
 30  11:       SET {
 32   9:         SEQUENCE {
 34   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER countryName (2 5 4 6)
 39   2:           PrintableString 'NL'
       :           }
       :         }
 43  17:       SET {
 45  15:         SEQUENCE {
 47   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER organizationName (2 5 4 10)
 52   8:           PrintableString 'PolarSSL'
       :           }
       :         }
 62  28:       SET {
 64  26:         SEQUENCE {
 66   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER commonName (2 5 4 3)
 71  19:           PrintableString 'Polarssl Test EC CA'
       :           }
       :         }
       :       }
 92  30:     SEQUENCE {
 94  13:       UTCTime 24/09/2013 15:52:04 GMT
109  13:       UTCTime 22/09/2023 15:52:04 GMT
       :       }
124  65:     SEQUENCE {
126  11:       SET {
128   9:         SEQUENCE {
130   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER countryName (2 5 4 6)
135   2:           PrintableString 'NL'
       :           }
       :         }
139  17:       SET {
141  15:         SEQUENCE {
143   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER organizationName (2 5 4 10)
148   8:           PrintableString 'PolarSSL'
       :           }
       :         }
158  31:       SET {
160  29:         SEQUENCE {
162   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER commonName (2 5 4 3)
167  22:           PrintableString 'PolarSSL Test Client 2'
       :           }
       :         }
       :       }
191  89:     SEQUENCE {
193  19:       SEQUENCE {
195   7:         OBJECT IDENTIFIER ecPublicKey (1 2 840 10045 2 1)
204   8:         OBJECT IDENTIFIER prime256v1 (1 2 840 10045 3 1 7)
       :         }
214  66:       BIT STRING
       :         04 57 E5 AE B1 73 DF D3 AC BB 93 B8 81 FF 12 AE
       :         EE E6 53 AC CE 55 53 F6 34 0E CC 2E E3 63 25 0B
       :         DF 98 E2 F3 5C 60 36 96 C0 D5 18 14 70 E5 7F 9F
       :         D5 4B 45 18 E5 B0 6C D5 5C F8 96 8F 87 70 A3 E4
       :         C7
       :       }
282 157:     [3] {
285 154:       SEQUENCE {
288   9:         SEQUENCE {
290   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER basicConstraints (2 5 29 19)
295   2:           OCTET STRING, encapsulates {
297   0:             SEQUENCE {}
       :             }
       :           }
299  29:         SEQUENCE {
301   3:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER subjectKeyIdentifier (2 5 29 14)
306  22:           OCTET STRING, encapsulates {
308  20:             OCTET STRING
       :              7A 00 5F 86 64 FC E0 5D E5 11 10 3B B2 E6 3B C4
       :              26 3F CF E2
       :             }
       :           }
330 110:         SEQUENCE {
332   3:          OBJECT IDENTIFIER authorityKeyIdentifier (2 5 29 35)
337 103:          OCTET STRING, encapsulates {
339 101:             SEQUENCE {
341  20:               [0]
       :               9D 6D 20 24 49 01 3F 2B CB 78 B5 19 BC 7E 24 
       :               C9 DB FB 36 7C
363  66:               [1] {
365  64:                 [4] {
367  62:                   SEQUENCE {
369  11:                     SET {
371   9:                      SEQUENCE {
373   3:                       OBJECT IDENTIFIER countryName (2 5 4 6)
378   2:                       PrintableString 'NL'
       :                       }
       :                      }
382  17:                     SET {
384  15:                      SEQUENCE {
386   3:                        OBJECT IDENTIFIER organizationName 
       :                               (2 5 4 10)
391   8:                        PrintableString 'PolarSSL'
       :                        }
       :                      }
401  28:                     SET {
403  26:                      SEQUENCE {
405   3:                       OBJECT IDENTIFIER commonName (2 5 4 3)
410  19:                       PrintableString 'Polarssl Test EC CA'
       :                        }
       :                      }
       :                     }
       :                   }
       :                 }
431   9:               [2] 00 C1 43 E2 7E 62 43 CC E8
       :               }
       :             }
       :           }
       :         }
       :       }
       :     }
442  10:   SEQUENCE {
444   8:     OBJECT IDENTIFIER ecdsaWithSHA256 (1 2 840 10045 4 3 2)
       :     }
454 104:   BIT STRING, encapsulates {
457 101:     SEQUENCE {
459  48:       INTEGER
       :         4A 65 0D 7B 20 83 A2 99 B9 A8 0F FC 8D EE 8F 3D
       :         BB 70 4C 96 03 AC 8E 78 70 DD F2 0E A0 B2 16 CB
       :         65 8E 1A C9 3F 2C 61 7E F8 3C EF AD 1C EE 36 20
509  49:       INTEGER
       :         00 9D F2 27 A6 D5 74 B8 24 AE E1 6A 3F 31 A1 CA
       :         54 2F 08 D0 8D EE 4F 0C 61 DF 77 78 7D B4 FD FC
       :         42 49 EE E5 B2 6A C2 CD 26 77 62 8E 28 7C 9E 57
       :         45
       :       }
       :     }
       :   }
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>To include the certificate shown in <xref target="example-certificate"/> in a TLS/DTLS Certificate message it is prepended with a message header. This Certificate message header in our example is 0b 00 02 36 00 02 33 00 02 00 02 30, which indicates:

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="Message Type:"> 0b -- 1 byte type field indicating a Certificate message</t>
<t hangText="Length:"> 00 02 36 -- 3 byte length field indicating a 566 bytes payload</t>
<t hangText="Certificates Length:"> 00 02 33 -- 3 byte length field indicating 563 bytes for the entire certificates_list structure, which may contain multiple certificates. In our example only one certificate is included.</t>
<t hangText="Certificate Length:"> 00 02 30 -- 3 byte length field indicating 560 bytes of the actual certificate following immediately afterwards. In our example, this is the certificate content with 30 82 02 .... 9E 57 45 shown in <xref target="example-cert-hex"/>.</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>The hex encoding of the ASN.1 encoded certificate payload shown in <xref target="example-certificate"/> leads to the following encoding.</t>

<t><figure anchor="example-cert-hex" title="Hex Encoding of the Example Certificate.">
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
          30 82 02 2C 30 82 01 B2  A0 03 02 01 02 02 01 0D
          30 0A 06 08 2A 86 48 CE  3D 04 03 02 30 3E 31 0B
          30 09 06 03 55 04 06 13  02 4E 4C 31 11 30 0F 06
          03 55 04 0A 13 08 50 6F  6C 61 72 53 53 4C 31 1C
          30 1A 06 03 55 04 03 13  13 50 6F 6C 61 72 73 73
          6C 20 54 65 73 74 20 45  43 20 43 41 30 1E 17 0D
          31 33 30 39 32 34 31 35  35 32 30 34 5A 17 0D 32
          33 30 39 32 32 31 35 35  32 30 34 5A 30 41 31 0B
          30 09 06 03 55 04 06 13  02 4E 4C 31 11 30 0F 06
          03 55 04 0A 13 08 50 6F  6C 61 72 53 53 4C 31 1F
          30 1D 06 03 55 04 03 13  16 50 6F 6C 61 72 53 53
          4C 20 54 65 73 74 20 43  6C 69 65 6E 74 20 32 30
          59 30 13 06 07 2A 86 48  CE 3D 02 01 06 08 2A 86
          48 CE 3D 03 01 07 03 42  00 04 57 E5 AE B1 73 DF
          D3 AC BB 93 B8 81 FF 12  AE EE E6 53 AC CE 55 53
          F6 34 0E CC 2E E3 63 25  0B DF 98 E2 F3 5C 60 36
          96 C0 D5 18 14 70 E5 7F  9F D5 4B 45 18 E5 B0 6C
          D5 5C F8 96 8F 87 70 A3  E4 C7 A3 81 9D 30 81 9A
          30 09 06 03 55 1D 13 04  02 30 00 30 1D 06 03 55
          1D 0E 04 16 04 14 7A 00  5F 86 64 FC E0 5D E5 11
          10 3B B2 E6 3B C4 26 3F  CF E2 30 6E 06 03 55 1D
          23 04 67 30 65 80 14 9D  6D 20 24 49 01 3F 2B CB
          78 B5 19 BC 7E 24 C9 DB  FB 36 7C A1 42 A4 40 30
          3E 31 0B 30 09 06 03 55  04 06 13 02 4E 4C 31 11
          30 0F 06 03 55 04 0A 13  08 50 6F 6C 61 72 53 53
          4C 31 1C 30 1A 06 03 55  04 03 13 13 50 6F 6C 61
          72 73 73 6C 20 54 65 73  74 20 45 43 20 43 41 82
          09 00 C1 43 E2 7E 62 43  CC E8 30 0A 06 08 2A 86
          48 CE 3D 04 03 02 03 68  00 30 65 02 30 4A 65 0D
          7B 20 83 A2 99 B9 A8 0F  FC 8D EE 8F 3D BB 70 4C
          96 03 AC 8E 78 70 DD F2  0E A0 B2 16 CB 65 8E 1A
          C9 3F 2C 61 7E F8 3C EF  AD 1C EE 36 20 02 31 00
          9D F2 27 A6 D5 74 B8 24  AE E1 6A 3F 31 A1 CA 54
          2F 08 D0 8D EE 4F 0C 61  DF 77 78 7D B4 FD FC 42
          49 EE E5 B2 6A C2 CD 26  77 62 8E 28 7C 9E 57 45
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

<t>Applying the SHA-256 hash function to the Certificate message, which is starts with 0b 00 02 and ends with 9E 57 45, produces 0x086eefb4859adfe977defac494fff6b73033b4ce1f86b8f2a9fc0c6bf98605af.</t>

</section> 

    </back>
</rfc>
