<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2629 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4006 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4006.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3588 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.asveren-dime-dupcons PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.asveren-dime-dupcons.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-integrated PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-integrated.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-diameter-qos PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-diameter-qos.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-qos-attributes PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-qos-attributes.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-dime-app-design-guide-16"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>Diameter Applications Design Guidelines</title>

    <author fullname="Lionel Morand" initials="L." role="editor"
            surname="Morand">
      <organization>Orange Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <email>lionel.morand@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Victor Fajardo" initials="V." surname="Fajardo">
      <address>
        <email>vf0213@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>

          <city>Espoo</city>

          <code>02600</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>

        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="22" month="October" year="2012"/>

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

    <workgroup>Diameter Maintenance and Extensions (DIME)</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Diameter Base protocol provides facilities for protocol
      extensibility enabling to define new Diameter applications or modify
      existing applications. This document is a companion document to the
      Diameter base protocol that further explains and clarifies the rules to
      extend the Diameter base protocol. It is meant as a guidelines document
      and therefore it does not add, remove or change existing rules.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Diameter base protocol provides facilities to extend the Diameter
      base protocol (see Section 1.3 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>) for supporting new functionalities.
      In the context of this document, extending Diameter means one of the
      following:<vspace blankLines="1"/> <list style="numbers">
          <t>Addition of a new functionality to an existing Diameter
          application without defining a new application.<vspace
          blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>Addition of a new functionality to an existing Diameter
          application that requires the definition of a new application.
          <vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>The definition of a new Diameter application to provide a set of
          functionalities not supported by existing applications. <vspace
          blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>The definition of a new generic functionality that can be reused
          across different applications.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>
        </list>All of these choices are design decisions that can be done by
      any combination of reusing existing or defining new commands, AVPs or
      AVP values. However, application designers do not have total freedom
      when making their design. A number of rules have been defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> and place constraints on when an
      extension requires the allocation of a new Diameter application
      identifier or a new command code value. The objective of this document
      is the following:<vspace blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
          <t>Clarify updated Diameter extensibility rules in the Diameter base
          protocol. <vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>Clarify usage of certain Diameter functionalities that are not
          explicitly described in the Diameter Base specification.<vspace
          blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>Discuss design choices and provide guidelines when defining new
          applications. <vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>Present trade-off of design choices.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document reuses the terminology used in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>As designed, the Diameter base protocol <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> can be seen as a two-layer protocol.
      The lower layer is mainly responsible for managing connections between
      neighboring peers and for message routing. The upper layer is where the
      Diameter applications reside. This model is in line with a Diameter node
      having an application layer and a peer-to-peer delivery layer. The
      Diameter base protocol document defines the architecture and behavior of
      the message delivery layer and then provides the framework for designing
      Diameter applications on the application layer. This framework includes
      definitions of application sessions and accounting support (see Section
      8 and 9 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>). Accordingly, a
      Diameter node is seen in this document as a single instance of a
      Diameter message delivery layer and one or more Diameter applications
      using it.</t>

      <t>The Diameter base protocol is designed to be extensible and the
      principles are described in the section 1.3 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>. Extending Diameter can mean either
      the definition of a completely new Diameter application or the reuse of
      commands, AVPs and AVP values in any combination for the purpose of
      inheriting the features of an existing Diameter application. The
      recommendation for re-using as much as possible existing implementations
      is meaningful as most of the requirements defined for a new application
      are likely already fulfilled by existing applications.</t>

      <t>However, when reusing existing applications, there is a greater
      likelihood of ambiguity on how much of the existing application can be
      enhanced without being distorted too much and therefore requiring the
      definition of a new application.</t>

      <t>The impacts of extending existing applications can be categorized as
      follow:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Minor Extension:">Enhancing the functional scope of an
          existing application by the addition of optional features to
          support. Such enhancement has no backward compatibility issue with
          the existing application. A typical example would be the definition
          of a new optional AVP to use in an existing command. Diameter
          implementations supporting the existing application but not the new
          AVP will simply ignore it, without major consequences on the
          Diameter message handling. In general, this includes everything that
          is not covered by the next category. The standardization effort will
          be fairly small. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

          <t hangText="Major Extension:">Enhancing the functional scope of an
          existing application in such a way that this implies backward
          compatible change to the existing application and then requires the
          definition of a new Diameter application. Typical examples would be
          the creation of a new command for providing functionality not
          supported by existing applications or the definition of a new AVP
          with M-bit set to carry in an existing command. For such extension,
          a significant specification effort is required and a careful
          approach is recommended.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The rules outlined in the section 1.3 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> indicate when an extension requires
      a new command code to be registered and when new Diameter applications
      have to be defined. The subsequent sections further explain and clarify
      the rules to extend the Diameter base protocol. It is meant as a
      guidelines document and therefore it does not add, remove or change
      existing rules.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Reusing Existing Diameter Applications">
      <t>When selecting the Diameter base protocol to support new
      functionalities, protocol designers are advised to reuse as much as
      possible existing Diameter applications in order to simplify
      standardization, implementation and avoid potential interoperability
      issues. However, existing application needs to be adapted to support new
      requirements and these modifications can be at the command level and/or
      at the AVP level. The following sections describe the possible
      modifications that can be performed on existing applications and their
      related impacts.</t>

      <section title="Adding a New Command">
        <t>Adding a new command is considered as a major extension and
        requires a new Diameter application to be defined. Adding a new
        command to an application means either defining a completely new
        command or importing the command's CCF syntax specification from
        another application whereby the new application inherits some or all
        of the functionality of the application where the command came from.
        In the former case, the decision to create a new application is
        straightforward since this is typically a result of adding a new
        functionality that does not exist yet. For the latter, the decision to
        create a new application will depend on whether importing the command
        in a new application is more suitable than simply using the existing
        application as it is in conjunction with any other application.
        Therefore, a case by case study of each application requirement should
        be applied.</t>

        <t>An illustrative example is the command pair defined in Diameter EAP
        application <xref target="RFC4072"/> that can be re-used conjointly
        with any other application (e.g. the Diameter NASREQ application <xref
        target="RFC4005"/>) as soon as standard EAP-based authentication
        procedures need to be supported by the implementation. It may
        therefore not be required to import the command pair in the new
        defined application.</t>

        <t>However, in general, it is difficult to come to a hard guideline,
        and so a case-by-case study of each application requirement should be
        applied. Before adding or importing a command, application designers
        should consider the following:<vspace blankLines="1"/> <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Can the new functionality be fulfilled by creating a new
            command independent from any existing command? In this case, the
            resulting new application and the existing application can work
            independent of, but cooperating with each other.<vspace
            blankLines="0"/></t>

            <t>Can the existing command be reused without major extensions and
            therefore without the need for the definition of a new
            application, e.g. new functionality introduced by the creation of
            new optional AVPs.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

            <t>Care should be taken to avoid a liberal method of importing an
            existing command's CCF syntax specification. This would result in
            a monolithic and hard to manage application supporting too many
            different functionalities and can cause interoperability issues
            between the different applications.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>
          </list><vspace blankLines="0"/></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Deleting an Existing Command">
        <t>Although this process is not typical, removing a command from an
        application requires a new Diameter application to be defined. This is
        due to the fact that the reception of the deleted command would
        systematically result in a protocol error
        (DIAMETER_COMMAND_UNSUPPORTED).</t>

        <t>It is unusual to delete an existing command from an application for
        the sake of deleting it or the functionality it represents. This
        normally indicates of a flawed design. An exception might be if the
        intent of the deletion is to create a newer version of the same
        application that is somehow simpler than the previous version.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reusing Existing Commands">
        <t>This section discusses rules in adding and/or deleting AVPs from an
        existing command of an existing application. The cases described in
        this section may not necessarily result in the creation of new
        applications.</t>

        <t>It is worth to note that the strong recommendation to re-use
        existing commands in the <xref target="RFC3588"/> was to prevent rapid
        scarcity of code values available for vendor-specific commands. <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> relaxes the policy with respect to
        the allocation of command codes for vendor-specific uses and enlarges
        the range of available code values for vendor-specific applications.
        Although reuse of existing commands is still recommended, protocol
        designers can consider defining a new command when it provides a
        solution more suitable than the twisting of an existing command's use
        and applications.</t>

        <section title="Adding AVPs to a Command">
          <t>Based on the rules in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>,
          AVPs that are added to an existing command can be categorized
          into:<vspace blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
              <t>Mandatory (to understand) AVPs. As defined in <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>, these are AVPs with the
              M-bit flag set, which means that a Diameter node receiving them
              is required to understand not only their values but their
              semantics. Failure to do so will cause an message handling
              error. This is regardless of whether these AVPs are required or
              optional as specified by the command's CCF syntax
              specification.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

              <t>Optional (to understand) AVPs. As defined in <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>, these are AVPs with the
              M-bit flag cleared, which mean that a Diameter node receiving
              these AVPs can simply ignore them if not supported in the
              process of the received command.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The rules are strict in the case where the AVPs to be added are
          mandatory to understand i.e. with the M-bit set. A mandatory AVP
          cannot be added to an existing command without defining a new
          Diameter application, as stated in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>. This falls into the "Major
          Extensions" category. Despite the clarity of the rule, ambiguity
          still arises when evaluating whether a new AVP being added should be
          mandatory to begin with. Application designers should consider the
          following questions when deciding to set the M-bit for a new AVP:
          <vspace blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
              <t>Would it be required for the receiving side to be able to
              process and understand the AVP and its content?<vspace
              blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Would the new AVPs change the state machine of the
              application?<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Would the presence of the new AVP lead to a different number
              of round-trips, effectively changing the state machine of the
              application?<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Would the new AVP be used to differentiate between old and
              new versions of the same application whereby the two versions
              are not backward compatible?<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Would the new AVP have duality in meaning i.e. be used to
              carry application-related information as well as be used to
              indicate that the message is for a new application?</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>When one of the above questions can be answered in the
          affirmative then the M-bit has to be set for the new AVP. This list
          of questions is non-exhaustive and other criteria can be taken into
          account in the decision process.</t>

          <t>If application designers are instead contemplating the use of
          optional AVPs i.e. with the M-bit cleared, then the following are
          some of the pitfalls that should be avoided:<vspace
          blankLines="1"/></t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Use of optional AVPs with intersecting meaning. One AVP has
              partially the same usage and meaning as another AVP. The
              presence of both can lead to confusion. <vspace
              blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>An optional AVPs with dual purpose, i.e. to carry application
              data as well as to indicate support for one or more features.
              This has a tendency to introduce interpretation issues.<vspace
              blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Adding one or more optional AVPs and indicating (usually
              within descriptive text for the command) that at least one of
              them has to be present in the command. This essentially
              circumventing the ABNF and is equivalent to adding a mandatory
              AVP to the command.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>
            </list>These practices generally result in interoperability issues
          and should be avoided as much as possible.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Deleting AVPs from a Command">
          <t>The impacts of deleting an AVP from a command depend on its
          command code format specification and M-bit setting: <vspace
          blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
              <t>Deleting an AVP that is indicated as { AVP } in the command's
              CCF syntax specification, whatever the setting of the M-bit set.
              This means the definition of a new command. In this case, a new
              command code and subsequently a new Diameter application have to
              be specified.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Deleting an AVP with M-bit set that is indicated as [ AVP ]
              in the command's CCF syntax specification. No new command code
              has to be specified but the definition of a new Diameter
              application is required.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

              <t>Deleting an AVP with the M-bit cleared that is indicated as [
              AVP ] in the command's CCF syntax specification. In this case,
              the AVP can be deleted without consequences.<vspace
              blankLines="1"/></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>If possible application designers should attempt the reuse the
          command's CCF syntax specification without modification and simply
          ignore (but not delete) any optional AVP that will not be used. This
          is to maintain compatibility with existing applications that will
          not know about the new functionality as well as maintain the
          integrity of existing dictionaries.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Reusing Existing AVPs">
        <t>This section discusses rules in reusing existing AVP when reusing
        an existing command or defining a new command in a new
        application.</t>

        <section title="Setting of the AVP Flags">
          <t>When reusing AVPs in a new application, the AVP flag setting,
          such as the mandatory flag ('M'-bit), has to be re-evaluated for a
          new Diameter application and, if necessary, even for every command
          within the application. In general, for AVPs defined outside of the
          Diameter base protocol, its mandatory characteristics are tied to
          its role within an application and command.</t>

          <t>All other AVP flags shall remain unchanged.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Reuse of AVP of Type Enumerated">
          <t>When modifying the set of values supported by an AVP of type
          Enumerated, this means defining a new AVP. Modifying the set of
          Enumerated values includes adding a value or deprecating the use of
          a value defined initially for the AVP. Defining a new AVP will avoid
          interoperability issues.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Defining New Diameter Applications">
      <section title="Introduction">
        <t>The general recommendation for Diameter extensibility is to reuse
        commands, AVPs and AVP values as much as possible. However, some of
        the extensibility rules described in the previous sections also apply
        to scenarios where a designer is trying to define a completely new
        Diameter application.</t>

        <t>This section discusses the case where new applications have
        requirements that cannot be filled by existing applications and would
        require definition of completely new commands, AVPs and/or AVP values.
        Typically, there is little ambiguity about the decision to create
        these types of applications. Some examples are the interfaces defined
        for the IP Multimedia Subsystem of 3GPP, i.e. Cx/Dx (<xref
        target="TS29.228"/> and <xref target="TS29.229"/>), Sh (<xref
        target="TS29.328"/> and <xref target="TS29.329"/>) etc.</t>

        <t>Application designers should also follow the theme of Diameter
        extensibility, which in this case means to import existing AVPs and
        AVP values for any newly defined commands. In certain cases where
        accounting will be used, the models described in <xref
        target="other-accounting"/> should also be considered. Though some
        decisions may be clear, designers should also consider certain aspects
        of defining a new application. Some of these aspects are described in
        following sections.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Defining New Commands">
        <t>As a general recommendation, reusing as much as possible of
        existing material is encouraged when defining new commands. Protocol
        designers can thus usefully benefit from the experience gained with
        the implementation of existing commands. This includes good practices
        to reuse but also known mistakes not to repeat. Therefore it is
        advisable to avoid the definition of a command from scratch and rather
        take as an example an existing command that would be functionally
        close to command under definition.</t>

        <t>Moreover, the new command's CCF should be carefully defined when
        considering applicability and extensibility of the application. If
        most of the AVPs contained in the command are indicated as fixed or
        required, it might be difficult to reuse the same command and
        therefore the same application if the context has slightly changed and
        some AVPs become obsolete. Defining a command with most of the AVPs
        indicated as optional must not be seen as a sub-optimal design
        introducing too much flexibility in the protocol. The protocol
        designers are only advised to clearly state the condition of presence
        of these AVPs and properly define the corresponding behaviour of the
        Diameter nodes when these AVPs are absent from the command.</t>

        <t>In the same way, the CCF should be defined in a way that it will be
        possible to add any arbitrary optional AVPs with the M-bit cleared
        (including vendor-specific AVPs) without modifying the application.
        For this purpose, it is strongly recommended to add "* [AVP]" in the
        command's CCF that will allow the addition of any arbitrary AVP as
        described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of Application-Id in a Message">
        <t>When designing new applications, designers should specify that the
        application ID carried in all session-level messages must be the
        application ID of the application using those messages. This includes
        the session-level messages defined in Diameter base protocol, i.e.,
        RAR/RAA, STR/STA, ASR/ASA and possibly ACR/ACA in the coupled
        accounting model, see <xref target="other-accounting"/>. Existing
        specifications may not adhere to this rule for historical or other
        reasons. However, this scheme should be followed to avoid possible
        routing problems for these messages.</t>

        <t>In general, when a new application has been allocated with a new
        application id and it also reuses existing commands with or without
        modifications (Sec 4.1), it must use the newly allocated application
        id in the header and in all relevant application id AVPs
        (Auth-Application-Id or Acct-Application-Id) present in the commands
        message body.</t>

        <t>Additionally, application designs using
        Vendor-Specific-Application-Id AVP should not use the Vendor-Id AVP to
        further dissect or differentiate the vendor-specification application
        id. Diameter routing is not based on the Vendor-Id. As such, the
        Vendor-ID should not be used as an additional input for routing or
        delivery of messages. In general, the Vendor-Id AVP is an
        informational AVP only and kept for backward compatibility
        reasons.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Application-Specific Session State Machines">
        <t>Section 8 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> provides
        session state machines for authentication, authorization and
        accounting (AAA) services and these session state machines are not
        intended to cover behavior outside of AAA. If a new application cannot
        clearly be categorized into any of these AAA services, it is
        recommended that the application define its own session state machine.
        Support for server-initiated request is a clear example where an
        application-specific session state machine would be needed, for
        example, the Rw interface for ITU-T push model (cf.<xref
        target="Q.3303.3"/>).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Session-Id AVP and Session Management">
        <t>Diameter applications are usually designed with the aim of managing
        user sessions, e.g. network access session (NASREQ application <xref
        target="RFC4005"/>) or specific service access session (Diameter SIP
        application <xref target="RFC4740"/>). In the Diameter base protocol,
        the session management is based on the Session-Id AVP that it used to
        identify a given session and all the Diameter messages including the
        same Session-Id will be bound to the same session. Diameter-based
        session management also implies that both Diameter client and server
        (and potentially proxy agents in the diameter path) are maintaining
        session state information associated with the Session-Id contained in
        the Diameter messages.</t>

        <t>However, some applications may not need to rely on the Session-Id
        to identify and manage user sessions because other information can be
        used instead to correlate Diameter messages. Indeed, the User-Name AVP
        or any other specific AVP can be present in every Diameter message and
        used therefore for message correlation. There might even be
        applications for which the notion of Diameter session management would
        not be required at all. For such applications, the Auth-Session-State
        AVP is usually set to NO_STATE_MAINTAINED in all the Diameter messages
        and these applications are therefore designed as a set of stand-alone
        transactions. Even if an explicit access session termination is
        required, application-specific commands are defined and used instead
        of the Session-Termination-Request/Answer (STR/STA) or
        Abort-Session-Request/Answer (ASR/ASA) defined in the Diameter base
        protocol. In such a case, the Session-Id is not significant.</t>

        <t>Based on these considerations, protocol designers should carefully
        appraise whether the application currently defined relies on the
        concept of session management and whether the Session-Id defined in
        the Diameter base protocol would be used for correlation of messages
        related to the same session. If not, the protocol designers could
        decide to define application commands without the Session-Id AVP. If
        any session management concept is supported by the application, the
        application documentation must clearly specify how the session is
        handled between client and server (as possibly Diameter agents in the
        path).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="AVPs Defined as Boolean Flag">
        <t>The type Enumerated was initially defined to provide a list of
        valid values for an AVP with their respective interpretation described
        in the specification. For instance, AVPs of type Enumerated can be
        used to provide further information on the reason for the termination
        of a session or a specific action to perform upon the reception of the
        request.</t>

        <t>However, AVPs of type Enumerated are too often used as a simple
        Boolean flag, indicating for instance a specific permission or
        capability, and therefore only two values are defined e.g. TRUE/FALSE,
        AUTORIZED/UNAUTHORIZED or SUPPORTED/UNSUPPORTED. This is a sub-optimal
        design since it limits the extensibility of the application: any new
        capability/permission would have to be supported by a new AVP or new
        Enumerated value of the already defined AVP, causing backwards
        compatibility issues with existing implementations.</t>

        <t>Instead of using an Enumerated AVP for a Boolean flag, protocol
        designers are encouraged to use Unsigned32 or Unsigned64 AVP type as
        bit mask whose bit settings are described in the relevant Diameter
        application specification. Such AVPs can be reused and extended
        without major impact on the Diameter application. The bit mask should
        leave room for future additions. Examples of bit mask AVP are the
        Session-Binding AVP defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> and the MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP
        defined in <xref target="RFC5447"/></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Application-Specific Message Routing">
        <t>Diameter request message routing usually relies on the
        Destination-Realm AVP and the Application Id present in the request
        message header. However, some applications may need to rely on the
        User-Name AVP or any other application-specific AVP present in the
        request to determine the final destination of a request e.g. find the
        target AAA server hosting the authorization information for a given
        user when multiple AAA servers are addressable in the realm.</t>

        <t>In such a context, basic routing mechanisms described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> are not fully suitable, and
        additional application-level routing mechanisms have to be described
        in the application documentation to provide such specific AVP-based
        routing. Such functionality will be basically hosted by an
        application-specific Proxy agent that will be responsible for routing
        decisions based on the received specific AVPs.</t>

        <t>Example of such application-specific routing functions can be found
        in the Cx/Dx applications (<xref target="TS29.228"/> and <xref
        target="TS29.229"/>) of the 3GPP IP Multimedia Subsystem, in which the
        proxy agent (Subscriber Location Function aka SLF) uses specific
        application-level identities found in the request to determine the
        final destination of the message.</t>

        <t>Whatever the criteria used to establish the routing path of the
        request, the routing of the answer should follow the reverse path of
        the request, as described in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>, with the answer being sent to the
        source of the received request, using transaction states and
        hop-by-hop identifier matching. In particular, this ensures that the
        Diameter Relay or Proxy agents in the request routing path will be
        able to release the transaction state upon receipt of the
        corresponding answer, avoiding unnecessary failover. Application
        designers are strongly dissuaded from modifying the answer-routing
        principles described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/> when
        defining a new application.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="About Translation Agent">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>, a
        translation agent is a device that provides interworking between
        Diameter and another protocol (e.g. RADIUS, TACACS+).</t>

        <t>In the case of RADIUS, it was initially thought that defining the
        translation function would be straightforward by adopting few basic
        principles e.g. use of a shared range of code values for RADIUS
        attributes and Diameter AVPs. Guidelines for implementing a
        RADIUS-Diameter translation agent were put into RFC 4005 (<xref
        target="RFC4005"/>).</t>

        <t>However, it was acknowledged that such translation mechanism was
        not so obvious and deeper protocol analysis was required to ensure
        efficient interworking between RADIUS and Diameter. Moreover, the
        interworking requirements depend on the functionalities provided by
        the Diameter application under specification, and a case-by-case
        analysis will be required.</t>

        <t>Therefore, protocol designers cannot assume the availability of a
        "standard" Diameter-to-RADIUS gateways agent when planning to
        interoperate with the RADIUS infrastructure. They should specify the
        required translation mechanism along with the Diameter application.
        This recommendation applies for any kind of translation (e.g.
        Diameter/MAP).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="End-to-End Application Capabilities Exchange">
        <t>New Diameter applications can rely on optional AVPs to exchange
        application-specific capabilities and features. These AVPs can be
        exchanged on an end-to-end basis at the application layer. Examples of
        this can be found in <xref target="RFC5447"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5777"/>.</t>

        <t>The end-to-end capabilities AVPs formalize the addition of new
        optional functionality to existing applications by announcing support
        for it. Applications that do not understand these AVPs can discard
        them upon receipt. Recevers of these AVPs can discover the addional
        functionalities supported the end-point orignating the request and
        behave accordingly when processing the request. Senders of these AVPs
        can safely assume the receiving end-point does not support any
        functionality carried by the AVP if it is not present in corresponding
        response. This is useful in cases where deployment choices are
        offered, and the generic design can be made available for a number of
        applications.</t>

        <t>When used in a new application, protocol designers should clearly
        specify this end-to-end capabilities exchange and the corresponding
        behaviour of the Diameter nodes supporting the application.</t>

        <t>It is also important to note that this end-to-end capabilities
        exchange relying on the use of optional AVPs is not meant as a generic
        mechanism to support extensibility of Diameter applications with
        arbitrary functionalities. When the added features drastically change
        the Diameter application or when Diameter agents have to be upgraded
        to support the new features, a new application should be defined.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="other-accounting" title="Diameter Accounting Support">
        <t>Accounting can be treated as an auxiliary application that is used
        in support of other applications. In most cases, accounting support is
        required when defining new applications. This document provides two(2)
        possible models for using accounting:<vspace blankLines="1"/> <list
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Split Accounting Model"><vspace blankLines="1"/>In
            this model, the accounting messages will use the Diameter base
            accounting application ID (value of 3). The design implication for
            this is that the accounting is treated as an independent
            application, especially during Diameter routing. This means that
            accounting commands emanating from an application may be routed
            separately from the rest of the other application messages. This
            may also imply that the messages end up in a central accounting
            server. A split accounting model is a good design choice when:
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
                <t>The application itself will not define its own unique
                accounting commands.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

                <t>The overall system architecture permits the use of
                centralized accounting for one or more Diameter
                applications.</t>
              </list><vspace blankLines="1"/>Centralizing accounting may have
            advantages but there are also drawbacks. The model assumes that
            the accounting server can differentiate received accounting
            messages. Since the received accounting messages can be for any
            application and/or service, the accounting server has to have a
            method to match accounting messages with applications and/or
            services being accounted for. This may mean defining new AVPs,
            checking the presence, absence or contents of existing AVPs, or
            checking the contents of the accounting record itself. But in
            general, there is no clean and generic scheme for sorting these
            messages. Therefore, the use of this model is recommended only
            when all received accounting messages can be clearly identified
            and sorted. For most cases, the use of Coupled Accounting Model is
            recommended. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

            <t hangText="Coupled Accounting Model"><vspace blankLines="1"/> In
            this model, the accounting messages will use the application ID of
            the application using the accounting service. The design
            implication for this is that the accounting messages are tightly
            coupled with the application itself; meaning that accounting
            messages will be routed like any other application messages. It
            would then be the responsibility of the application server
            (application entity receiving the ACR message) to send the
            accounting records carried by the accounting messages to the
            proper accounting server. The application server is also
            responsible for formulating a proper response (ACA). A coupled
            accounting model is a good design choice when:<vspace
            blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
                <t>The system architecture or deployment will not provide an
                accounting server that supports Diameter.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>

                <t>The system architecture or deployment requires that the
                accounting service for the specific application should be
                handled by the application itself.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

                <t>The application server is provisioned to use a different
                protocol to access the accounting server; e.g., via LDAP, SOAP
                etc. This includes attempting to support older accounting
                systems that are not Diameter aware.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
              </list> In all cases above, there will generally be no direct
            Diameter access to the accounting server.<vspace
            blankLines="1"/></t>
          </list>These models provide a basis for using accounting messages.
        Application designers may obviously deviate from these models provided
        that the factors being addressed here have also been taken into
        account. Though it is not recommended, examples of other methods might
        be defining a new set of commands to carry application-specific
        accounting records.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Diameter Security Mechanisms">
        <t>As specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis"/>, the
        Diameter message exchange should be secured by using TLS/TCP or
        DTLS/SCTP. However, IPsec can also be deployed to secure connections
        between Diameter peers. When IPsec is used instead of TLS or DTLS, the
        following recommendations apply.</t>

        <t>IPsec ESP 5.3 <xref target="RFC4301"/> in transport mode with
        non-null encryption and authentication algorithms is used to provide
        per-packet authentication, integrity protection and confidentiality,
        and support the replay protection mechanisms of IPsec. IKE is used for
        peer authentication, negotiation of security associations, and key
        management, using the IPsec DOI <xref target="RFC2407"/>. Peer
        authentication can be achieved by using a pre-shared key, or
        certificate-based peer authentication using digital signatures can be
        used as alternative. Peer authentication using the public key
        encryption methods outlined in IKE's Sections 5.2 and 5.3 <xref
        target="RFC2409"/> should not be used.</t>

        <t>Diameter implementations using IPsec as the security mechanism must
        support both IKE Main Mode and Aggressive Mode. When pre-shared keys
        are used for authentication, IKE Aggressive Mode should be used
        instead of IKE Main Mode. When digital signatures are used for
        authentication, either IKE Main Mode or IKE Aggressive Mode can be
        used.</t>

        <t>When digital signatures are used to achieve authentication, an IKE
        negotiator should use IKE Certificate Request Payload(s) to specify
        the certificate authority (or authorities) that are trusted in
        accordance with its local policy. IKE negotiators should use pertinent
        certificate revocation checks before accepting a PKI certificate for
        use in IKE's authentication procedures.</t>

        <t>The Phase 2 Quick Mode exchanges used to negotiate protection for
        Diameter connections must explicitly carry the Identity Payload fields
        (IDci and IDcr). The DOI provides for several types of identification
        data. However, when used in conformant implementations, each ID
        Payload must carry a single IP address and a single non-zero port
        number, and must not use the IP Subnet or IP Address Range formats.
        This allows the Phase 2 security association to correspond to specific
        TCP and SCTP connections.</t>

        <t>Since IPsec acceleration hardware may only be able to handle a
        limited number of active IKE Phase 2 SAs, Phase 2 delete messages may
        be sent for idle SAs, as a means of keeping the number of active Phase
        2 SAs to a minimum. The receipt of an IKE Phase 2 delete message
        should not be interpreted as a reason for tearing down a Diameter
        connection. Rather, it is preferable to leave the connection up, and
        if additional traffic is sent on it, to bring up another IKE Phase 2
        SA to protect it. This avoids the potential for continually bringing
        connections up and down.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="other-generic"
             title="Defining Generic Diameter Extensions">
      <t>Generic Diameter extensions are AVPs, commands or applications that
      are designed to support other Diameter applications. They are auxiliary
      applications meant to improve or enhance the Diameter protocol itself or
      Diameter applications/functionality. Some examples include the
      extensions to support auditing and redundancy (see <xref
      target="I-D.calhoun-diameter-res-mgmt"/>), improvements in duplicate
      detection scheme (see <xref target="I-D.asveren-dime-dupcons"/>), and
      piggybacking of QoS attributes (see <xref target="RFC5777"/>).</t>

      <t>Since generic extensions can cover many aspects of Diameter and
      Diameter applications, it is not possible to enumerate all the probable
      scenarios in this document. However, some of the most common
      considerations are as follows:<vspace blankLines="1"/> <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Backward compatibility: Dealing with existing applications that
          do not understand the new extension. Designers also have to make
          sure that new extensions do not break expected message delivery
          layer behavior.<vspace blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>Forward compatibility: Making sure that the design will not
          introduce undue restrictions for future applications. Future
          applications attempting to support this feature should not have to
          go through great lengths to implement any new extensions. <vspace
          blankLines="0"/></t>

          <t>Trade-off in signaling: Designers may have to choose between the
          use of optional AVPs piggybacked onto existing commands versus
          defining new commands and applications. Optional AVPs are simpler to
          implement and may not need changes to existing applications.
          However, this ties the sending of extension data to the
          application's transmission of a message. This has consequences if
          the application and the extensions have different timing
          requirements. The use of commands and applications solves this
          issue, but the trade-off is the additional complexity of defining
          and deploying a new application. It is left up to the designer to
          find a good balance among these trade-offs based on the requirements
          of the extension.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In practice, generic extensions often use optional AVPs because they
      are simple and non-intrusive to the application that would carry them.
      Peers that do not support the generic extensions need not understand nor
      recognize these optional AVPs. However, it is recommended that the
      authors of the extension specify the context or usage of the optional
      AVPs. As an example, in the case that the AVP can be used only by a
      specific set of applications then the specification must enumerate these
      applications and the scenarios when the optional AVPs will be used. In
      the case where the optional AVPs can be carried by any application, it
      is should be sufficient to specify such a use case and perhaps provide
      specific examples of applications using them.</t>

      <t>In most cases, these optional AVPs piggybacked by applications would
      be defined as a Grouped AVP and it would encapsulate all the
      functionality of the generic extension. In practice, it is not uncommon
      that the Grouped AVP will encapsulate an existing AVP that has
      previously been defined as mandatory ('M'-bit set) e.g., 3GPP IMS Cx/Dx
      interfaces (<xref target="TS29.228"/> and <xref
      target="TS29.229"/>).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document provides guidelines and considerations for extending
      Diameter and Diameter applications. It does not define nor address
      security-related protocols or schemes.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>The content of this document was influenced by a design team created
      to revisit the Diameter extensibility rules. The team consisting of the
      members listed below was formed in February 2008 and finished its work
      in June 2008. <vspace blankLines="1"/> <list style="symbols">
          <t>Avi Lior</t>

          <t>Glen Zorn</t>

          <t>Jari Arkko</t>

          <t>Lionel Morand</t>

          <t>Mark Jones</t>

          <t>Victor Fajardo</t>

          <t>Tolga Asveren</t>

          <t>Jouni Korhonen</t>

          <t>Glenn McGregor</t>

          <t>Hannes Tschofenig</t>

          <t>Dave Frascone</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>We would like to thank Tolga Asveren, Glenn McGregor, and John
      Loughney for their contributions as co-authors to earlier versions of
      this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>We greatly appreciate the insight provided by Diameter implementers
      who have highlighted the issues and concerns being addressed by this
      document. The authors would also like to thank A. Jean Mahoney and Ben
      Campbell for their invaluable detailed review and comments on this
      document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      &rfc3588;

      &I-D.ietf-dime-rfc3588bis;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC4072"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4072.txt">
        <front>
          <title>Diameter Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP)
          Application</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="P. Eronen et al.">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4005"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4005.txt">
        <front>
          <title>Diameter Network Access Server Application</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="P. Calhoun et al.">
            <organization>P.</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4740"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4740.txt">
        <front>
          <title>Diameter Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
          Application</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="M. Garcia-Martin et al.">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2006"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5447"
                 target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5447.txt">
        <front>
          <title>Diameter Mobile IPv6: Support for Network Access Server to
          Diameter Server Interaction</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="J. Korhonen et al.">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2009"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4301">
        <front>
          <title>Security Architecture for the Internet Protocol</title>

          <author surname="S. Kent">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author surname="K. Seo">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2407">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet IP Security Domain of Interpretation for
          ISAKMP</title>

          <author surname="D. Piper">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2409">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet Key Exchange (IKE)</title>

          <author surname="D. Harkins">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author surname="D. Carrel">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5777">
        <front>
          <title>Traffic Classification and Quality of Service (QoS)
          Attributes for Diameter</title>

          <author surname="J. Korhonen et al.">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      &I-D.asveren-dime-dupcons;

      <reference anchor="I-D.calhoun-diameter-res-mgmt">
        <front>
          <title>Diameter Resource Management Extensions</title>

          <author fullname="Pat Calhoun" initials="P." surname="Calhoun">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2001"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-calhoun-diameter-res-mgmt-08.txt"/>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-calhoun-diameter-res-mgmt-08.txt"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS29.228"
                 target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/29272.htm">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS 29.228; Technical Specification Group Core Network
          and Terminals; IP Multimedia (IM) Subsystem Cx and Dx Interfaces;
          Signalling flows and message contents</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="3GPP">3rd Generation Partnership
            Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS29.229"
                 target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/29229.htm">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS 29.229; Technical Specification Group Core Network
          and Terminals; Cx and Dx interfaces based on the Diameter protocol;
          Protocol details</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="3GPP">3rd Generation Partnership
            Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS29.328"
                 target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/29328.htm">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS 29.328; Technical Specification Group Core Network
          and Terminals; IP Multimedia (IM) Subsystem Sh interface; signalling
          flows and message content</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="3GPP">3rd Generation Partnership
            Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS29.329"
                 target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/29329.htm">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS 29.329; Technical Specification Group Core Network
          and Terminals; Sh Interface based on the Diameter protocol; Protocol
          details</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="3GPP">3rd Generation Partnership
            Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Q.3303.3" target="">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T Recommendation Q.3303.3, "Resource control protocol no.
          3 (rcp3): Protocol at the Rw interface between the Policy Decision
          Physical Entity (PD-PE) and the Policy Enforcement Physical Entity
          (PE-PE): Diameter"</title>

          <author>
            <organization abbrev="3GPP">3rd Generation Partnership
            Project</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2008"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
