<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    ]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-hansen-privacy-terminology-00.txt">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Privacy Terminology">Terminology for Talking about Privacy by Data Minimization:
      Anonymity, Unlinkability, Undetectability, Unobservability, Pseudonymity, and Identity
      Management</title>
    <author initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann" fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" role="editor">
      <organization>TU Dresden</organization>
      <address>
            <email>pfitza@inf.tu-dresden.de</email>
          </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Hansen" fullname="Marit Hansen" role="editor">
      <organization>ULD Kiel</organization>
      <address>
            <email>marit.hansen@datenschutzzentrum.de</email>
          </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
            <postal>
              <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
              <city>Espoo</city>
              <code>02600</code>
              <country>Finland</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
            <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
            <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
          </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2010"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document is an attempt to consolidate terminology in the field privacy by data
        minimization. It motivates and develops definitions for anonymity/identifiability,
        (un)linkability, (un)detectability, (un)observability, pseudonymity, identity, partial
        identity, digital identity and identity management. Starting the definitions from the
        anonymity and unlinkability perspective and not from a definition of identity (the latter is
        the obvious approach to some people) reveals some deeper structures in this field.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

      <t> Early papers from the 1980ies about privacy by data minimization already deal with
        anonymity, unlinkability, unobservability, and pseudonymity and introduce these terms within
        the respective context of proposed measures. </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> Data minimization means that first of all, the possibility to collect personal data
            about others should be minimized. Next within the remaining possibilities, collecting
            personal data should be minimized. Finally, the time how long collected personal data is
            stored should be minimized. </t>
          <t>Data minimization is the only generic strategy to enable anonymity, since all correct
            personal data help to identify if we exclude providing misinformation (inaccurate or
            erroneous information, provided usually without conscious effort at misleading,
            deceiving, or persuading one way or another <xref target="Wils93"/>) or disinformation
            (deliberately false or distorted information given out in order to mislead or deceive
              <xref target="Wils93"/>).</t>
          <t>Furthermore, data minimization is the only generic strategy to enable unlinkability,
            since all correct personal data provide some linkability if we exclude providing
            misinformation or disinformation. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> We show relationships between these terms and thereby develop a consistent terminology.
        Then, we contrast these definitions with newer approaches, e.g., from ISO IS 15408. Finally,
        we extend this terminology to identity (as a negation of anonymity and unlinkability) and
        identity management. Identity management is a much younger and much less well-defined field
        - so a really consolidated terminology for this field does not
        exist.<!-- But nevertheless, after development and broad discussion since 2004, we believe this terminology to be the most consolidated one in this rapidly emerging field.-->
      </t>
      <t>The adoption of this terminology will help to achieve better progress in the field by
        avoiding that those working on standards and research invent their own language from
        scratch.
        <!-- Of course, each paper will need additional vocabulary, which might be added consistently to the terms defined here.-->
      </t>
      <t> This document is organized as follows: First, the setting used is described. Then,
        definitions of anonymity, unlinkability, linkability, undetectability, and unobservability
        are given and the relationships between the respective terms are outlined. Afterwards, known
        mechanisms to achieve anonymity, undetectability and unobservability are listed. The next
        sections deal with pseudonymity, i.e., pseudonyms, their properties, and the corresponding
        mechanisms. Thereafter, this is applied to privacy-enhancing identity management. To give an
        overview of the main terms defined and their negations, a corresponding table follows.
        Finally, concluding remarks are given. In appendices, we (A1) depict the relationships
        between some terms used and (A2 and A3) briefly discuss the relationship between our
        approach (to defining anonymity and identifiability) and other approaches. To make the
        document readable to as large an audience as possible, we did put information which can be
        skipped in a first reading or which is only useful to part of our readership, e.g., those
        knowing information theory, in footnotes. </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology and Requirements Notation">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Privacy:">"Privacy is the claim of individuals, groups, or institutions to
            determine for themselves when, how, and to what extent information about them is
            communicated to others. Viewed in terms of the relation of the individual to social
            participation, privacy is the voluntary and temporary withdrawal of a person from the
            general society through physical or psychological means, either in a state of solitude
            or small-group intimacy or, when among larger groups, in a condition of anonymity or
            reserve.", see page 7 of <xref target="West67"/></t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="setting" title="Setting">

      <t> We develop this terminology in the usual setting that senders send messages to recipients
        using a communication network, i.e., stations send and receive messages using a wired and/or
        wireless communication medium. </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> To keep the setting as simple as possible, usually, we do not distinguish between
            human senders and the stations which are used to send messages. Putting it the other way
            round, usually, we assume that each station is controlled by exactly one human being,
            its owner. If a differentiation between human communication and computer communication
            is necessary or if the assumption that each station is controlled by exactly one human
            being is wrong, the setting has to be more complex. We then use sender and recipient for
            human beings and message for their communication. For computers and their
            communications, we use stations sending bit strings. If we have to look even deeper than
            bits which are "abstractions" of physical signals, we call the representation of bit
            strings signals. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> For other settings, e.g., users querying a database, customers shopping in an e-commerce
        shop, the same terminology can be derived by instantiating the terms "sender", "recipient",
        and "message". But for ease of explanation, we use the specific setting here, see <xref
          target="fig1"/>. Only if what we have to say is valid in a broader context without
        requiring further explanations, we speak more generally about acting entities called actors
        (such as senders) and entities acted upon called actees (such as recipients). </t>
      <t> Irrespective whether we speak of senders and recipients or whether we generalize to actors
        and actees, we regard a subject as a possibly acting entity such as, e.g., a human being
        (i.e., a natural person), a legal person, or a computer. An organization not acting as a
        legal person we neither see as a single subject nor as a single entity, but as (possibly
        structured) sets of subjects or entities. Otherwise, the distinction between "subjects" and
        "sets of subjects" would completely blur. </t>

      <t> If we make our setting more concrete, we may l it a system. For our purposes, a system has
        the following relevant properties: <list style="numbers">
          <t>The system has a surrounding, i.e., parts of the world are "outside" the system.
            Together, the system and its surrounding form the universe. </t>
          <t>The state of the system may change by actions within the system. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig1" title="Setting">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 Senders                                                 Recipients
                        Communication Network
    --                                                         --
   |  | ----                    -----------                ---|  |
    --      ------         /----           ----\       ----    --
                  ----  ///                     \\\  --
                      //                           \\
                    //                               \\
                   /                        +-+        \          --
                  |                         +-+         |    ----|  |
       /-\       |        +-+       +-+                  |---     --
      |   |----  |        +-+       +-+                  |
       \-/      |                                         |
                |                 Messages                |
                 |            +-+           +-+          |
                 |            +-+           +-+          |
                  |                                     |--   --
              ---  \                                   /   --|  |
    --    ----      \\                               //       --
   |  | --            \\                           //
    --                  \\\                     ///   \
                           \----           ----/       \\
                                -----------              \ /-\
                                                          |   |
                                                           \-/
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>All statements are made from the perspective of an attacker , who may be interested in
        monitoring what communication is occurring, what patterns of communication exist, or even in
        manipulating the communication. The perspective describes the set of all possible
        observations. In the following, a property holds "from an attacker's perspective" iff it
        holds for all possible observations of that perspective. The attacker's perspective depends
        on the information the attacker has available. If we assume some limits on how much
        processing the attacker might be able to do, the information available to the attacker will
        not only depend on the attacker's perspective, but on the attacker's processing (abilities),
        too. The attacker may be an outsider tapping communication lines or an insider able to
        participate in normal communications and controlling at least some stations, cf. <xref
          target="fig2"/>. We assume that the attacker uses all information available to him to
        infer (probabilities of) his items of interest (IOIs), e.g., who did send or receive which
        messages. Related to the IOIs are attributes (and their values) because they may be items of
        interest themselves or their observation may give information on IOIs: An attribute is a
        quality or characteristic of an entity or an action. Some attributes may take several
        values. Then it makes sense to make a distinction between more abstract attributes and more
        concrete attribute values. Mainly we are interested in attributes of subjects. Examples for
        attributes in this setting are "sending a message" or "receiving a message". </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig2" title="Example of an attacker's domain within the setting">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 Senders                                                 Recipients
                        Communication Network
    --                                                         --
   |  | ----                    -----------                ---|  |
    --      ------         /----           ----\       ----    --
   Alice          ----  ///                     \\\  --       Carol
                      //                           \\
                    //                               \\
                   /     Message                       \
                  |      by Alice                       |
       /-\       |        +-+                            |
      |   |----  |        +-+                            |
       \-/      |                           Malice's      |
       Bob      |                           Message       |
                 |                          +-+          |
                 |          Bob's           +-+          |
                  |         Message                     |--   --
              ---  \         +-+                       /   --|  |
    --    ----      \\       +-+                     //       --
   |  | --            \\                           //       Complice
    --                  \\\                     ///         of
   Malice                  \----           ----/            Malice
(the attacker)                  -----------
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t> Throughout the subsequent sections we assume that the attacker is not able to get
        information on the sender or recipient from the message content. Of course, encryption of
        messages provides protection of the content against attackers observing the communication
        lines and end-to-end encryption even provides protection of the content against all stations
        passed, e.g., for the purpose of forwarding and/or routing. But message content can neither
        be hidden from the sender nor from the recipient(s) of the message. Therefore, we do not
        mention the message content in these sections. For most applications it is unreasonable to
        assume that the attacker forgets something. Thus, normally the knowledge of the attacker
        only increases. "Knowledge" can be described by probabilities of IOIs. More knowledge then
        means more accurate probabilities, i.e., the probabilities the attacker assumes to be true
        are closer to the "true" probabilities. </t>
    </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="anonymity" title="Anonymity">
      <t>To enable anonymity of a subject, there always has to be an appropriate set of subjects
        with potentially the same attributes . Since sending and receiving of particular messages
        are special cases of "attributes" of senders and recipients, this is slightly more general
        than the setting in <xref target="setting"/>. This generality is very fortunate to stay
        close to the everyday meaning of "anonymity" which is not only used w.r.t. subjects active
        in a particular context, e.g., senders and recipients of messages, but w.r.t. subjects
        passive in a particular context as well, e.g., subjects the records within a database relate
        to. This leads to the following definition: </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Anonymity of a subject means that the subject is not
            identifiable within a set of subjects, the anonymity set. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> "not identifiable within the anonymity set" means that only using the information the
            attacker has at his discretion, the subject is "not uniquely characterized within the
            anonymity set". In more precise language, only using the information the attacker has at
            his discretion, the subject is "not distinguishable from the other subjects within the
            anonymity set". </t>
          <t> From <xref target="ISO99"/>: "Anonymity ensures that a user may use a resource or
            service without disclosing the user's identity. The requirements for anonymity provide
            protection of the user identity. Anonymity is not intended to protect the subject
            identity. [...] Anonymity requires that other users or subjects are unable to determine
            the identity of a user bound to a subject or operation." Compared with this explanation,
            our definition is more general as it is not restricted to identifying users, but any
            subjects. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> The anonymity set is the set of all possible subjects. The set of possible subjects
        depends on the knowledge of the attacker. Thus, anonymity is relative with respect to the
        attacker. With respect to actors, the anonymity set consists of the subjects who might cause
        an action. With respect to actees, the anonymity set consists of the subjects who might be
        acted upon. Therefore, a sender may be anonymous (sender anonymity) only within a set of
        potential senders, his/her sender anonymity set, which itself may be a subset of all
        subjects worldwide who may send a message from time to time. The same for the recipient
        means that a recipient may be anonymous (recipient anonymity) only within a set of potential
        recipients, his/her recipient anonymity set, cf. <xref target="fig3"/>. Both anonymity sets
        may be disjoint, be the same, or they may overlap. The anonymity sets may vary over time.
        Since we assume that the attacker does not forget anything he knows, the anonymity set
        cannot increase w.r.t. a particular IOI. Especially subjects joining the system in a later
        stage, do not belong to the anonymity set from the point of view of an attacker observing
        the system in an earlier stage. (Please note that if the attacker cannot decide whether the
        joining subjects were present earlier, the anonymity set does not increase either: It just
        stays the same.) Due to linkability, cf. below, the anonymity set normally can only
        decrease. </t>
      <t> Anonymity of a set of subjects within an (potentially larger) anonymity set means that all
        these individual subjects are not identifiable within this anonymity set. In this
        definition, "set of subjects" is just taken to describe that the anonymity property holds
        for all elements of the set. Another possible definition would be to consider the anonymity
        property for the set as a whole. Then a semantically quite different definition could read:
        Anonymity of a set S of subjects within a larger anonymity set A means that it is not
        distinguishable whether the subject whose anonymity is at stake (and which clearly is within
        A) is within S or not. </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig3" title="Anonymity sets within the setting">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 +----------+                                             +---------+
 |          |           Communication Network             |         |
 |  --      |                                             |    --   |
 | |  | ----|                   -----------               |---|  |  |
 |  --      +-----         /----           ----\       ---+    --   |
 |          |     ----  ///                     \\\  --   |         |
 |          |         //                           \\     |         |
 |          |       //                               \\   |         |
 |          |      /                        +-+        \  |     --  |
 |          |     |                         +-+         | |  --|  | |
 |     /-\  |    |        +-+       +-+                  |+--   --  |
 |    |   |-+--  |        +-+       +-+                  ||         |
 |     \-/  |   |                                         |         |
 |          |   |                 Messages                |         |
 |          |    |            +-+           +-+          ||         |
 |          |    |            +-+           +-+          ||         |
 |          |     |                                     |-+     --  |
 |          | ---  \                                   /  |----|  | |
 |  --    --+-      \\                               //   |     --  |
 | |  | --  |         \\                           //     |         |
 |  --      |           \\\                     ///   \   |         |
 |          |              \----           ----/       \\ |         |
 |          |                   -----------              \|  /-\    |
 |          |                                             |\|   |   |
 |          |                                             |  \-/    |
 +----------+                                             |         |
                                                          +---------+
  Sender             (1) & (2)
  Anonymity          Largest Possible                      Recipient
  Set                Anonymity Set                         Anonymity
  (1)                                                      Set (2)
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>The definition given above for anonymity basically defines anonymity as a binary property:
        Either a subject is anonymous or not. To reflect the possibility to quantify anonymity in
        our definition and to underline that all statements are made from the perspective of an
        attacker (cf. <xref target="fig4"/>), it is appropriate to work with a slightly more
        complicated definition in the following:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Anonymity of a subject from an attacker's perspective means
            that the attacker cannot sufficiently identify the subject within a set of subjects, the
            anonymity set. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> In this revised definition, "sufficiently" underlines both that there is a possibility to
        quantify anonymity and that for some applications, there might be a need to define a
        threshold where anonymity begins.</t>

      <t> If we do not focus on the anonymity of one individual subject, called individual
        anonymity, but on the anonymity provided by a system to all of its users together, called
        global anonymity, we can state: All other things being equal, global anonymity is the
        stronger, the larger the respective anonymity set is and the more evenly distributed the
        sending or receiving, respectively, of the subjects within that set is. </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> The entropy of a message source as defined by Claude E. Shannon <xref target="Shan48"
            /> might be an appropriate measure to quantify global anonymity - just take who is the
            sender/recipient as the "message" in Shannon's definition. For readers interested in
            formalizing what we informally say: "No change of probabilities" means "no change of
            knowledge" and vice versa. "No change of probabilities" (or what is equivalent: "no
            change of knowledge") implies "no change of entropy", whereas "no change of entropy"
            neither implies "no change of probabilities" nor "no change of knowledge". In an easy to
            remember notation: No change of probabilities = no change of knowledge => no change of
            entropy. </t>
          <t>The definition of anonymity is an analog to the definition of "perfect secrecy" by
            Claude E. Shannon <xref target="Shan49"/>, whose definition takes into account that no
            security mechanism whatsoever can take away knowledge from the attacker which he already
            has.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>For a fixed anonymity set, global anonymity is maximal iff all subjects within the
        anonymity set are equally likely. Since subjects may behave quite distinct from each other
        (and trying to persuade them to behave more equally may both fail and be not compatible with
        basic human rights), achieving maximal anonymity or even something close to it usually is
        impossible. Strong or even maximal global anonymity does not imply strong anonymity or even
        maximal anonymity of each particular subject. What maximal anonymity of one individual
        subject (maximal individual anonymity, for short) means is unclear. On the one hand, if her
        probability approaches zero, her Shannon entropy (as a measure for anonymity) gets larger
        and larger. On the other hand, if her probability gets zero, she is outside the anonymity
        set. Even if global anonymity is strong, one (or a few) individual subjects might be quite
        likely, so their anonymity is weak. W.r.t. these "likely suspects", nothing is changed if
        the anonymity set is made larger and sending and receiving of the other subjects are, e.g.,
        distributed evenly. That way, arbitrarily strong global anonymity can be achieved without
        doing anything for the "likely suspects" <xref target="ClSc06"/>. So there is need to define
        anonymity measures not only for the system as a whole, but for individual subjects
        (individual anonymity) or small sets of subjects. </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig4" title="Anonymity sets w.r.t. attacker within the setting">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 +----------+
 |          |           Communication Network
 |  --      |                                                  --
 | |  | ----|                   -----------               ----|  |
 |  --      +-----         /----           ----\       ---     --
 |          |     ----  ///                     \\\  --    Attacker
 |          |         //                           \\
 | +--------+       //                               \\   +---------+
 | |               /                        +-+        \  |     --  |
 | |              |                         +-+         | |  --|  | |
 | |   /-\       |        +-+       +-+                  |+--   --  |
 | |  |   |-+--  |        +-+       +-+                  ||         |
 | |   \-/      |                                        ||         |
 | | Attacker   |                 Messages               ||         |
 | |             |            +-+           +-+          ||         |
 | +--------+    |            +-+           +-+          ||         |
 |          |     |                                     |-+     --  |
 |          | ---  \                                   /  |----|  | |
 |  --    --+-      \\                               //   |     --  |
 | |  | --  |         \\                           //     |         |
 |  --      |           \\\                     ///   \   |         |
 |          |              \----           ----/       \\ |         |
 |          |                   -----------              \|  /-\    |
 |          |                                             |\|   |   |
 |          |                                             |  \-/    |
 +----------+                                             |         |
                                                          +---------+
  Sender             (1) & (2)
  Anonymity          Largest Possible                      Recipient
  Set                Anonymity Set                         Anonymity
  (1)                w.r.t. to attacker                    Set (2)
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t> From the above discussion follows that anonymity in general as well as the anonymity of
        each particular subject is a concept which is very much context dependent (on, e.g.,
        subjects population, attributes, time frame, etc). In order to quantify anonymity within
        concrete situations, one would have to describe the system in sufficient detail, which is
        practically not (always) possible for large open systems (but maybe for some small data
        bases for instance). Besides the quantity of anonymity provided within a particular setting,
        there is another aspect of anonymity: its robustness. Robustness of anonymity characterizes
        how stable the quantity of anonymity is against changes in the particular setting, e.g., a
        stronger attacker or different probability distributions. We might use quality of anonymity
        as a term comprising both quantity and robustness of anonymity. To keep this text as simple
        as possible, we will mainly discuss the quantity of anonymity in the following, using the
        wording "strength of anonymity". </t>
      <t> The above definitions of anonymity and the mentioned measures of quantifying anonymity are
        fine to characterize the status of a subject in a world as is. If we want to describe
        changes to the anonymity of a subject if the world is changed somewhat, e.g., the subject
        uses the communication network differently or uses a modified communication network, we need
        another definition of anonymity capturing the delta. The simplest way to express this delta
        is by the observations of "the" attacker. </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> An anonymity delta (regarding a subject's anonymity) from an
            attacker's perspective specifies the difference between the subject's anonymity taking
            into account the attacker's observations (i.e., the attacker's a-posteriori knowledge)
            and the subject's anonymity given the attacker's a-priori knowledge only.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> In some publications, the a-priori knowledge of the attacker is called "background
            knowledge" and the a-posteriori knowledge of the attacker is called "new knowledge".
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t> As we can quantify anonymity in concrete situations, so we can quantify the anonymity
        delta. This can be done by just defining: quantity(anonymity delta) :=
        quantity(anonymity_a-posteriori) - quantity(anonymity_a-priori) If anonymity_a-posteriori
        and anonymity_a-priori are the same, their quantification is the same and therefore the
        difference of these quantifications is 0. If anonymity can only decrease (which usually is
        quite a reasonable assumption), the maximum of quantity(anonymity delta) is 0. </t>
      <t> Since anonymity cannot increase, the anonymity delta can never be positive. Having an
        anonymity delta of zero means that anonymity stays the same. This means that if the attacker
        has no a-priori knowledge about the particular subject, having no anonymity delta implies
        anonymity. But if the attacker has an a-priori knowledge covering all actions of the
        particular subject, having no anonymity delta does not imply any anonymity at all. If there
        is no anonymity from the very beginning, even preserving it completely does not yield any
        anonymity. To be able to express this conveniently, we use wordings like "perfect
        preservation of a subject's anonymity". It might be worthwhile to generalize "preservation
        of anonymity of single subjects" to "preservation of anonymity of sets of subjects", in the
        limiting case all subjects in an anonymity set. An important special case is that the "set
        of subjects" is the set of subjects having one or several attribute values A in common. Then
        the meaning of "preservation of anonymity of this set of subjects" is that knowing A does
        not decrease anonymity. Having a negative anonymity delta means that anonymity is decreased. </t>

    </section>
    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="unlinkability" title="Unlinkability">
      <t>Unlinkability only has a meaning after the system in which we want to describe anonymity
        properties has been defined and the entities interested in linking (the attacker) have been
        characterized. Then:</t>


      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Unlinkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g.,
            subjects, messages, actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the
            system (comprising these and possibly other items), the attacker cannot sufficiently
            distinguish whether these IOIs are related or not. , </t>
        </list>
      </t>


      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> From <xref target="ISO99"/>: "Unlinkability ensures that a user may make multiple uses
            of resources or services without others being able to link these uses together. [...]
            Unlinkability requires that users and/or subjects are unable to determine whether the
            same user caused certain specific operations in the system." In contrast to this
            definition, the meaning of unlinkability in this text is less focused on the user, but
            deals with unlinkability of "items" and therefore takes a general approach. </t>
          <t> As the entropy of a message source might be an appropriate measure to quantify
            (global) anonymity (and thereafter "anonymity" might be used as a quantity), we may use
            definitions to quantify unlinkability (and thereafter "unlinkability" might be used as a
            quantity as well). Quantifications of unlinkability can be either probabilities or
            entropies, or whatever is useful in a particular context. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Linkability is the negation of unlinkability: </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Linkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g.,
            subjects, messages, actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the
            system (comprising these and possibly other items), the attacker can sufficiently
            distinguish whether these IOIs are related or not.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t> For example, in a scenario with at least two senders, two messages sent by subjects within
        the same anonymity set are unlinkable for an attacker if for him, the probability that these
        two messages are sent by the same sender is sufficiently close to 1/(number of senders). In
        case of unicast the same is true for recipients; in case of multicast it is slightly more
        complicated. </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> An unlinkability delta of two or more items of interest (IOIs,
            e.g., subjects, messages, actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective specifies the
            difference between the unlinkability of these IOIs taking into account the attacker's
            observations and the unlinkability of these IOIs given the attacker's a-priori knowledge
            only. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> Since we assume that the attacker does not forget anything, unlinkability cannot increase.
        Normally, the attacker's knowledge cannot decrease (analogously to Shannon's definition of
        "perfect secrecy", see above). An exception of this rule is the scenario where the use of
        misinformation (inaccurate or erroneous information, provided usually without conscious
        effort at misleading, deceiving, or persuading one way or another <xref target="Wils93"/>)
        or disinformation (deliberately false or distorted information given out in order to mislead
        or deceive <xref target="Wils93"/>) leads to a growing uncertainty of the attacker which
        information is correct. A related, but different aspect is that information may become wrong
        (i.e., outdated) simply because the state of the world changes over time. Since privacy is
        not only about to protect the current state, but the past and history of a data subject as
        well, we will not make use of this different aspect in the rest of this document. Therefore,
        the unlinkability delta can never be positive. Having an unlinkability delta of zero means
        that the probability of those items being related from the attacker's perspective stays
        exactly the same before (a-priori knowledge) and after the attacker's observations
        (a-posteriori knowledge of the attacker). If the attacker has no a-priori knowledge about
        the particular IOIs, having an unlinkability delta of zero implies unlinkability. But if the
        attacker has a-priori knowledge covering the relationships of all IOIs, having an
        unlinkability delta of zero does not imply any unlinkability at all. If there is no
        unlinkability from the very beginning, even preserving it completely does not yield any
        unlinkability. To be able to express this conveniently, we use wordings like "perfect
        preservation of unlinkability w.r.t. specific items" to express that the unlinkability delta
        is zero. It might be worthwhile to generalize "preservation of unlinkability of two IOIs" to
        "preservation of unlinkability of sets of IOIs", in the limiting case all IOIs in the
        system. </t>

      <t> For example, the unlinkability delta of two messages is sufficiently small (zero) for an
        attacker if the probability describing his a-posteriori knowledge that these two messages
        are sent by the same sender and/or received by the same recipient is sufficiently (exactly)
        the same as the probability imposed by his a-priori knowledge. Please note that
        unlinkability of two (or more) messages of course may depend on whether their content is
        protected against the attacker considered. In particular, messages may be unlinkable if we
        assume that the attacker is not able to get information on the sender or recipient from the
        message content, cf. <xref target="setting"/>. Yet with access to their content even without
        deep semantical analysis the attacker can notice certain characteristics which link them
        together - e.g. similarities in structure, style, use of some words or phrases, consistent
        appearance of some grammatical errors, etc. In a sense, content of messages may play a role
        as "side channel" in a similar way as in cryptanalysis - i.e., content of messages may leak
        some information on their linkability. </t>
      <t>Roughly speaking, no unlinkability delta of items means that the ability of the attacker to
        relate these items does not increase by observing the system or by possibly interacting with
        it.</t>

      <t> The definitions of unlinkability, linkability and unlinkability delta do not mention any
        particular set of IOIs they are restricted to. Therefore, the definitions of unlinkability
        and unlinkability delta are very strong, since they cover the whole system. We could weaken
        the definitions by restricting them to part of the system: "Unlinkability of two or more
        IOIs from an attacker's perspective means that within an unlinkability set of IOIs
        (comprising these and possibly other items), the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish
        whether these IOIs are related or not." </t>

    </section>
    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="ano-unlink" title="Anonymity in Terms of Unlinkability">
      <t>To describe anonymity in terms of unlinkability, we have to augment the definitions of
        anonymity given in <xref target="anonymity"/> by making explicit the attributes anonymity
        relates to. This is best explained by looking at an example in detail. In our setting, cf.
          <xref target="setting"/>, we choose the attribute "having sent a message" as the example.
        Then we have:</t>

      <t>A sender s is anonymous w.r.t. sending, iff s is anonymous within the set of potential
        senders, i.e., within the sender anonymity set.</t>

      <t>This mainly is a re-phrasing of the definition in <xref target="setting"/>. If we make the
        message under consideration explicit, the definition reads:</t>

      <t>A sender s sends a message m anonymously, iff s is anonymous within the set of potential
        senders of m, the sender anonymity set of m.</t>

      <t>This can be generalized to sets of messages easily:</t>

      <t> A sender s sends a set of messages M anonymously, iff s is anonymous within the set of
        potential senders of M, the sender anonymity set of M.</t>

      <t>If the attacker's focus is not on the sender, but on the message, we can define:</t>

      <t>A message m is sent anonymously, iff m can have been sent by each potential sender, i.e.,
        by any subject within the sender anonymity set of m.</t>

      <t>Again, this can be generalized to sets of messages easily:</t>

      <t>A set of messages M is sent anonymously, iff M can have been sent by each set of potential
        senders, i.e., by any set of subjects within the cross product of the sender anonymity sets
        of each message m within M.</t>

      <t>Of course, all 5 definitions would work for receiving of messages accordingly. For more
        complicated settings with more operations than these two, appropriate sets of definitions
        can be developed.</t>

      <t>Now we are prepared to describe anonymity in terms of unlinkability.</t>

      <t>We do this by using our setting, cf. <xref target="setting"/>. So we consider sending and
        receiving of messages as attributes; the items of interest (IOIs) are "who has sent or
        received which message". Then, anonymity of a subject w.r.t. an attribute may be defined as
        unlinkability of this subject and this attribute. Unlinkability is a sufficient condition of
        anonymity, but it is not a necessary condition. Thus, failing unlinkability w.r.t. some
        attribute value(s) does not necessarily eliminate anonymity as defined in <xref
          target="anonymity"/>; in specific cases (i.e., depending on the attribute value(s)) even
        the strength of anonymity may not be affected. </t>
      <t> So we have: Sender anonymity of a subject means that to this potentially sending subject,
        each message is unlinkable. </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> The property unlinkability might be more "fine-grained" than anonymity, since there
            are many more relations where unlinkability might be an issue than just the relation
            "anonymity" between subjects and IOIs. Therefore, the attacker might get to know
            information on linkability while not necessarily reducing anonymity of the particular
            subject - depending on the defined measures. An example might be that the attacker, in
            spite of being able to link, e.g., by timing, all encrypted messages of a transactions,
            does not learn who is doing this transaction. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Correspondingly, recipient anonymity of a subject means that to this potentially receiving
        subject, each message is unlinkable.</t>

      <t>Relationship anonymity of a pair of subjects, the potentially sending subject and the
        potentially receiving subject, means that to this potentially communicating pair of
        subjects, each message is unlinkable. In other words, sender and recipient (or each
        recipient in case of multicast) are unlinkable. As sender anonymity of a message cannot hold
        against the sender of this message himself nor can recipient anonymity hold against any of
        the recipients w.r.t. himself, relationship anonymity is considered w.r.t. outsiders only,
        i.e., attackers being neither the sender nor one of the recipients of the messages under
        consideration.</t>

      <t>Thus, relationship anonymity is a weaker property than each of sender anonymity and
        recipient anonymity: The attacker might know who sends which messages or he might know who
        receives which messages (and in some cases even who sends which messages and who receives
        which messages). But as long as for the attacker each message sent and each message received
        are unlinkable, he cannot link the respective senders to recipients and vice versa, i.e.,
        relationship anonymity holds. The relationship anonymity set can be defined to be the cross
        product of two potentially distinct sets, the set of potential senders and the set of
        potential recipients or - if it is possible to exclude some of these pairs - a subset of
        this cross product. So the relationship anonymity set is the set of all possible
        sender-recipient(s)-pairs. In case of multicast, the set of potential recipients is the
        power set of all potential recipients. If we take the perspective of a subject sending (or
        receiving) a particular message, the relationship anonymity set becomes the set of all
        potential recipients (senders) of that particular message. So fixing one factor of the cross
        product gives a recipient anonymity set or a sender anonymity set.</t>


      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>The following is an explanation of the statement made in the previous paragraph
            regarding relationship anonymity: For all attackers it holds that sender anonymity
            implies relationship anonymity, and recipient anonymity implies relationship anonymity.
            This is true if anonymity is taken as a binary property: Either it holds or it does not
            hold. If we consider quantities of anonymity, the validity of the implication possibly
            depends on the particular definitions of how to quantify sender anonymity and recipient
            anonymity on the one hand, and how to quantify relationship anonymity on the other.
            There exists at least one attacker model, where relationship anonymity does neither
            imply sender anonymity nor recipient anonymity. Consider an attacker who neither
            controls any senders nor any recipients of messages, but all lines and - maybe - some
            other stations. If w.r.t. this attacker relationship anonymity holds, you can neither
            argue that against him sender anonymity holds nor that recipient anonymity holds. The
            classical MIX-net (cf. <xref target="known-mechs"/>) without dummy traffic is one
            implementation with just this property: The attacker sees who sends messages when and
            who receives messages when, but cannot figure out who sends messages to whom. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="undect-unobs" title="Undetectability and Unobservability">
      <t>In contrast to anonymity and unlinkability, where not the IOI, but only its relationship to
        subjects or other IOIs is protected, for undetectability, the IOIs are protected as such.
        Undetectability can be regarded as a possible and desirable property of steganographic
        systems (see <xref target="known-mechs"/>). Therefore it matches the information hiding
        terminology <xref target="Pfit96"/>, <xref target="ZFKP98"/>. In contrast, anonymity,
        dealing with the relationship of discernible IOIs to subjects, does not directly fit into
        that terminology, but independently represents a different dimension of properties.</t>


      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Undetectability of an item of interest (IOI) from an attacker's
            perspective means that the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish whether it exists or
            not.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> From <xref target="ISO99"/>: "Unobservability ensures that a user may use a resource
            or service without others, especially third parties, being able to observe that the
            resource or service is being used. [...] Unobservability requires that users and/or
            subjects cannot determine whether an operation is being performed." As seen before, our
            approach is less user-focused and insofar more general. With the communication setting
            and the attacker model chosen in this text, our definition of unobservability shows the
            method how to achieve it: preventing distinguishability of IOIs. Thus, the ISO
            definition might be applied to a different setting where attackers are prevented from
            observation by other means, e.g., by encapsulating the area of interest against third
            parties. </t>
          <t> In some applications (e.g. steganography), it might be useful to quantify
            undetectability to have some measure how much uncertainty about an IOI remains after the
            attacker's observations. Again, we may use probabilities or entropy, or whatever is
            useful in a particular context. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>If we consider messages as IOIs, this means that messages are not sufficiently discernible
        from, e.g., "random noise". A slightly more precise formulation might be that messages are
        not discernible from no message. A quantification of this property might measure the number
        of indistinguishable IOIs and/or the probabilities of distinguishing these IOIs.</t>

      <t>Undetectability is maximal iff whether an IOI exists or not is completely
        indistinguishable. We call this perfect undetectability.</t>


      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> An undetectability delta of an item of interest (IOI) from an
            attacker's perspective specifies the difference between the undetectability of the IOI
            taking into account the attacker's observations and the undetectability of the IOI given
            the attacker's a-priori knowledge only. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The undetectability delta is zero iff whether an IOI exists or not is indistinguishable to
        exactly the same degree whether the attacker takes his observations into account or not. We
        call this "perfect preservation of undetectability".</t>

      <t> Undetectability of an IOI clearly is only possible w.r.t. subjects being not involved in
        the IOI (i.e., neither being the sender nor one of the recipients of a message). Therefore,
        if we just speak about undetectability without spelling out a set of IOIs, it goes without
        saying that this is a statement comprising only those IOIs the attacker is not involved in.</t>

      <t> As the definition of undetectability stands, it has nothing to do with anonymity - it does
        not mention any relationship between IOIs and subjects. Even more, for subjects being
        involved in an IOI, undetectability of this IOI is clearly impossible. Therefore, early
        papers describing new mechanisms for undetectability designed the mechanisms in a way that
        if a subject necessarily could detect an IOI, the other subject(s) involved in that IOI
        enjoyed anonymity at least. The rational for this is to strive for data minimization: No
        subject should get to know any (potentially personal) data - except this is absolutely
        necessary. Given the setting described in <xref target="setting"/>, this means: 1. Subjects
        being not involved in the IOI get to know absolutely nothing. 2. Subjects being involved in
        the IOI only get to know the IOI, but not the other subjects involved - the other subjects
        may stay anonymous. Since in the setting described in <xref target="setting"/> the
        attributes "sending a message" or "receiving a message" are the only kinds of attributes
        considered, 1. and 2. together provide data minimization in this setting in an absolute
        sense. Undetectability by uninvolved subjects together with anonymity even if IOIs can
        necessarily be detected by the involved subjects has been called unobservability: </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Unobservability of an item of interest (IOI) means <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>undetectability of the IOI against all subjects uninvolved in it and</t>
              <t>anonymity of the subject(s) involved in the IOI even against the other subject(s)
                involved in that IOI.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t> As we had anonymity sets of subjects with respect to anonymity, we have unobservability
        sets of subjects with respect to unobservability, see <xref target="fig5"/>. Mainly,
        unobservability deals with IOIs instead of subjects only. Though, like anonymity sets,
        unobservability sets consist of all subjects who might possibly cause these IOIs, i.e. send
        and/or receive messages.</t>
      <t> Sender unobservability then means that it is sufficiently undetectable whether any sender
        within the unobservability set sends. Sender unobservability is perfect iff it is completely
        undetectable whether any sender within the unobservability set sends.</t>
      <t> Recipient unobservability then means that it is sufficiently undetectable whether any
        recipient within the unobservability set receives. Recipient unobservability is perfect iff
        it is completely undetectable whether any recipient within the unobservability set receives. </t>
      <t> Relationship unobservability then means that it is sufficiently undetectable whether
        anything is sent out of a set of could-be senders to a set of could-be recipients. In other
        words, it is sufficiently undetectable whether within the relationship unobservability set
        of all possible sender-recipient(s)-pairs, a message is sent in any relationship.
        Relationship unobservability is perfect iff it is completely undetectable whether anything
        is sent out of a set of could-be senders to a set of could-be recipients. </t>
      <t> All other things being equal, unobservability is the stronger, the larger the respective
        unobservability set is, see <xref target="fig6"/>. </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig5" title="Unobservability sets within the setting">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  +----------+                                             +---------+
  |          |           Communication Network             |         |
  |  --      |                                             |    --   |
  | |  | ----|                   -----------               |---|  |  |
  |  --      +-----         /----|+++++++++|----\       ---+    --   |
  |          |     ----  ///++++++++++++++++++++ \\\  --   |         |
  |          |         // ++++++++++++++++++++++++++\\     |         |
  |          |       //+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++\\   |         |
  |          |      |++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++|\  |     --  |
  |          |     |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++| |  --|  | |
  |     /-\  |    |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++|+--   --  |
  |    |   |-+--  |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
  |     \-/  |   |++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
  |          |   |++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
  |          |    |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
  |          |    |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
  |          |     ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++|-+     --  |
  |          | ---  \+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++/  |----|  | |
  |  --    --+-      \\+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++//   |     --  |
  | |  | --  |         \\+++++++++++++++++++++++++++//     |         |
  |  --      |           \|\+++++++++++++++++++++///   \   |         |
  |          |              \----+++++++++++----/       \\ |         |
  |          |                   -----------              \|  /-\    |
  |          |                                             |\|   |   |
  |          |                                             |  \-/    |
  +----------+                                             |         |
                                                           +---------+
   Sender
   Unobservability    Largest Possible                      Recipient
   Set                Unobservability Set             Unobservability
                                                            Set
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>



      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig6" title="Unobservability sets w.r.t. attacker within the setting">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 +----------+
 |          |                                                  --
 |  --      |           Communication Network             ----|  |
 | |  |-----|                                            -     --
 |  --      +-                  -----------                Attacker
 |          | ----         /----|+++++++++|----\       --
 |          |     ----  ///++++++++++++++++++++ \\\  --   +---------+
 | +--------+         // ++++++++++++++++++++++++++\\     |     --  |
 | |                //+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++\\   |  --|  | |
 | |               |++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++|\ |+--   --  |
 | |   /-\        |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++|||         |
 | |  |   |---   |++++++++++++Observable+++++++++++++++++||         |
 | |   \-/    -- |++++++++++++by attacker++++++++++++++++||         |
 | | Attacker   |++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
 | |            |++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++||         |
 | +--------+    |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++-+     --  |
 |          |    |+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ |----|  | |
 |          |     ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++| |     --  |
 |  --    --+----  \+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++/  |         |
 | |  | --  |       \\+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++//   |         |
 |  --      |         \\+++++++++++++++++++++++++++//     |         |
 |          |           \|\+++++++++++++++++++++///   \  \|  /-\    |
 |          |              \----+++++++++++----/       \\ |\|   |   |
 |          |                   -----------               |  \-/    |
 |          |                                             |         |
 +----------+                                             +---------+
  Sender                                                   Recipient
  Unobservability    Largest Possible                Unobservability
  Set                Unobservability Set                   Set
                     w.r.t. to attacker
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>



      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:">An unobservability delta of an item of interest (IOI) means
              <list style="symbols">
              <t>undetectability delta of the IOI against all subjects uninvolved in it and</t>
              <t>anonymity delta of the subject(s) involved in the IOI even against the other
                subject(s) involved in that IOI.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Since we assume that the attacker does not forget anything, unobservability cannot
        increase. Therefore, the unobservability delta can never be positive. Having an
        unobservability delta of zero w.r.t. an IOI means an undetectability delta of zero of the
        IOI against all subjects uninvolved in the IOI and an anonymity delta of zero against those
        subjects involved in the IOI. To be able to express this conveniently, we use wordings like
        "perfect preservation of unobservability" to express that the unobservability delta is zero.</t>

    </section>


    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="relationship" title="Relationships between Terms">

      <t>With respect to the same attacker, unobservability reveals always only a subset of the
        information anonymity reveals. <xref target="ReRu98"/> propose a continuum for describing
        the strength of anonymity. They give names: "absolute privacy" (the attacker cannot perceive
        the presence of communication, i.e., unobservability) - "beyond suspicion" - "probable
        innocence" - "possible innocence" - "exposed" - "provably exposed" (the attacker can prove
        the sender, recipient, or their relationship to others). Although we think that the terms
        "privacy" and "innocence" are misleading, the spectrum is quite useful. We might use the
        shorthand notation </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>unobservability => anonymity</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> for that (=> reads "implies"). Using the same argument and notation, we have </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>sender unobservability => sender anonymity</t>
          <t>recipient unobservability => recipient anonymity</t>
          <t>relationship unobservability => relationship anonymity</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> As noted above, we have </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>sender anonymity => relationship anonymity</t>
          <t>recipient anonymity => relationship anonymity</t>
          <t>sender unobservability => relationship unobservability</t>
          <t>recipient unobservability => relationship unobservability</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> With respect to the same attacker, unobservability reveals always only a subset of the
        information undetectability reveals </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t> unobservability => undetectability</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="known-mechs"
      title="Known Mechanisms for Anonymity, Undetectability, and Unobservability">

      <t>Before it makes sense to speak about any particular mechanisms for anonymity,
        undetectability, and unobservability in communications, let us first remark that all of them
        assume that stations of users do not emit signals the attacker considered is able to use for
        identification of stations or their behavior or even for identification of users or their
        behavior. So if you travel around taking with you a mobile phone sending more or less
        continuously signals to update its location information within a cellular radio network,
        don't be surprised if you are tracked using its signals. If you use a computer emitting lots
        of radiation due to a lack of shielding, don't be surprised if observers using high-tech
        equipment know quite a bit about what's happening within your machine. If you use a
        computer, PDA, or smartphone without sophisticated access control, don't be surprised if
        Trojan horses send your secrets to anybody interested whenever you are online - or via
        electromagnetic emanations even if you think you are completely offline.</t>

      <t>DC-net <xref target="Chau85"/>, <xref target="Chau88"/>, and MIX-net <xref target="Chau81"
        /> are mechanisms to achieve sender anonymity and relationship anonymity, respectively, both
        against strong attackers. If we add dummy traffic, both provide for the corresponding
        unobservability <xref target="PfPW91"/>. If dummy traffic is used to pad sending and/or
        receiving on the sender's and/or recipient's line to a constant rate traffic, MIX-nets can
        even provide sender and/or recipient anonymity and unobservability. </t>

      <t>Broadcast <xref target="Chau85"/>, <xref target="PfWa86"/>, <xref target="Waid90"/> and
        private information retrieval <xref target="CoBi95"/> are mechanisms to achieve recipient
        anonymity against strong attackers. If we add dummy traffic, both provide for recipient
        unobservability.</t>
      <t> This may be summarized: A mechanism to achieve some kind of anonymity appropriately
        combined with dummy traffic yields the corresponding kind of unobservability.</t>
      <t> Of course, dummy traffic alone can be used to make the number and/or length of sent
        messages undetectable by everybody except for the recipients; respectively, dummy traffic
        can be used to make the number and/or length of received messages undetectable by everybody
        except for the senders. (Note: Misinformation and disinformation may be regarded as semantic
        dummy traffic, i.e., communication from which an attacker cannot decide which are real
        requests with real data or which are fake ones. Assuming the authenticity of misinformation
        or disinformation may lead to privacy problems for (innocent) bystanders.) </t>
      <t>As a side remark, we mention steganography and spread spectrum as two other well-known
        undetectability mechanisms.</t>
      <t> The usual concept to achieve undetectability of IOIs at some layer, e.g., sending
        meaningful messages, is to achieve statistical independence of all discernible phenomena at
        some lower implementation layer. An example is sending dummy messages at some lower layer to
        achieve, e.g., a constant rate flow of messages looking - by means of encryption - randomly
        for all parties except the sender and the recipient(s). </t>
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
    -->


    <section anchor="pseudonymity" title="Pseudonymity">

      <t>Having anonymity of human beings, unlinkability, and maybe unobservability is superb w.r.t.
        data minimization, but would prevent any useful two-way communication. For many
        applications, we need appropriate kinds of identifiers: </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:">A pseudonym is an identifier of a subject other than one of the
            subject's real names.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>The term 'pseudonym' comes from the Greek word "pseudonumon" and means "falsely named"
            (pseudo: false; onuma: name). Thus, it means a name other than the 'real name'. To avoid
            the connotation of "pseudo" = false, some authors call pseudonyms as defined in this
            paper simply nyms. This is nice and short, but we stick with the usual wording, i.e.,
            pseudonym, pseudonymity, etc. However the reader should not be surprised to read nym,
            nymity, etc. in other texts.</t>
          <t>An identifier is a name or another bit string. Identifiers, which are generated using
            random data only, i.e., fully independent of the subject and related attribute values,
            do not contain side information on the subject they are attached to, whereas non-random
            identifiers may do. E.g., nicknames chosen by a user may contain information on heroes
            he admires; a sequence number may contain information on the time the pseudonym was
            issued; an e-mail address or phone number contains information how to reach the user.</t>
          <t>In our setting 'subject' means sender or recipient.</t>
          <t>The term 'real name' is the antonym to "pseudonym". There may be multiple real names
            over lifetime, in particular the legal names, i.e., for a human being the names which
            appear on the birth certificate or on other official identity documents issued by the
            State; for a legal person the name under which it operates and which is registered in
            official registers (e.g., commercial register or register of associations). A human
            being's real name typically comprises their given name and a family name. In the realm
            of identifiers, it is tempting to define anonymity as "the attacker cannot sufficiently
            determine a real name of the subject". But despite the simplicity of this definition, it
            is severely restricted: It can only deal with subjects which have at least one real
            name. It presumes that it is clear who is authorized to attach real names to subjects.
            It fails to work if the relation to real names is irrelevant for the application at
            hand. Therefore, we stick to the definitions given in <xref target="anonymity"/>.
            <!-- A slightly broader discussion of this topic is given in Appendix A3. --> Note that
            from a mere technological perspective it cannot always be determined whether an
            identifier of a subject is a pseudonym or a real name.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>We can generalize pseudonyms to be identifiers of sets of subjects - see below -, but we do
        not need this in our setting.</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> The subject which the pseudonym refers to is the holder of the
              pseudonym.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="Definition:">A subject is pseudonymous if a pseudonym is used as identifier
            instead of one of its real names.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>We prefer the term "holder" over "owner" of a pseudonym because it seems to make no
            sense to "own" identifiers, e.g., bit strings. Furthermore, the term "holder" sounds
            more neutral than the term "owner", which is associated with an assumed autonomy of the
            subject's will. The holder may be a natural person (in this case we have the usual
            meaning and all data protection regulations apply), a legal person, or even only a
            computer.</t>
          <t>Fundamentally, pseudonyms are nothing else than another kind of attribute values. But
            whereas in building an IT system, its designer can strongly support the holders of
            pseudonyms to keep the pseudonyms under their control, this is not equally possible
            w.r.t. attributes and attribute values in general. Therefore, it is useful to give this
            kind of attribute a distinct name: pseudonym.</t>
          <t>For pseudonyms chosen by the user (in contrast to pseudonyms assigned to the user by
            others), primarily, the holder of the pseudonym is using it. Secondarily, all others he
            communicated to using the pseudonym can utilize it for linking. Each of them can, of
            course, divulge the pseudonym and all data related to it to other entities. So finally,
            the attacker will utilize the pseudonym to link all data related to this pseudonym he
            gets to know being related.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Defining the process of preparing for the use of pseudonyms, e.g., by establishing certain
        rules how and under which conditions to identify holders of pseudonyms by so-called identity
        brokers or how to prevent uncovered claims by so-called liability brokers (cf. <xref
          target="acc-authz"/>), leads to the more general notion of pseudonymity, as defined below. </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>Identity brokers have for the pseudonyms they are the identity broker for the
            information who is their respective holder. Therefore, identity brokers can be
            implemented as a special kind of certification authorities for pseudonyms. Since
            anonymity can be described as a particular kind of unlinkability, cf. <xref
              target="ano-unlink"/>, the concept of identity broker can be generalized to
            linkability broker. A linkability broker is a (trusted) third party that, adhering to
            agreed rules, enables linking IOIs for those entities being entitled to get to know the
            linking.</t>
          <t>Concerning the natural use of the English language, one might use "pseudonymization"
            instead of "pseudonymity". But at least in Germany, the law makers gave
            "pseudonymization" the meaning that first personal data known by others comprise some
            identifiers for the civil identity and later these identifiers are replaced by
            pseudonyms. Therefore, we use a different term (coined by David Chaum: "pseudonymity")
            to describe that from the very beginning pseudonyms are used.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:">Pseudonymity is the use of pseudonyms as identifiers.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>From <xref target="ISO99"/>: "Pseudonymity ensures that a user may use a resource or
            service without disclosing its user identity, but can still be accountable for that use.
            [...] Pseudonymity requires that a set of users and/or subjects are unable to determine
            the identity of a user bound to a subject or operation, but that this user is still
            accountable for its actions." This view on pseudonymity covers only the use of digital
            pseudonyms. Therefore, our definition of pseudonymity is much broader as it does not
            necessarily require disclosure of the user's identity and accountability. Pseudonymity
            alone - as it is used in the real world and in technological contexts - does not tell
            anything about the strengths of anonymity, authentication or accountability; these
            strengths depend on several properties, cf. below.</t>
          <t>Quantifying pseudonymity would primarily mean quantifying the state of using a
            pseudonym according to its different dimensions (cf. <xref target="acc-authz"/> and
              <xref target="pseudo-link"/>), i.e., quantifying the authentication and accountability
            gained and quantifying the anonymity left over (e.g., using entropy as the measure).
            Roughly speaking, well-employed pseudonymity could mean in e-commerce appropriately
            fine-grained authentication and accountability to counter identity theft or to prevent
            uncovered claims using, e.g., the techniques described in <xref target="BuPf90"/>,
            combined with much anonymity retained. Poorly employed pseudonymity would mean giving
            away anonymity without preventing uncovered claims.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>So sender pseudonymity is defined as the sender being pseudonymous, recipient pseudonymity
        is defined as the recipient being pseudonymous, see <xref target="fig7"/>. Providing sender
        pseudonymity and recipient pseudonymity is the basic interface communication networks have
        to provide to enhance privacy for two-way communications.</t>


      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig7" title="Pseudonymity">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 Senders                                                     Recipients

         Pseudonyms                                 Pseudonyms

    --                     Communication Network
   |  | ----                       ------
    --      \\  -              ----      ----
              \| |----       //              \\          -       --
                -     ---- //                  \\ ------| |-----|  |
                          /                      \       -       --
                         /           +-+          \
                        /            +-+           \
   /-\          -      |                            |
  |   |------- | |---  |        +-+       +-+       |
   \-/          -    --|        +-+       +-+       |    -      /-\
                      |                              |--| |----|   |
                      |           Messages           |   -      \-/
                      |                              |
                       |          +-+               |
                -   ---|          +-+               |
    --    -----| |--   |                  +-+       |\\  -
   |  | --      -       \                 +-+      /   \| |---   --
    --                   \                        /      -    --|  |
       holder-            \                      /               --
       ship                \\                  //
                             \\              //            holder-
                               ----      ----              ship
                                   ------

   Sender
   Pseudonymity                                          Recipient
                                                         Pseudonymity
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>


      <t>In our usual setting, we assume that each pseudonym refers to exactly one specific holder,
        invariant over time.</t>

      <t>Specific kinds of pseudonyms may extend this setting: A group pseudonym refers to a set of
        holders, i.e., it may refer to multiple holders; a transferable pseudonym can be transferred
        from one holder to another subject becoming its holder.</t>

      <t>Such a group pseudonym may induce an anonymity set: Using the information provided by the
        pseudonym only, an attacker cannot decide whether an action was performed by a specific
        subject within the set. Please note that the mere fact that a pseudonym has several holders
        does not yield a group pseudonym: For instance, creating the same pseudonym may happen by
        chance and even without the holders being aware of this fact, particularly if they choose
        the pseudonyms and prefer pseudonyms which are easy to remember. But the context of each use
        of the pseudonym (e.g., used by which subject - usually denoted by another pseudonym - in
        which kind of transaction) then usually will denote a single holder of this pseudonym.</t>

      <t>Transferable pseudonyms can, if the attacker cannot completely monitor all transfers of
        holdership, serve the same purpose, without decreasing accountability as seen by an
        authority monitoring all transfers of holdership.</t>

      <t>An interesting combination might be transferable group pseudonyms - but this is left for
        further study.</t>

    </section>


    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->


    <section anchor="acc-authz"
      title="Pseudonymity with respect to accountability and authorization">

      <section anchor="acc-authz1" title="Digital pseudonyms to authenticate messages">
        <t>A digital pseudonym is a bit string which, to be meaningful in a certain context, is
            <list style="symbols">
            <t>unique as identifier (at least with very high probability) and</t>
            <t>suitable to be used to authenticate the holder's IOIs relatively to his/her digital
              pseudonym, e.g., to authenticate his/her messages sent.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Using digital pseudonyms, accountability can be realized with pseudonyms - or more
          precisely: with respect to pseudonyms.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="acc-authz2" title="Accountability for digital pseudonyms">
        <t>To authenticate IOIs relative to pseudonyms usually is not enough to achieve
          accountability for IOIs. </t>
        <t>Therefore, in many situations, it might make sense to either <list style="symbols">
            <t>attach funds to digital pseudonyms to cover claims or to </t>
            <t>let identity brokers authenticate digital pseudonyms (i.e., check the civil identity
              of the holder of the pseudonym and then issue a digitally signed statement that this
              particular identity broker has proof of the identity of the holder of this digital
              pseudonym and is willing to divulge that proof under well-defined circumstances) or</t>
            <t>both.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Note:<list style="empty">
            <t>If the holder of the pseudonym is a natural person or a legal person, civil identity
              has the usual meaning, i.e. the identity attributed to an individual person by a State
              (e.g., represented by the social security number or the combination of name, date of
              birth, and location of birth etc.). If the holder is, e.g., a computer, it remains to
              be defined what "civil identity" should mean. It could mean, for example, exact type
              and serial number of the computer (or essential components of it) or even include the
              natural person or legal person responsible for its operation.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>If sufficient funds attached to a digital pseudonym are reserved and/or the digitally
          signed statement of a trusted identity broker is checked before entering into a
          transaction with the holder of that pseudonym, accountability can be realized in spite of
          anonymity.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="acc-authz3"
        title="Transferring authenticated attributes and authorizations between pseudonyms">
        <t>To transfer attributes including their authentication by third parties (called
          "credentials" by David Chaum <xref target="Chau85"/>) - all kinds of authorizations are
          special cases - between digital pseudonyms of one and the same holder, it is always
          possible to prove that these pseudonyms have the same holder.</t>
        <t>But as David Chaum pointed out, it is much more anonymity-preserving to maintain the
          unlinkability of the digital pseudonyms involved as much as possible by transferring the
          credential from one pseudonym to the other without proving the sameness of the holder. How
          this can be done is described in <xref target="Chau90"/>
          <xref target="CaLy04"/>.</t>
        <t>We will come back to the just described property "convertibility" of digital pseudonyms
          in <xref target="known-other"/>. </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->


    <section anchor="pseudo-link" title="Pseudonymity with respect to linkability">

      <t>Whereas anonymity and accountability are the extremes with respect to linkability to
        subjects, pseudonymity is the entire field between and including these extremes. Thus,
        pseudonymity comprises all degrees of linkability to a subject. Ongoing use of the same
        pseudonym allows the holder to establish or consolidate a reputation. Establishing and/or
        consolidating a reputation under a pseudonym is, of course, insecure if the pseudonym does
        not enable to authenticate messages, i.e., if the pseudonym is not a digital pseudonym, cf.
          <xref target="acc-authz1"/>. Then, at any moment, another subject might use this pseudonym
        possibly invalidating the reputation, both for the holder of the pseudonym and all others
        having to do with this pseudonym. Some kinds of pseudonyms enable dealing with claims in
        case of abuse of unlinkability to holders: Firstly, third parties (identity brokers, cf.
          <xef target="acc-authz2"/>) may have the possibility to reveal the civil identity of the
        holder in order to provide means for investigation or prosecution. To improve the robustness
        of anonymity, chains of identity brokers may be used <xref target="Chau81"/>. Secondly,
        third parties may act as liability brokers of the holder to clear a debt or settle a claim.
          <xref target="BuPf90"/> presents the particular case of value brokers.</t>

      <t>There are many properties of pseudonyms which may be of importance in specific application
        contexts. In order to describe the properties of pseudonyms with respect to anonymity, we
        limit our view to two aspects and give some typical examples:</t>

      <section anchor="pseudo-link1"
        title="Knowledge of the linking between the pseudonym and its holder">

        <t>The knowledge of the linking may not be a constant, but change over time for some or even
          all people. Normally, for non-transferable pseudonyms the knowledge of the linking cannot
          decrease (with the exception of misinformation or disinformation, which may blur the
          attacker's knowledge.). Typical kinds of such pseudonyms are:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="Public pseudonym:"> The linking between a public pseudonym and its holder
              may be publicly known even from the very beginning. E.g., the linking could be listed
              in public directories such as the entry of a phone number in combination with its
              owner. </t>

            <t hangText="Initially non-public pseudonym:"> The linking between an initially
              non-public pseudonym and its holder may be known by certain parties, but is not public
              at least initially. E.g., a bank account where the bank can look up the linking may
              serve as a non-public pseudonym. For some specific non-public pseudonyms,
              certification authorities acting as identity brokers could reveal the civil identity
              of the holder in case of abuse.</t>

            <t hangText="Initially unlinked pseudonym:"> The linking between an initially unlinked
              pseudonym and its holder is - at least initially - not known to anybody with the
              possible exception of the holder himself/herself. Examples for unlinked pseudonyms are
              (non-public) biometrics like DNA information unless stored in databases including the
              linking to the holders.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>Public pseudonyms and initially unlinked pseudonyms can be seen as extremes of the
          described pseudonym aspect whereas initially non-public pseudonyms characterize the
          continuum in between.</t>

        <t>Anonymity is the stronger, the less is known about the linking to a subject. The strength
          of anonymity decreases with increasing knowledge of the pseudonym linking. In particular,
          under the assumption that no gained knowledge on the linking of a pseudonym will be
          forgotten and that the pseudonym cannot be transferred to other subjects, a public
          pseudonym never can become an unlinked pseudonym. In each specific case, the strength of
          anonymity depends on the knowledge of certain parties about the linking relative to the
          chosen attacker model.</t>

        <t>If the pseudonym is transferable, the linking to its holder can change. Considering an
          unobserved transfer of a pseudonym to another subject, a formerly public pseudonym can
          become non-public again.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="pseudo-link2"
        title="Linkability due to the use of a pseudonym across different contexts">

        <t>With respect to the degree of linkability, various kinds of pseudonyms may be
          distinguished according to the kind of context for their usage:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Person pseudonym:"> A person pseudonym is a substitute for the holder's
              name which is regarded as representation for the holder's civil identity. It may be
              used in many different contexts, e.g., a number of an identity card, the social
              security number, DNA, a nickname, the pseudonym of an actor, or a mobile phone number.</t>

            <t hangText="Role pseudonym:"> The use of role pseudonyms is limited to specific roles,
              e.g., a customer pseudonym or an Internet account used for many instantiations of the
              same role "Internet user". See <xref target="idm3"/> for a more precise
              characterization of the term "role". The same role pseudonym may be used with
              different communication partners. Roles might be assigned by other parties, e.g., a
              company, but they might be chosen by the subject himself/herself as well.</t>

            <t hangText="Relationship pseudonym:"> For each communication partner, a different
              relationship pseudonym is used. The same relationship pseudonym may be used in
              different roles for communicating with the same partner. Examples are distinct
              nicknames for each communication partner. In case of group communication, the
              relationship pseudonyms may be used between more than two partners. </t>

            <t hangText="Role-relationship pseudonym:"> For each role and for each communication
              partner, a different role-relationship pseudonym is used. This means that the
              communication partner does not necessarily know, whether two pseudonyms used in
              different roles belong to the same holder. On the other hand, two different
              communication partners who interact with a user in the same role, do not know from the
              pseudonym alone whether it is the same user. As with relationship pseudonyms, in case
              of group communication, the role-relationship pseudonyms may be used between more than
              two partners.</t>

            <t hangText="Transaction pseudonym:"> Apart from "transaction pseudonym" some employ the
              term "one-time-use pseudonym", taking the naming from "one-time pad". For each
              transaction, a transaction pseudonym unlinkable to any other transaction pseudonyms
              and at least initially unlinkable to any other IOI is used, e.g., randomly generated
              transaction numbers for online-banking. Therefore, transaction pseudonyms can be used
              to realize as strong anonymity as possible. In fact, the strongest anonymity is given
              when there is no identifying information at all, i.e., information that would allow
              linking of anonymous entities, thus transforming the anonymous transaction into a
              pseudonymous one. If the transaction pseudonym is used exactly once, we have the same
              strength of anonymity as if no pseudonym is used at all. Another possibility to
              achieve strong anonymity is to prove the holdership of the pseudonym or specific
              attribute values (e.g., with zero-knowledge proofs) without revealing the information
              about the pseudonym or more detailed attribute values themselves. Then, no
              identifiable or linkable information is disclosed. </t>
          </list>
        </t>


      </section>

      <t>Linkability across different contexts due to the use of these pseudonyms can be represented
        as the lattice that is illustrated in the following diagram, see <xref target="fig8"/>. The
        arrows point in direction of increasing unlinkability, i.e., A -> B stands for "B enables
        stronger unlinkability than A". Note that "->" is not the same as "=>" of <xref
          target="relationship"/>, which stands for the implication concerning anonymity and
        unobservability. </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig8"
          title="Lattice of pseudonyms according to their use across different contexts">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                                          linkable

                                      +-----------------+  *
            Person                    |                 |  *
          / Pseudonym \                |   decreasing  |  *
        //             \\              |   linkability |  *
       /                 \             |    across    |  *
      /                   \-+           |  contexts   |  *
   +-/                      v           |            |   *
   v Role               Relationship    |            |  *
Pseudonym               Pseudonym        |           |  *
    --                     --            |          |  *
      --                ---              |          |  *
        ---         ----                  |        |   *
           --+  +---                      |        |  *
             v  v                          |      |   *
         Role-Relationship                 |      |  |*
         Pseudonym                         |     |   *
              |                             |    |   *
              |                             |    |  *
              |                             |   |   *
              |                              |  |   *
              |                              | |   *
              v                              | |   *
         Transaction                          |   *
         Pseudonym                            |   v

                                                 unlinkable
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>In general, unlinkability of both role pseudonyms and relationship pseudonyms is stronger
        than unlinkability of person pseudonyms. The strength of unlinkability increases with the
        application of role-relationship pseudonyms, the use of which is restricted to both the same
        role and the same relationship. If a role-relationship pseudonym is used for roles
        comprising many kinds of activities, the danger arises that after a while, it becomes a
        person pseudonym in the sense of: "A person pseudonym is a substitute for the holder's name
        which is regarded as representation for the holder's civil identity." This is even more true
        both for role pseudonyms and relationship pseudonyms. Ultimate strength of unlinkability is
        obtained with transaction pseudonyms, provided that no other information, e.g., from the
        context or from the pseudonym itself, enabling linking is available.</t>

      <t>Anonymity is the stronger, ... <list style="symbols">
          <t> the less personal data of the pseudonym holder can be linked to the pseudonym;</t>
          <t> the less often and the less context-spanning pseudonyms are used and therefore the
            less data about the holder can be linked;</t>
          <t> the more often independently chosen, i.e., from an observer's perspective unlinkable,
            pseudonyms are used for new actions.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The amount of information of linked data can be reduced by different subjects using the
        same pseudonym (e.g., one after the other when pseudonyms are transferred or simultaneously
        with specifically created group pseudonyms) or by misinformation or disinformation. The
        group of pseudonym holders acts as an inner anonymity set within a, depending on context
        information, potentially even larger outer anonymity set.</t>

    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="known-other" title="Known mechanisms and other properties of pseudonyms">

      <t>A digital pseudonym could be realized as a public key to test digital signatures where the
        holder of the pseudonym can prove holdership by forming a digital signature which is created
        using the corresponding private key <xref target="Chau81"/>. The most prominent example for
        digital pseudonyms are public keys generated by the user himself/herself, e.g., using PGP.
        In using PGP, each user may create an unlimited number of key pairs by himself/herself (at
        this moment, such a key pair is an initially unlinked pseudonym), bind each of them to an
        e-mail address, self-certify each public key by using his/her digital signature or asking
        another introducer to do so, and circulate it.</t>

      <t>A public key certificate bears a digital signature of a so-called certification authority
        and provides some assurance to the binding of a public key to another pseudonym, usually
        held by the same subject. In case that pseudonym is the civil identity (the real name) of a
        subject, such a certificate is called an identity certificate. An attribute certificate is a
        digital certificate which contains further information (attribute values) and clearly refers
        to a specific public key certificate. Independent of certificates, attributes may be used as
        identifiers of sets of subjects as well. Normally, attributes refer to sets of subjects
        (i.e., the anonymity set), not to one specific subject.</t>

      <t>There are several other properties of pseudonyms related to their use which shall only be
        briefly mentioned, but not discussed in detail in this text. They comprise different degrees
        of, e.g.,<list style="symbols">

          <t>limitation to a fixed number of pseudonyms per subject <xref target="Chau81"/>, <xref
              target="Chau85"/>, <xref target="Chau90"/>. For pseudonyms issued by an agency that
            guarantees the limitation of at most one pseudonym per individual person, the term
            "is-a-person pseudonym" is used.</t>
          <t>guaranteed uniqueness <xref target="Chau81"/>
            <xref target="StSy00"/>, e.g., "globally unique pseudonyms".</t>
          <t>transferability to other subjects.</t>
          <t>authenticity of the linking between a pseudonym and its holder (possibilities of
            verification/falsification or indication/repudiation).</t>
          <t>provability that two or more pseudonyms have the same holder. For digital pseudonyms
            having only one holder each and assuming that no holders cooperate to provide wrong
            "proofs", this can be proved trivially by signing, e.g., the statement
            "&lt;Pseudonym1> and &lt;Pseudonym2> have the same holder." digitally with
            respect to both these pseudonyms. Putting it the other way round: Proving that
            pseudonyms have the same holder is all but trivial.</t>
          <t>convertibility, i.e., transferability of attributes of one pseudonym to another <xref
              target="Chau85"/>, <xref target="Chau90"/>. This is a property of convertible
            credentials.</t>
          <t>possibility and frequency of pseudonym changeover.</t>
          <t>re-usability and, possibly, a limitation in number of uses.</t>
          <t>validity (e.g., guaranteed durability and/or expiry date, restriction to a specific
            application).</t>
          <t>possibility of revocation or blocking.</t>
          <t>participation of users or other parties in forming the pseudonyms. </t>
          <t>information content about attributes in the pseudonym itself.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>In addition, there may be some properties for specific applications (e.g., an addressable
        pseudonym serves as a communication address which enables to contact its holder) or due to
        the participation of third parties (e.g., in order to circulate the pseudonyms, to reveal
        civil identities in case of abuse, or to cover claims).</t>

      <t>Some of the properties can easily be realized by extending a digital pseudonym by
        attributes of some kind, e.g., a communication address, and specifying the appropriate
        semantics. The binding of attributes to a pseudonym can be documented in an attribute
        certificate produced either by the holder himself/herself or by a certification authority.
        The non-transferability of the attribute certificate can be somewhat enforced, e.g., by
        biometrical means, by combining it with individual hardware (e.g., chipcards), or by
        confronting the holder with legal consequences.</t>

    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="idm" title="Identity management">


      <section anchor="idm1" title="Setting">
        <t>To adequately address privacy-enhancing identity management, we have to extend our
            setting:<list style="symbols">
            <t> It is not realistic to assume that an attacker might not get information on the
              sender or recipient of messages from the message content and/or the sending or
              receiving context (time, location information, etc.) of the message. We have to
              consider that the attacker is able to use these attributes for linking messages and,
              correspondingly, the pseudonyms used with them.</t>
            <t>In addition, it is not just human beings, legal persons, or simply computers sending
              messages and using pseudonyms at their discretion as they like at the moment, but they
              use (computer-based) applications, which strongly influence the sending and receiving
              of messages and may even strongly determine the usage of pseudonym.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="idm2" title="Identity and identifiability">
        <t> Identity can be explained as an exclusive perception of life, integration into a social
          group, and continuity, which is bound to a body and - at least to some degree - shaped by
          society. This concept of identity distinguishes between "I" and "Me" <xref target="Mead34"
          /> : "I" is the instance that is accessible only by the individual self, perceived as an
          instance of liberty and initiative. "Me" is supposed to stand for the social attributes,
          defining a human identity that is accessible by communications and that is an inner
          instance of control and consistency (see <xref target="ICPP03"/> for more information). In
          this terminology, we are interested in identity as communicated to others and seen by
          them. Therefore, we concentrate on the "Me".</t>
        <t>Note:<list style="empty">
            <t>Here (and in <xref target="idm"/> throughout), we have human beings in mind, which is
              the main motivation for privacy. From a structural point of view, identity can be
              attached to any subject, be it a human being, a legal person, or even a computer. This
              makes the terminology more general, but may lose some motivation at first sight.
              Therefore, we start in our explanation with identity of human beings, but implicitly
              generalize to subjects thereafter. This means: In a second reading of this paper, you
              may replace "individual person" by "individual subject" (introduced as "possibly
              acting entity" at the beginning of <xref target="setting"/>) throughout as it was used
              in the definitions of the <xref target="setting"/> through <xref target="known-other"
              />. It may be discussed whether the definitions can be further generalized and apply
              for any "entity", regardless of subject or not.</t>
            <t>According to Mireille Hildebrandt, the French philosopher Paul Ricoeur made a
              distinction between "idem and ipse. Idem (sameness) stands for the third person,
              objectified observer's perspective of identity as a set of attributes that allows
              comparison between different people, as well as unique identification, whereas ipse
              (self) stands for the first person perspective constituting a 'sense of self'.", see
              page 274 in <xref target="RaRD09"/>. So what George H. Mead called "I" is similar to
              what Paul Ricoeur called "ipse" (self). What George H. Mead called "Me" is similar to
              what Paul Ricoeur called "idem" (sameness).</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t> Motivated by identity as an exclusive perception of life, i.e., a psychological
          perspective, but using terms defined from a computer science, i.e., a mathematical
          perspective (as we did in the sections before), identity can be explained and defined as a
          property of an entity in terms of the negation of anonymity and the negation of
          unlinkability. In a positive wording, identity enables both to be identifiable as well as
          to link IOIs because of some continuity of life. Here we have the negation of anonymity
          (identifiability) and the negation of unlinkability (linkability) as positive properties.
          So the perspective changes: What is the aim of an attacker w.r.t. anonymity, now is the
          aim of the subject under consideration, so the attacker's perspective becomes the
          perspective of the subject. And again, another attacker (attacker2) might be considered
          working against identifiability and/or linkability. I.e., attacker2 might try to mask
          different attributes of subjects to provide for some kind of anonymity or attacker2 might
          spoof some messages to interfere with the continuity of the subject's life.</t>
        <t> Corresponding to the anonymity set introduced in the beginning of this text, we can work
          with an "identifiability set" <xref target="Hild03"/>, which is the set is a set of
          possible subjects, to define "identifiability" and "identity". This definition is
          compatible with the definitions given in <xref target="HoWi03"/> and it is very close to
          that given by <xref target="Chi03"/>: "An identity is any subset of attributes of a person
          which uniquely characterizes this person within a community." </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Definition:">Identifiability of a subject from an attacker's perspective
              means that the attacker can sufficiently identify the subject within a set of
              subjects, the identifiability set.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t><xref target="fig9"/> contrasts anonymity set and identifiability set.</t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="fig9" title="Anonymity set vs. identifiability set">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
       Anonymity                          Identifiability
       within an                            within an
           --                                   --
         --  --                               --  --
        /      \                             /      \
        /      \                             /      \
       /   --   \                           /   --/  \
      /   |  |   \                         /   |//|   \
      /    --    \                         /   /--    \
      /          \                         /          \
     /            \                       /            \
     /     --     \                       /     --     \
     /    |  |    \                       /    |  |    \
     |     --     |                       |     --     |
    |              |                     |              |
    |              |                     |              |
     |     --     |                       |     --/    |
     \    |  |    /                       \    |//|    /
     \     --     /                       \    /--     /
     \            /                       \            /
      \          /                         \          /
      \    --    /                         \    --/   /
      \   |  |   /                         \   |//|   /
       \   --   /                           \  /--   /
        \      /                             \      /
        \      /                             \      /
         --  --                               --  --
           --                                   --
      anonymity set                      identifiability set
 ]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>All other things being equal, identifiability is the stronger, the larger the respective
          identifiability set is. Conversely, the remaining anonymity is the stronger, the smaller
          the respective identifiability set is.</t>. <t>Identity of an individual person should be
          defined independent of an attacker's perspective:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Definition:">An identity is any subset of attribute values of an individual
              person which sufficiently identifies this individual person within any set of persons.
              So usually there is no such thing as "the identity", but several of them.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Note:<list style="empty">
            <t>Whenever we speak about "attribute values" in this text, this shall comprise not only
              a measurement of the attribute value, but the attribute as well. E.g., if we talk
              about the attribute "color of one's hair" the attribute value "color of one's hair" is
              not just, e.g., "grey", but ("color of one's hair", "grey").</t>
            <t>An equivalent, but slightly longer definition of identity would be: An identity is
              any subset of attribute values of an individual person which sufficiently
              distinguishes this individual person from all other persons within any set of
            persons.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t> Of course, attribute values or even attributes themselves may change over time.
          Therefore, if the attacker has no access to the change history of each particular
          attribute, the fact whether a particular subset of attribute values of an individual
          person is an identity or not may change over time as well. If the attacker has access to
          the change history of each particular attribute, any subset forming an identity will form
          an identity from his perspective irrespective how attribute values change. Any reasonable
          attacker will not just try to figure out attribute values per se, but the point in time
          (or even the time frame) they are valid (in), since this change history helps a lot in
          linking and thus inferring further attribute values. Therefore, it may clarify one's mind
          to define each "attribute" in a way that its value cannot get invalid. So instead of the
          attribute "location" of a particular individual person, take the set of attributes
          "location at time x". Depending on the inferences you are interested in, refining that set
          as a list ordered concerning "location" or "time" may be helpful. </t>
        <t> Identities may of course comprise particular attribute values like names, identifiers,
          digital pseudonyms, and addresses - but they don't have to. </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="idm3" title="Identity-related terms">

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="Role:"> In sociology, a "role" or "social role" is a set of connected
              actions, as conceptualized by actors in a social situation (i.e., situation-dependent
              identity attributes). It is mostly defined as an expected behavior (i.e., sequences of
              actions) in a given individual social context. So roles provide for some linkability
              of actions. </t>
            <t hangText="Partial identity:"> An identity of an individual person may comprise many
              partial identities of which each represents the person in a specific context or role.
              (Note: As an identity has to do with integration into a social group, on the one hand,
              partial identities have to do with, e.g., relationships to particular group members
              (or to be more general: relationships to particular subsets of group members). On the
              other hand, partial identities might be associated with relationships to
              organizations.) A partial identity is a subset of attribute values of a complete
              identity, where a complete identity is the union of all attribute values of all
              identities of this person. (Note: If attributes are defined such that their values do
              not get invalid, "union" can have the usual meaning within set theory. We have to
              admit that usually nobody, including the person concerned, will know "all" attribute
              values or "all" identities. Nevertheless we hope that the notion "complete identity"
              will ease the understanding of "identity" and "partial identity".) On a technical
              level, these attribute values are data. Of course, attribute values or even attributes
              themselves of a partial identity may change over time. As identities, partial
              identities may comprise particular attribute values like names, identifiers, digital
              pseudonyms, and addresses - but they don't have to, either. A pseudonym might be an
              identifier for a partial identity. If it is possible to transfer attribute values of
              one pseudonym to another (as convertibility of credentials provides for, cf. <xref
                target="known-other"/>), this means transferring a partial identity to this other
              pseudonym. Re-use of the partial identity with its identifier(s), e.g., a pseudonym,
              supports continuity in the specific context or role by enabling linkability with,
              e.g., former or future messages or actions. If the pseudonym is a digital pseudonym,
              it provides the possibility to authenticate w.r.t. the partial identity which is
              important to prevent others to take over the partial identity (discussed as "identity
              theft" ). Linkability of partial identities arises by non-changing identifiers of a
              partial identity as well as other attribute values of that partial identity that are
              (sufficiently) static or easily determinable over time (e.g., bodily biometrics, the
              size or age of a person). All the data that can be used to link data sets such as
              partial identities belong to a category of "data providing linkability" (to which we
              must pay the same attention as to personal data w.r.t. privacy and data protection;
              "protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data" <xref
                target="DPD95"/>). Whereas we assume that an "identity" sufficiently identifies an
              individual person (without limitation to particular identifiability sets), a partial
              identity may not do, thereby enabling different quantities of anonymity. So we may
              have linkability by re-using a partial identity (which may be important to support
              continuity of life) without necessarily giving up anonymity (which may be important
              for privacy). But we may find for each partial identity appropriately small
              identifiability sets, where the partial identity sufficiently identifies an individual
              person, see <xref target="fig10"/>. For identifiability sets of cardinality 1, this is
              trivial, but it may hold for "interesting" identifiability sets of larger cardinality
              as well. The relation between anonymity set and identifiability set can be seen in two
                ways:<list style="numbers">
                <t>Within an a-priori anonymity set, we can consider a-posteriori identifiability
                  sets as subsets of the anonymity set. Then the largest identifiability sets
                  allowing identification characterize the a-posteriori anonymity, which is zero iff
                  the largest identifiability set allowing identification equals the a-priori
                  anonymity set. </t>
                <t>Within an a-priori identifiability set, its subsets which are the a-posteriori
                  anonymity sets characterize the a-posteriori anonymity. It is zero iff all
                  a-posteriori anonymity sets have cardinality 1.</t>
              </list> As with identities, depending on whether the attacker has access to the change
              history of each particular attribute or not, the identifiability set of a partial
              identity may change over time if the values of its attributes change.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/>
              <figure anchor="fig10" title="Relation between anonymity set and identifiability set">
                <artwork><![CDATA[
         --
       --  --
      /      \
      /      \
     /   --/  \
    /   |//|   \                            --
    /   /--    \                          --  --
    /          \                         /      \
   /            \                        /      \
   /     --/    \                       /   --/  \
   /    |//|    \         --           /   |//|   \
   |    /--     |       --  --         /   /--    \
  |              |     /      \        /          \
  |              |     /      \       /            \
  |      --/     |    /   --/  \      /     --/    \
  |     |//|     |   /   |//|   \     /    |//|    \
  |     /--      |   /   /--    \     |    /--     |
  |              |   /          \    |              |
  |   +-------------------------------------------+ |
   |  |  --     |   /     --     \   |      -- (*)| |
   \  | |  |    /   /    |  |    \   |     |  |   | |
   \  |  --     /   |     --     |   |      --    | |
   \  +-------------------------------------------+ |
    \          /   |              |  |              |
    \    --/   /   |      --/     |   |     --/    |
    \   |//|   /   |     |//|     |   \    |//|    /
     \  /--   /    |     /--      |   \    /--     /
      \      /     |              |   \            /
      \      /     |              |    \          /
       --  --       |     --/    |     \    --/   /
         --         \    |//|    /     \   |//|   /
                    \    /--     /      \  /--   /
                    \            /       \      /
                     \          /        \      /
                     \    --/   /         --  --
                     \   |//|   /           --
                      \  /--   /
                       \      /
                       \      /
                        --  --
                          --

   *: Anonymity set of a partial identity given
      that the set of all possible subjects
      (the a-priori anonymity set) can be partitioned
      into the three disjoint identifiability sets
      of the partial identity shown.
 ]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
            <t hangText="Digital identity"> Digital identity denotes attribution of attribute values
              to an individual person, which are immediately operationally accessible by technical
              means. More to the point, the identifier of a digital partial identity can be a simple
              e-mail address in a news group or a mailing list. A digital partial identity is the
              same as a partial digital identity. In the following, we skip "partial" if the meaning
              is clear from the context. Its owner will attain a certain reputation. More generally
              we might consider the whole identity as a combination from "I" and "Me" where the "Me"
              can be divided into an implicit and an explicit part: Digital identity is the digital
              part from the explicated "Me". Digital identity should denote all those personal data
              that can be stored and automatically interlinked by a computer-based application. </t>
            <t hangText="Virtual identity"> Virtual identity is sometimes used in the same meaning
              as digital identity or digital partial identity, but because of the connotation with
              "unreal, non-existent, seeming" the term is mainly applied to characters in a MUD
              (Multi User Dungeon), MMORPG (Massively Multiplayer Online Role Playing Game) or to
              avatars. For these reasons, we do not use the notions physical world vs. virtual world
              nor physical person vs. virtual person defined in <xref target="RaRD09"/> (pp. 80ff).
              Additionally, we feel that taking the distinction between physical vs. digital
              (=virtual) world as a primary means to build up a terminology is not helpful. First we
              have to define what a person, an entity, and an identity is. The distinction between
              physical and digital is only of secondary importance and the structure of the
              terminology should reflect this fundamental fact. In other disciplines, of course, it
              may be very relevant whether a person is a human being with a physical body. Please
              remember <xref target="idm3"/>, where the sociological definition of identity includes
              "is bound to a body", or law enforcement when a jail sentence has to be carried out.
              Generalizing from persons, laws should consider and spell out whether they are
              addressing physical entities, which cannot be duplicated easily, or digital entities,
              which can. </t>
          </list>
        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Identity management-related terms">

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Identity management"> Identity management means managing various partial
              identities (usually denoted by pseudonyms) of an individual person, i.e.,
              administration of identity attributes including the development and choice of the
              partial identity and pseudonym to be (re-)used in a specific context or role.
              Establishment of reputation is possible when the individual person re-uses partial
              identities. A prerequisite to choose the appropriate partial identity is to recognize
              the situation the person is acting in. </t>
            <t hangText="Privacy-enhancing identity management"> Given the restrictions of a set of
              applications, identity management is called privacy-enhancing if it sufficiently
              preserves unlinkability (as seen by an attacker) between the partial identities of an
              individual person required by the applications. Note that due to our setting, this
              definition focuses on the main property of Privacy-Enhancing Technologies (PETs),
              namely data minimization: This property means to limit as much as possible the release
              of personal data and for those released, preserve as much unlinkability as possible.
              We are aware of the limitation of this definition: In the real world it is not always
              desired to achieve utmost unlinkability. We believe that the user as the data subject
              should be empowered to decide on the release of data and on the degree of linkage of
              his or her personal data within the boundaries of legal regulations, i.e., in an
              advanced setting the privacy-enhancing application design should also take into
              account the support of "user-controlled release" as well as "user-controlled linkage".
              Identity management is called perfectly privacy-enhancing if it perfectly preserves
              unlinkability between the partial identities, i.e., by choosing the pseudonyms (and
              their authorizations, cf. <xref target="acc-authz3"/>) denoting the partial identities
              carefully, it maintains unlinkability between these partial identities towards an
              attacker to the same degree as giving the attacker the attribute values with all
              pseudonyms omitted. (Note: Given the terminology defined in <xref target="setting"/>
              to <xref target="ano-unlink"/>, privacy-enhancing identity management is
              unlinkability-preserving identity management. So, maybe, the term "privacy-preserving
              identity management" would be more appropriate. But to be compatible to the earlier
              papers in this field, we stick to privacy-enhancing identity management.) </t>
            <t hangText="Privacy-enhancing identity management enabling application design"> An
              application is designed in a privacy-enhancing identity management enabling way if
              neither the pattern of sending/receiving messages nor the attribute values given to
              entities (i.e., human beings, organizations, computers) reduce unlinkability more than
              is strictly necessary to achieve the purposes of the application. </t>
            <t hangText="Identity management system (IMS)"> An identity management system in its
              broadest sense refers to technology-based administration of identity attributes
              including the development and choice of the partial identity and pseudonym to be
              (re-)used in a specific context or role. Note that some publications use the
              abbreviations IdMS or IDMS instead. We can distinguish between identity management
              system and identity management application: The term "identity management system" is
              seen as an infrastructure, in which "identity management applications" as components,
              i.e., software installed on computers, are co-ordinated. </t>
            <t hangText="Privacy-enhancing identity management system (PE-IMS)"> A Privacy-Enhancing
              IMS is an IMS that, given the restrictions of a set of applications, sufficiently
              preserves unlinkability (as seen by an attacker) between the partial identities and
              corresponding pseudonyms of an individual person.</t>

            <t hangText="User-controlled identity management system"> A user-controlled identity
              management system is an IMS that makes the flow of this user's identity attribute
              values explicit to the user and gives its user a large degree of control <xref
                target="CPHH02"/>. The guiding principle is "notice and choice".<vspace
                blankLines="1"/> Combining user-controlled IMS with PE-IMS means user-controlled
              linkability of personal data, i.e., achieving user-control based on thorough data
              minimization. According to respective situation and context, such a system supports
              the user in making an informed choice of pseudonyms, representing his or her partial
              identities. A user-controlled PE-IMS supports the user in managing his or her partial
              identities, i.e., to use different pseudonyms with associated identity attribute
              values according to different contexts, different roles the user is acting in and
              according to different interaction partners. It acts as a central gateway for all
              interactions between different applications, like browsing the web, buying in Internet
              shops, or carrying out administrative tasks with governmental authorities <xref
                target="HBCC04"/>. </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview of main definitions and their negations">

      <t>
        <texttable>

          <ttcol>Definition</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Negation</ttcol>

          <c>Anonymity of a subject from an attacker's perspective means that the attacker cannot
            sufficiently identify the subject within a set of subjects, the anonymity set.</c>
          <c>Identifiability of a subject from an attacker's perspective means that the attacker can
            sufficiently identify the subject within a set of subjects, the identifiability set.</c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c>Unlinkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g., subjects, messages,
            actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the system (comprising
            these and possibly other items), the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish whether
            these IOIs are related or not.</c>
          <c>Linkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g., subjects, messages, actions,
            ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the system (comprising these and
            possibly other items), the attacker can sufficiently distinguish whether these IOIs are
            related or not.</c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c>Undetectability of an item of interest (IOI) from an attacker's perspective means that
            the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish whether it exists or not.</c>
          <c>Detectability of an item of interest (IOI) from an attacker's perspective means that
            the attacker can sufficiently distinguish whether it exists or not.</c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>

          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c>Unobservability of an item of interest (IOI) means <list style="symbols">
              <t>undetectability of the IOI against all subjects uninvolved in it and </t>
              <t>anonymity of the subject(s) involved in the IOI even against the other subject(s)
                involved in that IOI.</t>
            </list>
          </c>
          <c>Observability of an item of interest (IOI) means "many possibilities to define the
            semantics".</c>
        </texttable>
      </t>

    </section>
    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Before this document was submitted to the IETF it already had a long history starting at
        2000 and a number of people helped to improve the quality of the document with their
        feedback. The original authors, Marit Hansen and Andreas Pfitzmann, would therefore like to
        thank Adam Shostack, David-Olivier Jaquet-Chiffelle, Claudia Diaz, Giles Hogben, Thomas
        Kriegelstein, Wim Schreurs, Sandra Steinbrecher, Mike Bergmann, Katrin Borcea, Simone
        Fischer-Huebner, Stefan Koepsell, Martin Rost, Marc Wilikens, Adolf Flueli, Jozef Vyskoc,
        Thomas Kriegelstein, Jan Camenisch, Vashek Matyas, Daniel Cvrcek, Wassim Haddad, Alf
        Zugenmair, Katrin Borcea-Pfitzmann, Thomas Kriegelstein, Elke Franz, Sebastian Clauss, Neil
        Mitchison, Rolf Wendolsky, Stefan Schiffner, Maritta Heisel, Katja Liesebach, Stefanie
        Poetzsch, Thomas Santen, Maritta Heisel, Manuela Berg, and Katie Tietze for their input. </t>
      <t>The terminology has been translated to other languages and the result can be found here:
        http://dud.inf.tu-dresden.de/Anon_Terminology.shtml.</t>
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="BuPf90">
        <front>
          <title>Value Exchange Systems Enabling Security and Unobservability</title>
          <author fullname="Holger Buerk" initials="H." surname="Buerk"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <date month="January" year="1990"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Computers & Security" value=", 9/8, 715-721"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CaLy04">
        <front>
          <title>Signature Schemes and Anonymous Credentials from Bilinear Maps</title>
          <author fullname="Jan Camenisch" initials="J." surname="Camenisch"> </author>
          <author fullname="Anna Lysyanskaya" initials="A." surname="Lysyanskaya"> </author>
          <date year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Crypto" value=", LNCS 3152, Springer, Berlin 2004, 56-72"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chau81">
        <front>
          <title>Untraceable Electronic Mail, Return Addresses, and Digital Pseudonyms</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1981"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Communications of the ACM" value=", 24/2, 84-88"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chau85">
        <front>
          <title>Security without Identification: Transaction Systems to make Big Brother Obsolete</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1985"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Communications of the ACM" value=", 28/10, 1030-1044"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chau88">
        <front>
          <title>The Dining Cryptographers Problem: Unconditional Sender and Recipient
            Untraceability</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1988"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Journal of Cryptology" value=", 1/1, 65-75"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chau90">
        <front>
          <title>Showing credentials without identification: Transferring signatures between
            unconditionally unlinkable pseudonyms</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1990"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Auscrypt" value=", LNCS 453, Springer, Berlin 1990, 246-264"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ClSc06">
        <front>
          <title>Structuring Anonymity Metrics</title>
          <author fullname="Sebastian Clauss" initials="S." surname="Clauss"> </author>
          <author fullname="Stefan Schiffner" initials="S." surname="Schiffner"> </author>
          <date year="2006"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=""
          value="in A. Goto (Ed.), DIM '06, Proceedings of the 2006 ACM Workshop on Digital Identity Management, Fairfax, USA, Nov. 2006, 55-62"
        />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CoBi95">
        <front>
          <title>Preserving Privacy in a Network of Mobile Computers</title>
          <author fullname="David A. Cooper" initials="D." surname="Cooper"> </author>
          <author fullname="Kenneth P. Birm" initials="K." surname="Birm"> </author>
          <date year="1995"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Symposium on Research in Security and Privacy"
          value=", IEEE Computer Society Press, Los Alamitos 1995, 26-38"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CPHH02">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy-Enhancing Identity Management</title>
          <author fullname="Sebastian Clauss" initials="S." surname="Clauss"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Marit Hansen" initials="M." surname="Hansen"> </author>
          <author fullname="Els Van Herreweghen" initials="E." surname="Herreweghen"> </author>
          <date month="September" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Symposium on Research in Security and Privacy"
          value=", IPTS Report 67, 8-16"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DPD95">
        <front>
          <title>Directive 95/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 October 1995
            on the protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data and on
            the free movement of such data</title>
          <author>
            <organization>European Commission</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Official Journal L 281" value=", 23/11/1995 P. 0031 - 0050"/>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31995L0046:EN:HTML"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HBCC04">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy-Enhancing Identity Management</title>
          <author fullname="Marit Hansen" initials="M." surname="Hansen"> </author>
          <author fullname="Peter Berlich" initials="P." surname="Berlich"> </author>
          <author fullname="Jan Camenisch" initials="J." surname="Camenisch"> </author>
          <author fullname="Sebastian Clauss" initials="S." surname="Clauss"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Information Security Technical Report (ISTR)"
          value=", Volume 9, Issue 1, 67, 8-16, Elsevier, UK, 35-44"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1363-4127(04)00014-7"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Hild03">
        <front>
          <title>Same selves? Identification of identity: a social perspective from a
            legal-philosophical point of view</title>
          <author fullname="Mireille Hildebrandt" initials="M." surname="Hildebrandt"> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="Presentation at the the Future of IDentity in the Information Society (FIDIS) workshop"
          value=", http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/"/>
        <format type="PPT"
          target="http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/presentation/VUB/VUB_fidis_wp2_workshop_dec2003.ppt"
        />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ICPP03">
        <front>
          <title>Identity Management Systems (IMS): Identification and Comparison Study</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Independent Centre for Privacy Protection & Studio Notarile
            Genghini</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Study commissioned by the Joint Research Centre Seville, Spain"
          value=", http://www.datenschutzzentrum.de/projekte/idmanage/study.htm"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.datenschutzzentrum.de/projekte/idmanage/study.htm"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ISO99">
        <front>
          <title>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security Evaluation</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC 15408" value=""/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Mart99">
        <front>
          <title> Local Anonymity in the Internet</title>
          <author fullname="David Michael Martin" initials="D." surname="Martin"> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="PhD dissertation"
          value=", Boston University, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, http://www.cs.uml.edu/~dm/pubs/thesis.pdf"/>
        <format type="PDF" target="http://www.cs.uml.edu/~dm/pubs/thesis.pdf"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Mead34">
        <front>
          <title>Mind, Self and Society</title>
          <author fullname="George H. Mead" initials="G." surname="Mead"> </author>
          <date year="1934"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Chicago Press" value=""/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="Pfit96">
        <front>
          <title>Information Hiding Terminology -- Results of an informal plenary meeting and
            additional proposals</title>
          <author fullname="Birgit Pfitzmann" initials="B." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <date year="1996"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Information Hiding" value=", NCS 1174, Springer, Berlin 1996, 347-350"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="PfPW91">
        <front>
          <title>ISDN-MIXes -- Untraceable Communication with Very Small Bandwidth Overhead</title>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Birgit Pfitzmann" initials="B." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Michael Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="1991"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="7th IFIP International Conference on Information Security (IFIP/Sec '91)"
          value=", Elsevier, Amsterdam 1991, 245-258"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="PfWa86">
        <front>
          <title>Networks without user observability -- design options</title>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Michael Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="1986"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Eurocrypt '85"
          value=", LNCS 219, Springer, Berlin 1986, 245-253; revised and extended version in: Computers & Security 6/2 (1987) 158-166"
        />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="RaRD09">
        <front>
          <title>The Future of Identity in the Information Society - Challenges and Opportunities</title>
          <author fullname="Kai Rannenberg" initials="K." surname="Rannenberg"> </author>
          <author fullname="Denis Royer" initials="D." surname="Royer"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andre Deuker" initials="A." surname="Deuker"> </author>
          <date year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Springer, Berlin 2009." value=""/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="ReRu98">
        <front>
          <title>Crowds: Anonymity for Web Transactions</title>
          <author fullname="Michael K. Reiter" initials="M." surname="Reiter"> </author>
          <author fullname="Aviel D. Rubin" initials="A." surname="Rubin"> </author>
          <date month="November" year="1998"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM Transactions on Information and System Security" value=", 1(1), 66-92"
        />
      </reference>




      <reference anchor="Shan48">
        <front>
          <title>A Mathematical Theory of Communication</title>
          <author fullname="Claude E. Shannon" initials="C." surname="Shannon"> </author>
          <date year="1948"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="The Bell System Technical Journal" value=", 27, 379-423, 623-656"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="Shan49">
        <front>
          <title>Communication Theory of Secrecy Systems</title>
          <author fullname="Claude E. Shannon" initials="C." surname="Shannon"> </author>
          <date year="1949"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="The Bell System Technical Journal" value=", 28/4, 656-715"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="StSy00">
        <front>
          <title>Authentic Attributes with Fine-Grained Anonymity Protection</title>
          <author fullname="Stuart Stubblebine" initials="S." surname="Stubblebine"> </author>
          <author fullname="Paul Syverson" initials="P." surname="Syverson"> </author>

          <date year="2000"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Financial Cryptography" value=", LNCS Series, Springer, Berlin 2000"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="Waid90">
        <front>
          <title>Unconditional Sender and Recipient Untraceability in spite of Active Attacks</title>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="1990"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Eurocrypt '89" value=", LNCS 434, Springer, Berlin 1990, 302-319"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="West67">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy and Freedom</title>
          <author fullname="Alan F. Westin" initials="A." surname="Westin"> </author>
          <date year="1967"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Atheneum, New York" value=""/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Wils93">
        <front>
          <title>The Columbia Guide to Standard American English</title>
          <author fullname="Kenneth G. Wilson" initials="K." surname="Wilson"> </author>
          <date year="1993"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Columbia University Press, New York" value=""/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="ZFKP98">
        <front>
          <title>Modeling the security of steganographic systems</title>
          <author fullname="Jan Zoellner" initials="J." surname="Zoellner"> </author>
          <author fullname="Hannes Federrath" initials="H." surname="Federrath"> </author>
          <author fullname="Herbert Klimant" initials="H." surname="Klimant"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Rudi Piotraschke" initials="R." surname="Piotraschke"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Westfeld" initials="A." surname="Westfeld"> </author>
          <author fullname="Guntram Wicke" initials="G." surname="Wicke"> </author>
          <author fullname="Gritta Wolf" initials="G." surname="Wolf"> </author>
          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="2nd Workshop on Information Hiding"
          value=", LNCS 1525, Springer, Berlin 1998, 345-355"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="HoWi03">
        <front>
          <title>On the Ontology of Digital Identification</title>
          <author fullname="Giles Hogben" initials="G." surname="Hogben"> </author>
          <author fullname="Marc Wilikens" initials="M." surname="Wilikens"> </author>
          <author fullname="Ioannis Vakalis" initials="I." surname="Vakalis"> </author>
          <date year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=""
          value=", in: Robert Meersman, Zahir Tari (Eds.): On the Move to Meaningful
          Internet Systems 2003: OTM 2003 Workshops, LNCS 2889, Springer, Berlin 2003, 579-593"
        />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Chi03">
        <front>
          <title>Towards the Identity</title>
          <author fullname="David-Olivier Jaquet-Chiffelle" initials="D." surname="Jaquet-Chiffelle"> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="Presentation at the the Future of IDentity in the Information Society (FIDIS) workshop"
          value=", http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/"/>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/presentation/VIP/vip_id_def2_files/frame.htm"
        />
      </reference>


    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
<!-- 
      
      References to sub-sections
      
      1 Introduction - intro
      2 Setting - setting
      3 Anonymity - anonymity
      4 Unlinkability - unlinkability
      5 Anonymity in terms of unlinkability - ano-unlink
      6 Undetectability and unobservability - undect-unobs
      7 Relationships between terms - relationship
      8 Known mechanisms for anonymity, undetectability, and unobservability - known-mechs
      9 Pseudonymity - pseudonymity	
      10 Pseudonymity with respect to accountability and authorization - acc-authz
      11 Pseudonymity with respect to linkability - pseudo-link
      12 Known mechanisms and other properties of pseudonyms - known-other
      13 Identity management - idm
      14 Overview of main definitions and their negations - overview
      
-->
