<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
    "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    ]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-hansen-privacy-terminology-02.txt">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
  <?rfc compact="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Privacy Terminology">Terminology for Talking about Privacy by Data Minimization:
      Anonymity, Unlinkability, Undetectability, Unobservability, Pseudonymity, and Identity
      Management</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Hansen" fullname="Marit Hansen" role="editor">
      <organization>ULD Kiel</organization>
      <address>
            <email>marit.hansen@datenschutzzentrum.de</email>
          </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
            <postal>
              <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
              <city>Espoo</city>
              <code>02600</code>
              <country>Finland</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
            <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
            <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
          </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document is an attempt to consolidate terminology in the field privacy by data
        minimization. It motivates and develops definitions for anonymity/identifiability,
        (un)linkability, (un)detectability, (un)observability, pseudonymity, identity, partial
        identity, digital identity and identity management. Starting the definitions from the
        anonymity and unlinkability perspective reveals some deeper structures in this field.</t>
		<t>Note: This document is discussed at https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/ietf-privacy </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

      <t>Early papers from the 1980ies about privacy by data minimization already deal with
        anonymity, unlinkability, unobservability, and pseudonymity. These terms are often used in 
        discussions about privacy properties of systems.</t>
        
      <t>Data minimization means that first of all, the ability for others to collect personal data
            should be minimized. Often, however, the collection of personal data cannot not be prevented 
            entirely. In such a case, the goal is to minimize the collection of 
            personal data. The time how long collected personal data is
            stored should be minimized. </t>
      <t>Data minimization is the only generic strategy to enable anonymity, since all correct
            personal data help to identify if we exclude providing misinformation (inaccurate or
            erroneous information, provided usually without conscious effort at misleading,
            deceiving, or persuading one way or another) or disinformation
            (deliberately false or distorted information given out in order to mislead or deceive).</t>
      <t>Furthermore, data minimization is the only generic strategy to enable unlinkability,
            since all correct personal data provide some linkability if we exclude providing
            misinformation or disinformation.</t>
      <t>This document does not aim to collect all terms used in the area of privacy. 
        Even the definition of the term 'privacy' itself difficult due to the contextual nature of it; the understanding 
        of privacy has changed over time. For the purpose of this document we refer to one 
        fairly well established definition by Alan Westin from 1967 <xref target="West67"/>:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty"> 
         <t>"Privacy is the claim of individuals, groups, or institutions to
            determine for themselves when, how, and to what extent information about them is
            communicated to others. Viewed in terms of the relation of the individual to social
            participation, privacy is the voluntary and temporary withdrawal of a person from the
            general society through physical or psychological means, either in a state of solitude
            or small-group intimacy or, when among larger groups, in a condition of anonymity or
            reserve.", see page 7 of <xref target="West67"/>.
         </t>
        </list>
      </t>   
      </section>

    <!-- **************************************************************************************** -->
    <section anchor="anonymity" title="Anonymity">
      <t>To enable anonymity of a subject, there always has to be an appropriate set of subjects
        with potentially the same attributes.</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Anonymity of a subject means that the subject is not
            identifiable within a set of subjects, the anonymity set. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> "not identifiable within the anonymity set" means that only using the information the
            attacker has at his discretion, the subject is not distinguishable from the other subjects within the
            anonymity set. </t>
          <t>In order to 
           underline that there is a possibility to
        quantify anonymity for some applications (instead to treating it purely as a binary value it is possible to 
        use the following variation of the previous definition: "Anonymity of a subject from an attacker's perspective means
            that the attacker cannot sufficiently identify the subject within a set of subjects, the
            anonymity set." </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> The anonymity set is the set of all possible subjects. The set of possible subjects
        depends on the knowledge of the attacker. Thus, anonymity is relative with respect to the
        attacker. With respect to actors, the anonymity set consists of the subjects who might cause
        an action. With respect to actees, the anonymity set consists of the subjects who might be
        acted upon. Therefore, a sender may be anonymous (sender anonymity) only within a set of
        potential senders, his/her sender anonymity set, which itself may be a subset of all
        subjects who may send a message. The same for the recipient
        means that a recipient may be anonymous (recipient anonymity) only within a set of potential
        recipients, his/her recipient anonymity set. Both anonymity sets
        may be disjoint, be the same, or they may overlap. The anonymity sets may vary over time.
        Since we assume that the attacker does not forget anything he knows, the anonymity set
        cannot increase w.r.t. a particular IOI. Especially subjects joining the system in a later
        stage, do not belong to the anonymity set from the point of view of an attacker observing
        the system in an earlier stage. (Please note that if the attacker cannot decide whether the
        joining subjects were present earlier, the anonymity set does not increase either: It just
        stays the same.) Due to linkability, cf. below, the anonymity set normally can only
        decrease. </t>
      <t>Anonymity of a set of subjects within an anonymity set means that all
        these individual subjects are not identifiable within this anonymity set. In this
        definition, "set of subjects" is just taken to describe that the anonymity property holds
        for all elements of the set. Another possible definition would be to consider the anonymity
        property for the set as a whole. Then a semantically quite different definition could read:
        Anonymity of a set S of subjects within a larger anonymity set A means that it is not
        distinguishable whether the subject S whose anonymity is at stake (and which clearly is within
        A) is within S or not. </t>
      <t>Anonymity in general as well as the anonymity of
        each particular subject is a concept which is very much context dependent (on, e.g.,
        subjects population, attributes, time frame, etc). In order to quantify anonymity within
        concrete situations, one would have to describe the system in sufficient detail, which is
        practically not always possible for large open systems. Besides the quantity of anonymity provided within a particular setting,
        there is another aspect of anonymity: its robustness. Robustness of anonymity characterizes
        how stable the quantity of anonymity is against changes in the particular setting, e.g., a
        stronger attacker or different probability distributions. We might use quality of anonymity
        as a term comprising both quantity and robustness of anonymity. To keep this text as simple
        as possible, we will mainly discuss the quantity of anonymity in the following, using the
        wording "strength of anonymity". </t>
      <t> The above definitions of anonymity and the mentioned measures of quantifying anonymity are
        fine to characterize the status of a subject in a world as it is. If we want to describe
        changes to the anonymity of a subject if the world is changed somewhat, e.g., the subject
        uses the communication network differently or uses a modified communication network, we need
        another definition of anonymity capturing the delta. The simplest way to express this delta
        is by the observations of "the" attacker. </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> An anonymity delta (regarding a subject's anonymity) from an
            attacker's perspective specifies the difference between the subject's anonymity taking
            into account the attacker's observations (i.e., the attacker's a-posteriori knowledge)
            and the subject's anonymity given the attacker's a-priori knowledge only.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> In some publications, the a-priori knowledge of the attacker is called "background
            knowledge" and the a-posteriori knowledge of the attacker is called "new knowledge".
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t> As we can quantify anonymity in concrete situations, so we can quantify the anonymity
        delta. This can be done by just defining: quantity(anonymity delta) :=
        quantity(anonymity_a-posteriori) - quantity(anonymity_a-priori)</t>
        <t>If anonymity_a-posteriori
        and anonymity_a-priori are the same, their quantification is the same and therefore the
        difference of these quantifications is 0. If anonymity can only decrease (which usually is
        quite a reasonable assumption), the maximum of quantity(anonymity delta) is 0. </t>
      <t> Since anonymity cannot increase, the anonymity delta can never be positive. Having an
        anonymity delta of zero means that anonymity stays the same. This means that if the attacker
        has no a-priori knowledge about the particular subject, having no anonymity delta implies
        anonymity. But if the attacker has an a-priori knowledge covering all actions of the
        particular subject, having no anonymity delta does not imply any anonymity at all. If there
        is no anonymity from the very beginning, even preserving it completely does not yield any
        anonymity. To be able to express this conveniently, we use wordings like "perfect
        preservation of a subject's anonymity". It might be worthwhile to generalize "preservation
        of anonymity of single subjects" to "preservation of anonymity of sets of subjects", in the
        limiting case all subjects in an anonymity set. An important special case is that the "set
        of subjects" is the set of subjects having one or several attribute values A in common. Then
        the meaning of "preservation of anonymity of this set of subjects" is that knowing A does
        not decrease anonymity. Having a negative anonymity delta means that anonymity is decreased. </t>

    </section>
    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="unlinkability" title="Unlinkability">
           <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Unlinkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g.,
            subjects, messages, actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the
            system (comprising these and possibly other items), the attacker cannot sufficiently
            distinguish whether these IOIs are related or not.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Linkability is the negation of unlinkability: </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Linkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g.,
            subjects, messages, actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the
            system (comprising these and possibly other items), the attacker can sufficiently
            distinguish whether these IOIs are related or not.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> For example, in a scenario with at least two senders, two messages sent by subjects within
        the same anonymity set are unlinkable for an attacker if for him, the probability that these
        two messages are sent by the same sender is sufficiently close to 1/(number of senders).</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> An unlinkability delta of two or more items of interest (IOIs,
            e.g., subjects, messages, actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective specifies the
            difference between the unlinkability of these IOIs taking into account the attacker's
            observations and the unlinkability of these IOIs given the attacker's a-priori knowledge
            only. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> Since we assume that the attacker does not forget anything, unlinkability cannot increase.
        Normally, the attacker's knowledge cannot decrease (analogously to Shannon's definition of
        "perfect secrecy"). An exception of this rule is the scenario where the use of
        misinformation (inaccurate or erroneous information, provided usually without conscious
        effort at misleading, deceiving, or persuading one way or another <xref target="Wils93"/>)
        or disinformation (deliberately false or distorted information given out in order to mislead
        or deceive <xref target="Wils93"/>) leads to a growing uncertainty of the attacker which
        information is correct. A related, but different aspect is that information may become wrong
        (i.e., outdated) simply because the state of the world changes over time. Since privacy is
        not only about to protect the current state, but the past and history of a data subject as
        well, we will not make use of this different aspect in the rest of this document. Therefore,
        the unlinkability delta can never be positive. Having an unlinkability delta of zero means
        that the probability of those items being related from the attacker's perspective stays
        exactly the same before (a-priori knowledge) and after the attacker's observations
        (a-posteriori knowledge of the attacker). If the attacker has no a-priori knowledge about
        the particular IOIs, having an unlinkability delta of zero implies unlinkability. But if the
        attacker has a-priori knowledge covering the relationships of all IOIs, having an
        unlinkability delta of zero does not imply any unlinkability at all. If there is no
        unlinkability from the very beginning, even preserving it completely does not yield any
        unlinkability. To be able to express this conveniently, we use wordings like "perfect
        preservation of unlinkability w.r.t. specific items" to express that the unlinkability delta
        is zero. It might be worthwhile to generalize "preservation of unlinkability of two IOIs" to
        "preservation of unlinkability of sets of IOIs", in the limiting case all IOIs in the
        system. </t>

      <t> For example, the unlinkability delta of two messages is sufficiently small (zero) for an
        attacker if the probability describing his a-posteriori knowledge that these two messages
        are sent by the same sender and/or received by the same recipient is sufficiently (exactly)
        the same as the probability imposed by his a-priori knowledge. Please note that
        unlinkability of two (or more) messages of course may depend on whether their content is
        protected against the attacker considered. In particular, messages may be unlinkable if we
        assume that the attacker is not able to get information on the sender or recipient from the
        message content. Yet with access to their content even without
        deep semantical analysis the attacker can notice certain characteristics which link them
        together - e.g. similarities in structure, style, use of some words or phrases, consistent
        appearance of some grammatical errors, etc. In a sense, content of messages may play a role
        as "side channel" in a similar way as in cryptanalysis - i.e., content of messages may leak
        some information on their linkability. </t>
      <t>Roughly speaking, no unlinkability delta of items means that the ability of the attacker to
        relate these items does not increase by observing the system or by possibly interacting with
        it.</t>

      <t> The definitions of unlinkability, linkability and unlinkability delta do not mention any
        particular set of IOIs they are restricted to. Therefore, the definitions of unlinkability
        and unlinkability delta are very strong, since they cover the whole system. We could weaken
        the definitions by restricting them to part of the system: "Unlinkability of two or more
        IOIs from an attacker's perspective means that within an unlinkability set of IOIs
        (comprising these and possibly other items), the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish
        whether these IOIs are related or not." </t>

    </section>
    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="ano-unlink" title="Anonymity in Terms of Unlinkability">
      <t>To describe anonymity in terms of unlinkability, we have to augment the definitions of
        anonymity given in <xref target="anonymity"/> by making explicit the attributes anonymity
        relates to. For example, if we choose the attribute "having sent a message" then we can define:
        </t>

      <t> A sender s sends a set of messages M anonymously, iff s is anonymous within the set of
        potential senders of M, the sender anonymity set of M.</t>

      <t>If the attacker's focus is not on the sender, but on the message, we can define:</t>

      <t>A set of messages M is sent anonymously, iff M can have been sent by each set of potential
        senders, i.e., by any set of subjects within the cross product of the sender anonymity sets
        of each message m within M.</t>

      <t>When considering sending and
        receiving of messages as attributes, the items of interest (IOIs) are "who has sent or
        received which message", then, anonymity of a subject w.r.t. an attribute may be defined as
        unlinkability of this subject and this attribute. In the wording of the definition of unlinkability: 
		a subject s is related to the attribute value "has sent message m" if s has sent message m. s is not 
		related to that attribute value if s has not sent message m. Same for receiving.Unlinkability is a 
		sufficient condition of
        anonymity, but it is not a necessary condition. Thus, failing unlinkability w.r.t. some
        attribute value(s) does not necessarily eliminate anonymity as defined in <xref
          target="anonymity"/>; in specific cases (i.e., depending on the attribute value(s)) even
        the strength of anonymity may not be affected. </t>
      <t><list style="hanging"> 
      <t hangText="Definition:">
      Sender anonymity of a subject means that to this potentially sending subject,
        each message is unlinkable. </t>
      </list> 
      </t>
      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t> The property unlinkability might be more "fine-grained" than anonymity, since there
            are many more relations where unlinkability might be an issue than just the relation
            "anonymity" between subjects and IOIs. Therefore, the attacker might get to know
            information on linkability while not necessarily reducing anonymity of the particular
            subject - depending on the defined measures. An example might be that the attacker, in
            spite of being able to link, e.g., by timing, all encrypted messages of a transactions,
            does not learn who is doing this transaction. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Correspondingly, recipient anonymity of a subject means that to this potentially receiving
        subject, each message is unlinkable.</t>

      <t>Relationship anonymity of a pair of subjects, the potentially sending subject and the
        potentially receiving subject, means that to this potentially communicating pair of
        subjects, each message is unlinkable. In other words, sender and recipient (or each
        recipient in case of multicast) are unlinkable. As sender anonymity of a message cannot hold
        against the sender of this message himself nor can recipient anonymity hold against any of
        the recipients w.r.t. himself, relationship anonymity is considered w.r.t. outsiders only,
        i.e., attackers being neither the sender nor one of the recipients of the messages under
        consideration.</t>

      <t>Thus, relationship anonymity is a weaker property than each of sender anonymity and
        recipient anonymity: The attacker might know who sends which messages or he might know who
        receives which messages (and in some cases even who sends which messages and who receives
        which messages). But as long as for the attacker each message sent and each message received
        are unlinkable, he cannot link the respective senders to recipients and vice versa, i.e.,
        relationship anonymity holds. The relationship anonymity set can be defined to be the cross
        product of two potentially distinct sets, the set of potential senders and the set of
        potential recipients or - if it is possible to exclude some of these pairs - a subset of
        this cross product. So the relationship anonymity set is the set of all possible
        sender-recipient(s)-pairs. In case of multicast, the set of potential recipients is the
        power set of all potential recipients. If we take the perspective of a subject sending (or
        receiving) a particular message, the relationship anonymity set becomes the set of all
        potential recipients (senders) of that particular message. So fixing one factor of the cross
        product gives a recipient anonymity set or a sender anonymity set.</t>


      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>The following is an explanation of the statement made in the previous paragraph
            regarding relationship anonymity: For all attackers it holds that sender anonymity
            implies relationship anonymity, and recipient anonymity implies relationship anonymity.
            This is true if anonymity is taken as a binary property: Either it holds or it does not
            hold. If we consider quantities of anonymity, the validity of the implication possibly
            depends on the particular definitions of how to quantify sender anonymity and recipient
            anonymity on the one hand, and how to quantify relationship anonymity on the other.
            There exists at least one attacker model, where relationship anonymity does neither
            imply sender anonymity nor recipient anonymity. Consider an attacker who neither
            controls any senders nor any recipients of messages, but all lines and - maybe - some
            other stations. If w.r.t. this attacker relationship anonymity holds, you can neither
            argue that against him sender anonymity holds nor that recipient anonymity holds. The
            classical MIX-net <xref target="Chau81"/> without dummy traffic is one
            implementation with just this property: The attacker sees who sends messages when and
            who receives messages when, but cannot figure out who sends messages to whom. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="undect-unobs" title="Undetectability and Unobservability">
      <t>In contrast to anonymity and unlinkability, where not the IOI, but only its relationship to
        subjects or other IOIs is protected, for undetectability, the IOIs are protected as such.
        Undetectability can be regarded as a possible and desirable property of steganographic
        systems. Therefore it matches the information hiding
        terminology (see <xref target="Pfit96"/>, <xref target="ZFKP98"/>). In contrast, anonymity,
        dealing with the relationship of discernible IOIs to subjects, does not directly fit into
        that terminology, but independently represents a different dimension of properties.</t>


      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Undetectability of an item of interest (IOI) from an attacker's
            perspective means that the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish whether it exists or
            not.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>If we consider messages as IOIs, this means that messages are not sufficiently discernible
        from, e.g., "random noise". A slightly more precise formulation might be that messages are
        not discernible from no message. A quantification of this property might measure the number
        of indistinguishable IOIs and/or the probabilities of distinguishing these IOIs.</t>

      <t>Undetectability is maximal iff whether an IOI exists or not is completely
        indistinguishable. We call this perfect undetectability.</t>


      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> An undetectability delta of an item of interest (IOI) from an
            attacker's perspective specifies the difference between the undetectability of the IOI
            taking into account the attacker's observations and the undetectability of the IOI given
            the attacker's a-priori knowledge only. </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The undetectability delta is zero iff whether an IOI exists or not is indistinguishable to
        exactly the same degree whether the attacker takes his observations into account or not. We
        call this "perfect preservation of undetectability".</t>

      <t> Undetectability of an IOI clearly is only possible w.r.t. subjects being not involved in
        the IOI (i.e., neither being the sender nor one of the recipients of a message). Therefore,
        if we just speak about undetectability without spelling out a set of IOIs, it goes without
        saying that this is a statement comprising only those IOIs the attacker is not involved in.</t>

      <t> As the definition of undetectability stands, it has nothing to do with anonymity - it does
        not mention any relationship between IOIs and subjects. Even more, for subjects being
        involved in an IOI, undetectability of this IOI is clearly impossible. Therefore, early
        papers describing new mechanisms for undetectability designed the mechanisms in a way that
        if a subject necessarily could detect an IOI, the other subject(s) involved in that IOI
        enjoyed anonymity at least. The rational for this is to strive for data minimization: No
        subject should get to know any (potentially personal) data - except this is absolutely
        necessary. This means that 
        <list style="numbers">
        <t>Subjects
        being not involved in the IOI get to know absolutely nothing.</t>
        <t>Subjects being involved in
        the IOI only get to know the IOI, but not the other subjects involved - the other subjects
        may stay anonymous.</t>
        </list>
        The
        attributes "sending a message" or "receiving a message" are the only kinds of attributes
        considered, 1. and 2. together provide data minimization in this setting in an absolute
        sense. Undetectability by uninvolved subjects together with anonymity even if IOIs can
        necessarily be detected by the involved subjects has been called unobservability: </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> Unobservability of an item of interest (IOI) means <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>undetectability of the IOI against all subjects uninvolved in it and</t>
              <t>anonymity of the subject(s) involved in the IOI even against the other subject(s)
                involved in that IOI.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t> As we had anonymity sets of subjects with respect to anonymity, we have unobservability
        sets of subjects with respect to unobservability. Mainly,
        unobservability deals with IOIs instead of subjects only. Though, like anonymity sets,
        unobservability sets consist of all subjects who might possibly cause these IOIs, i.e. send
        and/or receive messages.</t>
      <t> Sender unobservability then means that it is sufficiently undetectable whether any sender
        within the unobservability set sends. Sender unobservability is perfect iff it is completely
        undetectable whether any sender within the unobservability set sends.</t>
      <t> Recipient unobservability then means that it is sufficiently undetectable whether any
        recipient within the unobservability set receives. Recipient unobservability is perfect iff
        it is completely undetectable whether any recipient within the unobservability set receives. </t>
      <t> Relationship unobservability then means that it is sufficiently undetectable whether
        anything is sent out of a set of could-be senders to a set of could-be recipients. In other
        words, it is sufficiently undetectable whether within the relationship unobservability set
        of all possible sender-recipient(s)-pairs, a message is sent in any relationship.
        Relationship unobservability is perfect iff it is completely undetectable whether anything
        is sent out of a set of could-be senders to a set of could-be recipients. </t>
      <t> All other things being equal, unobservability is the stronger, the larger the respective
        unobservability set is.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:">An unobservability delta of an item of interest (IOI) means
              <list style="symbols">
              <t>undetectability delta of the IOI against all subjects uninvolved in it and</t>
              <t>anonymity delta of the subject(s) involved in the IOI even against the other
                subject(s) involved in that IOI.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Since we assume that the attacker does not forget anything, unobservability cannot
        increase. Therefore, the unobservability delta can never be positive. Having an
        unobservability delta of zero w.r.t. an IOI means an undetectability delta of zero of the
        IOI against all subjects uninvolved in the IOI and an anonymity delta of zero against those
        subjects involved in the IOI. To be able to express this conveniently, we use wordings like
        "perfect preservation of unobservability" to express that the unobservability delta is zero.</t>

    </section>



    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

<!--
    <section anchor="known-mechs"
      title="Known Mechanisms for Anonymity, Undetectability, and Unobservability">

      <t>Before it makes sense to speak about any particular mechanisms for anonymity,
        undetectability, and unobservability in communications, let us first remark that all of them
        assume that stations of users do not emit signals the attacker considered is able to use for
        identification of stations or their behavior or even for identification of users or their
        behavior. So if you travel around taking with you a mobile phone sending more or less
        continuously signals to update its location information within a cellular radio network,
        don't be surprised if you are tracked using its signals. If you use a computer emitting lots
        of radiation due to a lack of shielding, don't be surprised if observers using high-tech
        equipment know quite a bit about what's happening within your machine. If you use a
        computer, PDA, or smartphone without sophisticated access control, don't be surprised if
        Trojan horses send your secrets to anybody interested whenever you are online - or via
        electromagnetic emanations even if you think you are completely offline.</t>

      <t>DC-net <xref target="Chau85"/>, <xref target="Chau88"/>, and MIX-net <xref target="Chau81"
        /> are mechanisms to achieve sender anonymity and relationship anonymity, respectively, both
        against strong attackers. If we add dummy traffic, both provide for the corresponding
        unobservability <xref target="PfPW91"/>. If dummy traffic is used to pad sending and/or
        receiving on the sender's and/or recipient's line to a constant rate traffic, MIX-nets can
        even provide sender and/or recipient anonymity and unobservability. </t>

      <t>Broadcast <xref target="Chau85"/>, <xref target="PfWa86"/>, <xref target="Waid90"/> and
        private information retrieval <xref target="CoBi95"/> are mechanisms to achieve recipient
        anonymity against strong attackers. If we add dummy traffic, both provide for recipient
        unobservability.</t>
      <t> This may be summarized: A mechanism to achieve some kind of anonymity appropriately
        combined with dummy traffic yields the corresponding kind of unobservability.</t>
      <t> Of course, dummy traffic alone can be used to make the number and/or length of sent
        messages undetectable by everybody except for the recipients; respectively, dummy traffic
        can be used to make the number and/or length of received messages undetectable by everybody
        except for the senders. (Note: Misinformation and disinformation may be regarded as semantic
        dummy traffic, i.e., communication from which an attacker cannot decide which are real
        requests with real data or which are fake ones. Assuming the authenticity of misinformation
        or disinformation may lead to privacy problems for (innocent) bystanders.) </t>
      <t>As a side remark, we mention steganography and spread spectrum as two other well-known
        undetectability mechanisms.</t>
      <t> The usual concept to achieve undetectability of IOIs at some layer, e.g., sending
        meaningful messages, is to achieve statistical independence of all discernible phenomena at
        some lower implementation layer. An example is sending dummy messages at some lower layer to
        achieve, e.g., a constant rate flow of messages looking - by means of encryption - randomly
        for all parties except the sender and the recipient(s). </t>
    </section>

--> 
    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
    -->

    <section anchor="pseudonymity" title="Pseudonymity">

      <t>Having anonymity of human beings, unlinkability, and maybe unobservability is superb w.r.t.
        data minimization, but would prevent any useful two-way communication. For many
        applications, we need appropriate kinds of identifiers: </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:">A pseudonym is an identifier of a subject other than one of the
            subject's real names.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>An identifier is defined in <xref target="id"/> as "a lexical token that names entities".</t>
          <t>In our setting 'subject' means sender or recipient.</t>
          <t>The term 'real name' is the antonym to "pseudonym". There may be multiple real names
            over lifetime, in particular the legal names, i.e., for a human being the names which
            appear on the birth certificate or on other official identity documents issued by the
            State; for a legal person the name under which it operates and which is registered in
            official registers (e.g., commercial register or register of associations). A human
            being's real name typically comprises their given name and a family name. In the realm
            of identifiers, it is tempting to define anonymity as "the attacker cannot sufficiently
            determine a real name of the subject". But despite the simplicity of this definition, it
            is severely restricted: It can only deal with subjects which have at least one real
            name. It presumes that it is clear who is authorized to attach real names to subjects.
            It fails to work if the relation to real names is irrelevant for the application at
            hand. Therefore, we stick to the definitions given in <xref target="anonymity"/>.
            <!-- A slightly broader discussion of this topic is given in Appendix A3. --> Note that
            from a mere technological perspective it cannot always be determined whether an
            identifier of a subject is a pseudonym or a real name.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Additional useful terms are:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:"> The subject which the pseudonym refers to is the holder of the
              pseudonym.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
          <t hangText="Definition:">A subject is pseudonymous if a pseudonym is used as identifier
            instead of one of its real names.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Definition:">Pseudonymity is the use of pseudonyms as identifiers.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

        <t>So sender pseudonymity is defined as the sender being pseudonymous, recipient pseudonymity
        is defined as the recipient being pseudonymous.</t>

        <t>In order to be useful in the context of Internet communication we use the term digital pseudonym
        and declare it as a pseudonym that is suitable to be used to authenticate the holder's IOIs.</t>

        <t>Defining the process of preparing for the use of pseudonyms, e.g., by establishing certain
        rules how and under which conditions civil identities of holders of pseudonyms will be disclosed 
        by so-called identity brokers or how to prevent uncovered claims by so-called liability brokers, 
        leads to the more general notion of pseudonymity, as defined below. </t>
      
        <t>Note:<list style="empty">
          <t>Identity brokers have for the pseudonyms they are the identity broker for the
            information who is their respective holder. Therefore, identity brokers can be
            implemented as a special kind of certification authorities for pseudonyms. Since
            anonymity can be described as a particular kind of unlinkability, cf. <xref
              target="ano-unlink"/>, the concept of identity broker can be generalized to
            linkability broker. A linkability broker is a (trusted) third party that, adhering to
            agreed rules, enables linking IOIs for those entities being entitled to get to know the
            linking.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>To authenticate IOIs relative to pseudonyms usually is not enough to achieve
          accountability for IOIs. </t>
        <t>Therefore, in many situations, it might make sense to let identity brokers authenticate 
        digital pseudonyms (i.e., check the civil identity
              of the holder of the pseudonym and then issue a digitally signed statement that this
              particular identity broker has proof of the identity of the holder of this digital
              pseudonym and is willing to divulge that proof under well-defined circumstances) or
           both.</t>
        <t>Note:<list style="empty">
            <t>If the holder of the pseudonym is a natural person or a legal person, civil identity
              has the usual meaning, i.e. the identity attributed to that person by a State
              (e.g., a natural person being represented by the social security number or the combination of name, date of
              birth, and location of birth etc.). If the holder is, e.g., a computer, it remains to
              be defined what "civil identity" should mean. It could mean, for example, exact type
              and serial number of the computer (or essential components of it) or even include the
              natural person or legal person responsible for its operation.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>If the digitally
          signed statement of a trusted identity broker is checked before entering into a
          transaction with the holder of that pseudonym, accountability can be realized in spite of
          anonymity.</t>

      <t>Whereas anonymity and accountability are the extremes with respect to linkability to
        subjects, pseudonymity is the entire field between and including these extremes. Thus,
        pseudonymity comprises all degrees of linkability to a subject. Ongoing use of the same
        pseudonym allows the holder to establish or consolidate a reputation. Establishing and/or
        consolidating a reputation under a pseudonym is, of course, insecure if the pseudonym does
        not enable to authenticate messages, i.e., if the pseudonym is not a digital pseudonym. 
        Then, at any moment, another subject might use this pseudonym
        possibly invalidating the reputation, both for the holder of the pseudonym and all others
        having to do with this pseudonym. Some kinds of pseudonyms enable dealing with claims in
        case of abuse of unlinkability to holders: Firstly, third parties (identity brokers) may 
        have the possibility to reveal the civil identity of the
        holder in order to provide means for investigation or prosecution. To improve the robustness
        of anonymity, chains of identity brokers may be used <xref target="Chau81"/>. Secondly,
        third parties may act as liability brokers of the holder to clear a debt or settle a claim.
          <xref target="BuPf90"/> presents the particular case of value brokers.</t>

      <t>There are many properties of pseudonyms which may be of importance in specific application
        contexts. In order to describe the properties of pseudonyms with respect to anonymity, we
        limit our view to two aspects and give some typical examples:</t>

        <t>The knowledge of the linking may not be a constant, but change over time for some or even
          all people. Normally, for non-transferable pseudonyms the knowledge of the linking cannot
          decrease (with the exception of misinformation or disinformation, which may blur the
          attacker's knowledge.). Typical kinds of such pseudonyms are:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="Public Pseudonym:"> The linking between a public pseudonym and its holder
              may be publicly known even from the very beginning. E.g., the linking could be listed
              in public directories such as the entry of a phone number in combination with its
              owner. </t>

            <t hangText="Initially non-Public Pseudonym:"> The linking between an initially
              non-public pseudonym and its holder may be known by certain parties, but is not public
              at least initially. E.g., a bank account where the bank can look up the linking may
              serve as a non-public pseudonym. For some specific non-public pseudonyms,
              certification authorities acting as identity brokers could reveal the civil identity
              of the holder in case of abuse.</t>

            <t hangText="Initially Unlinked Pseudonym:"> The linking between an initially unlinked
              pseudonym and its holder is - at least initially - not known to anybody with the
              possible exception of the holder himself/herself. Examples for unlinked pseudonyms are
              (non-public) biometrics like DNA information unless stored in databases including the
              linking to the holders.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>Public pseudonyms and initially unlinked pseudonyms can be seen as extremes of the
          described pseudonym aspect whereas initially non-public pseudonyms characterize the
          continuum in between.</t>

        <t>Anonymity is the stronger, the less is known about the linking to a subject. The strength
          of anonymity decreases with increasing knowledge of the pseudonym linking. In particular,
          under the assumption that no gained knowledge on the linking of a pseudonym will be
          forgotten and that the pseudonym cannot be transferred to other subjects, a public
          pseudonym never can become an unlinked pseudonym. In each specific case, the strength of
          anonymity depends on the knowledge of certain parties about the linking relative to the
          chosen attacker model.</t>

        <t>If the pseudonym is transferable, the linking to its holder can change. Considering an
          unobserved transfer of a pseudonym to another subject, a formerly public pseudonym can
          become non-public again.</t>


        <t>With respect to the degree of linkability, various kinds of pseudonyms may be
          distinguished according to the kind of context for their usage:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Person pseudonym:"> A person pseudonym is a substitute for the holder's
              name which is regarded as representation for the holder's civil identity. It may be
              used in many different contexts, e.g., a number of an identity card, the social
              security number, DNA, a nickname, the pseudonym of an actor, or a mobile phone number.</t>

            <t hangText="Role pseudonym:"> The use of role pseudonyms is limited to specific roles,
              e.g., a customer pseudonym or an Internet account used for many instantiations of the
              same role "Internet user". The same role pseudonym may be used with
              different communication partners. Roles might be assigned by other parties, e.g., a
              company, but they might be chosen by the subject himself/herself as well.</t>

            <t hangText="Relationship pseudonym:"> For each communication partner, a different
              relationship pseudonym is used. The same relationship pseudonym may be used in
              different roles for communicating with the same partner. Examples are distinct
              nicknames for each communication partner. In case of group communication, the
              relationship pseudonyms may be used between more than two partners. </t>

            <t hangText="Role-relationship pseudonym:"> For each role and for each communication
              partner, a different role-relationship pseudonym is used. This means that the
              communication partner does not necessarily know, whether two pseudonyms used in
              different roles belong to the same holder. On the other hand, two different
              communication partners who interact with a user in the same role, do not know from the
              pseudonym alone whether it is the same user. As with relationship pseudonyms, in case
              of group communication, the role-relationship pseudonyms may be used between more than
              two partners.</t>

            <t hangText="Transaction pseudonym:"> Apart from "transaction pseudonym" some employ the
              term "one-time-use pseudonym", taking the naming from "one-time pad". For each
              transaction, a transaction pseudonym unlinkable to any other transaction pseudonyms
              and at least initially unlinkable to any other IOI is used, e.g., randomly generated
              transaction numbers for online-banking. Therefore, transaction pseudonyms can be used
              to realize as strong anonymity as possible. In fact, the strongest anonymity is given
              when there is no identifying information at all, i.e., information that would allow
              linking of anonymous entities, thus transforming the anonymous transaction into a
              pseudonymous one. If the transaction pseudonym is used exactly once, we have the same
              strength of anonymity as if no pseudonym is used at all. Another possibility to
              achieve strong anonymity is to prove the holdership of the pseudonym or specific
              attribute values (e.g., with zero-knowledge proofs) without revealing the information
              about the pseudonym or more detailed attribute values themselves. Then, no
              identifiable or linkable information is disclosed. </t>
          </list>
        </t>


      <t>Linkability across different contexts due to the use of these pseudonyms can be represented
        as the lattice that is illustrated in the following diagram, see <xref target="fig8"/>. The
        arrows point in direction of increasing unlinkability, i.e., A -> B stands for "B enables
        stronger unlinkability than A". Note that "->" is not the same as "=>" of <xref
          target="relationship"/>, which stands for the implication concerning anonymity and
        unobservability. </t>

      <t>
        <figure anchor="fig8"
          title="Lattice of pseudonyms according to their use across different contexts">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                                          linkable

                                      +-----------------+  *
            Person                    |                 |  *
          / Pseudonym \                |   decreasing  |  *
        //             \\              |   linkability |  *
       /                 \             |    across    |  *
      /                   \-+           |  contexts   |  *
   +-/                      v           |            |   *
   v Role               Relationship    |            |  *
Pseudonym               Pseudonym        |           |  *
    --                     --            |          |  *
      --                ---              |          |  *
        ---         ----                  |        |   *
           --+  +---                      |        |  *
             v  v                          |      |   *
         Role-Relationship                 |      |  |*
         Pseudonym                         |     |   *
              |                             |    |   *
              |                             |    |  *
              |                             |   |   *
              |                              |  |   *
              |                              | |   *
              v                              | |   *
         Transaction                          |   *
         Pseudonym                            |   v

                                                 unlinkable
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>In general, unlinkability of both role pseudonyms and relationship pseudonyms is stronger
        than unlinkability of person pseudonyms. The strength of unlinkability increases with the
        application of role-relationship pseudonyms, the use of which is restricted to both the same
        role and the same relationship. If a role-relationship pseudonym is used for roles
        comprising many kinds of activities, the danger arises that after a while, it becomes a
        person pseudonym in the sense of: "A person pseudonym is a substitute for the holder's name
        which is regarded as representation for the holder's civil identity." This is even more true
        both for role pseudonyms and relationship pseudonyms. Ultimate strength of unlinkability is
        obtained with transaction pseudonyms, provided that no other information, e.g., from the
        context or from the pseudonym itself, enabling linking is available.</t>

      <t>Anonymity is the stronger, ... <list style="symbols">
          <t> the less personal data of the pseudonym holder can be linked to the pseudonym;</t>
          <t> the less often and the less context-spanning pseudonyms are used and therefore the
            less data about the holder can be linked;</t>
          <t> the more often independently chosen, i.e., from an observer's perspective unlinkable,
            pseudonyms are used for new actions.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>The amount of information of linked data can be reduced by different subjects using the
        same pseudonym (e.g., one after the other when pseudonyms are transferred or simultaneously
        with specifically created group pseudonyms) or by misinformation or disinformation. The
        group of pseudonym holders acts as an inner anonymity set within a, depending on context
        information, potentially even larger outer anonymity set.</t>

    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

<!-- 
    <section anchor="known-other" title="Known mechanisms and other properties of pseudonyms">
      <t>A digital pseudonym could be realized as a public key to test digital signatures where the
        holder of the pseudonym can prove holdership by forming a digital signature which is created
        using the corresponding private key <xref target="Chau81"/>. The most prominent example for
        digital pseudonyms are public keys generated by the user himself/herself, e.g., using PGP.
        In using PGP, each user may create an unlimited number of key pairs by himself/herself (at
        this moment, such a key pair is an initially unlinked pseudonym), bind each of them to an
        e-mail address, self-certify each public key by using his/her digital signature or asking
        another introducer to do so, and circulate it.</t>

      <t>A public key certificate bears a digital signature of a so-called certification authority
        and provides some assurance to the binding of a public key to another pseudonym, usually
        held by the same subject. In case that pseudonym is the civil identity (the real name) of a
        subject, such a certificate is called an identity certificate. An attribute certificate is a
        digital certificate which contains further information (attribute values) and clearly refers
        to a specific public key certificate. Independent of certificates, attributes may be used as
        identifiers of sets of subjects as well. Normally, attributes refer to sets of subjects
        (i.e., the anonymity set), not to one specific subject.</t>

      <t>There are several other properties of pseudonyms related to their use, such as revocation, 
         lifetime of the pseudonym, non-transferability, frequency of pseudonym changeover, the 
         ability to reveal civil identities in case of abuse, etc. Some of the properties may require 
         extension of the digital pseudonym by attributes of some kind. The binding of attributes to 
         a pseudonym can be documented in an attribute certificate produced either by the holder 
         himself/herself or by a certification authority.
      </t>
    </section>
--> 
    

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="idm" title="Identity Management">


        <t> Identity can be explained as an exclusive perception of life, integration into a social
          group, and continuity, which is bound to a body and - at least to some degree - shaped by
          society. This concept of identity distinguishes between "I" and "Me" <xref target="Mead34"
          /> : "I" is the instance that is accessible only by the individual self, perceived as an
          instance of liberty and initiative. "Me" is supposed to stand for the social attributes,
          defining a human identity that is accessible by communications and that is an inner
          instance of control and consistency (see <xref target="ICPP03"/> for more information). In
          this terminology, we are interested in identity as communicated to others and seen by
          them. Therefore, we concentrate on the "Me".</t>

        <t> Motivated by identity as an exclusive perception of life, i.e., a psychological
          perspective, but using terms defined from a computer science, i.e., a mathematical
          perspective (as we did in the sections before), identity can be explained and defined as a
          property of an entity in terms of the opposite of anonymity and the opposite of
          unlinkability. In a positive wording, identity enables both to be identifiable as well as
          to link IOIs because of some continuity of life. Here we have the opposite of anonymity
          (identifiability) and the opposite of unlinkability (linkability) as positive properties.
          So the perspective changes: What is the aim of an attacker w.r.t. anonymity, now is the
          aim of the subject under consideration, so the attacker's perspective becomes the
          perspective of the subject. And again, another attacker (attacker2) might be considered
          working against identifiability and/or linkability. I.e., attacker2 might try to mask
          different attributes of subjects to provide for some kind of anonymity or attacker2 might
          spoof some messages to interfere with the continuity of the subject's life.</t>
<!--        <t> Corresponding to the anonymity set introduced in the beginning of this text, we can work
          with an "identifiability set" <xref target="Hild03"/>, which is the set is a set of
          possible subjects, to define "identifiability" and "identity". This definition is
          compatible with the definitions given in <xref target="HoWi03"/> and it is very close to
          that given by <xref target="Chi03"/>: "An identity is any subset of attributes of a person
          which uniquely characterizes this person within a community." </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Definition:">Identifiability of a subject from an attacker's perspective
              means that the attacker can sufficiently identify the subject within a set of
              subjects, the identifiability set.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
-->        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Definition:">An identity is any subset of attribute values of an individual
              person which sufficiently identifies this individual person within any set of persons.
              So usually there is no such thing as "the identity", but several of them.</t>
            
            <t hangText="Definition:"> Identity management means managing various 
              identities (usually denoted by pseudonyms) of an individual person, i.e.,
              administration of identity attributes including the development and choice of the
              partial identity and pseudonym to be (re-)used in a specific context or role.
              Establishment of reputation is possible when the individual person re-uses partial
              identities. A prerequisite to choose the appropriate partial identity is to recognize
              the situation the person is acting in. </t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t> Of course, attribute values or even attributes themselves may change over time.
          Therefore, if the attacker has no access to the change history of each particular
          attribute, the fact whether a particular subset of attribute values of an individual
          person is an identity or not may change over time as well. If the attacker has access to
          the change history of each particular attribute, any subset forming an identity will form
          an identity from his perspective irrespective how attribute values change. Any reasonable
          attacker will not just try to figure out attribute values per se, but the point in time
          (or even the time frame) they are valid (in), since this change history helps a lot in
          linking and thus inferring further attribute values. Therefore, it may clarify one's mind
          to define each "attribute" in a way that its value cannot get invalid. So instead of the
          attribute "location" of a particular individual person, take the set of attributes
          "location at time x". Depending on the inferences you are interested in, refining that set
          as a list ordered concerning "location" or "time" may be helpful. </t>
        <t> Identities may of course comprise particular attribute values like names, identifiers,
          digital pseudonyms, and addresses - but they don't have to. </t>
          
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="contributor" title="Contributors">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Andreas Pfitzmann for all his work on this document.</t>
    </section> 

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Before this document was submitted to the IETF it already had a long history starting at
        2000 and a number of people helped to improve the quality of the document with their
        feedback. A number of persons contributed to the original writeup and they are acknowledged in
        http://dud.inf.tu-dresden.de/Anon_Terminology.shtml. 
      </t>   
    </section>

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document introduces terminology for talking about privacy by data minimization. Since 
      privacy protection relies on security mechanisms this document is also related to security 
      in a broader context.</t>
    </section> 

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section> 

    <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="BuPf90">
        <front>
          <title>Value Exchange Systems Enabling Security and Unobservability</title>
          <author fullname="Holger Buerk" initials="H." surname="Buerk"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <date month="January" year="1990"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Computers & Security" value=", 9/8, 715-721"/>
      </reference>

<!--       <reference anchor="CaLy04">
        <front>
          <title>Signature Schemes and Anonymous Credentials from Bilinear Maps</title>
          <author fullname="Jan Camenisch" initials="J." surname="Camenisch"> </author>
          <author fullname="Anna Lysyanskaya" initials="A." surname="Lysyanskaya"> </author>
          <date year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Crypto" value=", LNCS 3152, Springer, Berlin 2004, 56-72"/>
      </reference>

--> 

      <reference anchor="Chau81">
        <front>
          <title>Untraceable Electronic Mail, Return Addresses, and Digital Pseudonyms</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1981"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Communications of the ACM" value=", 24/2, 84-88"/>
      </reference>

<!--       <reference anchor="Chau85">
        <front>
          <title>Security without Identification: Transaction Systems to make Big Brother Obsolete</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1985"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Communications of the ACM" value=", 28/10, 1030-1044"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chau88">
        <front>
          <title>The Dining Cryptographers Problem: Unconditional Sender and Recipient
            Untraceability</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1988"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Journal of Cryptology" value=", 1/1, 65-75"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chau90">
        <front>
          <title>Showing credentials without identification: Transferring signatures between
            unconditionally unlinkable pseudonyms</title>
          <author fullname="David Chaum" initials="D." surname="Chaum"> </author>
          <date year="1990"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Auscrypt" value=", LNCS 453, Springer, Berlin 1990, 246-264"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="ClSc06">
        <front>
          <title>Structuring Anonymity Metrics</title>
          <author fullname="Sebastian Clauss" initials="S." surname="Clauss"> </author>
          <author fullname="Stefan Schiffner" initials="S." surname="Schiffner"> </author>
          <date year="2006"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=""
          value="in A. Goto (Ed.), DIM '06, Proceedings of the 2006 ACM Workshop on Digital Identity Management, Fairfax, USA, Nov. 2006, 55-62"
        />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CoBi95">
        <front>
          <title>Preserving Privacy in a Network of Mobile Computers</title>
          <author fullname="David A. Cooper" initials="D." surname="Cooper"> </author>
          <author fullname="Kenneth P. Birm" initials="K." surname="Birm"> </author>
          <date year="1995"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Symposium on Research in Security and Privacy"
          value=", IEEE Computer Society Press, Los Alamitos 1995, 26-38"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CPHH02">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy-Enhancing Identity Management</title>
          <author fullname="Sebastian Clauss" initials="S." surname="Clauss"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Marit Hansen" initials="M." surname="Hansen"> </author>
          <author fullname="Els Van Herreweghen" initials="E." surname="Herreweghen"> </author>
          <date month="September" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Symposium on Research in Security and Privacy"
          value=", IPTS Report 67, 8-16"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="DPD95">
        <front>
          <title>Directive 95/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 October 1995
            on the protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data and on
            the free movement of such data</title>
          <author>
            <organization>European Commission</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Official Journal L 281" value=", 23/11/1995 P. 0031 - 0050"/>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31995L0046:EN:HTML"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="HBCC04">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy-Enhancing Identity Management</title>
          <author fullname="Marit Hansen" initials="M." surname="Hansen"> </author>
          <author fullname="Peter Berlich" initials="P." surname="Berlich"> </author>
          <author fullname="Jan Camenisch" initials="J." surname="Camenisch"> </author>
          <author fullname="Sebastian Clauss" initials="S." surname="Clauss"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Information Security Technical Report (ISTR)"
          value=", Volume 9, Issue 1, 67, 8-16, Elsevier, UK, 35-44"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1363-4127(04)00014-7"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Hild03">
        <front>
          <title>Same selves? Identification of identity: a social perspective from a
            legal-philosophical point of view</title>
          <author fullname="Mireille Hildebrandt" initials="M." surname="Hildebrandt"> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="Presentation at the the Future of IDentity in the Information Society (FIDIS) workshop"
          value=", http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/"/>
        <format type="PPT"
          target="http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/presentation/VUB/VUB_fidis_wp2_workshop_dec2003.ppt"
        />
      </reference>
--> 

      <reference anchor="ICPP03">
        <front>
          <title>Identity Management Systems (IMS): Identification and Comparison Study</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Independent Centre for Privacy Protection & Studio Notarile
            Genghini</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Study commissioned by the Joint Research Centre Seville, Spain"
          value=", http://www.datenschutzzentrum.de/projekte/idmanage/study.htm"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.datenschutzzentrum.de/projekte/idmanage/study.htm"/>
      </reference>

<!-- 
      <reference anchor="ISO99">
        <front>
          <title>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security Evaluation</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ISO</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC 15408" value=""/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Mart99">
        <front>
          <title> Local Anonymity in the Internet</title>
          <author fullname="David Michael Martin" initials="D." surname="Martin"> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="PhD dissertation"
          value=", Boston University, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, http://www.cs.uml.edu/~dm/pubs/thesis.pdf"/>
        <format type="PDF" target="http://www.cs.uml.edu/~dm/pubs/thesis.pdf"/>
      </reference>

--> 


      <reference anchor="Mead34">
        <front>
          <title>Mind, Self and Society</title>
          <author fullname="George H. Mead" initials="G." surname="Mead"> </author>
          <date year="1934"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Chicago Press" value=""/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="Pfit96">
        <front>
          <title>Information Hiding Terminology -- Results of an informal plenary meeting and
            additional proposals</title>
          <author fullname="Birgit Pfitzmann" initials="B." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <date year="1996"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Information Hiding" value=", NCS 1174, Springer, Berlin 1996, 347-350"/>
      </reference>


<!-- 
      <reference anchor="PfPW91">
        <front>
          <title>ISDN-MIXes -- Untraceable Communication with Very Small Bandwidth Overhead</title>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Birgit Pfitzmann" initials="B." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Michael Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="1991"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="7th IFIP International Conference on Information Security (IFIP/Sec '91)"
          value=", Elsevier, Amsterdam 1991, 245-258"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="PfWa86">
        <front>
          <title>Networks without user observability -- design options</title>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Michael Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="1986"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Eurocrypt '85"
          value=", LNCS 219, Springer, Berlin 1986, 245-253; revised and extended version in: Computers & Security 6/2 (1987) 158-166"
        />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RaRD09">
        <front>
          <title>The Future of Identity in the Information Society - Challenges and Opportunities</title>
          <author fullname="Kai Rannenberg" initials="K." surname="Rannenberg"> </author>
          <author fullname="Denis Royer" initials="D." surname="Royer"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andre Deuker" initials="A." surname="Deuker"> </author>
          <date year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Springer, Berlin 2009." value=""/>
      </reference>

--> 


      <reference anchor="ReRu98">
        <front>
          <title>Crowds: Anonymity for Web Transactions</title>
          <author fullname="Michael K. Reiter" initials="M." surname="Reiter"> </author>
          <author fullname="Aviel D. Rubin" initials="A." surname="Rubin"> </author>
          <date month="November" year="1998"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM Transactions on Information and System Security" value=", 1(1), 66-92"
        />
      </reference>


<!-- 

      <reference anchor="Shan48">
        <front>
          <title>A Mathematical Theory of Communication</title>
          <author fullname="Claude E. Shannon" initials="C." surname="Shannon"> </author>
          <date year="1948"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="The Bell System Technical Journal" value=", 27, 379-423, 623-656"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="Shan49">
        <front>
          <title>Communication Theory of Secrecy Systems</title>
          <author fullname="Claude E. Shannon" initials="C." surname="Shannon"> </author>
          <date year="1949"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="The Bell System Technical Journal" value=", 28/4, 656-715"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="StSy00">
        <front>
          <title>Authentic Attributes with Fine-Grained Anonymity Protection</title>
          <author fullname="Stuart Stubblebine" initials="S." surname="Stubblebine"> </author>
          <author fullname="Paul Syverson" initials="P." surname="Syverson"> </author>

          <date year="2000"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Financial Cryptography" value=", LNCS Series, Springer, Berlin 2000"/>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="Waid90">
        <front>
          <title>Unconditional Sender and Recipient Untraceability in spite of Active Attacks</title>
          <author fullname="Michael Waidner" initials="M." surname="Waidner"> </author>
          <date year="1990"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Eurocrypt '89" value=", LNCS 434, Springer, Berlin 1990, 302-319"/>
      </reference>

-->
      <reference anchor="West67">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy and Freedom</title>
          <author fullname="Alan F. Westin" initials="A." surname="Westin"> </author>
          <date year="1967"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Atheneum, New York" value=""/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="id">
        <front>
          <title>Identifier - Wikipeadia</title>
          <author/>
          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Wikipedia" value=""/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Identifier"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Wils93">
        <front>
          <title>The Columbia Guide to Standard American English</title>
          <author fullname="Kenneth G. Wilson" initials="K." surname="Wilson"> </author>
          <date year="1993"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Columbia University Press, New York" value=""/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="ZFKP98">
        <front>
          <title>Modeling the security of steganographic systems</title>
          <author fullname="Jan Zoellner" initials="J." surname="Zoellner"> </author>
          <author fullname="Hannes Federrath" initials="H." surname="Federrath"> </author>
          <author fullname="Herbert Klimant" initials="H." surname="Klimant"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Pfitzmann" initials="A." surname="Pfitzmann"> </author>
          <author fullname="Rudi Piotraschke" initials="R." surname="Piotraschke"> </author>
          <author fullname="Andreas Westfeld" initials="A." surname="Westfeld"> </author>
          <author fullname="Guntram Wicke" initials="G." surname="Wicke"> </author>
          <author fullname="Gritta Wolf" initials="G." surname="Wolf"> </author>
          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="2nd Workshop on Information Hiding"
          value=", LNCS 1525, Springer, Berlin 1998, 345-355"/>
      </reference>



<!--       <reference anchor="HoWi03">
        <front>
          <title>On the Ontology of Digital Identification</title>
          <author fullname="Giles Hogben" initials="G." surname="Hogben"> </author>
          <author fullname="Marc Wilikens" initials="M." surname="Wilikens"> </author>
          <author fullname="Ioannis Vakalis" initials="I." surname="Vakalis"> </author>
          <date year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=""
          value=", in: Robert Meersman, Zahir Tari (Eds.): On the Move to Meaningful
          Internet Systems 2003: OTM 2003 Workshops, LNCS 2889, Springer, Berlin 2003, 579-593"
        />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="Chi03">
        <front>
          <title>Towards the Identity</title>
          <author fullname="David-Olivier Jaquet-Chiffelle" initials="D." surname="Jaquet-Chiffelle"> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="Presentation at the the Future of IDentity in the Information Society (FIDIS) workshop"
          value=", http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/"/>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://www.calt.insead.edu/fidis/workshop/workshop-wp2-december2003/presentation/VIP/vip_id_def2_files/frame.htm"
        />
      </reference>

--> 

    </references>



    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview of Main Definitions and their Opposites">

      <t>
        <texttable>

          <ttcol>Definition</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Negation</ttcol>

          <c>Anonymity of a subject from an attacker's perspective means that the attacker cannot
            sufficiently identify the subject within a set of subjects, the anonymity set.</c>
          <c>Identifiability of a subject from an attacker's perspective means that the attacker can
            sufficiently identify the subject within a set of subjects, the identifiability set.</c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c>Unlinkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g., subjects, messages,
            actions, ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the system (comprising
            these and possibly other items), the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish whether
            these IOIs are related or not.</c>
          <c>Linkability of two or more items of interest (IOIs, e.g., subjects, messages, actions,
            ...) from an attacker's perspective means that within the system (comprising these and
            possibly other items), the attacker can sufficiently distinguish whether these IOIs are
            related or not.</c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c>Undetectability of an item of interest (IOI) from an attacker's perspective means that
            the attacker cannot sufficiently distinguish whether it exists or not.</c>
          <c>Detectability of an item of interest (IOI) from an attacker's perspective means that
            the attacker can sufficiently distinguish whether it exists or not.</c>
          <c> ------------------------------- </c>

          <c> ------------------------------- </c>
          <c>Unobservability of an item of interest (IOI) means <list style="symbols">
              <t>undetectability of the IOI against all subjects uninvolved in it and </t>
              <t>anonymity of the subject(s) involved in the IOI even against the other subject(s)
                involved in that IOI.</t>
            </list>
          </c>
          <c>Observability of an item of interest (IOI) means "many possibilities to define the
            semantics".</c>
        </texttable>
      </t>

    </section>
    
    
        <!--
          ****************************************************************************************
        -->
    <section anchor="relationship" title="Relationships between Terms">

      <t>With respect to the same attacker, unobservability reveals always only a subset of the
        information anonymity reveals. <xref target="ReRu98"/> propose a continuum for describing
        the strength of anonymity. They give names: "absolute privacy" (the attacker cannot perceive
        the presence of communication, i.e., unobservability) - "beyond suspicion" - "probable
        innocence" - "possible innocence" - "exposed" - "provably exposed" (the attacker can prove
        the sender, recipient, or their relationship to others). Although we think that the terms
        "privacy" and "innocence" are misleading, the spectrum is quite useful. We might use the
        shorthand notation </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>unobservability => anonymity</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> for that (=> reads "implies"). Using the same argument and notation, we have </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>sender unobservability => sender anonymity</t>
          <t>recipient unobservability => recipient anonymity</t>
          <t>relationship unobservability => relationship anonymity</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> As noted above, we have </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>sender anonymity => relationship anonymity</t>
          <t>recipient anonymity => relationship anonymity</t>
          <t>sender unobservability => relationship unobservability</t>
          <t>recipient unobservability => relationship unobservability</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> With respect to the same attacker, unobservability reveals always only a subset of the
        information undetectability reveals </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t> unobservability => undetectability</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
