<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN"
  "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3365 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3365.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4322 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6817 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6817.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6962 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6962.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.barnes-pervasive-problem SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.barnes-pervasive-problem.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.kent-opportunistic-security SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.kent-opportunistic-security.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.farrell-perpass-attack SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.farrell-perpass-attack.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4252 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4252.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
  href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/css' href='rfc2629.css' ?>

<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<!-- set to "no" to suppress the cref elements -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="1" ?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!-- Editorial issues are shown inline instead of collected at the end -->

<!-- The treatment of images isn't completely satisfactory. For the
online version on the STRINT Web site, things work OK: To distinguish
caption from credits, I used the preamble for the caption and the
postamble for the credits (see my script rfc2629-to-html.xslt). But it
would be nice if xml2rfc had a way to suppress the preamble and
postamble if the artwork cannot be shown... -->

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IAB"
  docName="draft-iab-strint-report-00">
  <front>
    <title>STRINT workshop report</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Farrell" fullname="Stephen Farrell">
      <organization>Trinity College, Dublin</organization>
      <address>
	<email>stephen.farrell@cs.tcd.ie</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Wenning" fullname="Rigo Wenning">
      <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>2004, route des Lucioles</street>
	  <street>B.P. 93</street>
	  <code>06902</code>
	  <city>Sophia-Antipolis</city>
	  <country>France</country>
	</postal>
	<email>rigo@w3.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Bos" fullname="Bert Bos">
      <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>2004, route des Lucioles</street>
	  <street>B.P. 93</street>
	  <code>06902</code>
	  <city>Sophia-Antipolis</city>
	  <country>France</country>
	</postal>
	<email>bert@w3org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

<author initials='M.' surname="Blanchet" fullname='Marc Blanchet'>
  <organization>Viagenie</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>246 Aberdeen</street>
      <city>Quebec</city>
      <region>QC</region>
      <code>G1R 2E1</code>
      <country>Canada</country>
    </postal>
    <email>Marc.Blanchet@viagenie.ca</email>
    <uri>http://viagenie.ca</uri>
  </address>
</author>

    <author initials="H.T." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig ">
      <organization>ARM Ltd.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>110 Fulbourn Rd</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <code> CB1 9NJ </code>
          <country>Great Britain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Hannes.tschofenig@gmx.net </email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/> <!-- day="21" month="March" year="2014" -->
    <area>Security</area>
    <!-- <workgroup></workgroup> -->
    <keyword>IAB</keyword>
    <keyword>W3C</keyword>
    <keyword>STREWS</keyword>
    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>pervasive monitoring</keyword>
    <keyword>London</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The STRINT workshop assembled one hundred participants in 
      London for two days in early 2014 to discuss how the technical
      community, and in particular the IETF and the W3C, should react
      to Pervasive Monitoring and more generally how to strengthen
	  the Internet in the face of such attacks. The discussions covered issues of
      terminology, the role of user interfaces, classes of mitigation,
      some specific use cases, transition strategies (including
      opportunistic encryption), and more. The workshop ended with a few
      high-level recommendations, which it is believed could be implemented
      and which could help strengthen the Internet. This is the report of that
      workshop.</t>
    </abstract>
    <!-- <note title=""></note> -->
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section anchor="context" title="Context">

	<t>[[Editorial note: This version was produced from the minutes,
	and then edited. It quite likely has some inaccuracies, so the
	authors would welcome corrections from those who attended the
	workshop. If you're a github person, 
	https://github.com/sftcd/strint-report has this so you can
	contribute there.]]</t>

      <t>The Vancouver IETF plenary concluded <xref target='vancouverplenary'/> that Pervasive
      Monitoring (PM)
      represents an attack on
      the Internet, and the IETF has begun to carry out 
      the more obvious actions required to try to handle this attack.
      However, there are additional much more complex questions
      arising that need further consideration before any additional
      concrete plans can be made.</t>

      <t>The <eref target="http://www.w3.org/" >W3C</eref> and <eref
      target="https://www.iab.org/" >IAB</eref> therefore decided to
      host a <eref
      target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/Overview.html"
      >workshop</eref> on the topic of &ldquo;Strengthening the Internet
      Against Pervasive Monitoring&rdquo; before <eref
      target="https://www.ietf.org/meeting/89/index.html"
      >IETF&nbsp;89</eref> in London in March 2014.
      The FP7-funded 
	<eref target="http://www.strews.eu/" >STREWS</eref> 
	project 
		organised the STRINT workshop on behalf of the IAB and W3C.
		</t>

		<t>
	The main workshop goal was to discuss what can be
      done, especially by the two standards organisations IETF and
      W3C, against PM, both for existing Internet
      protocols (HTTP/1, SMTP, etc.) and for new ones (WebRTC, HTTP/2,
      etc.).</t>

		<t>The starting point for the workshop was the existing
		IETF consensus that PM is an attack<xref target="I-D.farrell-perpass-attack"/>.
		</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="summary" title="Summary">

      <t>The workshop was well attended (registration closed when the
      maximum capacity of 100 was reached, but more than
      150 expressed a desire to register) and several people (about 165 at the
      maximum) listened to the streaming audio. The submitted papers
      (67 in total) were generally of good quality and all were
	  published (see <xref target="papers"/>), except for a few where authors who couldn't take part in
	  the workshop preferred not to publish. 
      </t>

      <t>The chairs of the workshop summarised the workshop in the
      final session in the form of the following recommendations:

	<list style="numbers">
	  <t>Well-implemented cryptography can be effective against PM and will benefit the Internet if used more, despite its
	  cost, which is steadily decreasing anyway.</t>

	  <t>Traffic analysis also needs to be considered, but is less well understood in
		the Internet community:
	  relevant research and protocol mitigations such
		as data minimisation need to
	  be better understood.</t>


	  <t>Work should continue on progressing the PM threat model
	draft<xref target="I-D.barnes-pervasive-problem"/> discussed in the workshop.  
	  </t>

	<t>
	Later, the IETF may be in a position
	to start to develop an update to
	  BCP 72 <xref target="RFC3552"/>, most likely as a new RFC enhancing
        that BCP and dealing with recommendations on how to
	mitigate PM and how to reflect that in IETF work.</t>

	  <t>The term "Opportunistic" has been widely used 
		to refer to a possible mitigation strategy for PM. We need
		to document definition(s) for this term, as it is being
		used differently by different people and in different
		contexts. We may also be able to develop a
	  cookbook-like set of related protocol techniques for developers. 
		Since the workshop, the IETF's security area has taken up
		this work, most recently favouring the generic term "Opportunistic
		Security" (OS) <xref target="I-D.kent-opportunistic-security"/>.
	  </t>

	  <t>The technical community could do better in explaining the
	  real technical downsides related to PM in terms that policy makers
		can understand.</t>

	  <t>Many User Interfaces (UI) could be better in terms of how they
		present security state, though this is a significantly hard
 		problem. There may be benefits if
	  certain dangerous choices were simply not
	  offered anymore. But that could require significant co-ordination among
	  competing software makers, otherwise some will be considered "broken"
	  by users. </t>

		<t>Ways to better integrate UI issues into the processes of
	  IETF and W3C needs further discussion.</t>

	  <t>Examples of good software configurations
	  that can be cut-and-paste'd for popular
	  software, etc., can help. This is not necessarily standards 
		work, but
	  maybe the standards organisations can help and can work
		with those developing such package-specific documentation.</t>

	  <t>The IETF and W3C can do more so that default
	  ("out-of-the-box") settings for protocols better protect
	  security and privacy.</t>

	  <t><eref
	  target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captive_portal"
	  >Captive portals,</eref> (and some firewalls, too) can and
	  should be distinguished from real man-in-the-middle
	  attacks. This might mean establishing common
	  conventions with makers of such middleboxes, but might also need
		new protocols. However, the incentives for deploying such
		new middlebox features might not align.</t>
	</list></t>

<!--
      <t><cref anchor="check-ipr" source="Bert">Check that the IPR is
      correct.</cref></t>

      <t><cref anchor="biblio" source="Bert">Should we convert the
      list of papers to BibTeX and/or Refer format for other people
      (and us) to use?</cref></t>

      <t><cref anchor="external" source="Bert">List and link other
      interesting documents (from the e-mail discussions,
      blogs&hellip;)? E.g.,
      http://www.pelicancrossing.net/netwars/2014/03/boiling_the_ocean.html
      by Wendy Grossman</cref></t>

-->

    </section>

    <section anchor="goals" title="Workshop goals">
      <t>As stated, the STRINT workshop started from the position that 
      PM is an attack. 
		<xref target="I-D.farrell-perpass-attack"/>
      While some dissenting voices are expected and need to be heard, that was the baseline assumption
      for the workshop, and the high-level goal was to provide 
      more consideration of that and how it ought to affect future work
      within the IETF and W3C.</t>

      <t>At the next level down the goals of the STRINT workshop were
      to:
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>Discuss and hopefully come to agreement among the
	  participants on concepts in PM for both threats and
	  mitigation, e.g., &ldquo;opportunistic&rdquo; as the term applies to
	  cryptography.</t>

	  <t>Discuss the PM threat model, and how that might be
	  usefully documented for the IETF at least, e.g., via an
	  update to <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp72"
	  >BCP72.</eref></t>

	  <t>Discuss and progress common understanding in the
	  trade-offs between mitigating and suffering PM.</t>

	  <t>Identify weak links in the chain of Web security
	  architecture with respect to PM.</t>

	  <t>Identify potential work items for the IETF, IAB, IRTF and
	  W3C that help mitigate PM.</t>

	  <t>Discuss the kinds of action outside the IETF/W3C context
	  might help those done within the IETF/W3C.</t>
	</list>

      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="structure" title="Workshop structure">

      <t>The workshop structure was designed to maximise discussion
      time. There were no direct presentations of submitted
      papers. Instead, the moderators of each session summarised
		topics that the Technical Programme Committee (TPC) had
 	  agreed based on the submitted
      papers. 
      These summary presentations took at most 50% of the session and
      usually less.</t>

      <t>Because the papers would not be presented during the
      workshop, participants were asked to read and discuss the
      papers beforehand, at least those relevant to their fields of
      interest. (To help people choose papers to read, 
      authors were asked to provide short abstracts.)</t>

      <t>Most of the sessions had two moderators, one
      to lead the discussion, while the other managed the queue of
      people who wanted to speak. This worked well: everybody got a
      chance to speak and each session still ended on time.</t>

      <t>The penultimate session consisted of
      break-outs. (Which turned out to be the most productive
		sessions of all, most likely simply due to the smaller
		numbers of people involved.) The subjects for the break-outs were 
      agreed during the 
      earlier sessions and just before the break-out session the
      participants collectively determined who would attend which.</t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="topics" title="Topics">
      <t>The following sections contain summaries of the various
      sessions. See the minutes (see <xref target="agenda"/>) for more
      details.</t>
      <section anchor="opening" title="Opening session">
	<t>The first session discussed the goals of the
	workshop. Possible approaches to improving security in the
	light of pervasive monitoring include a critical look at what
	metadata is actually required, whether old (less secure)
	devices can be replaced with new ones, what are
	"low-hanging fruit" (issues that can be handled quickly and
	easily), and what level of security is &ldquo;good enough&rdquo;: a good
	solution may be one that is good for 90% of people or 90% of
	organisations.</t>

	<t>Some paricipants felt that standards are needed so that people can see if their
	systems conform to a certain level of security as well as easy to remember names
	for those standards, so that a buyer can immediately see
	that a product &ldquo;conforms to the named intended standard.&rdquo;</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="threats" title="Threats">

	<t>One difference between &ldquo;traditional&rdquo; attacks and pervasive
	monitoring is modus-operandi of the attacker: typically, one
	determines what resources an attacker might want to target and
	at what cost and then one defends against that threat. But a
	pervasive attacker has no specific targets, other than to
	collect everything he can. The calculation of the cost of
	losing resources vs the cost of protecting them is thus
	different. And unlike someone motivated to make money, 
	a PM attacker may not be concerned at the cost of the
	attack (or may even prefer a higher cost, for "empire
	building" reasons). </t>

	<t>The terminology used to talk about threats has to be chosen
	carefully (this was a common theme in several sessions),
	because we need to explain to people outside the technical
	community what they need to do or not do. For example, authentication
	of endpoints doesn't so much &ldquo;protect against&rdquo;
	man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacks as make them visible. The
	attacker can still attack, but it does not remain invisible while he
	does so. Somebody on either end of the conversation needs to
	react to the alert from the system: stop the conversation or
	find a different channel.</t>

	<t>An interesting paradox is the role of big repositories of
	information, such as Facebook, Yahoo, Google, etc. Hopefully,
	they supervise their security better than the average Internet
	server, but they are also much more attractive as a target to
	attack. Avoiding overuse of such repositories for private or sensitive
	information may be a useful measure that increases the
	cost of collecting for a pervasive attacker. This is sometimes
	called the target-dispersal approach.</t>

	<t>Lack of interoperability between systems is in itself a
	threat as it leads to work-arounds and compromises that may
	be less secure. And
	thus improving interoperability needs to be high on the list
	of priorities of standards makers and even more for implementers. 
        Of course,
	testing, such as interop testing, is at some level, part of the process of IETF and W3C; and
	W3C is currently increasing its testing efforts.</t>

	<!--
	what's this mean? I've (SF) no idea.
	<t>Apart from identifying the threats, one desirable result of
	the workshop is also to document them, targeted at
	implementers.</t>
	-->

      </section>

      <section anchor="comsec-usage" title="Increase usage of security tools">

	<t>The first session on Communication Security (COMSEC) tools
	looked at the question why existing security tools aren't used
	more.</t>

	<t>The example of HTTPS is informative: it provides
	encryption and authentication and is widely available. In
	practice though, it is far from being used as much as it could be. It
	also has some problems. One problem is that certificate
	authorities (CA) are a potential weak link in the system. Any CA can
	issue a certificate for any server, and thus a single
	compromised CA can give a MITM the power to impersonate any
	server. Moreover, certificates can cost money, acquiring a
	certificate requires administrator time and
	effort, and certificates 
	need to be replaced when they expire, which is not the
	normal case for web technologies, so many server
	administrators forget or don't bother, making the 
	certificate infrastructure less relevant, and 
	causing https to provide less security.</t>

	<t>Some ideas were discussed for improving the CA system, e.g., via
	cross-certification of CAs and by means of &ldquo;certificate
	transparency&rdquo;: a public, permanent log of who issued which
	certificate. <xref target="RFC6962"/></t>

	<t>Using other models than the hierarchical certificate model
	(as alternative or in combination) may also help. The PGP
	model, e.g., is a flat network where people verify the
	identity (public key) of people they meet. And then they
	trust, to a certain level, that those people verified the
	identity of other people. This works for certain types of
	communication (it was more deployed for e-mail). However, an identity
	only verified by a friend of a friend provides a lower level of trust.</t>

	<t anchor="tofu">Yet another model is &ldquo;trust on first use&rdquo;
	(TOFU). This is used quite effectively by SSH <xref target='RFC4252'/>. On the first
	connection, one has no way to verify that the received public key
        belongs to the server one is contacting, therefore, the key is accepted without further verification. But on the subsequent
	connections, one can verify that the received key is the same key as the
	first time. So a MITM has to be there on all connections,
	including the first, otherwise it will be detected by a key mismatch.</t>

	<t>This works well for SSH, because people typically use SSH
	to communicate with a small number of servers over and over
	again. And, if they want, they may find a separate
	channel to get the public key (or its fingerprint). It may
	also work for Web servers used by small groups (the server of
	a sports club, a department of a company, etc.), but probably
	works less well for public servers that are visited once or a few times
	or for large services where many servers may be used.</t>

	  <t>A similar proposal <xref
	  target="draft-ietf-websec-key-pinning"/> for an HTTP header introduces an aspect of
	  TOFU into HTTP: Key pinning tells HTTP clients that for a
	  certain time after receiving this certificate, they should
	  not expect the certificate to change. If it does, even if
	  the new certificate looks valid, the client should assume a
	  security breach. </t>

	<!--
	We don't need this detail I think
	<figure>
	  <artwork>Public-Key-Pins: max-age=2592000;
  pin-sha256="E9CZ9IND...B9+xcprMF+44U1g=";
  pin-sha256="LPJNul+w...p0JecwQzYpOLmCQ=";
  report-uri="http://example.com/pkp-report"</artwork>
	</figure>
	-->

	<t>SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> is a complex protocol, in part because it potentially
	needs several different intermediaries in different stages of the
	communication to deal with NAT traversal and to handle policy. SIP provides
	hop-by-hop encryption and end-to-end authentication in theory,
	but in practice many SIP providers disable these functions and
	interoperability for end-to-end security in SIP is perhaps not
	in a good state. The reasons for disabling end-to-end security here
	are understandable: to overcome lack of interoperability they
	often need to change protocol headers and modify protocol
	data. Some workshop participants argued that SIP would never have taken off
	if it hadn't been possible for providers to monitor and
	interfere in communications in this way. Of course, that means
	an attacker can listen in just as easily.</t>

	<t>A new protocol for peer-to-peer communication of video and
	audio (and potentially other data) is WebRTC. 
        WebRTC
	re-uses many of the same architectural concepts as SIP, but 
	there is a reasonable
	chance that it can do better in terms of protecting users: The
	people implementing the protocols and offering the service
	have different goals and interests. In particular, the first
	implementers are browser makers, who may have different business
	models from other more traditional Voice over IP providers.</t>

	<t>XMPP suffers from yet another problem. It has encryption
	and authentication, and the OTR (&ldquo;off the record&rdquo;)
	extension even
	provides what is called Perfect Forward Secrecy (PFS, compromising
	the current communication never gives an attacker enough
	information to decrypt past communications that he may have
	recorded). But, in practice, many people don't use XMPP at
	all, but rather Skype, WhatsApp or other instant-messaging
	tools with unknown or no security. The problem here seems to
	be one of user awareness. And though OTR does provide 
	security, it is not well integrated with XMPP and nor is
	it available as a core feature of XMPP clients.</t>

	<t>To increase usage of existing solutions, some tasks can be identified,
	though how those map to actions for e.g. IETF/W3C is not clear:

	  <list style="symbols">

	    <t>Improvements to the certificate system, such as CT.</t>

	    <t>Making it easier (cheaper, quicker) for system
	    administrators to deploy secure solutions.</t>

	    <t>Improve awareness of the risks. Identify which
	    communities influence which decisions and what is the
	    appropriate message for each.</t>

	    <t>Provide an upgrade path that doesn't break existing
	    systems or require that everybody upgrade at the same
	    time. Opportunistic Security may be one model for that.</t>

	  </list></t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="policy" title="Policy issues and non-technical actions">

	<t>Previous sessions already concluded that the problem isn't
	just technical, such as getting the right algorithms in the standards,
	fixing interoperability, or educating implementers and systems
	administrators. There are user interface issues and education
	issues too. And there are also legal issues 
	and policy issues for governments.</t>

	<t>It appears that the public in general demand more
	privacy and security (e.g., for their children) but are also
	pessimistic about getting that. They trust that somebody assures
	that nothing bad happens to them, but they also expect to be
	spied on all the time.</t>

	<!--
	I (SF) have no idea what this means.
	<t>Economics may be partly to blame, as economic success has
	often been the result of carefully monitoring the clients. It
	is difficult to make that illegal.</t>
	-->

	<t>(Perceived) threats of terrorism gave governments a
	reason to allow widespread surveillance, far beyond what may
	previously have been considered dangerous for freedom.</t>

	<t>In this environment, the technical community will have a
	hard time developing and deploying technologies that fully
	counter PM. Which means there has to be action in
	the social and political spheres, too.</t>

<!-- ##TODO: needs a ref -->
	<!--
	I (SF) don't recall this discussion from the workshop at all.
	Are we being too editorial here maybe? Happy for it to be
	added back if we verify that it was discussed, but I'd be
	nervous of including it otherwise.

	<t>There are however initiatives that can be used as stepping
	stones. A suggestion such as German Chancellor Angela Merkel's
	&ldquo;Schengen Net&rdquo; (a communications network that keeps
	intra-european communications from passing over networks
	outside Europe and thus protects against foreign monitoring)
	may be a bad idea from a technical perspective (and actually
	make things easier for European spies&hellip;), but the underlying
	motive can be used as an argument to promote a solution that
	does work.</t>

	<t>Technical people often don't pay attention to individual
	cases that reach the news, because they are indeed just that:
	individual cases. That foreign spies try to listen to a government
        executive cellphone is not actually an example of pervasive
	monitoring, but an old-fashioned example of targeted
	spying&hellip; But it did make the news and therefore it should be
	used to best effect.</t>
	-->

	<t>Technology isn't the only thing that can make life harder
	for attackers. Government-sponsored PM
	is indirectly affected by trade agreements and
	treaties and thus it makes sense to lobby for those to be as
	privacy-friendly as possible.</t>

	<t>Court cases on the grounds of human rights can also
	influence policy, especially if they reach, for example, the European Court
	of Human Rights.</t>

	<!--
	I (SF) again don't recall this discussion.

	<t>And we need people to &ldquo;decode&rdquo; what politician say: what
	does a proposed law actually mean, how does a policy statement
	translate to concrete software configuration?</t>


	<t>And not all politicians are the same, or have the same
	goals. In Europe for example, one has to differentiate the European
	Parliament from the European Commission. They are important,
	but many people don't understand what they do.</t>
	-->

	<t>In medicine and law, it is common to have ethics committees,
	not so in software. Should standards bodies such as IETF and
	W3C have an ethics committee? While standards such as the
	Geolocation API <xref target="w3c-geo-api"/> have gotten scrutiny 
	from privacy experts, but
	only in an ad-hoc manner. (W3C has permanent groups to review standards for
	accessibility and internationalisation. It also has a Privacy
	group, but that currently doesn't do the same kind of systematic
	reviews.)</t>

	<!--
	SF sez: that's pure editorial commentary
	<t>The discussion above gives some hints as to why the laws
	aren't as supportive of privacy and security as we might want,
	but we don't fully understand the reasons yet.</t>
	-->

	<t anchor="collaborator">As the Internet Draft
	draft-barnes-pervasive-problem-00 (included as <eref
	target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/44.pdf"
	>paper&nbsp;44</eref>) explains, PM doesn't just
	monitor the networks, but also attacks at the endpoints,
	turning organisations or people into (willing, unwilling, or
	unwitting) collaborators. One technical means of protection is
	thus to design protocols such that there are fewer potential
	collaborators, e.g., a provider of cloud storage cannot hand
	over plaintext for content that is encrypted with a key he doesn't have, and
	cannot hand over names if his client is anonymous.</t>

	<t>It is important to distinguish between PM and fighting
	crime. PM is an attack, but a judge ordering the surveillance
	of a suspected criminal is not. The latter, often abbreviated
	in this context as LI (for Lawful Intercept), is outside the
	scope of this workshop.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="comsec-improvements" title="Improving the tools">

	<t>An earlier session discussed why existing COMSEC tools
	weren't used more. 
	This second session on COMSEC therefore discussed
	what improvements and/or new tools were needed.</t>

	<t>Discussion at the workshop indicated that an important meta-tool for
improving existing security technology could be 
Opportunistic Security (OS).  <xref target="I-D.kent-opportunistic-security"/>.
The idea is that software is enhanced
with a module that tries to encrypt communications when it detects that the
other end also has the same capablility but otherwise leaves the communication
continue in the old way. The detailed definition of OS is now being
discussed by the IETF security area. <xref target="saag"/>
</t>

	<t>OS would protect against a passive eavesdropper but should
	also allow for endpoint
	authentication to protect against an active attacker (a MITM). As OS spreads,
	more and more communications would be encrypted (and hopefully
	authenticated) and thus there is less and less for an
	eavesdropper to collect.</t>

	<t>Of course, an implementation of OS could give a false sense of security as well:
	some connections are encrypted, some are not. A user might see
	something like a padlock icon in browsers, but there was
	agreement at the workshop that such user interface features
	ought not be changed because OS is being used.
	</t>

	<t>There is also the possibility that a MITM intercepts the
	reply from a server that says &ldquo;yes, I can do encryption&rdquo; and
	removes it, causing the client to fall back to an unencrypted
	protocol. Mitigations against this can be to have other
	channels of finding out a server's capabilities and
	remembering that a server could do encryption previously.</t>

	<t>There is also, again, a terminology problem. The technical
	descriptions of OS talk about &ldquo;silent fail&rdquo; when a connection
	couldn't be encrypted and has to fall back to the old,
	unencrypted protocol. Actually, it's not a fail, it's no worse
	then it was before. A successful encryption would rather be a
	&ldquo;silent improvement.&rdquo;</t>

	<t>That raises the question of the UI: How do you explain to a
	user what their security options are, and, in case an error
	occurs, how do you explain the implications of the various
	responses?</t>

	<t>The people working on encryption are mathematicians and
	engineers, and typically not the same people who know about
	UI. We need to involve the experts. We also need to
	distinguish between usability of the UI, user understanding,
	and user experience. For an e-commerce site, e.g., it is not
	just important that the user's data is technically safe, but
	also that he feels secure. Otherwise he still won't buy
	anything.</t>

	<t>When talking about users, we also need to distinguish the
	end user (who we typically think about when we talk about UI)
	from the server administrators and other technical people
	involved in enabling a connection. When something goes wrong
	(e.g., the user's software detects an invalid certificate),
	the message usually goes to the end user. But he isn't
	necessarily the person who can do something about it. E.g., if
	the problem is a certificate that expired yesterday, the
	options for the user are to break the connection (the safe
	choice, but it means he can't get his work done) or continue
	anyway (there could be a MITM&hellip;). The server administrator,
	on the other hand, could actually solve the problem.</t>

	<t>Encryption and authentication have a cost, in terms of
	setting them up, but also in terms of the time it takes for
	software to do the calculations. The set-up cost can be
	reduced with sensible defaults, predefined profiles and
	cut-and-paste configurations. 
	
	<!--
	SF: I don't remember this and doubt it could work - a MITM would detect it.
	The cost of authentication
	could, if necessary, perhaps be diminished by authenticating only a
	random sample of connections. It is less secure, but still
	makes things harder for an eavesdropper. 
	-->
	And for some
	connections, authentication without encryption could be
	enough, in the case that the data doesn't need to be kept
	secret, but it is important to know that it is the real
	data. Most mail UAs already provide independent options for
	encryption and signing, but Web servers only support
	authentication if the connection is also encrypted.</t>

	<t>On the other hand, as e-mail also shows, it is difficult
	for users to understand what encryption and authentication do
	separately.</t>

	<t>And it also has to be kept in mind that encrypting only the
	&ldquo;sensitive&rdquo; data and not the rest decreases the cost for an
	attacker, too: It becomes easy to know which connections are
	worth attacking. Selective field confidentiality is also
	more prone to lead to developer error, as not all developers
	will know the provenance of values to be processed.</t>

	<t>One problem with the <xref pageno="true" format="none" target="tofu"
	>TOFU model</xref> as used by SSH (see explanation above) is
	that it lacks a solution for key continuity: When a key is
	changed (which can happen e.g., when a server is replaced or
	the software upgraded), there is no way to inform the client.
	(In practice, people use other means, such as calling people
	on the phone or asking their colleagues in the office, but
	that doesn't scale and doesn't always happen either.) An
	improvement in the SSH protocol could thus be a way to
	transfer a new key to a client in a safe way.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="metadata" title="Hiding metadata">

	<t>Encryption and authentication help protect the content of
	messages. Correctly implemented encryption is very hard to
	crack. (To get the content, an attacker would rather attempt
	to steal the keys, corrupt the encoding software, or get the
	content via a <xref pageno="true" format="none" target="collaborator"
	>collaborator</xref>.) But encrypting the content doesn't hide
	the fact that you are communicating. This metadata (who talks
	to whom, when and for how long) is often as interesting as the
	content itself, and in some cases the size and timing of
	messages is even an accurate predictor of the content. So how
	to stop an attacker from collecting metadata, given that much
	of that data is actually needed by routers and other services
	to deliver the message to the right place?</t>

	<t>It is useful to distinguish different kinds of metadata:
	explicit (or metadata proper) and implicit (sometimes called
	traffic data). Implicit metadata is things that can be derived
	from a message or are necessary for its delivery, such as the
	destination address, the size, the time, or the frequency with
	which messages pass. Explicit metadata is things like quality
	ratings, provenance or copyright data: data about the data,
	useful for an application, but not required to deliver the
	data to its endpoint.</t>

	<t>A system like Tor hides much of the metadata by passing
	through several servers, encrypting all the data except that
	which a particular server needs to see. Each server thus knows
	which server a message came from and where he has to send it
	to, but cannot know where the previous server got it from or
	where the next server is instructed to send it. However,
	deliberately passing through multiple servers makes the
	communication slower than taking the most direct route and
	increases the amount of traffic the network as a whole has to
	process.</t>

	<t>There are three kinds of measures that can be taken to make
	metadata harder to get: aggregation, contraflow and multipath
	(see <eref
	target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/04.pdf" >paper
	4</eref>). New protocols should be designed such that these
	measures are not inadvertently disallowed, e.g., because the
	design assumes that the whole of a conversation passes through
	the same route.</t>

	<t><spanx style="emph">Aggregation</spanx> means collecting
	conversations from multiple sources into one stream. E.g., if
	HTTP connections pass through a proxy, all the conversations
	appear to come from the proxy instead of from their original
	sources. (This assumes that telltale information in the
	headers is stripped by the proxy, or that the connection is
	encrypted.) It also works in the other direction: if multiple
	Web sites are hosted on the same server, an attacker cannot
	see which of those Web sites a user is reading. (This assumes
	that the name of the site is in the path info of the URL and
	not in the domain name, otherwise watching DNS queries can
	still reveal the name.)</t>

	<t><spanx style="emph">Contraflow</spanx> means routing a
	conversation via one or more other servers than the normal
	route, e.g., by using a tunnel (e.g., with SSH or a VPN) to
	another server. Tor is an example of this. An attacker must
	watch more routes and do more effort to correlate
	conversations. (Again, this assumes that there is no telltale
	information left in the messages that leave the tunnel.)</t>

	<t><spanx style="emph">Multipath</spanx> splits up a single
	conversation (or a set of related conversations) and routes
	the parts in different ways. E.g., send a request via a
	satellite link and receive the response via a land line; or
	starting a conversation on a cellular link and continuing it
	via wifi. This again increases the cost for an attacker, who
	has to monitor and correlate multiple networks.</t>

	<t>Protecting metadata automatically with technology at a
	lower layer than the application layer is difficult. The
	applications themselves need to pass less data, e.g., use
	anonymous temporary handles instead of permanent
	identifiers. There is often no real need for people to use the
	same identifier on different computers (smartphone, desktop,
	etc.) other than that the application they use was designed
	that way.</t>

	<t>One thing that can be done relatively easily in the short
	term is going through existing protocols to check what data
	they send that isn't really necessary. One candidate mentioned for such
	a study was XMPP.</t>

	<t><spanx style="emph">Fingerprinting</spanx> is the process
	of distinguishing different senders of messages based on
	metadata: Clients can be recognised (or at least grouped)
	because their messages always have a combination of features
	that other clients do not have. Reducing redundant metadata
	and reducing the number of optional features in a protocol
	reduces the variation between clients and thus makes
	fingerprinting harder.</t>

	<t>Traffic analysis is a research discipline that produces
	sometimes surprising findings, which are little known among
	protocol developers. Some collections of results are
	  <list style="symbols">
	    <t>A selected <eref target="http://freehaven.net/anonbib/"
	    >bibliography on anonymity</eref> by the Free Haven
	    Project</t>

	    <t>The yearly <eref
	    target="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~Ley/db/conf/pet/index.html"
	    >Symposium on Privacy Enhancing Technologies
	    (PETS).</eref></t>

	    <t>The yearly <eref
	    target="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~Ley/db/conf/wpes/index.html"
	    >Workshop on Privacy in the Electronic Society
	    (WPES).</eref></t>
	  </list></t>

	<t>Techniques that deliberately change the timing or size of
	messages, such as padding, can also help reduce
	fingerprinting. Obviously, they make conversations slower
	and/or use more bandwidth, but in some cases that is not an
	issue, e.g., if the conversation is limited by the speed of a
	human user anyway. HTTP/2 has a built-in padding
	mechanism. However, it is not so easy to use these techniques
	well, and not actually make messages easier to recognise
	rather than harder.</t>

	<t>Different users in different contexts may have different
	security needs, so maybe the priority can be a user
	choice. (If that can be done without making high-security
	users stand out from other users.) Although many people would
	not understand what their choices are, some do, such as
	political activists or journalists.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="deployment"
	title="Deployment, intermediaries and middleboxes">

	<t>Secure protocols have often been designed in the past for
	end-to-end security: Intermediaries cannot read or modify the
	messages. This is the model behind TLS for example.</t>

	<t>But in practice people have more or less valid reasons to
	insist on intermediaries: companies filtering incoming and
	outgoing traffic for viruses or other reasons, giving priority
	to certain communications or caching to reduce bandwidth.</t>

	<t>In the presence of end-to-end encryption and
	authentication, these intermediaries have two choices: using
	fake certificates to impersonate the endpoints or having
	access to the private keys of the endpoints. The former is a
	MITM attack that is difficult to distinguish from a more
	malicious one, the latter obviously decreases the security of
	the endpoints by copying supposedly protected data and
	concentrating such data in a single place.</t>

	<t>As mentioned in <xref pageno="true" target="threats"/> above,
	aggregation of data in a single place makes that place an
	attractive target. And in the case of PM even if the data is
	not concentrated physically in one place, but is under control
	of a single legal entity that can be made into a <xref pageno="true"
	format="none" target="collaborator" >collaborator</xref>.</t>

	<t>The way Web communication with TLS typically works is that
	the client authenticates the server, but the server does not 
	authenticate the
	client at the TLS layer. (If the client needs to be identified, that is mainly
	done at the application layer via passwords or cookies.) Thus
	the presence of a MITM (middlebox) could be detected by the
	client (because of the incorrect certificate), but not by the
	server. If the client doesn't immediately close the
	connection, (which they do not in many cases), the server may thus disclose information that the
	user would rather not have disclosed.</t>

	<t>One widespread example of middleboxes is captive portals,
	as found on the wifi hotspots in hotels, airports, etc. Even
	the hotspots offering free access often intercept communications
	to redirect the user to a login or policy page.</t>

	<t>When the communication they intercept is, e.g., the
	automatic update of your calendar program or a chat session,
	the redirect obviously doesn't work: these applications don't
	know how to display a Web page. With the increasing use of
	apps, it may be a while before the user actually opens a
	browser. The flood of error messages may also have as a result
	that the user no longer reads the errors, allowing an actual
	malicious attack to go unnoticed.</t>

	<t>Some operating systems now come
	with heuristics that try to recognise captive portals and
	either automatically login or show their login page in a
	separate application. (But some hotspot providers apparently
	don't want automatic logins and actually reverse-engineered
	the heuristics to try and fool them.)</t>

	<t>It seems some protocol is missing in this case. Captive
	portals shouldn't have to do MITM attacks to be noticed. Maybe
	something like an extension to DHCP that tells a connecting
	device about the login page can help, although that still
	doesn't solve the problem for devices that do not have a Web
	browser, such as game consoles or SIP phones. HTTP response
	code 511 (defined in <xref target="RFC6585"/>) is another
	attempt at a solution. (Partial, because it can only work at
	the moment the user uses a browser to connect to a Web site
	and doesn't use HTTPS.)</t>

	<t>A practical problem with deployment of such a protocol may
	be that many such captive portals are very old and never
	updated. The hotel staff only knows how to reboot the system
	and as long as it works, the hotel has no incentive to buy a
	new one. As evidence of this: how many such systems require
	you to get a password and the ticket shows the price as zero?
	This is typically because the owner doesn't know how to
	reconfigure the hotspot, but he does know how to change the
	price in his cash register&hellip;</t>

      </section>


      <section anchor="research" title="Break-out 1 &ndash; research">

	<!--
	<t><cref anchor="break-out-1" source="Bert">Who has a summary
	for the session of the challenge of connecting academics and
	standards bodies</cref></t>
	-->

    <t>
      Despite some requests earlier in the workshop, the research 
      break-out did not discuss clean-slate approaches. The 
      challenge was rather that the relation between security research
      and standardisation needs improvement. Research on linkability is 
      not yet well known in the IETF. But the other side of the coin 
      needs improvement too: While doing protocol design, 
      standardisation should indicate what specific problems are in 
      need of more research. 
    </t>
    <t>
      The break-out then made a non exclusive list of topics that are 
      in need of further research: 
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          The interaction of compression and encryption as demonstrated 
          by the <eref 
target="https://community.qualys.com/blogs/securitylabs/2012/09/14/crime 
           -information-leakage-attack-against-ssltls">CRIME SSL/TLS 
            vulnerability</eref>
        </t>
        <t>
          A more proactive deprecation of algorithms based 
          on research results.
        </t>
        <t>
          Mitigation for return oriented programming attacks
        </t>
        <t>
          How to better obfuscate so called "metadata", how to make the 
          existence of traffic and their endpoints stealthy
        </t>  
      </list>
    </t>

  </section>

      <section anchor="client" title="Break-out 2 &ndash; clients">

	<t>Browsers are the first clients one thinks of when talking
	about encrypted connections, authentication and certificates,
	but there are many others.</t>

	<t>Another common case of &ldquo;false&rdquo; alarms for MITM (after
	captive portals) is expired and mis-configured
	certificates. This is quite common in intranets, when the
	sysadmin hasn't bothered updating a certificate and rather
	tells his handful of users to just &ldquo;click continue.&rdquo; The
	problem is on the one hand that users may not understand the
	difference between this case and the same error message when
	they connect to a server outside the company, and on the other
	hand that the incorrect certificate installed by the sysadmin
	is not easily distinguishable from an incorrect certificate
	from a MITM. The error message is almost the same and the user
	may just click continue again.</t>

	<t>One way to get rid of such certificates is if client
	software no longer offers the option to continue after a
	certificate error. That requires that all major clients (such
	as browsers) change their behaviour at the same time, otherwise
	the first one to do so will be considered broken by users,
	because the others still work. Also it requires a period in
	which that software gives increasingly strong warnings about
	the cut-off date after which the connection will fail with
	this certificate.</t>

	<t>Yet another source of error messages is self-signed
	certificates. Such certificates are actually only errors for
	sites that are not expected to have them. If a message about a
	self-signed certificate appears when connecting to Facebook or
	Google, you're clearly not connected to the real Facebook or
	Google. But for a personal Website it shouldn't cause such
	scary warnings. There may be ways to improve the explanations
	in the error message and provide an easy way to verify the
	certificate (by e-mail, over the phone or some other channel)
	and import it.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="on-by-default" title="Break-out 3 &ndash; on by default">

	<t>One step in improving security is to require the relevant
	features, in particular encryption and authentication, to be
	implemented in compliant products: The features are labelled as
	MUST in the standard rather than MAY. This is sometimes
	referred to as MTI, Mandatory To Implement and is 
	the current practice for IETF protocols. <xref target="RFC3365"/> </t>

	<t>But that may not be enough to counter PM. It may be that the features are
	there, but not used, because only very knowledgeable users or
	sysadmins turn them on. Or it may be that implementations do not
	actually follow the MTI parts of specifications. Or it may be
	that some security features are implemented but interoperability
	for those doesn't really work. Or, even worse, it may be that
	protocol designers have only followed the letter of the MTI best 
	practice and not its spirit, with the result that security
	features are hard to use or make deployment harder.
	One can thus argue that such features should be defined 
	to be on by default.</t>

	<t>Going further one might argue that these features should not even be options,
	i.e., there should be no way to turn them off. This is
	sometimes called MTU, Mandatory To Use.</t>

	<t>The question raised at this session was for what protocols on-by-default is
	appropriate, and how to explain to the developers of such
	protocols that it is needed?</t>

	<t>There would of course be resistance to MTU security from
	implemeters and deployments that practice deep packet inspection (DPI) and also
	perhaps from some governments. On the other hand, there may also be
	governments that outlaw protocols <spanx
	style="emph">without</spanx> proper encryption. 
	</t>

	<t>This break-out concluded that there could be value in
	attempting to document a new Best Current Practice for the
	IETF that moves from the current MTI position to one
	where security features are on-by-default. Some of the 
	workshop participants expressed interest in authoring
	a draft for such a new BCP and progressing that through
	the IETF consensus process. (Where it would no doubt be
	controversial.) </t>
	

      </section>

      <section anchor="measure" title="Break-out 4 &ndash; measurement">

	<t>There was a small break-out on the idea of measurement as
	a way to encourage or gamify the increased use of security
	mechanisms. [[We don't currently have notes from that.]]</t>

      </section>


      <section anchor="opportunistic" title="Break-out 5 &ndash; opportunistic">


	<t>This break out considered the use of the term "opportunistic" as
	it applies to crytpgraphic security and attempted to progress the
	work towards arriving at an agreed definition for use of that 
	term, at it applies to IETF and W3C work.</t>

	<t>While various terms had been used, with many people talking
	about opportunistic encryption, that usage was felt to be 
	problematic both because it conflicted with the use of the
	same term in <xref target="RFC4322"/> and because it was
	being used differently in different parts of the community.</t>

	<t>At the session it was felt that the term "opportunistic 
	keying" was better, but as explained above subsequent list
	discussion resulted in a move to the term "Opportunistic
	Security" (OS). </t>

	<t>Aside from terminology, disussion focused on the use
	of Diffie-Hellman (D-H) key exchange as the preferred mechanism
	of OS, with fall back to cleartext if D-H doesn't succeed
	as a counter for passive attacks.</t>

	<t>There was also of course the desire to be able to
	easily escalate from countering passive attacks to
	also handling endpoint authentication and thereby 
	also countering MITM attacks.</t>

	<t>Making OS visible to users was again considered to
	be undesirable, as users could not be expected to 
	distinguish between cleartext, OS and (one-sided or
	mutal) endpoint authentication.</t>

	<t>Finally, it was noted that it may take some 
	effort to establish how middleboxes might affect OS at different layers
	and that OS really is not suitable as the only migitation
	to use for high-sensitivity sessions such as financial
	transactions.</t>

      </section>

	<section title="Unofficial Transport/Routing Break-out">

	
<t>
Some routing and transport area directors felt a little left
out by all the application layer break-outs:-) So they had their own
brainstorm about what
could be done at the Transport and Routing layers from which
these notes resulted.</t>

<t>
The LEDBAT <xref target="RFC6817"/> 
protocol was targeted towards a
bulk-transfer service that is reordering and delay insensitive.  Use of
LDEBAT could offer the following benefits for an application:
<list style="letters">
<t>
    Because it is reordering insensitive, traffic can be sprayed across
a large number of forwarding paths.  Assuming such different paths exist,
this would make it more challenging to capture and analyze a full
interaction.
</t>
<t>
    The application can vary the paths by indicating per packet a
different microflow.  In IPv6, this can be done via different IPv6 flow
labels.  For IPv4, this can be done by encapsulating the IP packet into UDP
and varying the UDP src port.
</t>
<t>
    Since LEDBAT is delay insensitive and applications using it would
need to be as well, it would be possible to obfuscate the application
signatures by varying the packet lengths and frequency.
</t>
<t>
    This can also hide the transport header (for IP in UDP).
</t>
<t>
    If we could fix the reverse SPF check problem, perhaps the source
could be hidden - but that has assumptions on trusted perimeters.
</t>
<t>
    The use of LEDBAT is orthogonal to the use of encryption and provides
different benefits (harder to intercept the whole conversation, ability to
obfuscate the traffic analysis), and also has different costs (longer latency, new
transport protocol usage) to its users.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
We also discussed the idea of encrypting traffic from CE to CE as part of a
L3VPN or such.  This could allow hiding of addresses, including source, and
headers.  From my further conversation with Ron Bonica, some customers
already do encryption (though not hiding the source address) like this.
 So, I'm not sure this is very practically useful as an enhancement except
for encouraging deployment and use.
</t>

<t>
Finally, we discussed whether it would be useful to have a means of
communicating where and what layers are doing encryption on an
application's traffic path.  The initial idea of augmenting ICMP has some
issues (not visible to application, ICMP packets frequently filtered) as
well as potential work (determining how to trust the report of encryption).
 It would be interesting to understand if such communication is actually
needed and what the requirements would be.
</t>

	</section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="after" title="After the workshop">
      <t>Holding the workshop just before the IETF had the intended
      effect: a number of people went to both the workshop and the
      IETF. And they took the opportunity of being together at the
      IETF to continue the discussions.</t>

      <t>Working groups of the IETF who met in London took the
      recommendations from the workshop into account. It was even the
      first item in the report about the IETF meeting by the IETF
      chair, Jari Arkko:
	<list style="empty">
	  <t><spanx style="emph">&ldquo;Strengthening the security and
	  privacy of the
	  Internet continued to draw a lot of attention. The STRINT
	  workshop organised by the IAB and W3C just before the IETF
	  attracted 100 participants and over 60 papers. Even more
	  people would have joined us, but there was no space. During
	  the IETF meeting, we continued discussing the topic at
	  various working groups. A while ago we created the first
	  working group specifically aimed at addressing some of the
	  issues surrounding pervasive monitoring. The Using TLS for
	  Applications (UTA) working group had its first meeting in
	  London. But many other working groups also address these
	  issues in their own work. The TCPM working group discussed a
	  proposal to add opportunistic keying mechanisms directly
	  onto the TCP protocol. And the DNSE BOF considered the
	  possibility of adding confidentiality support to DNS
	  queries. Finally, there is an ongoing effort to review old
	  specifications to search for areas that might benefit from
	  taking privacy and data minimisation better into
	  account.&rdquo;</spanx> &ndash; <xref target="Arkko1"/></t>
	  </list></t>

      <t>Two papers that were written for the workshop, but not
      finished in time, are worth mentioning, too: One by the same
      Jari Arkko, titled &ldquo;Privacy and Networking
      Functions&rdquo; <xref target="Arkko2"/>; and one by Johan
      Pouwelse, &ldquo;The Shadow Internet: liberation from
      Surveillance, Censorship and Servers&rdquo; <xref
      target="draft-pouwelse-perpass-shadow-internet"/></t>
    </section>

	<!-- 
	SF: This is all (I think) in the summary so no point repeating it.
 
    <section anchor="conclusions" title="Conclusions and recommendations">
      <t>The main conclusions from the workshop are the following:
	<list style="numbers">
	  <t>Encryption works and needs to be used more, despite its
	  cost (which is steadily going down anyway).</t>

	  <t>Data minimisation is worthwhile, too, but difficult:
	  Traffic analysis research and protocol development need to
	  work together.</t>

	  <t>The threat models discussed in the workshop should be
	  written up in an RFC (either separately or as an update to
	  <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp72"
	  >BCP&nbsp;72</eref>).</t>

	  <t>&ldquo;Opportunistic Encryption&rdquo; could benefit from a
	  cookbook-like explanation for developers. (The term itself
	  may also be confusing. Best effort encryption or
	  opportunistic keying were suggested as alternatives.)</t>

	  <t>The technical community can do better in explaining the
	  issues of Pervasive Monitoring to policy makers.</t>

	  <t>Similarly, user interfaces could be better. (Some people
	  even argue that certain dangerous choices should simply not
	  be offered anymore. But that requires concertation among
	  software makers, otherwise some will be considered &ldquo;broken&rdquo;
	  by users.) How to integrate UI issues into the processes of
	  IETF and W3C needs further discussion.</t>

	  <t>Examples of good software configurations, guidelines for
	  developers, cut-and-paste configurations for popular
	  software, etc., can help. This is not standards work, but
	  maybe the standards organisations can still help.</t>

	  <t>Software makers can do more to make the default
	  (&ldquo;out-of-the-box&rdquo;) settings better for protecting
	  privacy.</t>

	  <t><eref
	  target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captive_portal"
	  >Captive portals,</eref> (and some firewalls, too) can and
	  should be distinguished from real man-in-the-middle
	  attacks. Maybe this just needs establishing common
	  conventions with makers of such proxies, but maybe also new
	  protocols.</t>
	</list></t>

	<t>Some recommendations also emerged from the discussions.
	Some are meant for the developers of standards, some do not
	have a clear target yet:
	<list style="letters">
	  <t>Lack of interoperability generally reduces security.
	  Standards organisations should do everything they can to
	  improve interoperability.</t>

	  <t>The hierarchical certificate system used by TLS has some
	  problems that may be solvable e.g., with Certificate
	  Transparency (CT).</t>

	  <t>Standards organisations should investigate the
	  possibility of a permanent committee that reviews proposed
	  standards in the light of privacy protection.</t>

	  <t>Developers of standards should do more to get the
	  expertise that is available from academics, such as in
	  traffic analysis and user interfaces.</t>

	  <t>Create example configurations, standard profiles and
	  cut-and-paste solutions to help sysadmins deploy correctly
	  configured secure systems.</t>

	  <t>Develop an upgrade path from current, insecure systems to
	  secure systems, without hindrance to users.</t>

	  <t>Technical solutions for increased security will have
	  difficulty being deployed unless they are socially and
	  legally accepted, or better still: demanded. Educating
	  people within the technical community only is thus not
	  enough.</t>
	</list></t>
    </section>
	-->

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA considerations">
	<t>There are none. We hope the RFC editor deletes this section.</t>
	</section>
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security considerations">
      <t>This document does not define a technology but is all about security and privacy.</t>

      <figure>
	<preamble>Plenary.</preamble>

	<artwork src="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/lib/workshop-6"
	type="image/jpeg" alt="(foto: view from the back of the room)"
	/>

	<postamble><eref
	target="http://www.stonehousephotographic.com/" >&copy;
	Stonehouse Photographic</eref></postamble>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Informative references">

	&RFC3261;
	&RFC3365;
	&RFC3552;
    &RFC4252;
	&RFC4322;
	&RFC6817;
	&RFC6962;
	&I-D.barnes-pervasive-problem;
	&I-D.kent-opportunistic-security;
	&I-D.farrell-perpass-attack;

      <reference anchor='vancouverplenary' target='http://www.ietf.org/proceedings/88/minutes/minutes-88-iab-techplenary'>
        <front>
         <title>IETF 88 Technical Plenary Minutes</title>
         <author surname='IETF'/>
         <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <!-- Downloaded from
      http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6585.xml -->
      <reference anchor='RFC6585'>
	<front>
	  <title>Additional HTTP Status Codes</title>
	  <author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'/>
	  <author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'/>
	  <date year='2012' month='April' />
	  <abstract>
	    <t>This document specifies additional HyperText Transfer
	    Protocol (HTTP) status codes for a variety of common
	    situations. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
	  </abstract>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6585' />
	<format type='TXT' octets='17164'
	  target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6585.txt' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="draft-ietf-websec-key-pinning">
	<front>
	  <title>Public Key Pinning Extension for HTTP</title>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Evans" fullname="Chris Evans">
	    <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
	    <address>
	      <postal>
		<street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
		<city>Mountain View</city>
		<region>CA</region>
		<code>94043</code>
		<country>US</country>
	      </postal>
	      <email>cevans@google.com</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Palmer" fullname="Chris Palmer">
	    <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
	    <address>
	      <postal>
		<street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
		<city>Mountain View</city>
		<region>CA</region>
		<code>94043</code>
		<country>US</country>
	      </postal>
	      <email>cevans@google.com</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="R." surname="Sleevi" fullname="Ryan Sleevi">
	    <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
	    <address>
	      <postal>
		<street>1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy</street>
		<city>Mountain View</city>
		<region>CA</region>
		<code>94043</code>
		<country>US</country>
	      </postal>
	      <email>sleevi@google.com</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <date day="8" month="February" year="2014"/>
	  <area>Web Security</area>
	  <abstract>
	    <t>This memo describes an extension to the HTTP protocol
	    allowing web host operators to instruct user agents (UAs)
	    to remember ("pin") the hosts' cryptographic identities
	    for a given period of time.  During that time, UAs will
	    require that the host present a certificate chain
	    including at least one Subject Public Key Info structure
	    whose fingerprint matches one of the pinned fingerprints
	    for that host.  By effectively reducing the number of
	    authorities who can authenticate the domain during the
	    lifetime of the pin, pinning may reduce the incidence of
	    man-in-the-middle attacks due to compromised Certification
	    Authorities.</t>
	  </abstract>
	</front>
	<format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-websec-key-pinning-11" type="TXT"/>
	<annotation>(Work in progress.)</annotation>
      </reference>

	<reference anchor="w3c-geo-api"
		target="http://www.w3.org/TR/geolocation-API/">
	<front>
	  <title>Geolocation API Specification</title>
	  <author initials="A." surname="Popescu" fullname="Andrei Popescu">
	  </author>
	  <date day="24" month="October" year="2013"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
	

      <reference anchor="saag"
	target="https://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/saag/current/maillist.html">
	<front>
	  <title>IETF Security Area mailing list</title>
	  <author initials="S." surname="Area" fullname="Security Area">
	  </author>
	  <date day="10" month="March" year="2014"/>
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Arkko1"
	target="http://www.ietf.org/blog/2014/03/ietf-89-summary/">
	<front>
	  <title>IETF-89 Summary</title>
	  <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
	  </author>
	  <date day="10" month="March" year="2014"/>
	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="draft-pouwelse-perpass-shadow-internet"
	target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-pouwelse-perpass-shadow-internet/">
	<front>
	  <title>The Shadow Internet: liberation from Surveillance,
	  Censorship and Servers</title>
	  <author initials="J." surname="Pouwelse" fullname="Johan Pouwelse" role="editor">
	    <organization>Delft University of
	    Technology</organization>
	    <address>
	      <postal>
		<street>Mekelweg 4</street>
		<city>Delft</city>
		<country>The Netherlands</country>
	      </postal>
	      <phone>+31 15 278 2539</phone>
	      <email>J.A.pouwelse@tudelft.nl</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <date day="14" month="February" year="2014"/>
	  <abstract>
	    <t>This IETF Perpass document describes some scenarios and
	    requirements for Internet hardening by creating what we
	    term a shadow Internet, defined as an infrastructure in
	    which the ability of governments to conduct indiscriminate
	    eavesdropping or censor media dissemination is reduced.
	    Internet-deployed code is available for most components of
	    this shadow Internet.</t>
	  </abstract>
	</front>
	<annotation>(Work in progress.)</annotation>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Arkko2"
	target="http://www.arkko.com/ietf/strint/draft-arkko-strint-networking-functions.txt">
	<front>
	  <title>Privacy and Networking Functions</title>
	  <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
	    <organization>Ericsson</organization>
	    <address>
	      <postal>
		<street></street>
		<city>Jorvas</city>
		<code>02420</code>
		<country>Finland</country>
	      </postal>
	      <email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>
	    </address>
	  </author>
	  <date day="6" month="March" year="2014"/>
	  <abstract>
	    <t> This paper discusses the inherent tussle between
	    network functions and some aspects of privacy.  There is
	    clearly room for a much improved privacy in Internet
	    communications, but there are also interesting
	    interactions with network functions, e.g., what
	    information networks need to provide a service.  Exploring
	    these limits is useful to better understand potential
	    improvements.</t>
	  </abstract>
	</front>
	<annotation>(Work in progress.)</annotation>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="logistics" title="Logistics">
      <t>The workshop was organised by the 
	<eref target="http://www.strews.eu/" >STREWS</eref> 
		project (a
      research project funded under the European Union's <eref
      target="http://cordis.europa.eu/fp7/ict/" >7th Framework
      Programme</eref>), as the first of two workshops in its work
      plan. The organisers were supported by the IAB and W3C, and, for
      the local organisation, by <eref
      target="http://blog.digital.telefonica.com/" >Telefonica
      Digital.</eref></t>
      <t>One of the suggestions in the project description of the
      STREWS project was to attach the first workshop to an IETF
      meeting. The best opportunity was <eref
      target="https://www.ietf.org/meeting/89/index.html"
      >IETF&nbsp;89</eref> in London, which would begin on Sunday
      March&nbsp;2, 2014. Telefonica Digital offered meeting rooms at
      its offices in central London for the preceding Friday and
      Saturday, just minutes away from the IETF's location.</t>
      <t>The room held 100 people, which was thought to be
      sufficient. There turned out to be more interest than expected
      and we could have filled a larger room, but 100 people is
      probably an upper limit for good discussions anyway.</t>
<!--
      <figure title="ASCII-art rendering of https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/lib/workshop-2">
	<artwork src="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/lib/workshop-2"
	type="image/jpeg" alt="(foto: room full of sitting people)" >
	</artwork>
	<postamble><eref
	target="http://www.stonehousephotographic.com/" >&copy;
	Stonehouse Photographic</eref></postamble>
      </figure>
-->
      <t>Apart from the usual equipment in the room (projector, white
      boards, microphones, coffee&hellip;), we also set up some extra
      communication channels:
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>A mailing list where participants could discuss the
	  agenda and the published papers about three weeks in advance
	  of the workshop itself. (Only participants were allowed to
	  write to the mailing list, but the <eref
	  target="http://lists.i1b.org/pipermail/strint-attendees-i1b.org/"
	  >archive</eref> is public.)</t>
	  <t>Publicly advertised streaming audio (one-way only). At
	  some point, no less than 165 people were listening.</t>
	  <t>An IRC channel for live minute taking, passing links and
	  other information, and as a help for remote participants to
	  follow the proceedings.</t>
	  <t>An Etherpad, where the authors of papers could provide an
	  abstract of their submissions, to help participants who
	  could not read all 66 papers in full in advance of the
	  workshop. (The abstracts were also used on the workshop's
	  Web site and are <xref pageno="true" target="papers" >reproduced in this
	  report</xref>.)</t>
	  <t>A &ldquo;Twitter hashtag&rdquo; (#strint). Four weeks
	  after the workshop, there were still a few new <eref
	  target="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23strint"
	  >messages</eref> about events related to workshop
	  topics.</t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="agenda" title="Agenda">
      <t>This was the final agenda of the workshop, as 
      determined by the TPC and participants on the mailing list prior to the
      workshop. The included links are to the slides that the
      moderators used to introduce each discussion topic and to the
      minutes.</t>
<!--
      <figure>
	<preamble>Break out.</preamble>
	<artwork alt="(foto: people around a big table)"
	type="image/jpeg"
	src="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/lib/workshop-3" />
	<postamble><eref
	target="http://www.stonehousephotographic.com/" >&copy;
	Stonehouse Photographic</eref></postamble>
      </figure>
-->
      <section anchor="friday" title="Friday 28 February">
	<t>(<eref
	  target="http://www.w3.org/2014/02/28-strint-minutes.html"
	  >minutes</eref>)
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="13:00">Registration, Coffee, play with n/w,
	    power, find seat</t>
	  <t hangText="14:00">Workshop starts, welcome, logistics,
	  opening/overview <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s0-welcome.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>Goal is to plan how we respond to PM threats</t>
	      <t>Specific questions to be discussed in sessions</t>
	      <t>Outcomes are actions for IETF, W3C, IRTF, etc.</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="14:30">I. Threats &ndash; What problem are we trying
	  to solve?  (Presenter: Richard Barnes; Moderator: Cullen
	  Jennings) <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s1-threat.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>What attacks have been described? (Attack taxonomy)</t>
	      <t>What should we assume the attackers' capabilities are?</t>
	      <t>When is it really &ldquo;pervasive monitoring&rdquo; and when is
	      it not?</t>
	      <t>Scoping &ndash; what's in and what's out? (for IETF/W3C)</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="15:30">Break</t>
	  <t hangText="16:00">II. COMSEC 1 &ndash; How can we increase
	  usage of current COMSEC tools? (Presenter: Hannes
	  Tschofenig; Moderator: Leif Johansson) <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s2-comsec.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>Whirlwind catalog of current tools</t>
	      <t>Why aren't people using them?  In what situations
	      are / aren't they used?</t>
	      <t>Securing AAA and management protocols &ndash; why not?</t>
	      <t>How can we (IETF/W3C/community) encourage more/better use?</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="17:30">Break</t>
	  <t hangText="17:45">III. Policy &ndash; What policy / legal/
	  other issues need to be taken into account? (Presenter:
	  Christine Runnegar; Moderator: Rigo Wenning) <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s3-policy.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>
	    <list style="symbols">
              <t>What non-technical activities do we need to be aware of?</t>
	      <t>How might such non-technical activities impact on IETF/W3C?</t>
	      <t>How might IETF/W3C activities impact on those
	      non-technical activities?</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="18:30">Session IV &ndash; Saturday plan,
	  open-mic, wrap up day</t>
	  <t hangText="19:00">Social event</t>
	  </list></t>
	<figure>
	  <preamble>Break out.</preamble>
	  <artwork alt="(foto: people around a big table)"
	  type="image/jpeg"
	  src="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/lib/workshop-4" />
	  <postamble><eref
	  target="http://www.stonehousephotographic.com/" >&copy;
	  Stonehouse Photographic</eref></postamble>
	</figure>
      </section>
      <section anchor="saturday" title="Saturday 1 March">
	<t>(<eref
	target="http://www.w3.org/2014/03/01-strint-minutes.html"
	>minutes</eref>)
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="09:00">Welcome again, logistics</t>
	    <t hangText="09:15">IV. COMSEC 2 &ndash; What improvements
	    to COMSEC tools are needed?(Presenter: Mark Nottingham;
	    Moderator: Steve Bellovin) <eref
	    target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s4-opportunistic.pdf"
	    >[slides]</eref>
	      <list style="symbols">
		<t>Opportunistic encryption &ndash; what is it and where it
		might apply</t>
		<t>Mitigations aiming to block PM vs. detect PM &ndash; when
		to try which?</t>
	      </list></t>
	  <t hangText="10:30">Break</t>
	  <t hangText="10:45">V. Metadata &ndash; How can we reduce
	  the metadata that protocols expose? (Presenter: Alfredo
	  Pironti <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s5-1metadata-pironti.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref> / Ted Hardie <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s5-2metadata-hardie.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>; Moderator: Alissa Cooper <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s5-3metadata-cooper.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>)
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>Meta-data, fingerprinting, minimisation</t>
	      <t>What's out there?</t>
	      <t>How can we do better?</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="12:00">Lunch (Buffet)</t>
	  <t hangText="13:00">VI. Deployment &ndash; How can we
	  address PM in deployment / operations? (Presenter: Eliot
	  Lear; Moderator: Barry Leiba) <eref
	  target="http://down.dsg.cs.tcd.ie/strint-slides/s6-deploy.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>&ldquo;Mega&rdquo;-commercial services (clouds, large
	      scale email &amp; SN, SIP, WebRTC&hellip;)</t>
	      <t>Target dispersal &ndash; good goal or wishful thinking?</t>
	      <t>Middleboxes: when a help and when a hindrance?</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="14:30">Break</t>
	  <t hangText="15:00">VII. 3 x Break-out Sessions / Bar-Camp
	  style (Hannes Tschofenig)
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>Content to be defined during meeting, as topics come up</t>
	      <t>Sum up at the end to gather conclusions for report</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="15:00">Break-outs:
	    <list style="numbers">
	      <t>Research Questions (Moderator:
	      Kenny Paterson)
		<list style="symbols">
		  <t>Do we need more/different crypto tools?</t>
		  <t>How can applications make better use of COMSEC tools?</t>
		  <t>What research topics could be handled in IRTF?</t>
		  <t>What other research would help?</t>
		</list></t>
	      <t>clients</t>
	      <t>on by default</t>
	      <t>measuring</t>
	      <t>opportunistic</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="16:15">VIII. Break-out reports, Open mic &amp;
	  Conclusions &ndash; What are we going to do to address PM?
	  <eref
	  target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/slides/summary.pdf"
	  >[slides]</eref>
	    <list style="symbols">
	      <t>Gather conclusions / recommendations / goals from
	      earlier sessions</t>
	    </list></t>
	  <t hangText="17:15">End</t>
	</list></t>
	<figure>
	  <preamble>Whiteboard notes.</preamble>
	  <artwork src="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/lib/workshop-5"
	  type="image/jpeg" alt="(foto: the back of somebody looking
	  at a whiteboard full of text and arrows)" />
	  <postamble><eref
	  target="http://www.stonehousephotographic.com/" >&copy;
	  Stonehouse Photographic</eref></postamble>
	</figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="papers" title="The submitted papers">

      <t><cref anchor="sort-papers" source="Bert">Group the papers by
      (rough) topic?</cref></t>

      <t>The following papers were submitted to the workshop. The
      abstracts were provided by the authors themselves. (We set up an
      <eref target="https://strint.pads.ccc.de/1">editable page
      (&ldquo;Etherpad&rdquo;)</eref> where the authors could insert them.)</t>

      <section title="Privacy Protected Email &ndash; Phillip Hallam-Baker">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/01.pdf"
	>01.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This proposal is two things: First it shows that with some
	small adjustments to S/MIME and PGP we can merge two competing
	end-to-end security proposals that are too hard for people to
	use into one scheme that provides a useful degree of security
	with no thought from the user. In cases where the user has
	security concerns they can easily determine that they are
	met. The second part of the proposal is that it the Trust set
	deployed to secure email encryption can be leveraged to solve
	pretty much every other end-to-end security requirement. If
	people generate keys for their email we can secure chat,
	video, 2-factor authentication as well.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Opportunistic Encryption for MPLS &ndash; Stephen Farrell, Adrian Farrrell">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/02.pdf"
	>02.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This is an early proposal for a way to do open-channel D-H
	key agreement and encryption in MPLS. Two things are maybe
	interesting: a) its an example of trying to add
	confidentiality to an existing protocol with making PM harder
	as a specific goal and b) maybe it shows that there could be a
	benefit in a generic protocol for after-the-fact MITM
	detection for such cases. It'd probably be most interesting to
	discuss (a) as one example of something we want to do more
	generally and not the specifics of MPLS at the workshop; and
	I'd be interested in whether or not (b) is tractable (I'm not
	sure).</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Overcoming the Friend-or-Foe Paradigm in Secure Communication &ndash; Sebastian Gajek, Jan Seedorf, Marc Fischlin, Oezguer Dagdalen">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/03.pdf"
	>03.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Essentially, our point is that with the existing
	end-to-end client-server security paradigm, e.g. as
	instantiated in TLS, the &ldquo;good guys&rdquo; often actually have to
	mount attacks in order for middleboxes (which are on the path
	between client ans server being able) to perform their
	job. The good guys are thus technically indistinguishable from
	the bad guys.</t>

	<t>Concretely, we are proposing to extend
	TLS in a way that would allow authorized modification of
	certain, dedicated parts of the TLS payload by middleboxes,
	while still allowing for integrity verification by
	clients. The crypto for such &ldquo;Interferable Secure
	Communication&rdquo; exists and we think it is feasible to extend
	TLS in this way in a reasonable timeframe.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Flows and Pervasive Monitoring &ndash; Ted Hardie">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/04.pdf"
	>04.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This document describes methods that may hinder a pervasive
	monitor's efforts to derive metadata from flows.  There are
	three main methods discussed in the paper: aggregation,
	contraflow, and multipath.  These are largely side-effects of
	other efforts at this time, but the paper discusses how they
	might fit into the design space of efforts intended to combat
	pervasive monitoring and the related consequences for network
	operations.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="BetterCrypto.org Applied Crypto Hardening &ndash; Aaron Zauner, L. Aaron Kaplan">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/05.pdf"
	>05.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	BetterCrypto is a community-driven project where admins,
	engineers, cryptographers, security researchers alike
	participate in finding well researched best-practices for
	commonly deployed networked applications and
	infrastructure. We try to outline a proper interim solution
	until better protocols and standards are widely deployed. Our
	hope is that we can contribute to a safer internet for all and
	better understanding of cryptographic primitives for the
	operations community that needs to deploy sound security on
	the public internet. Our focus group: sysadmins / ops.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="A Complimentary Analysis (The Danger Of The New Internet Choke Points) &ndash; Andrei Robachevsky, Christine Runnegar, Karen O'Donoghue, Mat Ford">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/06.pdf"
	>06.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	The ongoing disclosures of pervasive surveillance of
	Internet users' communications and data by national signals
	intelligence agencies have prompted protocol designers,
	software and hardware vendors, as well as Internet service and
	content providers, to re-evaluate prevailing security and
	privacy threat models and to refocus on providing more
	effective security and confidentiality. At IETF88, there was
	consensus to address pervasive monitoring as an attack and to
	consider the pervasive attack threat model when designing a
	protocol.  In this paper, we offer a complimentary
	analysis. We identify some of the components of the Internet
	architecture that provide attractive opportunities for
	wholesale monitoring and/or interception, and, therefore,
	represent architectural vulnerabilities, or choke points. We
	also suggest possible mitigation strategies and pose some of
	the questions that need to be considered if the Internet is to
	evolve to reduce such vulnerabilities. Finally, we identify
	some significant areas of tension or trade-offs, and we
	consider possible areas for additional efforts.  Also: <eref
	target="http://www.internetsociety.org/blog/tech-matters/2014/02/danger-new-internet-choke-points"
	>danger-new-internet-choke-points</eref> and <eref
	target="http://www.circleid.com/posts/20140218_mind_the_step_function_are_we_really_less_secure_than_a_year_ago/"
	>mind_the_step_function</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Trust Issues with Opportunistic Encryption &ndash; Scott Rose, Stephen Nightingale, Doug Montgomery">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/07.pdf"
	>07.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	&ldquo;Once is happenstance. Twice is coincidence. Three times is
	enemy action&rdquo;</t>

	<t>The lack of authentication in opportunistic encryption
	could have the perverse affect of putting more end users at
	risk: thinking that they are &ldquo;secure&rdquo;, an end user may divulge
	private information to an imposter instead of the service they
	believe they have contacted. When adding protection mechanisms
	to protocols, designers and implementers should not downplay
	the importance of authentication in order to make
	opportunistic encryption easier to deploy. We advocate that
	while opportunistic encryption can solve one set of problems,
	authentication is often desired by end users.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Challenges with End-to-End Email Encryption &ndash; Jiangshan Yu, Vincent Cheval, Mark Ryan">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/08.pdf"
	>08.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	In this paper we show how the use of an extended
	certificate transparency can build a secure end-to-end email
	or messaging system using PKI without requiring trusted
	parties nor complex p2p key-signing arrangements such as
	PGP. This makes end-to-end encrypted mail possible, and users
	do not need to understand or concern themselves with keys or
	certificates. In addition, we briefly present some related
	concerns i.e. metadata protection, key loss mitigation, spam
	detection, and the security of webmail.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Strengthening the path and strengthening the end-points &ndash; Xavier Marjou, Emile Stephan, Jean-Michel Combes, Iuniana Oprescu">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/09.pdf"
	>09.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Internet data is more and more subject to pervasive
	monitoring. This paper investigates ways of enhancing this
	situation depending on where such pervasive monitoring may
	occur. There are two different locations to secure: the
	endpoints and the path between these endpoints. In the present
	document, we also emphasize the fact that encryption, although
	bringing additional data confidentiality, might in some cases
	contradict security's two other pillars, which are
	availability and integrity.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="SIP is Difficult &ndash; Jon Peterson">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/10.pdf"
	>10.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	While SIP is widely used as a protocol for real-time
	communications, it is very difficult to secure from pervasive
	monitoring. In fact, one could argue that SIP's susceptibility
	to mass surveillance was essential to its success in the
	marketplace. This paper shows why SIP's design left the door
	open for eavesdropping, and what lessons RTCWeb could learn
	from this.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Thoughts of Strengthening Network Devices in
	the Face of Pervasive Surveillance &ndash; Dacheng Zhang, Fuyou
	Miao">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/11.pdf"
	>11.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	The material released by Edward Snowden has raised serious
	concerns about pervasive surveillance. People worry that their
	privacy is not properly protected when they are using the
	Internet. Network product vendors also encounter the doubts on
	the security of their products (e.g., routers, switches,
	firewalls). Such doubts are seriously damaging the Internet
	ecosystem. In this paper we try to analyze the affects brought
	by the Snowden scandal on our ability to trust products at the
	core of the Internet and discuss what the standard
	organization can do to help vendors address these security
	concerns.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Opportunistic Encryption for HTTP URIs &ndash;
	Mark Nottingham">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/12.pdf"
	>12.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This is a proposed method for using TLS with http:// URIs
	under discussion in the HTTPbis WG, in particular for HTTP/2
	but also applicable to HTTP/1. One of the biggest decisions to
	make is whether or not to require the certs to validate in
	this scenario.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Cyberdefense-Oriented Multilayer Threat
	Analysis &ndash; Yuji Sekiya, Daisuke Miyamoto, Hajime Tazaki">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/13.pdf"
	>13.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="A Threat Model for Pervasive Passive
	Surveillance &ndash; Brian Trammell, Daniel Borkmann, Christian
	Huitema">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/14.pdf"
	>14.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This document elaborates a threat model for pervasive
	surveillance, assuming an adversary with an interest in
	indiscriminate eavesdropping that can passively observe
	network traffic at every layer at every point in the network
	between the endpoints. We provide guidelines on evaluating the
	observability and inferability of information and
	metainformation radiated from Internet protocols. The central
	message to protocol designers: pervasive encryption for
	confidentiality, protocol and implementation design for
	simplicity and auditability, flexibility to allow
	fingerprinting resistance, and moving away from static
	identifiers can increase protocol-level resistance to
	pervasive surveillance.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Why Provable Transparency is Useful Against
	Surveillance &ndash; Ben Laurie">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/15.pdf"
	>15.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Withheld">
      </section>
      <section title="Monitoring message size to break privacy &ndash;
	Current issues and proposed solutions &ndash; Alfredo Pironti">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/17.pdf"
	>17.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	One of the Internet traffic features that can be easily
	collected by passive pervasive monitoring is the size of the
	exchanged messages, or the total bandwidth used by a
	conversation. Several works have showed that careful analysis
	of this data can break users' expected privacy, even for
	encrypted traffic. Despite this, little has been done in
	practice to hide message sizes, perhaps because deemed too
	inefficient or not a realistic threat.</t>

	<t>In this short paper,
	we contextualize message size analysis in the wider pervasive
	monitoring scenario, which encompasses other powerful analysis
	techniques, and we re-state the severity of the privacy breach
	that message size analysis constitutes. We finally discuss
	proposals to fix this issue, considering practical aspects
	such as required developer awareness, ease of deployment,
	efficiency, and interaction with other countermeasures.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Withheld">
      </section>
      <section title="Making The Internet Secure By Default &ndash;
	Michael H. Behringer, Max Pritkin, Steinthor Bjarnason">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/19.pdf"
	>19.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Pervasive monitoring on the Internet is enabled by the lack
	of general, fundamental security. In his presentation at the
	88th IETF Bruce Schneier called for ubiquitous use of security
	technologies to make pervasive monitoring too expensive and
	thus impractical. However, today security is too operationally
	expensive, and thus only used where strictly required. In this
	position paper we argue that all network transactions can be
	secure by default, with minimal or no operator
	involvement. This requires an autonomic approach where all
	devices in a domain enrol automatically in a trust
	domain. Once they share a common trust anchor they can secure
	communications between themselves, following a domain policy
	which is by default secure. The focus of this proposal is the
	network itself, with all protocols between network elements,
	including control plane protocols (e.g., routing protocols)
	and management plane protocols (e.g., SSH, netconf, etc). The
	proposal is evolutionary and allows a smooth migration from
	today's Internet technology, device by device.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Increasing HTTP Transport Confidentiality
	with TLS Based Alternate Services &ndash; Patrick McManus">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/20.pdf"
	>20.pdf</eref></t> <t></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Balance &ndash; Societal security versus
	individual liberty &ndash; Scott Cadzow">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/21.pdf"
	>21.pdf</eref></t> <t></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Strengthening the Extensible Messaging and
	Presence Protocol (XMPP) &ndash; Peter Saint-Andre">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/22.pdf"
	>22.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This document describes existing and potential future
	efforts at strengthening the Extensible Messaging and Presence
	Protocol (XMPP), for discussion at the W3C/IAB workshop on
	Strengthening the Internet Against Pervasive Monitoring
	(STRINT).</t>
      </section>
      <section title="The Internet We Want or the Internet We
	Deserve? &ndash; David Rogers">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/23.pdf"
	>23.pdf</eref></t> <t></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Beyond Encrypt Everything: Passive
	Monitoring &ndash; Mark Donnelly, Sam Hartman">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/24.pdf"
	>24.pdf</eref></t> <t></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Examining Proxies to Mitigate Pervasive
	Surveillance &ndash; Eliot Lear, Barbara Fraser">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/25.pdf"
	>25.pdf</eref> &ndash; The notion of pervasive surveillance
	assumes that it is possible for an attacker to have access to
	all links and devices between end points, as well as end
	points themselves. We examine this threat is some detail with
	an eye toward whether trusted intermediaries can provide
	relief from the attack. We go on to examine the costs
	associated with the various remediation methods. In at least
	one case, we challenge the notion that one should encrypt
	absolutely everything in all cases, as was implied in at least
	one threat analysis. Finally we summarize in a set of four
	principles that should be considered in future work.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Spontaneous Wireless Networking to Counter
	Pervasive Monitoring &ndash; Emmanuel Baccelli, Oliver Hahm,
	Matthias Waehlisch">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/26.pdf"
	>26.pdf</eref> &ndash; Several approaches can be employed to
	counter pervasive monitoring at large scale on the
	Internet. One category of approaches aims to harden the
	current Internet architecture and to increase the security of
	high profile targets (data centers, exchange points
	etc.). Another category of approaches aims instead for target
	dispersal, i.e. disabling systematic mass surveillance via the
	elimination of existing vantage points, thus forcing
	surveillance efforts to be more specific and
	personalized. This paper argues how networking approaches that
	do not rely on central entities &ndash; but rather on spontaneous
	interaction, as locally as possible, between autonomous peer
	entities &ndash; can help realize target dispersal and thus counter
	pervasive monitoring.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Is Opportunistic Encryption the Answer?
	Practical Benefits and Disadvantages &ndash; John Mattsson">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/27.pdf"
	>27.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	In this paper, we give an overview of various opportunistic
	and unauthenticated encryption techniques, and discuss their
	benefits, limits, and disadvantages. We recommend the Internet
	community to clearly define the term &ldquo;opportunistic
	encryption&rdquo; or to use other terms.  We conclude that while
	opportunistic and unauthenticated encryption certainly has its
	uses and may with the right choices provide good enough
	security for a low cost, general deployment of unauthenticated
	encryption is not an effective way to thwart pervasive
	monitoring.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Clearing off the Cloud over the Internet of
	Things &ndash; Carsten Bormann, Stefanie Gerdes, Olaf Bergmann">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/28.pdf"
	>28.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	As was foreshadowed by product introductions in 2013, the
	Consumer Electronics Show 2014 has seen the introduction of a
	large number of &ldquo;Internet of Things&rdquo; (IoT) innovations.
	Almost all of these have in common that they are meant to
	operate via Cloud-based services.  In the light of the recent
	attention to threats by state-level tenacious attackers with
	significant infrastructure (STASI), in particular to their
	practice of pervasive monitoring, we discuss the implications
	of a cloud-centric IoT landscape, and attempt to outline a set
	of principles as a program to improve the long-term
	outlook.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Withheld">
      </section>
      <section title="The Trust-to-Trust Model of Cloud Services &ndash;
	Alissa Cooper, Cullen Jennings">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/30.pdf"
	>30.pdf</eref></t> <t></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Linkability Considered Harmful &ndash; Leif
	Johansson">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/31.pdf"
	>31.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Current debate on pervasive monitoring often focus on
	passive attacks on the protocol and transport layers but even
	if these issues were eliminated through the judicious use of
	encryption, roughly the same information would still be
	available to an attacker who is able to (legally or otherwize)
	obtain access to linked data sets which are being maintained
	by large content and service providers.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Simple Opportunistic Encryption &ndash; Andrea
	Bittau, Michael Hamburg, Mark Handley, David Mazieres, Dan
	Boneh">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/32.pdf"
	>32.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Network traffic encryption is becoming a requirement, not
	an option.  Enabling encryption will be a communal effort so a
	solution that gives partial benefits until fully deployed is
	needed.  A solution that requires little changes to existing
	infrastructure will also help as it can be quickly deployed to
	give immediate short-term benefits.  We argue that tcpcrypt, a
	TCP option for opportunistic encryption is the path of
	least-resistance for a solution against large-scale traffic
	encryption.  Tcpcrypt requires no changes to applications, is
	compatible with existing networks (works with NATs), and just
	works by default.  It is high performance, so it can be
	deployed on servers without much concern.  tcpcrypt attempts
	to maximize security for any given setting.  By default, it
	will protect against passive eavesdropping, and also allows
	detecting large scale interception.  With authentication,
	tcpcrypt can provide full security against active attackers
	and so it is a complete solution both for the short-term and
	long-term.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="An Architecture for a Secure Cloud
	Collaboration System &ndash; Cullen Jennings, Suhas Nandakumar">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/33.pdf"
	>33.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	The Internet technical community is looking at ways to
	address pervasive attacks as described in several other
	internet drafts.  [I-D.barnes-pervasive-problem] describes
	threat model to characterize various pervasive attacks on the
	Internet communications.  There are many systems that need to
	be secured against such attacks but this paper considers one
	possible way to secure cloud based collaborations systems.  At
	a high level, this paper sugests that users or enterprises
	could run a key server that manages the keys to access their
	content.  The cloud service provider would not have access to
	decrypt the data stored in the cloud but various users of the
	cloud service could get the keys to encrypt and decrypt the
	contents of collaboration sessions facilitated by the cloud
	service.  This does not protect the meta data of who is
	talking to who but can help protect the content of the
	conversations.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Security and Simplicity &ndash; Steven Bellovin">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/34.pdf"
	>34.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Privacy at the Link Layer &ndash; Piers O'Hanlon,
	Joss Wright, Ian Brown">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/35.pdf"
	>35.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This paper gives an overview of the privacy issues around
	the use of link layer identifiers and associated
	protocols. Whilst the IETF generally specifies IP level
	protocols it does also address the link layer in protocols
	such as address resolution, network attachment detection,
	tunnelling and router redundancy.</t>

	<t>The indiscriminate
	broadcast of a device's MAC address, a unique and effectively
	personal identifier, allows for unregulated and broad-scale
	tracking of individuals via their personal devices, whether or
	not those devices have made use of a particular service or
	not. These addresses typically remain unchanged for the
	lifetime of a device, creating a persistent, lifelong tracking
	capability. The collation of such addresses, primarily WiFi
	and Bluetooth, has been been gathering pace and is already in
	use by organisations such as security agencies and
	advertisers.</t>

	<t>Ephemeral addresses are used further up the
	stack so why not at the link layer?  As default devices should
	use a randomised MAC address and any higher level associations
	can be maintained as and when approved by the user.  Moreover
	various other 'performance enhancing' approaches further
	degrade the privacy of individuals such as proactive discovery
	of WLAN SSIDs, Detection of Network Attachment (DNA), Wireless
	ISP roaming (WISPr), name lookups and so on.</t>

	<t>All these mechanisms need to be re-examined in the light of
	pervasive monitoring.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Erosion of the moral authority of
	middleboxes &ndash; Joe Hildebrand">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/36.pdf"
	>36.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Many middleboxes on the Internet attempt to add value to
	the connections that traverse that point on the
	network. Problems in their implementations erode the moral
	authority that otherwise might accrue to the legitimate value
	that they add.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Policy Responses, Implications and
	Opportunities &ndash; Joseph Lorenzo Hall &amp; Runa Sandvik">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/37.pdf"
	>37.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	We raise issues for discussion that lie in the interface
	between policy and technology. Specifically, we discuss 1)
	routing, processing and data localization policy mandates
	(i.e., new laws that may affect how data flows through the
	'net; 2) the uncertain possibility of dilution of credibility
	of IETF and w3c given what we've seen with NIST after
	NSA-coziness allegations; 3) the claim that strenghtening the
	internet and web will &ldquo;help the bad guys&rdquo; and the dubious need
	for &ldquo;lawful intercept&rdquo; funcationality; and 3) abusive content,
	cryptography as a controlled export technology, and the need
	to standardize more anonymity primitives (onion routing,
	pluggable transport protocols). We also highlight our own work
	in ensuring that technologists have a voice in policy
	environments and discuss a few interventions we coordinated
	over the past year, focusing on software backdoors and NSA
	surviellance.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Is it time to bring back the hosts file? &ndash;
	Peter Eckersley">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/38.pdf"
	>38.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Metaphors matter; application-layer;
	distribute more &ndash; Larry Masinter">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/39.pdf"
	>39.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	
	  <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Dont say Attack: IETF should stay away from political
	    theatre: changing protocols or workflows not because the
	    change works but just to say you did something. Metaphors
	    matter.</t>

	    <t>For most relevant threats, traffic analysis is enough,
	    and encyption doesnt mitigate.</t>

	    <t>The only deployable protection &ndash; if that is what is
	    wanted &ndash; means shifting architecture from client-server
	    to mesh.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Levels of Opportunistic Privacy Protection
	for Messaging-Oriented Architectures &ndash; Dave Crocker, Pete
	Resnick">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/40.pdf"
	>40.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Messaging protection against pervasive monitoring (PM)
	needs to cover primary payload, descriptive meta-data, and
	traffic-related analysis.  Complete protection against PM, for
	traffic through complex handling sequences, has not yet been
	achieved reliably in real-world operation.  Consequently, this
	document considers a range of end-to-end, object-based
	mechanisms, distinct from channel-based mechanisms. Each
	approach offers incremental protection levels that can be
	provided with existing, or low-risk, component technologies,
	such as through the DNS and MIME conventions.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Fingerprinting Guidance for Web
	Specification Authors &ndash; Nick Doty">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/41.pdf"
	>41.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	<eref
	target="http://w3c.github.io/fingerprinting-guidance/">http://w3c.github.io/fingerprinting-guidance/</eref> &ndash;
	Exposure of settings and characteristics of browsers can
	impact user privacy by allowing for browser
	fingerprinting. This document defines different types of
	fingerprinting, considers distinct levels of mitigation for
	the related privacy risks and provides guidance for Web
	specification authors on how to balance these concerns when
	designing new Web features.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Eradicating Bearer Tokens for Session Management &ndash; 
	Philippe De Ryck, Lieven Desmet, Frank Piessens, Wouter
	Joosen">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/42.pdf"
	>42.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Session management is a crucial component in every modern
	web application. It links multiple requests and temporary
	stateful information together, enabling a rich and interactive
	user experience. The de facto cookie-based session management
	mechanism is however flawed by design, enabling the theft of
	the session cookie through simple eavesdropping or script
	injection attacks. Possession of the session cookie gives an
	adversary full control the user's sover ession, allowing him
	to impersonate the user to the target application and perform
	transactions in the user's name. While several alternatives
	for secure session management exist, they fail to be adopted
	due to the introduction of additional roundtrips and overhead,
	as well as incompatibility with current Web technologies, such
	as third-party authentication providers, or widely deployed
	middleboxes, such as web caches.  We identify four key
	objectives for a secure session management mechanism, aiming
	to be compatible with the current and future Web. We propose
	SecSess, a lightweight session management mechanism based on a
	shared secret between client and server, used to authenticate
	each request. SecSess ensures that a session remains under
	control of the parties that established it, and only
	introduces limited overhead. During session establishment,
	SecSess introduces no additional roundtrips and only adds 4.3
	milliseconds to client-side and server-side processing. Once a
	session is established, the overhead becomes negligible
	(&lt;0.1ms), and the average size of the request headers is
	even smaller than with common session cookies. Additionally,
	SecSess works well with currently deployed systems, such as
	web caches and third-party services. SecSess also supports a
	gradual migration path, while remaining compatible with
	currently existing applications.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="STREWS Web-platform security guide: security
	assessment of the Web ecosystem &ndash; Martin Johns, Lieven
	Desmet">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/43.pdf"
	>43.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	In this document, we report on the Web-platform security
	guide, which has been developed within the EC-FP7 project
	STREWS. Based on their research, the STREWS consortium argues
	that in order to strengthening the Internet (e.g. against
	pervasive monitoring), it is crucial to also strengthen the
	web application ecosystem, the de-facto Internet application
	platform.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Pervasive Attack: A Threat Model and Problem
	Statement &ndash; Richard Barnes, Bruce Schneier, Cullen Jennings,
	Ted Hardie">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/44.pdf"
	>44.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Documents published in 2013 have revealed several classes
	of &ldquo;pervasive&rdquo; attack on Internet communications.  In this
	document, we review the main attacks that have been published,
	and develop a threat model that describes these pervasive
	attacks.  Based on this threat model, we discuss the
	techniques that can be employed in Internet protocol design to
	increase the protocols robustness to pervasive attacks.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Cryptech &ndash; Building a More Assured HSM with
	a More Assured Tool-Chain &ndash; Randy Bush">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/45.pdf"
	>45.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Replacing passwords on the Internet AKA
	post-Snowden Opportunistic Encryption &ndash; Ben Laurie, Ian
	Goldberg">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/46.pdf"
	>46.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="End-User Concerns about Pervasive Internet
	Monitoring: Principles and Practice &ndash; Tara Whalen, Stuart
	Cheshire, David Singer">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/47.pdf"
	>47.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This position paper will discuss pervasive monitoring on
	the Internet from the perspective of end users: what are
	overarching concerns around pervasive monitoring, and what are
	some steps that could be taken to address those concerns?  We
	begin by exploring a preliminary set of characteristics of
	systemic surveillance, which can be used to pinpoint dominant
	concerns of end users that should be addressed through
	technical means. We then illustrate one specific significant
	problem facing end users, namely that of certificate errors,
	which can be exploited to facilitate pervasive
	surveillance. We suggest that users should not be required to
	determine whether a certificate error is valid, but instead to
	block access to websites that generate such errors. We believe
	this approach would be more effective in protecting end users
	in an environment of persistent network threats.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Developer-Resistant Cryptography &ndash; Kelsey
	Cairns, Graham Steel">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/48.pdf"
	>48.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	&ldquo;Properly implemented strong crypto systems are one of the
	few things that you can rely on&rdquo; &ndash; Edward Snowden. So why is
	mass surveillance so successful? One (big) problem is endpoint
	security. Another is that strong crypto systems are
	sufficiently difficult to implement that often either mistakes
	are made resulting in catastrophic loss of security, or
	cryptography is not used at all. What can we do to make
	cryptography easier to use and more resistant to developer
	errors?</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Improving the reliability of key ownership
	assertions &ndash; Kai Engert">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/49.pdf"
	>49.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	A majority of today's secure Internet connections rely on
	Certificate Authorities not being abused for issueing false
	certificates (key ownership assertions), which might get
	abused for interception purposes, despite the risk of
	detection. I suggest to enhance Internet protocols with
	protective mechanisms to detect false key ownership
	assertions.  Ideas: (1) Using a network of proxy services, for
	example as implemented by the The Onion Router (Tor),
	consistency checking chould be performed by individual
	clients, in order to detect assertions that are likely false,
	prior to allowing a connection (see Detector.io). (2) Extend
	the idea that notary services provide a second opinion about
	the correctness of key ownership assertions, by requiring CAs
	to run such services (kuix.de/mecai).  (3) Implement protocol
	extensions, where client software reports previously seen key
	ownership assertions to the operators of services, allowing
	the discovery of false ownership assertions.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Mike O'Neill's Position Paper &ndash; Mike
	O'Neill">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/50.pdf"
	>50.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Detecting MITM Attacks on Ephemeral
	Diffie-Hellman without Relying on a PKI in Real-Time
	Communications &ndash; Alan Johnston">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/51.pdf"
	>51.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	With the recent revelations about pervasive surveillance on
	the Internet, there is renewed interest in techniques that
	protect against passive eavesdropping without relying on a
	Public Key Infrastructure (PKI). An ephemeral Diffie-Hellman
	(DH) key agreement can provide such protection, but (without
	authentication) the exchange is vulnerable to a Man in the
	Middle (MitM) attack. An example of a protocol that has MitM
	protection for a DH key agreement is ZRTP, RFC 6189, "ZRTP:
	Media Path Key Agreement for Unicast Secure RTP." ZRTP
	provides pervasive surveillance resistant security for Voice
	over IP (VoIP), video communication, and other real-time
	communication services. This paper describes the techniques
	used by ZRTP to detect MitM attacks, and explores whether
	these techniques could be used to develop a general MitM
	detection protocol to be used by other non-real-time
	communication protocols. An example of how ZRTP can provide
	MitM detection for another protocol, DTLS-SRTP, Datagram
	Transport Layer Security &ndash; Secure Real-time Transport
	Protocol, is given.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Trust &amp; Usability on the Web, a
	Social/Legal perspective &ndash; Rigo Wenning, Bert Bos">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/52.pdf"
	>52.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	(1) The browsers' UIs for security are very technical and
	seem to avoid saying anything useful, maybe so that the
	browsers and CAs cannot be held responsible. (2) A user
	wanting to configure security has difficulty finding the UI
	and then often discovers that settings are hard-coded or
	unclear. (3) The security model is based on trusting a few
	commercial entities and mistrusting the user, who ends up
	without control over his software if one of those entities is
	compromised or doesn't share his goals.  Conclusion: We need
	better UIs, which in turn requires a PKI that has the metadata
	and social aspects that help users understand and explore the
	keys and the organizations behind them.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Hardening Operations and Management Against
	Passive Eavesdropping &ndash; Bernard Aboba">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/53.pdf"
	>53.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Today within service providers protocols used for
	operations and management frequently send data in the clear,
	enabling the data to be collected by passive
	eavesdroppers. Examples of operations and management protocols
	include Authentication, Authorization and Accounting (AAA),
	syslog and Simple Networking Monitoring Protocol (SNMP). Since
	the publication of &ldquo;Operational Security Current Practices in
	Internet Service Provider Environments&rdquo; [RFC4778], the IETF
	has developed specifications that enable per-packet
	confidentiality to be applied to operations and management
	protocols. By developing updated operational guidance
	recommending deployment of per-packet confidentiality based on
	recent IETF Request for Comments (RFCs) and work-in-progress,
	the IETF can assist in bringing customer and regulatory
	pressure to bear in improving operational practices.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="A few theses regarding privacy and security
	&ndash; Andreas Kuckartz">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/54.pdf"
	>54.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Meet the new threat model, same as the old
	threat model &ndash; Eric Rescorla">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/55.pdf"
	>55.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	The Internet environment has a fairly well understood
	threat model. In general, we assume that the end-systems
	engaging in a protocol exchange have not themselves been
	compromised. Protecting against an attack when one of the
	end-systems has been compromised is extraordinarily
	difficult. It is, however, possible to design protocols which
	minimize the extent of the damage done under these
	circumstances.</t>

	<t>By contrast, we assume that the attacker has nearly
	complete control of the communications channel over which the
	end-systems communicate. This means that the attacker can read
	any PDU (Protocol Data Unit) on the network and undetectably
	remove, change, or inject forged packets onto the wire. This
	includes being able to generate packets that appear to be from
	a trusted machine. Thus, even if the end-system with which you
	wish to communicate is itself secure, the Internet environment
	provides no assurance that packets which claim to be from that
	system in fact are. &ndash; <xref target="RFC3552"/></t>
      </section>
      <section title="It's Time for Application-Centric Security &ndash;
	Yuan Gu, Harold Johnson">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/56.pdf"
	>56.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	An 'application' is an organized data/executable-code
	compound performing a specific function or service. We hold
	that applications should be protected intrinsically (by
	obfuscated, tamper-resistant code and data), as well as
	extrinsically (by encrypted communication, hardened hardware
	platforms, authenticated access). (1) Cloud-based applications
	are vulnerable to their hosting services or neighbors. (2)
	Peripheral-based applications (on phones, pads, PDAs, or more
	generally in the Internet of Things) are vulnerable because
	hardware security is inconsistent and very expensive to
	repair. (3) Browser-based applications are vulnerable because
	they run on potentially hostile or malware-infected browsers
	or platforms which we don't control.  Application obfuscations
	such as homomorphic transforms on data and computation (motto:
	avoid data or computation in plain form) and increased
	interdependency (motto: aggressive fragility under tampering)
	can effectively address these vulnerabilities.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Sabatini Monatesti position paper &ndash; Sabatine
	Monatesti">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/57.pdf"
	>57.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Trust problems in pervasive monitoring &ndash;
	Melinda Shore, Karen O'Donoghue">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/58.pdf"
	>58.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Beyond &quot;Just TLS Everywhere&quot;: From
	Client-encrypted Messaging to Defending the Social Graph &ndash;
	Harry Halpin, George Danezis">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/59.pdf"
	>59.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Network Security as a Public Good &ndash; Wendy
	Seltzer">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/60.pdf"
	>60.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Network security depends on cooperation of multiple actors
	in the Internet ecosystem. Standards consortia should support
	and help coordinate activity to protect the commons.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Statement of Interest on behalf of the W3C
	TAG &ndash; Dan Appelquist">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/61.pdf"
	>61.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Improving Security on the Internet &ndash; Hannes
	Tschofenig">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/62.pdf"
	>62.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Securing the Internet has been an on-going activity since
	the early days of the IETF and a variety of technical
	specifications have been standardized. Someone reading through
	IETF RFCs might easily get the impression that the Internet
	should be very secure. This is, however, not the entire story
	as the never-ending series of breaches and recently the
	Snowden revelations have illustrated. While on paper
	everything looks pretty good many problems can be found in
	implementations and with deployments.</t>

	<t>In this position paper the author makes the argument that
	improving the collaboration between different communities in
	the Internet software development life-cycle will be crucial
	for improving security on the Internet.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="Protecting customer data from government
	snooping &ndash; Orit Levin">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/63.pdf"
	>63.pdf</eref></t>
      </section>
      <section title="Privacy Aware Internet Development
	Initiative 2014 &ndash; Achim Klabunde">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/64.pdf"
	>64.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	Protecting privacy on the Internet requires more than using
	encryption. Protocols, implementations and applications must
	minimise the amount of personal data that is distributed and
	collected. Work is required to develop and disseminate privacy
	aware design and impmementation techniques to the actual
	developers. The paper is a call for interest for an initiative
	aiming to address this need, supported by privacy and
	technology experts.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="The Internet is Broken: Idealistic Ideas for
	Building a NEWGNU Network &ndash; Christian Grothoff, Bartlomiej
	Polot, Carlo von Loesch">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/65.pdf"
	>65.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This paper describes issues for security and privacy at all
	layers of the Internet stack and proposes radical changes to
	the architecture to build a network that offers strong
	security and privacy by default.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Opportunistic Keying as a Countermeasure to
	Pervasive Monitoring &ndash; Stephen Kent">

	<t><eref target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/papers/66.pdf"
	>66.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This document was prepared as part of the IETF response to
	concerns about &ldquo;pervasive monitoring&rdquo; as articulated in
	[draft-farrell-perpass-attack]. It begins by exploring
	terminology that has been used in IETF standards (and in
	academic publications) to describe encryption and key
	management techniques, with a focus on authentication
	vs. anonymity. Based on this analysis, it propose a new term,
	&ldquo;opportunistic keying&rdquo; (OK) to describe a goal for IETF
	security protocols, one possible countermeasure to pervasive
	monitoring. It reviews key management mechanisms used in IETF
	security protocol standards, with respect to these properties,
	to identify what changes might be needed to offer OK with
	minimal changes. The document ends by examining possible
	impediments to and potential adverse effects associated with
	deployment and use of techniques that would increase the use
	of encryption, even when keys are distributed in an
	unauthenticated manner.</t>
      </section>
<!--
      <section title="999: The Shadow Internet: liberation from Surveillance, Censorship and Servers &ndash; Johan Pouwelse">

	<t><eref
	target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-pouwelse-perpass-shadow-internet/" >.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This IETF Perpass
        document describes some scenarios and requirements for
        Internet hardening by creating what we term a shadow Internet,
        defined as an infrastructure in which the ability of
        governments to conduct indiscriminate eavesdropping or censor
        media dissemination is reduced.  Internet-deployed code is
        available for most components of this shadow Internet.  This
        18-page document is not available via the STRINT website.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="998: Privacy and Networking Functions &ndash; Jari Arkko">

	<t><eref
	target="http://www.arkko.com/ietf/strint/draft-arkko-strint-networking-functions.txt"
	>draft-arkko-strint-networking-functions.txt.pdf</eref> &ndash;
	This paper
	discusses the inherent tussle between network functions and
	some aspects of privacy.  There is clearly room for a much
	improved privacy in Internet communications, but there are
	also interesting interactions with network functions, e.g.,
	what information networks need to provide a service.
	Exploring these limits is useful to better understand
	potential improvements.</t>
      </section>
-->
    </section>
    <section anchor="committee" title="Workshop chairs &amp; program committee">
      <t>The workshop chairs were three: <eref
      target="https://www.cs.tcd.ie/Stephen.Farrell/" >Stephen
      Farrell</eref> (TCD) and <eref
      target="http://www.w3.org/People/Rigo/">Rigo Wenning</eref>
      (W3C) from the STREWS project, and <eref
      target="http://www.tschofenig.priv.at/wp/?page_id=5">Hannes
      Tschofenig</eref> (ARM) from the STREWS Interest Group.</t>

      <t>A program committee (PC) was charged with evaluating the
      submitted papers. It was made up of the members of the STREWS
      project, the members of the STREWS Interest Group, plus invited
      experts: Bernard Aboba (Microsoft), Dan Appelquist
      (Telef&oacute;nica &amp; W3C TAG), Richard Barnes (Mozilla),
      Bert Bos (W3C), Lieven Desmet (KU Leuven), Karen O'Donoghue
      (ISOC), Russ Housley (Vigil Security), Martin Johns (SAP), Ben
      Laurie (Google), Eliot Lear (Cisco), Kenny Paterson (Royal
      Holloway), Eric Rescorla (RTFM), Wendy Seltzer (W3C), Dave
      Thaler (Microsoft) and Sean Turner (IECA).</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="participants" title="Participants">
      <t>The participants to the workshop were: <list style="symbols">
	  <t><!-- Aboba, Bernard --> <spanx style="strong">Bernard Aboba</spanx> (Microsoft Corporation)</t>
	  <t><!-- Alkemade, Thijs --> <spanx style="strong">Thijs Alkemade</spanx> (Adium)</t>
	  <t><!-- Appelquist, Daniel --> <spanx style="strong">Daniel Appelquist</spanx> (Telef&oacute;nica Digital)</t>
	  <t><!-- Arkko, Jari --> <spanx style="strong">Jari Arkko</spanx> (Ericsson)</t>
	  <t><!-- Atlas, Alia --> <spanx style="strong">Alia Atlas</spanx> (Juniper Networks)</t>
	  <t><!-- Baccelli, Emmanuel --> <spanx style="strong">Emmanuel Baccelli</spanx> (INRIA)</t>
	  <t><!-- Barnes, Mary --> <spanx style="strong">Mary Barnes</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- Barnes, Richard --> <spanx style="strong">Richard Barnes</spanx> (Mozilla)</t>
	  <t><!-- Bellovin, Steve --> <spanx style="strong">Steve Bellovin</spanx> (Columbia University)</t>
	  <t><!-- Bittau, Andrea --> <spanx style="strong">Andrea Bittau</spanx> (Stanford University)</t>
	  <t><!-- Blanchet, Marc --> <spanx style="strong">Marc Blanchet</spanx> (Viagenie)</t>
	  <t><!-- Bormann, Carsten --> <spanx style="strong">Carsten Bormann</spanx> (Uni Bremen TZI)</t>
	  <t><!-- Bos, Bert --> <spanx style="strong">Bert Bos</spanx> (W3C)</t>
	  <t><!-- Brown, Ian --> <spanx style="strong">Ian Brown</spanx> (Oxford University)</t>
	  <t><!-- Bryant, Stewart --> <spanx style="strong">Stewart Bryant</spanx> (Cisco Systems)</t>
	  <t><!-- Bush, Randy --> <spanx style="strong">Randy Bush</spanx> (IIJ / Dragon Research Labs)</t>
	  <t><!-- Cairns, Kelsey --> <spanx style="strong">Kelsey Cairns</spanx> (Washington State University)</t>
	  <t><!-- Cheshire, Stuart --> <spanx style="strong">Stuart Cheshire</spanx> (Apple)</t>
	  <t><!-- Cheval, Vincent --> <spanx style="strong">Vincent Cheval</spanx> (University of Birmingham)</t>
	  <t><!-- Claise, Benoit --> <spanx style="strong">Benoit Claise</spanx> (Cisco)</t>
	  <t><!-- Cooper, Alissa --> <spanx style="strong">Alissa Cooper</spanx> (Cisco)</t>
	  <t><!-- Crocker, Dave --> <spanx style="strong">Dave Crocker</spanx> (Brandenburg InternetWorking)</t>
	  <t><!-- Daigle, Leslie --> <spanx style="strong">Leslie Daigle</spanx> (Internet Society)</t>
	  <t><!-- Danezis, George --> <spanx style="strong">George Danezis</spanx> (University College London)</t>
	  <t><!-- Dawkins, Spencer --> <spanx style="strong">Spencer Dawkins</spanx> (Huawei)</t>
	  <t><!-- Donnelly, Mark --> <spanx style="strong">Mark Donnelly</spanx> (Painless Security)</t>
	  <t><!-- Doty, Nick --> <spanx style="strong">Nick Doty</spanx> (W3C)</t>
	  <t><!-- Druta, Dan --> <spanx style="strong">Dan Druta</spanx> (AT&amp;T)</t>
	  <t><!-- Eckersley, Peter --> <spanx style="strong">Peter Eckersley</spanx> (Electronic Frontier Foundation)</t>
	  <t><!-- Eggert, Lars --> <spanx style="strong">Lars Eggert</spanx> (NetApp)</t>
	  <t><!-- Engert, Kai --> <spanx style="strong">Kai Engert</spanx> (Red Hat)</t>
	  <t><!-- Ermert, Monika --> <spanx style="strong">Monika Ermert</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- Farrell, Stephen --> <spanx style="strong">Stephen Farrell</spanx> (Trinity College Dublin)</t>
	  <t><!-- Fraser, Barbara --> <spanx style="strong">Barbara Fraser</spanx> (Cisco)</t>
	  <t><!-- Galindo, Virginie --> <spanx style="strong">Virginie Galindo</spanx> (gemalto)</t>
	  <t><!-- Gerdes, Stefanie --> <spanx style="strong">Stefanie Gerdes</spanx> (Uni Bremen TZI)</t>
	  <t><!-- Gillmor, Daniel Kahn --> <spanx style="strong">Daniel Kahn Gillmor</spanx> (ACLU)</t>
	  <t><!-- Grossman, Wendy M. --> <spanx style="strong">Wendy M. Grossman</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- Grothoff, Christian --> <spanx style="strong">Christian Grothoff</spanx> (The GNUnet Project)</t>
	  <t><!-- Hahm, Oliver --> <spanx style="strong">Oliver Hahm</spanx> (INRIA)</t>
	  <t><!-- Hall, Joseph Lorenzo --> <spanx style="strong">Joseph Lorenzo Hall</spanx> (Center for Democracy &amp; Technology)</t>
	  <t><!-- Hallam-Baker, Phillip --> <spanx style="strong">Phillip Hallam-Baker</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- Halpin, Harry --> <spanx style="strong">Harry Halpin</spanx> (W3C/MIT and IRI)</t>
	  <t><!-- Hardie, Ted --> <spanx style="strong">Ted Hardie</spanx> (Google)</t>
	  <t><!-- Hildebrand, Joe --> <spanx style="strong">Joe Hildebrand</spanx> (Cisco Systems)</t>
	  <t><!-- Housley, Russ --> <spanx style="strong">Russ Housley</spanx> (Vigil Security, LLC)</t>
	  <t><!-- Jennings, Cullen --> <spanx style="strong">Cullen Jennings</spanx> (CISCO)</t>
	  <t><!-- Johansson, Leif --> <spanx style="strong">Leif Johansson</spanx> (SUNET)</t>
	  <t><!-- Johnson, Harold --> <spanx style="strong">Harold Johnson</spanx> (Irdeto)</t>
	  <t><!-- Johnston, Alan --> <spanx style="strong">Alan Johnston</spanx> (Avaya)</t>
	  <t><!-- Kaplan, L. Aaron --> <spanx style="strong">L. Aaron Kaplan</spanx> (CERT.at)</t>
	  <t><!-- Kent, Steve --> <spanx style="strong">Steve Kent</spanx> (BBN Technologies)</t>
	  <t><!-- Klabunde, Achim --> <spanx style="strong">Achim Klabunde</spanx> (European Data Protection Supervisor)</t>
	  <t><!-- Kuhn, Hans --> <spanx style="strong">Hans Kuhn</spanx> (NOC)</t>
	  <t><!-- Larrinaga, Christian de --> <spanx style="strong">Christian de Larrinaga</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- Laurie, Ben --> <spanx style="strong">Ben Laurie</spanx> (Google)</t>
	  <t><!-- Lear, Eliot --> <spanx style="strong">Eliot Lear</spanx> (Cisco Ssytems)</t>
	  <t><!-- Leiba, Barry --> <spanx style="strong">Barry Leiba</spanx> (Huawei Technologies)</t>
	  <t><!-- Lekies, Sebastian --> <spanx style="strong">Sebastian Lekies</spanx> (SAP AG)</t>
	  <t><!-- Levin, Orit --> <spanx style="strong">Orit Levin</spanx> (Microsoft Corporation)</t>
	  <t><!-- lynX, carlo von --> <spanx style="strong">carlo von lynX</spanx> (#youbroketheinternet)</t>
	  <t><!-- Marjou, Xavier --> <spanx style="strong">Xavier Marjou</spanx> (Orange)</t>
	  <t><!-- Masinter, Larry --> <spanx style="strong">Larry Masinter</spanx> (Adobe)</t>
	  <t><!-- Mattsson, John --> <spanx style="strong">John Mattsson</spanx> (Ericsson)</t>
	  <t><!-- McManus, Patrick --> <spanx style="strong">Patrick McManus</spanx> (Mozilla)</t>
	  <t><!-- Montgomery, Doug --> <spanx style="strong">Doug Montgomery</spanx> (NIST)</t>
	  <t><!-- Moriarty, Kathleen --> <spanx style="strong">Kathleen Moriarty</spanx> (EMC)</t>
	  <t><!-- Muffett, Alec --> <spanx style="strong">Alec Muffett</spanx> (Facebook)</t>
	  <t><!-- Nandakumar, Suhas --> <spanx style="strong">Suhas Nandakumar</spanx> (Cisco Systems)</t>
	  <t><!-- Nguyen, Linh --> <spanx style="strong">Linh Nguyen</spanx> (ERCIM/W3C)</t>
	  <t><!-- Nordberg, Linus --> <spanx style="strong">Linus Nordberg</spanx> (NORDUnet)</t>
	  <t><!-- Nottingham, Mark --> <spanx style="strong">Mark Nottingham</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- O'Donoghue, Karen --> <spanx style="strong">Karen O'Donoghue</spanx> (Internet Society)</t>
	  <t><!-- O'Hanlon, Piers --> <spanx style="strong">Piers O'Hanlon</spanx> (Oxford Internet Institute)</t>
	  <t><!-- Paterson, Kenny --> <spanx style="strong">Kenny Paterson</spanx> (Royal Holloway, University of London)</t>
	  <t><!-- Peterson, Jon --> <spanx style="strong">Jon Peterson</spanx> (Neustar)</t>
	  <t><!-- Phillips, Joshua --> <spanx style="strong">Joshua Phillips</spanx> (University of Birmingham)</t>
	  <t><!-- Pironti, Alfredo --> <spanx style="strong">Alfredo Pironti</spanx> (INRIA)</t>
	  <t><!-- Polatin-Reuben, Dana --> <spanx style="strong">Dana Polatin-Reuben</spanx> (University of Oxford)</t>
	  <t><!-- Pouwelse, Prof. Johan --> <spanx style="strong">Prof. Johan Pouwelse</spanx> (Delft University of Technology)</t>
	  <t><!-- Pritikin, Max --> <spanx style="strong">Max Pritikin</spanx> (Cisco)</t>
	  <t><!-- Rescorla, Eric --> <spanx style="strong">Eric Rescorla</spanx> (Mozilla)</t>
	  <t><!-- Resnick, Pete --> <spanx style="strong">Pete Resnick</spanx> (Qualcomm Technologies, Inc.)</t>
	  <t><!-- Ristenpart, Tom --> <spanx style="strong">Tom Ristenpart</spanx> (University of Wisconsin)</t>
	  <t><!-- Robachevsky, Andrei --> <spanx style="strong">Andrei Robachevsky</spanx> (Internet Society)</t>
	  <t><!-- Rogers, David --> <spanx style="strong">David Rogers</spanx> (Copper Horse)</t>
	  <t><!-- Rose, Scott --> <spanx style="strong">Scott Rose</spanx> (NIST)</t>
	  <t><!-- Runnegar, Christine --> <spanx style="strong">Christine Runnegar</spanx> (Internet Society)</t>
	  <t><!-- Ryck, Philippe De --> <spanx style="strong">Philippe De Ryck</spanx> (DistriNet - KU Leuven)</t>
	  <t><!-- Saint-Andre, Peter --> <spanx style="strong">Peter Saint-Andre</spanx> (&amp;yet)</t>
	  <t><!-- Sandvik, Runa A. --> <spanx style="strong">Runa A. Sandvik</spanx> (Center for Democracy and Technology)</t>
	  <t><!-- Schlyter, Jakob --> <spanx style="strong">Jakob Schlyter</spanx> (&#12461;&#12524;&#12452;)</t>
	  <t><!-- Seedorf, Dr. Jan --> <spanx style="strong">Dr. Jan Seedorf</spanx> (NEC Laboratories Europe)</t>
	  <t><!-- Seltzer, Wendy --> <spanx style="strong">Wendy Seltzer</spanx> (W3C)</t>
	  <t><!-- Shore, Melinda --> <spanx style="strong">Melinda Shore</spanx> (No Mountain Software)</t>
	  <t><!-- Thaler, Dave --> <spanx style="strong">Dave Thaler</spanx> (Microsoft)</t>
	  <t><!-- Trammell, Brian --> <spanx style="strong">Brian Trammell</spanx> (ETH Zurich)</t>
	  <t><!-- Tschofenig, Hannes --> <spanx style="strong">Hannes Tschofenig</spanx> (ARM Limited)</t>
	  <t><!-- Turner, Sean --> <spanx style="strong">Sean Turner</spanx> (IECA, Inc.)</t>
	  <t><!-- W&auml;hlisch, Matthias --> <spanx style="strong">Matthias W&auml;hlisch</spanx> (Freie Universit&auml;t Berlin)</t>
	  <t><!-- Walton, Greg --> <spanx style="strong">Greg Walton</spanx> (Oxford University)</t>
	  <t><!-- Wenning, Rigo --> <spanx style="strong">Rigo Wenning</spanx> (W3C)</t>
	  <t><!-- Whalen, Tara --> <spanx style="strong">Tara Whalen</spanx> (Apple Inc.)</t>
	  <t><!-- Wood, Greg --> <spanx style="strong">Greg Wood</spanx> (Internet Society)</t>
	  <t><!-- Yu, Jiangshan --> <spanx style="strong">Jiangshan Yu</spanx> (University of Birmingham)</t>
	  <t><!-- Zauner, Aaron --> <spanx style="strong">Aaron Zauner</spanx></t>
	  <t><!-- Zhang, Dacheng --> <spanx style="strong">Dacheng Zhang</spanx> (Huawei)</t>
	  <t><!-- Zimmermann, Phil --> <spanx style="strong">Phil Zimmermann</spanx> (Silent Circle LLC)</t>
	  <t><!-- Zuniga, Juan-Carlos --> <spanx style="strong">Juan-Carlos Zuniga</spanx> (InterDigital)</t>
	</list></t>
    </section> 
  </back>
</rfc>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-indent-data:t
End:
-->
