<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-tls-oob-pubkey-08.txt" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="TLS OOB Public Key Validation">Out-of-Band Public Key Validation for Transport Layer Security (TLS)</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author role="editor" fullname="Paul Wouters" initials="P." surname="Wouters">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>paul@nohats.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>


        <author role="editor"  initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
            <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
                    <city>Espoo</city>
                    <code>02600</code>
                    <country>Finland</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
                <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
                <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
            </address>
        </author>


    <author fullname="John Gilmore" initials="J." surname="Gilmore">
      <organization />
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>PO Box 170608</street>
          <city>San Francisco</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>94117</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 415 221 6524</phone>
        <email>gnu@toad.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.toad.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Samuel Weiler" initials="S." surname="Weiler">
      <organization>SPARTA, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7110 Samuel Morse Drive</street>
          <city>Columbia, Maryland</city>
          <code>21046</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>weiler@tislabs.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

 <author initials="T." surname="Kivinen" fullname="Tero Kivinen">
            <organization>AuthenTec</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Eerikinkatu 28</street>
                    <city>HELSINKI</city>
                    <code>FI-00180</code>
                    <country>FI</country>
                </postal>
                <email>kivinen@iki.fi</email>
            </address>
        </author>
    <date year="2013" />


    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
         to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
         purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
         specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Security</area>

    <workgroup>TLS</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
         If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>TLS</keyword>
    <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
    <keyword>DANE</keyword>
    <keyword>Raw Public Key</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
         This document specifies a new certificate type for exchanging
         raw public keys in Transport Layer Security (TLS)
         and Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) for use with out-of-band
         public key validation. When using private/public key cryptography for 
authentication, TLS currently uses certified public keys either with X.509 certificates issued by a 
Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) or OpenPGP certificates. By specifying a minimum resource for raw
         public key exchange, implementations can use alternative public key validation
         methods.
      </t>
      <t>
         One such alternative public key valiation method is offered by the DNS-Based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE) together with DNS Security. Another alternative is to utilize pre-configured keys, as is the case with sensors and other
         embedded devices. The usage of raw public keys, instead of X.509-based certificates, leads to a smaller 
         code footprint. 
      </t>

      <t>This document introduces the support for raw public keys in TLS.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

   <middle>
    <section anchor="into" title="Introduction">
       <t>Traditionally, TLS server public keys are obtained in PKIX containers
          in-band using the TLS handshake and validated using trust anchors
          based on a  <xref target='PKIX'/> certification authority (CA). This
          method can add a complicated trust relationship that is difficult
          to validate. Examples of such complexity can be seen in
          <xref target='Defeating-SSL'/>.</t>

       <t>Alternative methods are available that allow a TLS client to obtain
          the TLS server public key:</t>

       <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The TLS server public key is obtained from a DNSSEC secured resource records              
             using DANE <xref target="RFC6698"/>.</t>

          <t>The TLS server public key is obtained from a <xref target='PKIX'/>
             certificate chain from an Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) <xref target="LDAP"/> server.</t>

          <t>The TLS client and server public key is provisioned into the operating system firmware image,
             and updated via software updates.</t>

          </list>
       </t>

       <t>Some smart objects use the UDP-based Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap"/> to
	      interact with a Web server to upload sensor data at a regular intervals, such as
          temperature readings. CoAP <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap"/> can utilize
          DTLS for securing the client-to-server communication. As part of the manufacturing process,
          the embeded device may be configured with the address and the public key of a
          dedicated CoAP server, as well as a public key for the client itself. 
		  The usage of X.509-based PKIX certificates <xref target='PKIX'/> may not suit all 
		  smart object deployments and would therefore be an unneccesarry burden.
       </t>
	   
	   <t>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/> provides
         a framework for extensions to TLS as well as guidelines for
         designing such extensions.  This document registers a new value to the IANA certificate types registry for the support of raw public keys. </t>
      </section>
	  
      <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>


    <section title="New TLS Extension">
  <t>This section describes the changes to the TLS handshake message contents when raw public key certificates are to be used.
<xref target="flow"/> illustrates the exchange of messages as described in the sub-sections below. The client and the server exchange make use of two new TLS extensions, namely 'client_certificate_type' and 'server_certificate_type', and an already available IANA TLS Certificate Type registry <xref target="TLS-Certificate-Types-Registry"/> to indicate their ability and desire to exchange raw public keys. These raw public keys, in the form of a SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure, are then carried inside the Certificate payload. The Certificate and the SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure is shown in <xref target="Certificate"/>.
</t>   
   
<t>
<figure anchor="Certificate" title="TLS Certificate Structure.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[    
opaque ASN.1Cert<1..2^24-1>;

struct {
 	select(certificate_type){
        
		// certificate type defined in this document.
    	case RawPublicKey:      		
          opaque ASN.1_subjectPublicKeyInfo<1..2^24-1>;
		
		// X.509 certificate defined in RFC 5246
        case X.509:
		  ASN.1Cert certificate_list<0..2^24-1>;	 
		  
		// Additional certificate type based on TLS 
        // Certificate Type Registry		
 	};
} Certificate;
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
     
<t>The SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure is defined in Section 4.1 of RFC 5280 <xref target="PKIX"/> and does not only contain the raw keys, such as the public exponent and the modulus of an RSA public key, but also an algorithm identifier. The structure, as shown in <xref target="SubjectPublicKeyInfo"/>, is encoded in an ASN.1 format and therefore contains length information as well. An example is provided in <xref target="Example"/>.</t>

<t>
<figure anchor="SubjectPublicKeyInfo" title="SubjectPublicKeyInfo ASN.1 Structure.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[    
   SubjectPublicKeyInfo  ::=  SEQUENCE  {
        algorithm            AlgorithmIdentifier,
        subjectPublicKey     BIT STRING  }
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

  <t>The algorithm identifiers are Object Identifiers (OIDs). RFC 3279 <xref target="RFC3279"/>, for example, defines the following OIDs shown in <xref target="alg-ids"/>.</t>
  <t>
<figure anchor="alg-ids" title="Example Algorithm Identifiers.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[    
Key Type               | Document                   | OID
-----------------------+----------------------------+-------------------
RSA                    | Section 2.3.1 of RFC 3279  | 1.2.840.113549.1.1
.......................|............................|...................
Digital Signature      |                            |
Algorithm (DSS)        | Section 2.3.2 of RFC 3279  | 1.2.840.10040.4.1
.......................|............................|...................
Elliptic Curve         |                            |
Digital Signature      |                            |
Algorithm (ECDSA)      | Section 2.3.5 of RFC 3279  | 1.2.840.10045.2.1
-----------------------+----------------------------+-------------------
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

  <t>The message exchange in <xref target="flow"/> shows the 'client_certificate_type' and 'server_certificate_type' extensions added to the client and server hello messages. 
  
<figure anchor="flow" title="Basic Raw Public Key TLS Exchange.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
 client_hello, 
 client_certificate_type
 server_certificate_type   ->

                           <-  server_hello,
                               client_certificate_type,
                               server_certificate_type,
                               certificate,
                               server_key_exchange,
                               certificate_request,
                               server_hello_done
 certificate,
 client_key_exchange,
 certificate_verify,
 change_cipher_spec,
 finished                  ->

                           <- change_cipher_spec,
                              finished

Application Data        <------->     Application Data
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

   <t>
   
   The semantic of the two extensions is defined as follows:
   <list style="empty"> 

   <t>The 'client_certificate_type' and 'server_certificate_type' sent in the client hello, may carry a list of supported certificate types, sorted by client preference. It is a list in the case where the client supports multiple certificate types.
These extension MUST be omitted if the client only supports X.509 certificates. The 'client_certificate_type' sent in the client hello indicates the certificate types the client is able to provide to the server, when requested using a certificate_request message. The 'server_certificate_type' in the client hello indicates the type of certificates the client is able to process when provided by the server in a subsequent certificate payload. </t>

   <t>The 'client_certificate_type' returned in the server hello indicates the certificate type found in the attached certificate payload. Only a single value is permitted. The 'server_certificate_type' in the server hello indicates the type of certificates the client is requested to provide in a subsequent certificate payload. The value conveyed in the 'server_certificate_type' MUST be selected from one of the values provided in the 'server_certificate_type' sent in the client hello. If the server does not send a certificate_request payload or none of the certificates supported by the client (as indicated in the 'server_certificate_type' in the client hello) match the server-supported certificate types the 'server_certificate_type' payload sent in the server hello is omitted.</t>
   </list> 
   </t> 
   
   <t>The
   "extension_data" field of this extension contains the ClientCertTypeExtension or the ServerCertTypeExtension
   structure, as shown in <xref target="types"/>. The CertificateType structure is an enum with with values from TLS Certificate Type Registry. </t>

<!-- 

// Enum with values from TLS Certificate Type Registry
enum { 
   	  X.509 (0), 
   	  OpenPGP (1),
   	  RawPublicKey (TBD),
      (255)
} CertificateType;

--> 
   
<t>
<figure anchor="types" title="CertTypeExtension Structure.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[
struct {
        select(ClientOrServerExtension)
            case client:
              CertificateType client_certificate_types<1..2^8-1>;
            case server:
              CertificateType client_certificate_type;
        }
} ClientCertTypeExtension;

struct {
        select(ClientOrServerExtension)
            case client:
              CertificateType server_certificate_types<1..2^8-1>;
            case server:
              CertificateType server_certificate_type;
        }
} ServerCertTypeExtension;   
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

<t>No new cipher suites are required to use raw public keys.  All
   existing cipher suites that support a key exchange method compatible
   with the defined extension can be used.</t>

</section>

   <section title="TLS Handshake Extension">
   
  <section title="Client Hello">

   <t>
   In order to indicate the support of out-of-band raw public keys,
   clients MUST include the 'client_certificate_type' and 'server_certificate_type' extensions extended
   client hello message. The hello extension mechanism is described in TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/>.
   </t>


</section>

<section title="Server Hello">

<t>If the server receives a client hello that contains the 'client_certificate_type' and 'server_certificate_type' 
   extensions and chooses a cipher suite then three outcomes are possible:
   
   <list style="numbers"> 
   <t>The server does not support the extension defined in this document. In this case the server returns the server hello 
   without the extensions defined in this document.</t>
   <t>The server supports the extension defined in this document and has at least one certificate type in common with the client. 
   In this case it returns the 'server_certificate_type' and indicates the selected certificate type value. 
   </t> 
   <t>The server supports the extension defined in this document but does not have a certificate type in common with the client. In this case the server terminate the session with a
   fatal alert of type "unsupported_certificate".</t>
   </list> 
   </t> 
   
<t>If the TLS server also requests a certificate from the client (via the certificate_request) it MUST include the 'client_certificate_type' extension with a value chosen from the list of client-supported certificates types (as provided 
in the 'client_certificate_type' of the client hello). 
</t>

<t>If the client indicated the support of raw public keys in the 'client_certificate_type' extension in the client hello and the server is able to provide such raw public key then the TLS server MUST place the SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure into the Certificate payload. The public key algorithm MUST match the selected key exchange algorithm.</t>

</section>

<section title="Certificate Request">

<t>
   The semantics of this message remain the same as in the TLS
   specification.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Other Handshake Messages">

<t>All the other handshake messages are identical to the TLS
   specification.</t>

</section>

<section title="Client authentication">

<t>Client authentication by the TLS server is supported only through
   authentication of the received client SubjectPublicKeyInfo via an
   out-of-band method.</t>
</section>

 </section>


	  <!-- ******************************************************************************************** -->


<section title="Examples">

<t><xref target="flow1"/>, <xref target="flow2"/>, and <xref target="flow3"/> illustrate example exchanges. </t> 
   
<!--  <t> 
    The "RawPublicKey" value
   in the 'raw-public-key' extension allows the client to provide an 
   indication to the server that it supports the raw public key extension 
   in this document. The server responds with a certificate payload that 
   contains the raw public key as defined in this document. 
   Note that the certificate payloads only 
   contain the SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure instead of the entire
   certificate. 
  </t>
  
  --> 
  
  <t>The first example shows an exchange where the TLS client indicates its ability to 
  receive and validate raw public keys from the server. In our example the client is quite restricted since it is unable to process other certificate types sent by the server. It also does not have credentials (at the TLS layer) it could send. The 'client_certificate_type' extension indicates this in [1]. When the TLS server receives the client hello it 
  processes the 'client_certificate_type' extension. Since it also has a raw public key it indicates 
  in [2] that it had choosen to place the SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure into the Certificate 
  payload [3]. The client uses this raw public key in the TLS handshake and an out-of-band technique, 
  such as DANE, to verify its validity.</t>
  
  <t>
<figure anchor="flow1" title="Example with Raw Public Key provided by the TLS Server">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
client_hello,
server_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey) -> // [1]

                         <-  server_hello,
                             server_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey), // [2]
                             certificate, // [3]
                             server_key_exchange,
                             server_hello_done

client_key_exchange,
change_cipher_spec,
finished                  ->

                         <- change_cipher_spec,
                            finished

Application Data        <------->     Application Data
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

 <t>In our second example the TLS client as well as the TLS server use raw public keys. This is a use case envisioned for smart object networking. The TLS client in this case is an embedded device that is configured with a raw public key for use with TLS and is also able to process raw public keys sent by the server. Therefore, it indicates these capabilities in [1]. As in the previously shown example the server fulfills the client's request, indicates this via the "RawPublicKey" value in the server_certificate_type payload, and provides a raw public key into the Certificate payload back to the client (see [3]). The TLS server, however, demands client authentication and therefore a certificate_request is added [4]. The certificate_type payload in [2] indicates that the TLS server accepts raw public keys. The TLS client, who has a raw public key pre-provisioned, 
returns it in the Certificate payload [5] to the server.</t> 
<t>
<figure anchor="flow2" title="Example with Raw Public Key provided by the TLS Server and the Client">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
client_hello,
client_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey) // [1]
server_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey) // [1]
                         -> 
                         <-  server_hello,
                             server_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey)//[2]
                             certificate, // [3]
                             client_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey)//[4]
                             certificate_request, // [4]
                             server_key_exchange,
                             server_hello_done

certificate, // [5]
client_key_exchange,
change_cipher_spec,
finished                  ->

                         <- change_cipher_spec,
                            finished

Application Data        <------->     Application Data
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

<t>In our last example we illustrate a combination of raw public key and X.509 usage. The client uses a raw public key 
for client authentication but the server provides an X.509 certificate. This exchange starts with the client indicating its ability to process X.509 certificates provided by the server, and the ability to send raw public keys (see [1]). The server provides the X.509 certificate in [3] with the indication present in [2]. For client authentication the server indicates in [4] that it selected the raw public key format and requests a certificate from the client in [5]. The TLS client provides a raw public key in [6] after receiving and processing the TLS server hello message.</t>

 <t>
<figure anchor="flow3" title="Hybrid Certificate Example">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
client_hello,
server_certificate_type=(X.509)
client_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey) // [1] 
                         ->
                         <-  server_hello,
                             server_certificate_type=(X.509)//[2]
                             certificate, // [3]
                             client_certificate_type=(RawPublicKey)//[4]
                             certificate_request, // [5]
                             server_key_exchange,
                             server_hello_done
certificate, // [6]
client_key_exchange,
change_cipher_spec,
finished                  ->

                          <- change_cipher_spec,
                             finished

Application Data        <------->     Application Data
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>


</section> 



    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">

	<t>The transmission of raw public keys, as described in this document, 
	provides benefits by lowering the over-the-air transmission overhead since 
	raw public keys are quite naturally smaller than an entire certificate. 
	There are also advantages from a codesize point of view for parsing and
    processing these keys. The crytographic procedures for assocating the 
	public key with the possession of a private key also follows standard 
	procedures.</t>

    <t>The main security challenge is, however, how to associate the public 
    key with a specific entity. This information will be needed to make 
    authorization decisions. Without a secure binding, man-in-the-middle 
    attacks may be the consequence. This document assumes that such 
	binding can be made out-of-band and we list a few examples in <xref target="into"/>. 
	DANE <xref target="RFC6698"/> offers one such approach. 
	If public keys are obtained using DANE, these public keys are authenticated via DNSSEC.
	Pre-configured keys is another out of band method for authenticating raw public keys.
	 While pre-configured keys are not suitable for 
	a generic Web-based e-commerce environment such keys are a reasonable approach
	for many smart object deployments where there is a close relationship between 
	the software running on the device and the server-side communication endpoint. 
	Regardless of the chosen mechanism for out-of-band public key validation an 
	assessment of the most suitable approach has to be made prior to the start of a 
	deployment to ensure the security of the system.</t>
	
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is asked to register a new value in the "TLS Certificate Types"
registry of Transport Layer Security (TLS) Extensions <xref target="TLS-Certificate-Types-Registry"/>,
as follows:
<figure>
<artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
Value: 2
Description: Raw Public Key
Reference: [[THIS RFC]]
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

     <t>
   This document asks IANA to allocate two new TLS extensions, "client_certificate_type" and "server_certificate_type", from the TLS ExtensionType registry defined in <xref target="RFC5246"/>.
   These extensions are used in both
   the client hello message and the server hello message.  The new
   extension type is used for certificate type negotiation. The values carried in these extensions 
   are taken from the TLS Certificate Types registry <xref target="TLS-Certificate-Types-Registry"/>. </t>
    </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acknowledgements">
      <t>The feedback from the TLS working group meeting at IETF#81 has 
	     substantially shaped the document and we would like to thank the 
	     meeting participants for their input.  The support for hashes of 
	     public keys has been moved to <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-cached-info"/> after the discussions at the IETF#82 
	     meeting.</t>
	     
      <t>We would like to thank the following persons for their review comments: Martin Rex, Bill Frantz, Zach Shelby, 
	     Carsten Bormann, Cullen Jennings, Rene Struik, Alper Yegin, Jim Schaad, Barry Leiba, Paul Hoffman, Robert Cragie, Nikos Mavrogiannopoulos, Phil Hunt, John Bradley, Klaus Hartke, Stefan Jucker, Kovatsch Matthias, Daniel Kahn Gillmor, Peter Sylvester, and James Manger. Nikos Mavrogiannopoulos contributed the design for re-using the certificate type registry. Barry Leiba contributed guidance for the IANA consideration text. Stefan Jucker, Kovatsch Matthias, and Klaus Hartke provided implementation feedback regarding the SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure.</t>
	  <t>Finally, we would like to thank our TLS working group chairs, Eric Rescorla and Joe Salowey, for their guidance and support.</t>
      </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml"?>

  <reference anchor='TLS-Certificate-Types-Registry' target='http://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-extensiontype-values#tls-extensiontype-values-2'>
       <front>
       <title>TLS Certificate Types Registry</title>
       <author initials='' surname='' fullname='IANA'>
       <organization /></author>
       <date year='2013' month='February' />
       </front>
       <format type='HTML' target='http://www.iana.org/assignments/tls-extensiontype-values#tls-extensiontype-values-2' />
    </reference>

   <reference anchor='PKIX'>
      <front>
      <title>Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile</title>
      <author initials='D.' surname='Cooper' fullname='D. Cooper'>
      <organization /></author>
      <author initials='S.' surname='Santesson' fullname='S. Santesson'>
      <organization /></author>
      <author initials='S.' surname='Farrell' fullname='S. Farrell'>
      <organization /></author>
      <author initials='S.' surname='Boeyen' fullname='S. Boeyen'>
      <organization /></author>
      <author initials='R.' surname='Housley' fullname='R. Housley'>
      <organization /></author>
      <author initials='W.' surname='Polk' fullname='W. Polk'>
      <organization /></author>
      <date year='2008' month='May' />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5280' />
      <format type='TXT' octets='352580' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5280.txt' />
   </reference>


</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3279.xml"?> 
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6698.xml"?>  
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-core-coap.xml"?>  
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-cached-info.xml"?>  


   <reference anchor='LDAP'>
      <front>
      <title>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): The Protocol</title>
      <author initials='J.' surname='Sermersheim' fullname='J. Sermersheim'>
      <organization /></author>
      <date year='2006' month='June' />      
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4511' />
      <format type='TXT' octets='150116' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4511.txt' />
   </reference>
   
    <reference anchor='Defeating-SSL' target='http://www.blackhat.com/presentations/bh-dc-09/Marlinspike/BlackHat-DC-09-Marlinspike-Defeating-SSL.pdf'>
       <front>
       <title>New Tricks for Defeating SSL in Practice</title>
       <author initials='M.' surname='Marlinspike' fullname='Moxie Marlinspike'>
       <organization /></author>
       <date year='2009' month='February' />
       </front>
       <format type='PDF' target='http://www.blackhat.com/presentations/bh-dc-09/Marlinspike/BlackHat-DC-09-Marlinspike-Defeating-SSL.pdf' />
    </reference>

    <reference anchor='ASN.1-Dump' target='http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/'>
       <front>
       <title>ASN.1 Object Dump Program</title>
       <author initials='P.' surname='Gutmann' fullname='Peter Gutmann'>
       <organization /></author>
       <date year='2013' month='February' />
       </front>
       <format type='HTML' target='http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/' />
    </reference>
    
    
    
</references>
<section anchor="Example" title="Example Encoding"> 

<t>For example, the following hex sequence describes a SubjectPublicKeyInfo structure inside the certificate payload:
<figure anchor="example1" title="Example SubjectPublicKeyInfo Structure Byte Sequence.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[
       0     1     2     3     4     5     6     7     8     9
---+------+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----
1  | 0x30, 0x81, 0x9f, 0x30, 0x0d, 0x06, 0x09, 0x2a, 0x86, 0x48, 
2  | 0x86, 0xf7, 0x0d, 0x01, 0x01, 0x01, 0x05, 0x00, 0x03, 0x81, 
3  | 0x8d, 0x00, 0x30, 0x81, 0x89, 0x02, 0x81, 0x81, 0x00, 0xcd, 
4  | 0xfd, 0x89, 0x48, 0xbe, 0x36, 0xb9, 0x95, 0x76, 0xd4, 0x13, 
5  | 0x30, 0x0e, 0xbf, 0xb2, 0xed, 0x67, 0x0a, 0xc0, 0x16, 0x3f, 
6  | 0x51, 0x09, 0x9d, 0x29, 0x2f, 0xb2, 0x6d, 0x3f, 0x3e, 0x6c, 
7  | 0x2f, 0x90, 0x80, 0xa1, 0x71, 0xdf, 0xbe, 0x38, 0xc5, 0xcb, 
8  | 0xa9, 0x9a, 0x40, 0x14, 0x90, 0x0a, 0xf9, 0xb7, 0x07, 0x0b, 
9  | 0xe1, 0xda, 0xe7, 0x09, 0xbf, 0x0d, 0x57, 0x41, 0x86, 0x60, 
10 | 0xa1, 0xc1, 0x27, 0x91, 0x5b, 0x0a, 0x98, 0x46, 0x1b, 0xf6, 
11 | 0xa2, 0x84, 0xf8, 0x65, 0xc7, 0xce, 0x2d, 0x96, 0x17, 0xaa, 
12 | 0x91, 0xf8, 0x61, 0x04, 0x50, 0x70, 0xeb, 0xb4, 0x43, 0xb7, 
13 | 0xdc, 0x9a, 0xcc, 0x31, 0x01, 0x14, 0xd4, 0xcd, 0xcc, 0xc2, 
14 | 0x37, 0x6d, 0x69, 0x82, 0xd6, 0xc6, 0xc4, 0xbe, 0xf2, 0x34, 
15 | 0xa5, 0xc9, 0xa6, 0x19, 0x53, 0x32, 0x7a, 0x86, 0x0e, 0x91, 
16 | 0x82, 0x0f, 0xa1, 0x42, 0x54, 0xaa, 0x01, 0x02, 0x03, 0x01, 
17 | 0x00, 0x01
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

<t>The decoded byte-sequence shown in <xref target="example1"/> (for example using Peter's ASN.1 decoder <xref target="ASN.1-Dump"/>) illustrates the structure, as shown in <xref target="example2"/>.

<figure anchor="example2" title="Decoding of Example SubjectPublicKeyInfo Structure.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[ 
Offset  Length   Description
-------------------------------------------------------------------
   0     3+159:   SEQUENCE {
   3      2+13:     SEQUENCE {
   5       2+9:      OBJECT IDENTIFIER Value (1 2 840 113549 1 1 1)
              :             PKCS #1, rsaEncryption
  16       2+0:      NULL
              :      }
  18     3+141:    BIT STRING, encapsulates {
  22     3+137:      SEQUENCE {
  25     3+129:        INTEGER Value (1024 bit)
 157       2+3:        INTEGER Value (65537)
              :        }
              :      }
              :    }              
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

</section> 

  </back>
</rfc>
