<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
<!ENTITY RFC2284 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2284.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4849 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4849.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3575 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3575.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2607 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2607.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3579 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3579.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3580 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3580.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6158 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6158.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-lior-radius-prepaid-extensions-21.txt">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Prepaid Extentions for RADIUS">Prepaid Extensions to Remote Authentication
            Dial-In User Service (RADIUS)</title>
        <author initials="A." surname="Lior" fullname="Avi Lior">
            <organization>Independent</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                  <street/>
                  <city/>
                  <region/>
                  <code/>
                  <country/>
                </postal>        
                <email>avi.ietf@lior.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="P." surname="Yegani" fullname="Parviz Yegani">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                <street/>
                <city/>
                <region/>
                <code/>
                <country/>
            </postal>        
            <email>pyegani@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="K." surname="Chowdhury" fullname="Kuntal Chowdhury">
            <organization abbrev="Starent Networks">Starent Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>30 International Place, 3rd Floor</street>
                    <city>Tewksbury</city>
                    <region>MA</region>
                    <code>01876</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <email>kchowdhury@starentnetworks.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
            <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
                    <city>Espoo</city>
                    <code>02600</code>
                    <country>Finland</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
                <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
                <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Pashalidis" fullname="Andreas Pashalidis">
            <organization abbrev="KUL">K.U.Leuven, ESAT/SCD/COSIC</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Kasteelpark Arenberg 10, bus 2446</street>
                    <city>Leuven-Heverlee</city>
                    <code>B-3001</code>
                    <country>Belgium</country>
                </postal>
                <email>andreas.pashalidis@esat.kuleuven.be</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2012"/>
<!--        <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
        <workgroup>RADEXT</workgroup> --> 
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t> This document specifies an extension to the Remote Authentication Dial-In User
                Service (RADIUS) protocol that enables service providers to charge for prepaid
                services. The supported charging models supported are volume-based, duration-based,
                and based on one-time events. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
            <t> This document specifies an extension to the RADIUS protocol that enables service
                providers to perform accounting and charging in an "online" fashion. In particular,
                they enable the service provider to </t>
            <t>
                <list style="empty">
                    <t>(a) ensure that subscriber's remaining funds suffice before the service is
                        delivered, and </t>
                    <t>(b) interrupt service provision when the funds are exhausted.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>These capabilities are typically used in scenarios where the subscriber
                maintains a prepaid account with the service provider; hence, this extension is
                called the "prepaid" extension for RADIUS. The functionality described in this
                document is often referred as "online charging" in comparison to "offline charging"
                support provided by RFC 2866 <xref target="RFC2866"/>.</t>
                
            <t>Note that this document does not follow the RADIUS design guidelines outlined in 
            RFC 6158 <xref target="RFC6158"/> since this document predates RFC 6158 and documents 
            existing implementations.</t> 
            
            <t>The extensions were designed with the following goals in mind: </t>
            <t>
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t> Make use of existing infrastructure as much as possible (including enabling
                        the interworking of RADIUS-based and Diameter-based infrastructures), and
                        thereby limit the amount of necessary capital expenditures, </t>
                    <t> provide the ability to rate service requests in an "online" fashion,</t>
                    <t> provide the ability to charge the user's account prior to service provision,</t>
                    <t> protect against revenue loss, i.e., to prevent an end user from obtaining
                        service when the available funds do not suffice, </t>
                    <t> protect against fraud, and </t>
                    <t> be deployable for a number of services independent of the access network
                        technology. </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> The architecture between the entities that execute the RADIUS protocols, with the
                extensions defined in this document, assumes that the rating of chargeable events
                does not occur in the element that provides the service. Instead, the rating may be
                performed at a dedicated server, termed the "prepaid-enabled AAA server" or simply
                "prepaid server" (PPS). Alternatively, the actual rating may occur in an entity
                related to this prepaid server.</t>
            <t> Furthermore, this document assumes that a "quota server" is available which, through
                co-ordination with the rating entity and an account balance manager, is able to
                provide a quota indication for a particular user when requested. This quota server
                may or may not coexist in the prepaid server. </t>
                
            <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
                    "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
                    interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Prepaid Client (PPC):"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The entity
                            which triggers the RADIUS message exchange, including the prepaid
                            extensions defined in this document. The PPC provides the service to the
                            users, and executes the RADIUS client which, for the purposes of this
                            document, is termed the "PrePaid Client" (PPC). When the prepaid service
                            is used the PPC collects service event information and reports it while
                            the services is provided to the user. This event information is sent to
                            the PPS using the extensions defined in this document. <vspace
                                blankLines="1"/></t>
                        <t hangText="Prepaid Server (PPS):">
                            <vspace blankLines="1"/>The entity that interacts with the PPC using the
                            RADIUS prepaid extensions defined in this document. <vspace
                                blankLines="1"/></t>
                        <t hangText="Rating Entity:">
                            <vspace blankLines="1"/>This entity converts the credit that is
                            allocated by the PPS into a "quota". This quota is then returned to the
                            requesting PPC via the PPS. The rating entity may also determine that
                            during service provision a tariff switch will occur. In this case the
                            rating entity will include details of when exactly tariff switch will
                                occur.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
                        <t hangText="Quota:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>A quota denotes the amount of
                            granted units to be consumed without performing another credit control
                            interaction. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Home Network:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The network which
                            contains the user profile and the user's prepaid account. <vspace
                                blankLines="1"/></t>
                        <t hangText="Authorize-Only Access Request:">
                            <vspace blankLines="1"/>A RADIUS message of type "Access Request" (code
                            field = 1) that contains a "Service-Type" AVP (type = 6) with value
                            "Authorize-Only". <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
                        <t hangText="Offline Charging:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Offline charging is
                            a process where charging information for resource usage is collected
                            concurrently with that resource usage. The charging information is then
                            passed through a chain of logical charging functions. At the end of this
                            process, Charging Data Record (CDR) files are generated, which are then
                            transferred to the operator's billing domain for the purpose of
                            subscriber billing and/or inter-operator accounting (or additional
                            functions, e.g., statistics, at the operator's discretion). The billing
                            domain typically comprises post-processing systems, such as the
                            operator's billing system or billing mediation device. In conclusion,
                            offline charging is a mechanism where charging information does not
                            affect, in real-time, the service rendered. [TS32240]<vspace
                                blankLines="1"/></t>
                        <t hangText="Online Charging:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Online charging is a
                            process where charging information for resource usage is collected
                            concurrently with that resource usage in the same fashion as in offline
                            charging. However, authorization for the network resource usage must be
                            obtained prior to the actual resource usage to occur. This authorization
                            is granted by the PPS upon request from the PPC. When receiving a
                            resource usage request, the PPS assembles the relevant charging
                            information and generates a charging event in real-time. The PPS then
                            returns an appropriate resource usage authorization. The resource usage
                            authorization may be limited in its scope (e.g., volume of data or
                            duration), therefore the authorization may have to be renewed from time
                            to time as long as the resource usage persists. Note that the charging
                            information utilized in online charging is not necessarily identical to
                            the charging information employed in offline charging. In conclusion,
                            online charging is a mechanism where charging information can affect, in
                            real-time, the service rendered and therefore a direct interaction of
                            the charging mechanism with the control of resource usage is required.
                            [TS32240]</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
                <t> This section provides an overview of the prepaid charging models and
                    architectures, which are supported by the extensions described in this document.</t>
                <t>A number of models of how to charge customers for services in a prepaid manner
                    are supported: </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>Volume-based charging (e.g., 2 Cents/KiloByte).</t>
                        <t>Duration-based charging (e.g., 3 Cents/minute).</t>
                        <t>Resource-based charging (e.g., 3 videos for 10 Euros)</t>
                        <!--            <t>Subscription-based charging (e.g., 10 USD/month).</t> -->
                        <t>Event-based charging (e.g., 7 Cents/ring tone) .</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> This draft assumes that the user maintains a prepaid account with his home
                    network. This account may be used to fund multiple services, some of which may
                    use the extensions defined in this document, and some may use other mechanisms.
                    The interworking of these mechanisms is outside the scope of this document.
                    Similarly, the means by which the subscriber obtains funds is also outside the
                    scope of this document. </t>
                <section anchor="archmodel" title="Architectural Model">
                    <t> This section describes the architectural model of the protocol extensions
                        described in this document. <xref target="basicpparch"/> describes the
                        involved entities.</t>
                    <t> The end user establishes a connection with one of possibly multiple PPCs
                        during service access. The selected PPC communicates with a HAAA server
                        (directly or indirectly via a broker network).</t>
                    <t> The interface between the HAAA and the PPS is implemented using the RADIUS
                        protocol together with the extensions described in this document. However,
                        in cases where the PPS does not implement the RADIUS protocol, the
                        implementation would have to map the requirements defined in this document
                        to a functionally equivalent protocol. </t>
                    <t> The requesting PPC meters the consumption of the service according to the
                        instructions provided by the PPS. After service completion, or on reception
                        of a subsequent request for service, the PPS deducts the corresponding
                        amount of credit from the user account. When a user terminates an on-going
                        service, the PPC informs the PPS with a suitable indication about the unused
                        portion of the allocated quota. The PPS then refunds the user account
                        accordingly. Note that multiple PPSs may be deployed for reasons of
                        redundancy and load sharing. The system may also employ multiple rating
                        servers.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure anchor="basicpparch" title="Basic Prepaid Architecture">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
                    Service       
                 Access Device   Accounting
+----------+      +---------+    Protocol  +------------+
|  End     |<---->|+-------+|<------------>| Accounting |
|  User    |   +->||  PCC  ||              |   Server   |
|          |   |  ||       ||<----+        |            |
+----------+   |  |+-------+|     |        +------------+
               |  +---------+     |      
+----------+   |                  |      
|  End     |<--+                  |              
|  User    |                      |        +----------+
+----------+                      +------->|          |
                                  Prepapid | PPS      |
                                  Protocol |          |
                                           +----------+
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t> The PPS and the accounting server in this architecture MAY be combined. The
                        PPC must have the ability to meter the consumption of a prepaid data
                        session. This metering is typically based on time (i.e., seconds) or volume
                        (i.e., octets). </t>
                    <t> The device running the PPC may also have "Dynamic Session Capabilities",
                        such as the ability to terminate a data session or to change the filters
                        associated with a specific data session by processing "Disconnect" messages
                        and "Change of Authorization" messages as per RFC 3576 <xref
                            target="RFC3576"/>.</t>
                    <t> This document assumes that the PPS is used as the AAA server. There are
                        three types of AAA server, as follows. </t>
                    <t> The AAA server in the home network (HAAA) is responsible for authentication
                        of the subscriber. In addition, the HAAA communicates with the PPS using the
                        RADIUS protocol in order to authorize subscribers. </t>
                    <t> This document assumes that the PPS communicates with the HAAA for the
                        purposes of authentication and authorisation. The PPS, in turn, interfaces
                        to entities which </t>
                    <t>
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t> keep the subscriber's account balance (balance manager),</t>
                            <t> rate access service requests in real-time (rating engine), and </t>
                            <t> manage quota for a particular prepaid service (quota server). </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t> The balance manager, the rating engine and the quota server belong to the
                        service provider's backend infrastructure and are outside the scope of this
                        specification. In particular, as far as this specification is concerned,
                        they are assumed to exist in the PPS.</t>
                    <t> Accounting messages are not needed to deliver a prepaid service. However,
                        accounting messages can be used to keep the PPS up-to-date as to what is
                        happening with the prepaid data session.</t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="motivation" title="Motivation">
                    <t> Why not use existing RADIUS attributes to construct a protocol for prepaid
                        scenarios? This could lead to a solution where no code has to be modified at
                        existing devices.</t>
                    <t> It is indeed possible to construct a solution for prepaid scenarios using
                        existing RADIUS attributes. The RADIUS server would send an Access-Accept
                        message containing a Session-Timeout(27) and include a
                        Termination-Action(29) in the RADIUS-request. Upon receiving the
                        Access-Accept message, the NAS would meter the duration of the session and
                        upon termination of the session the NAS would generate an Access-Request
                        message again. The RADIUS server would then re-authenticate the session and
                        reply with an Access-Accept message indicating the amount of additional time
                        in a Session-Timeout(27). Alternatively, it could respond with an
                        Access-Reject message if there were no more resources in the user account. </t>
                    <t> Moreover, if the user terminates the session prematurely, the NAS could
                        indicate this in the accounting stream so that unused funds can be returned
                        into the prepaid user account.</t>
                    <t> Unfortunately, the above "solution" has a number of drawbacks, including the
                        following.</t>
                    <t>
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t> It only supports time-based charging. The solution presented in this
                                document supports multiple charging metrics.</t>
                            <t> Using accounting messages to recoup unused time may be problematic
                                because RADIUS accounting messages are not delivered in real-time. A
                                RADIUS server may store-and-forward accounting messages in batches.
                                Thus, relying on accounting messages for the purposes of prepaid may
                                cause revenue leakage. The solution presented in this document does
                                not rely on Accounting packets at all. It uses Access-Request
                                messages, which are required to flow through any network in
                                real-time.</t>
                            <t> Session-Timeout(27) is not a mandatory attribute. If a prepaid
                                subscriber is served by a NAS that does not adhere to
                                Session-Timeout then that subscriber may use the service for an
                                undetermined period of time. </t>
                            <t> Termination-Action(29) presents its own issues. Firstly, the
                                behaviour of Termination-Action(29) is not mandatory. Secondly,
                                according to RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865"/>, Termination-Action
                                fires when the provision of the service has completed. However,
                                service should not be terminated when negotiating additional quota,
                                because this should happen in a manner transparent to the
                                subscriber. Due to the fact that Termination-Action occurs when the
                                service is completed, it is unclear whether or not user experience
                                would be affected if this attribute would be used in a prepaid
                                scenario. The RADIUS server might even allocate a new IP address to
                                the subscriber device after a Termination-Action. Also, the RADIUS
                                server has no way of telling why a given Access-Request message was
                                generated. The RADIUS server might have to wait for the
                                corresponding accounting packet to determine the reason. Finally,
                                re-authenticating the subscriber may take too long. The solution
                                presented in this document allows quota replenishing to occur
                                without affecting user experience. No re-authentication is required
                                and quotas can be negotiated before the available credit actually
                                runs out.</t>
                            <t> Due to the fact that the standard RADIUS attributes are not
                                mandatory, the correct prepaid operation is really an act of faith
                                on the part of the RADIUS server. If Session-Timeout(27) and/or
                                Termination-Action(29) are not supported, the prepaid subscriber
                                might be able to obtain the service for free. The solution described
                                in this document requires that a PPC informs the RADIUS server,
                                regardless of whether or not the latter supports the prepaid
                                extensions. The RADIUS server can then determine whether or not
                                service should be granted. For example, if a prepaid subscriber is
                                connected to a NAS that does not support prepaid, the RADIUS server
                                can either instruct the NAS to tunnel the traffic to another entity
                                in the home network (e.g., an Home Agent) that supports prepaid, or
                                cause it to provide only a restricted service. </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t> The solution presented in this document requires the support of two
                        mandatory and one optional attribute. Furthermore, it does not require a
                        great amount of additional code at a NAS (or similar device) that already
                        supports time or volume-based metering. The solution requires that RADIUS
                        entities advertise their prepaid capabilities in an Access-Request and that
                        they generate an Access-Request packet with Service-Type="Authorize-Only" in
                        order to obtain more quota when or before the current quota is used up. It
                        also requires the NAS to send an Access-Request with
                        Service-Type="Authorize-Only" when the session terminates in order to refund
                        the subscriber account. </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Assumptions">
                <t>This document makes the following assumptions. <list style="symbols">
                        <t>The values carried in the Service Identifiers are pre-configured between
                            the PPC and the PPS.</t>
                        <t> The decision about the service rating happens at the PPS. </t>
                        <t> The decision whether credit control requests for two services are placed
                            in a resource pool are made by the PPS. </t>
                        <t> The decision which services belong to the same rating group are
                            pre-configured at the PPC. Once a rating group is authorized it is not
                            necessary to re-authorize an additional service that belongs to the same
                            rating group at the PPS again. </t>
                        <t> A price enquiry is done purely for the purpose of providing AoC for the
                            end user, not for processing at the PPC nor to trigger any specific
                            actions.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="case" title="Example Use Case">
                <t> This section describes the sequence of events in an example RADIUS prepaid
                    transaction.</t>
                <t>
                    <list style="numbers">
                        <t> When an end host attaches to a network (for example, using IEEE 802.1X),
                            as usual, the PPC that is servicing the subscriber uses the AAA
                            infrastructure in order to authenticate and authorize the subscriber
                            with respect to the requested service. In order to do this, it sends a
                            RADIUS Access-Request to the AAA server. This Access-Request contains
                            the subscriber's credentials and may contain the prepaid capabilities of
                            the PPC. </t>
                        <t> The authentication procedure proceeds. This may involve several message
                            exchanges, as it is the case with the Extensible Authentication Protocol
                            (EAP) <xref target="RFC2284"/>. Once the subscriber has been
                            successfully authenticated, the home AAA server determines that the
                            subscriber is a prepaid subscriber and requests authorisation from the
                            PPS. This request MUST include the prepaid capabilities of the serving
                            PPC. </t>
                        <t> The PPS, possibly with the help of the backend infrastructure, validates
                            that the subscriber has a prepaid account and that the account is
                            active. It further validates that the PPC has the appropriate prepaid
                            capabilities. If all is in order, the PPS authorises the subscriber to
                            use the network. Otherwise it rejects the request. The decision is sent
                            to the AAA system in the form of a response message. In the case of
                            success, this message contains attributes that indicate the allocation
                            of a portion of the subscriber credit. This portion is called the
                            "initial quota" and is expressed in units of time or volume. The
                            response may also include a threshold value. Note that only a portion of
                            the user's funds is allocated because the user may be engaged in other
                            services that may draw on the same account. For example, the user may be
                            engaged in a data session and a voice session. Although these two
                            services would draw from the same account, they form separate parts of
                            the overall system. If the entire quota was allocated to the data
                            session then the user would have no more funds for a voice session. </t>
                        <t> The AAA system incorporates the attributes received from the PPS into an
                            Access-Accept message that it sends to the PPC. Note that the AAA system
                            is responsible for authorizing the service whereas the prepaid system is
                            responsible for prepaid authorization. </t>
                        <t> Upon receiving the Access-Response, the PPC starts the prepaid data
                            session and meters the session based on time or volume, as indicated in
                            the message.</t>
                        <t> Once the consumption approaches the allocated limit (as expressed by the
                            threshold), the PPC will request additional quota. Re-authorization for
                            additional quota flows through the AAA system to the PPS. The PPS
                            revalidates the subscriber account and subtracts the previously
                            allocated quota from the current balance. If there is remaining balance,
                            it reauthorizes the request with an additional quota allotment.
                            Otherwise, the PPS rejects the request. Note that the replenishment of
                            the quota is a re-authorization procedure and does not require the
                            subscriber to authenticate himself again. </t>
                        <t> Upon receiving a re-allotment of the quota, the PPC continues to provide
                            the requested service until the new threshold is reached. If the request
                            for additional quota cannot be fulfilled then the PPC lets the
                            subscriber use the remaining quota and terminates the session.
                            Alternatively, instead of terminating the session, the PPC may restrict
                            service access in such a way that the subscriber can only reach a
                            particular web server. This web server maybe used to allow the
                            subscriber to replenish his account. This restriction can also be used
                            to allow new subscribers to set up prepaid accounts in the first place. </t>
                        <t> Should the subscriber terminate the session before the quota is
                            exhausted, the remaining balance allotted to the session is refunded
                            into his account. </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> Note that the subscriber may have disconnected while the PPC is waiting for the
                    initial quota. The entire allocated quota will have to be credited back to the
                    subscribers account in this case. Also note that the PPS maintains session state
                    for the subscriber. This state includes how much account balance was allocated
                    during the last quota enquiry and how much is left in the account. Therefore, it
                    is required that all messages about the session reach the same (and correct)
                    PPS.</t>
                <t> For a simple message flow, along the lines of this use case, please see <xref
                        target="flows"/>.</t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section anchor="features" title="Supported Features">
            <t> This section describes the features that are supported by the extensions specified
                in this document.</t>
            <section anchor="mservices" title="Services and Quotas">
                <t> Examples of services that the user may be using are browsing the web,
                    participating in a VoIP conversation, watching streaming video and downloading a
                    ring tone. Some operators may want to distinguish between these services and to
                    charge them at different rates and meters them differently. Therefore, the
                    prepaid solution needs to be able to distinguish services, and allocate quota to
                    the services using different unit types (time, volume) and allow for those
                    quotas to be consumed at different rates. </t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="mservicesdiagram"
                        title="Multiple services within a single session">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
+---------+            +---------+            +-------+
|         | 1        N |         | 1        1 |       |
| Session |<---------->| Service |<---------->| Quota |
|         |            |         |            |       |
+---------+            +---------+            +-------+
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> As shown in <xref target="mservicesdiagram"/>, a session may be associated with
                    multiple services. Each service is identified by a service identifier
                    (Service-ID). The format of the Service-ID is not in the scope of this document.
                    It may, for example, be expressed as a 5-tuple {i.e., source IP address,
                    destination IP address, source port, destination port, and protocol type}. Each
                    service is associated with a quota whereby a quota might be applicable to
                    multiple services. An example message flow that involves multiple services
                    within a single session is given in the <xref target="flows"/>. </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="rpools" title="Resource Pools">

                <t> When working with multiple services a new problem arises because one service may
                    consume its quota faster than another service. When the user balance is close to
                    exhaustion, a situation could arise where one service is unable to obtain quota
                    while another service has plenty of quota remaining. Unless the quotas can be
                    rebalanced, the SAD would then have to terminate the former service. Moreover,
                    it is likely that each service generates a certain amount of RADIUS prepaid
                    traffic. In an environment with many users and charged services, this amount of
                    traffic may become a considerable overhead that could lead to inefficiency. </t>

                <t> One method to circumvent the above situation is to use a so-called "resource
                    pool". Resource pools enable the allocation of resources to multiple services of
                    a session by allocating resources to a pool and have services draw their quota
                    from the pool at a rate appropriate to that service. When the quota that has
                    been allocated to the pool is close to exhaustion, the entire pool (rather than
                    individual services) is replenished.</t>

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="rpoolsdiagram" title="Resource pool example">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
           +-----------+ 
           | Service-A |-----+         +--------+ 
           +-----------+     |    Ma   |        | 
                             +-------->|        | 
                                       |  Pool  | 
                             +-------->|   (1)  | 
           +-----------+     |    Mb   |        | 
           | Service-B |-----+         +--------+ 
           +-----------+                          
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>


                <t> As shown in <xref target="rpoolsdiagram"/>, Service-A and Service-B are bound to
                    Pool(1). Ma and Mb are the pool multipliers (that are associated with Service-A
                    and Service-B respectively) that determine the rate at which Service-A and
                    Service-B draw from the pool.</t>

                <t> The pool is initialized by taking the quota allocated to service n and
                    multiplying it by Mn. Therefore, the amount of resources allocated to a pool is
                    given by Poolr = Ma*Qa + Mb*Qb + . . ., where Qn denotes the amount of quota
                    that is allocated to service n. Further, the pool is considered to be empty if </t>

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="rpoolempty">

                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
        Poolr <= Ca*Ma + Cb*Mb + . . .,
]]></artwork>

                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t> where Ca and Cb are resources consumed by Service-A and Service-B respectively. </t>

                <t> Note that the resources assigned to the pool are not associated with a metric.
                    That is, Service-A can be rated at $1 per MB and Service-B can rated at $0.10
                    per minute. In this case, if $5 worth of resources are allocated for service-A
                    to the pool and if Ma = 10, then 50 units would be placed into the pool. If a
                    further $5 are allocated for service-B to the pool, then M=1 and 50 units are
                    deposited into the pool. The pool would then have a total sum of 100 units to be
                    shared between the two services. The PPC would then mater the services such that
                    each Mbyte used by Service-A will draw 10 units from the pool and each minute
                    used by Service-B will draw 1 unit from the pool. </t>
            </section>


            <section anchor="cratefunc" title="Rating Groups">
                <t> A Rating Group gathers a set of services, identified by a service identifier,
                    and subject to the same cost and rating type (e.g., $0.1/minute). </t>
                <t> The rating of a service can be quite complex. While some operators follow linear
                    pricing models, others may wish to apply more complex functions. For example, a
                    service provider may wish to rate a service such that the first N MBytes are
                    free, then the next M Mbytes are rated at $1 per MB and volume above (N+M) MB be
                    rated at $0.50 per MB. Such a function could be implemented by repeated message
                    exchanges in the prepaid system.</t>
                <t> To avert the need to exchange many messages while still supporting such complex
                    rating functions, the concept of the Rating Group was introduced. </t>
                <t>As shown in <xref target="ratinggroupdiagram"/>, a Rating Group is associated
                    with one or more services and defines the rate that the services associated with
                    the Rating Group consume an allocated amount of quota.</t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="ratinggroupdiagram" title="Rating Group">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
                         
                        +--------------+       +--------------+ 
+-----------+ N     1   |              | M  1  | Resource Pool| 
| Service-A +---------->| Rating Group |------>|      or      | 
+-----------+           |              |       |    Quota     | 
                        +--------------+       +--------------+ 
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> During the usage of a service that is associated with a Rating Group, the PPC
                    sends the ID of the Rating Group to the PPS. The PPS authorises the Rating Group
                    by allocating a quota to it and assign it to a Resource Pool. When an additional
                    service that belongs to an already authorised Rating Group is instantiated, the
                    PPC does not need to re-authorize this service. This effectively means that the
                    PPC meters the service such that it draws from the already allocated quota.
                    Therefore, no RADIUS messages need to be exchanged in this case. This limits the
                    amount of traffic between the PPC and the PPS. An example of a flow that uses
                    Rating Groups is given in <xref target="rpoolflow"/>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="tarswitch" title="Tariff Switching">
                <t>Tariff is the set of parameters defining the utilization charges for the use of a
                    particular service. </t>
                <t> This mechanism is useful if, for example, as shown in <xref target="tsdiagram"
                    />, traffic before 18:00 is rated at rate r1 and traffic after 18:00 is rated at
                    rate r2. The mechanism requires the PPC to report usage before and after the
                    switch occured. </t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="tsdiagram" title="Example of Tariff Switching">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
                        18:00 
         ------------------+----------------- 
                r1         |      r2          
         ------------------+----------------- 
              ^                        ^ 
              |<----TSI--->            | 
              |                        | 
        Access-Accept            Access-Request 
        (quota allocated)        (quota consumed)
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> The PPC indicates support for tariff switching by setting the appropriate bit in
                    the PPAC. If the PPS needs to signal a tariff switch time it will send a PTS
                    attribute that indicates the point in time when the switch will occur. This
                    indication represents the number of seconds from current time
                    (TariffSwitchInterval TSI).</t>
                <t> At some point after the tariff switch the PPC sends another Access-Request, as a
                    result of either the user having logged off or the volume threshold being
                    reached. The PPC reports how much volume was used in total (in a PPAQ attribute)
                    and how much volume was used after the tariff switch (in a PTS VUATS subtype
                    attribute). </t>
                <t> In situations with multiple tariff switches, the PPS has to specify the length
                    of the tariff switch period using the TimeIntervalAfterTariffSwitchUpdate
                    (TITSU) field in the PTS attribute, as shown in <xref target="mtsdiagram"/>.</t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="mtsdiagram" title="Multiple Tariff Switches">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
                         18:00                 23:30 
         ------------------+---------------------+-------------- 
                r1         |      r2             |     r3 
         ------------------+---------------------+-------------- 
              ^                        ^         ^ 
              |<----TSI---><-----------|-------->|TITSU 
              |                        | 
        Access-Accept            Access-Request 
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t> When a TITSU is specified in the PTS, the PPC MUST generate an Access-Request
                    within the time after TSI and before TITSU expires. Note that, typically, the
                    PPC will be triggered by the Volume Threshold. However, it is possible that,
                    during period r2, resources are not entirely consumed and, thus, the threshold
                    is not reached. The TITSU attribute ensures that, even in this case, the PPC
                    will generate the new Access-Request in good time. </t>
                <t> For time based services, the quota is continuously consumed at the regular rate
                    of 60 seconds per minute. At the time when credit resources are allocated, the
                    server already knows how many units will be consumed before the tariff time
                    change and how many units will be consumed afterward. Similarly, the server can
                    determine the units consumed at the before rate and the units consumed at the
                    rate afterward in the event that the end user closes the session before the
                    consumption of the allotted quota. There is no need for additional traffic
                    between the PPC and the PPS in the case of tariff time changes for continuous
                    time based service. Therefore, the tariff change mechanism is not used for such
                    services. For time-based services in which the quota is not continuously
                    consumed at a regular rate, the tariff change mechanism described for volume and
                    event units may be used. </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="roaming" title="Support for Roaming">
                <t> In certain networks it is essential for prepaid data services to be available to
                    roaming subscribers. Support for both static and dynamic roaming models is
                    needed. In a static roaming scenario the subscriber connects to a foreign
                    network which has a roaming agreement either directly with the home network, or
                    through a broker network. When the subscriber logs into another foreign network,
                    a new login procedure has to be executed. </t>
                <t> In a dynamic roaming scenario the subscriber may move between networks while
                    maintaining his connection. In such a scenario the data session is seamlessly
                    handed off between the networks. </t>
                <t> In both roaming scenarios, the subscriber always authenticates himself to the
                    home network. Authorization for the prepaid session and quota replenishing
                    occurs at the home network and more specifically at the PPS where state is being
                    maintained. </t>
                <t> Roaming is challenging because a subscriber who established a prepaid data
                    session may move to another PPC that does not support the prepaid
                extensions.</t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="dynterm" title="Dynamic Termination">
                <t> When fraud or an error is detected, either only the affected session, or all
                    sessions of the affected subscriber should be immediately terminated. Under
                    certain conditions, the system may wish to terminate the session in order to
                    make sure that the user is not charged for services it does not use.</t>
                <t> Certain handoff procedures used in dynamic roaming scenarios require that the
                    system terminates the subscribers prepaid data session at a PPC. This is the
                    case, for example, when time-based prepaid is used and the mobile subscriber
                    performs a dormant handoff. </t>
            </section>

            <section title="One Time Event">

                <section anchor="onetimec" title="One-Time Charging">
                    <t> One-time charging is a mode of operation where the RADIUS prepaid extensions
                        are used for charging of a service that is provided instansteneously. An
                        example of such an event is the purchase of a ring tone. Subscription based
                        services can also be modeled as a one-time event. In this case the one-time
                        service event is the purchase of a subscription.</t>
                    <t> For a given user, one-time charging may occur in parallel with other
                        charging models. For example, the subscriber may be connected to the
                        Internet, which is metered (based on time or volume), while he also
                        purchases a ring tone (a one-time-based event). </t>
                    <t>Note that it is up to the service providers to decide whether or not the user
                        will be charged for the download of, for example, the video and also be
                        charged for the data volume required to download the video. The facilities
                        provided by this document gives the service provider the capability to
                        achieve their service charging business goals.</t>
                    <t> The PPC signals one-time charging to the PPS with an indication that
                        identifies the service and the units that should be debited from the user
                        account.</t>
                    <t> A PPC may decide to perform one-time charging and the PPC may need to
                        authenticate the user before sending the relevant message to the user's home
                        AAA server (and to the PPS).</t>
                    <t> Note that one-time charging can also be used to credit the prepaid account.
                        For example, the PPC can return resources to the subscriber by issuing a
                        one-time charging request that includes the amount of resources to be
                        credited into the account. </t>
                </section>

                <section anchor="rebalancing" title="Resource Consumption Query">
                    <t> It should be possible for the PPS to query the PPC for the current resource
                        consumption and to adjust the users account balance. For example, a request
                        to the PPS is made (e.g., a one-time charging event), the account is
                        depleted and resources have been allocated to the PPC. The PPS should have
                        the ability to query the PPC and, if it has the spare resources, to reassign
                        the quotas to the PPC and to the pending request. Note that the PPS does not
                        know resource usage until the PPC request for more resources. This can be a
                        long time. </t>
                    <!--                    
                        <t>[Editor's Note: This is my guess..... The PPS initiates the procedure with a
                        Change-of Authorization message In the response the PPC provides a RADIUS
                        Authorize- Only Access-Request message, it indicates the resources used in
                        total, including both incoming and outgoing chargeable traffic.]</t> -->
                    <t> In the absence of this capability the PPS can minimize the effect of this
                        phenomenon by allocating small quotas, a practice that results in more
                        message exchanges. </t>
                </section>


                <section anchor="servpriceenc" title="Service Price Enquiry">
                    <t> The PPC may need to know the price of the service event. Services offered by
                        application service providers whose prices are not known in the PPC might
                        exist. The end user might also want to get an estimation of the price of a
                        service event before requesting it. </t>
                    <t> A PPC issues a PPAQ to the PPS including the Requested-Action SubType with
                        the value set to "Price Enquiry" (2). The request includes enough
                        information to identify the service, namely a Service-Identifier or a
                        Rating-Group-Identifer. </t>
                    <t> The PPS calculates the cost of the requested service event, but it does not
                        perform any account balance check or credit reservation from the account. </t>
                    <t> The estimated cost of the requested service event is returned to the PPS
                        with a PPAQ in the Cost-Information SubType. The PPC may transfer the
                        information to the end user as an advice of charge. </t>
                    <t>More information regarding the price enquiry functionality is provided in
                            <xref target="reqactavp"/> and in <xref target="costinfo"/>.</t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="bceck" title="Balance Check">
                    <t> The PPC may only have to verify that the end user's account balance covers
                        the cost of a certain service without reserving any units from the account
                        at the time of the inquiry. This method does not guarantee that credit would
                        be left when the PPC requests the debiting of the account with a separate
                        request. </t>
                    <t> A PPC issues a PPAQ to the PPS including the Requested-Action SubType with
                        the value set to "Balance Check" (1). The request includes enough
                        information to identify the service, namely a Service-Identifier or a
                        Rating-Group-Identifer. </t>
                    <t> The PPS makes the balance check, but it does not make any credit-reservation
                        from the account. </t>
                    <t> The result of balance check, namely "Success" (1) or "Failure" (2), is
                        returned to the PPC in the Check-Balance-Result SubType conveyed in the PPAQ
                        attribute from the PPS to the PPC.</t>
                    <t>More information regarding the balance check functionality is provided in
                            <xref target="reqactavp"/> and in <xref target="checkbalres"/>.</t>

                </section>
                <section title="Refund">
                    <t>Some services may refund service units to the end user's account; for
                        example, gaming services. </t>
                    <t>To initiate refunding the PPC includes the PPAQ attribute in an
                        Access-Request packet and the amount (as a negative value) to be refunded is
                        specified using the Resource Quota and Resource Quota overflow subtypes.
                        This functionality is similar to one-time charging with the difference that
                        refunding uses negative values </t>
                    <t> Information about the service need to be provided by the PPC to allow
                        service identification, namely the Service-ID field of the PPAQ identifies
                        the prepaid service. </t>
                    <t>Note that a monetary amount itself to be refunded is not provided but rather
                        abstract units. Based on prior out-of-band agreements between the PPC and
                        the PPS these abstract units are translated into a monetary amount.</t>
                    <t>More information regarding the refund functionality is provided in <xref
                            target="onetimecharging"/>.</t>
                </section>
                <!--            <section title="Direct Debiting">
                    <t>[Editor's Note: Do we provide this functionality?]</t>
                </section>
     -->
            </section>

        </section>
        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="operations" title="Operations">
            <t> This section contains the normative text for the prepaid extension.</t>

            <section title="Capability Discovery">
                <t> The PPC initiates the authentication and authorization procedure by sending a
                    RADIUS Access-Request to the HAAA. Since the PPC MUST include a PPAC attribute
                    in the RADIUS Access-Request. The PPAC attribute indicates to the PPS which
                    prepaid capabilities are possessed by the PPC. These are required in order to
                    complete the prepaid authorization procedure.Moreover, if the PPC supports the
                    Disconnect-Message or the Change-of-Authorization capabilities, then it SHOULD
                    include the Session Termination attribute. </t>

                <t> In certain deployments, there may be other ways to terminate a data session, or
                    change authorization of an active session. For example, some PPCs provide a
                    session termination service via Telnet or SNMP. In these cases, the AAA server
                    MAY add the Dynamic-Capabilities message to the Access-Request. Upon receiving
                    the Change-of-Authorization message, the AAA server would then be responsible
                    for terminating the session using the means that are supported by the device. </t>

                <t> If the authentication procedure involves multiple message exchanges (as it is
                    the case with EAP), the PPC MUST include the PPAC attribute in at least the last
                    Access-Request of the authentication procedure. </t>

            </section>

            <section anchor="authandauthz" title="Authentication and Authorization Operation">

                <t> Once the Access-Request arrives at the HAAA, the HAAA authenticates the
                    subscriber. If this fails, the HAAA sends an Access-Reject message to the
                    client. If authentication succeeds, the HAAA determines whether or not the
                    subscriber is a prepaid subscriber. If the subscriber is not a prepaid
                    subscriber, then the HAAA responds as usual with an Access-Accept or an
                    Access-Reject message. If the subscriber is a prepaid subscriber then the HAAA
                    MAY forward the Access-Request to the PPS for further authorization.</t>


                <t> The Access-Request contains the PPAC attribute and the Dynamic-Capabilities
                    attribute if one was included. The User-Name(1) attribute MAY be set to a value
                    that identifies the subscriber. This attribute is used by the PPS to locate his
                    account. For added security, the HAAA MAY also set the User-Password(2)
                    attribute to the password used between the HAAA and the PPS. </t>

                <t> The PPS locates the subscriber account and authorizes him. During this
                    procedure, the PPS takes into consideration the PPCs capabilities. Upon
                    successful authorization, the PPS generates an Access-Accept containing an PPAC
                    attribute and an PPAQ attribute. The PPAC attribute returned to the client
                    indicates the type of prepaid service to be provided for the session. The PPAQ
                    attribute includes the following information. </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t> The QID, which is set by the PPS to a unique value, is used to correlate
                            quota requests.</t>

                        <t> Volume and/or Time quota, which is set to a value representing a portion
                            of the subscriber's credit.</t>

                        <t>Time or Volume Threshold that indicates when the PPC should request
                            additional quota. This information is optional. </t>

                        <t> The IP address of the serving PPS and one or more alternative PPSs. This
                            is used by the HAAA to route subsequent quota replenishing messages to
                            the appropriate PPS(s). </t>

                        <t> A State attribute, as defined in RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865"/>. This
                            is necessary in order to satisfy the requirements of Section 5.44 of RFC
                            2865 <xref target="RFC2865"/>, which mandates that an Access-Request
                            with Service-Type="Authorize-Only" must contain a State attribute. Since
                            the PPC sends subsequent quota replenishment requests in the form of
                            such "Authorize-Only" requests, a State attribute MUST be present in all
                            Access-Accept messages that also carry a PPAQ attribute.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>

                <t> Note: The Idle-Timeout(28) attribute can be used to trigger the premature
                    termination of a prepaid service, for example as a result of inactivity. </t>

                <t> Depending on site policies, after failed authorization, the PPS may generate an
                    Access-Reject in order to terminate the session immediately. Alternatively, the
                    PPS may generate an Access-Accept blocking some or all of the traffic and/or
                    redirect some or all of the traffic to a location to a fixed server. (This
                    feature could be used, for example, to prompt the user to replenish their
                    account.) Blocking of traffic is achieved by either Filter-ID(11) or
                    NAS-Filter-Rule (see <xref target="RFC4849"/>). A description of the redirect
                    functionality is outside the scope of this document. The time period before the
                    session is blocked/redirected is specified by the Session-Timeout(27) attribute. </t>

                <t> Upon receiving an Access-Accept from the PPS, the HAAA appends the usual service
                    attributes and forward the packet to the PPC. The HAAA SHOULD NOT overwrite any
                    attributes already set by the PPS. If the HAAA receives an Access-Reject
                    message, it will simply forward the packet to its client. Depending on site
                    policies, if the HAAA does not receive an Access-Accept or an Access-Reject
                    message from the PPS it MAY do nothing or send an Access-Reject or an Access-
                    Accept message back to the PPC. </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="sessionstart" title="Session Start Operation">

                <t> The start of the session is indicated by the arrival of an
                    Accounting-Request(Start) packet. The Accounting-Request (Start) MAY be routed
                    to the PPS such that it can confirm the initial quota allocation. </t>

                <t> Note that the role of the PPS is not to record accounting messages and therefore
                    it SHOULD NOT respond with an Accounting Response packet. If the PPS does not
                    receive the Accounting-Request(start) message it will only know that the session
                    has started upon the first reception of a quota replenishment operation. </t>

                <t> If the PPS does not receive indication directly (via Accounting-Request(start))
                    or indirectly, it SHOULD, after some configurable time, deduce that the session
                    has not started. If the PPC supports termination capabilities, the PPS SHOULD
                    send a Disconnect Message to the PPC as a measure to ensure that the session is
                    indeed dead.</t>

            </section>

            <section anchor="midsessions" title="Mid-Session Operation">

                <t> During the lifetime of a prepaid data session the PPC may request the
                    replenishment of the quotas using an Authorize-Only Access-Request message. Once
                    either the allocated quota has been exhausted or the threshold has been reached,
                    the PPC MUST send an Access-Request with Service-Type(6) set to a value of
                    "Authorize-Only" and the PPAQ attribute.</t>

                <t> The PPC MUST also include NAS identifiers, and Session Identifier attributes in
                    the Authorize-Only Access-Request. The Session Identifier should be the same as
                    the one used during the initial Access-Request. For example, if the User-Name(1)
                    attribute was used in the Access-Request it has to be included in the
                    Authorize-Only Access-Request as well, especially if the User-Name(1) attribute
                    is used to route the Access-Request to the Home AAA server.</t>

                <t> The Authorize-Only Access-Request MUST NOT include a User Password and MUST NOT
                    include a CHAP Password. In order to enable the receiver to authenticate the
                    message, the PPC MUST include a Message-Authenticator(80). In order to satisfy
                    the requirements of Section 5.44 of RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865"/>, the PPC
                    MUST also include the State attribute. It is anticipated that the inclusion of
                    the State attribute will enable the PPS to map the Authorize-Only Access Request
                    to the authentication context that was established when the PPC authenticated
                    itself at the beginning of the session. The PPC computes the value for the
                    Message-Authenticator and the State attributes according to RFC 2869 <xref
                        target="RFC2869"/> and RFC 2865 <xref target="RFC2865"/> respectively. </t>

                <t> When the HAAA receives an Authorize-Only Access-Request that contains a PPAQ, it
                    validates the message using the Message-Authenticator(80), according to RFC
                    2869. If the HAAA receives an Authorize-Only Access-Request that contains a PPAQ
                    and either no or an invalid Message-Authenticator(80) it SHALL silently discard
                    the message. An Authorize Only Access-Request message that does not contain a
                    PPAQ is either erroneous or belongs to another application (for example, a
                    Change of Authorization message <xref target="RFC3576"/>). In this case the
                    Authorize-Only Access-Request is either silently discarded or handled by another
                    application. </t>

                <t> Once the Authorize-Only Access-Request message is validated, the HAAA SHALL
                    forward the Authorize-Only Access-Request to the appropriate PPS. The HAAA MUST
                    forward the Authorize-Only Access-Request to the PPS specified in the PPAQ. The
                    HAAA MUST add a Message-Authenticator(80) to the message, according to RFC 2869.
                    As with the Access-Request message, the HAAA MAY modify the User-Name(1)
                    attribute such that it identifies the user to the PPS.</t>

                <t> When the PPS receives the Authorize-Only Access-Request containing a PPAQ
                    attribute, it MUST validate the Message-Authenticator(80) as described in RFC
                    2869. If validation fails, the PPS MUST silently discard the message. If it
                    receives an Authorize-Only Access-Request message that does not contain a PPAQ,
                    it MUST silently discard the message. </t>

                <t> The PPS locates the prepaid session state and uses the QID contained within the
                    PPAQ to detect replays. The PPS takes the most recently allocated quota and
                    subtracts it from the user balance. If sufficient balance remains, the PPS
                    authorizes the PPS and allocates additional quota. The PPS may also calculate a
                    new threshold value. Upon successful re-authorization, the PPS generates an
                    Access-Accept containing the PPAQ attribute.</t>

                <t> Depending on site policies, upon unsuccessful authorization, the PPS generates
                    an Access-Reject or an Access-Accept with Filter-Id(11) or Ascend-Data-Filter
                    attribute (if supported) and the Session-Timeout(27) attribute such that the
                    subscriber can get access to a restricted set of locations for a short period of
                    time. This feature could be used to enable users to replenish their accounts,
                    create new accounts, or to access free content. </t>

                <t> Upon receiving an Access-Accept from the PPS, the HAAA forwards the message to
                    its client. If the HAAA receives an Access-Reject message, it forwards the
                    message. Depending on site policies, if the HAAA does not receive an
                    Access-Accept or an Access-Reject message from the PPS it MAY do nothing or it
                    MAY send an Access-Reject message back to its client. </t>

                <t> Upon receiving an Access-Accept, the PPC updates its quotas and threshold
                    parameters with the values contained in the PPAQ attribute. Note that the PPS
                    MAY update the PrePaidServer attribute(s) and these may have to be saved as
                    well. If the Access-Accept message contains a Filter-Id(11), an
                    Ascend-Data-Filter attribute, or Session Timeout(27), the PPC SHALL restrict the
                    subscriber session accordingly.</t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="dynops" title="Dynamic Operations">

                <t> The PPS may take advantage of the dynamic capabilities that are supported by the
                    PPC as advertised in the Session Termination and the PPAC attribute during the
                    initial Access-Request. There are two types of actions that the PPS may perform.
                    Firstly, it may request the session to be terminated. Secondly, it may request
                    the attributes associated with the session to be modified. More specifically, it
                    may modify a previously sent PPAQ. </t>

                <t> Both of these actions require that the session be uniquely identified at the PPC
                    as described in <xref target="RFC3576"/>. </t>


                <section anchor="sessiontermination"
                    title="Unsolicited Session Termination Operation">

                    <t> At anytime during a session the PPS may send a Disconnect Message in order
                        to terminate a session, see in <xref target="RFC3576"/>. Upon successful
                        termination of a session the PPC MUST return any unused quota to the PPS by
                        issuing an Authorize-Only Access-Request containing the PPAQ which contains
                        any unused quota and the Update-Reason set to "Remote Forced Disconnection".</t>

                </section>

                <section anchor="coachange" title="Unsolicited Change of Authorization Operation">

                    <t> At any time during the session the PPC may receive a Change of Authorization
                        (CoA) message. A PPS may send a new quota to either add or to remove quota
                        that is allocated to the service. If the Change of Authorization contains a
                        PPAQ then that PPAQ overrides a previously received PPAQ. The PPS MUST NOT
                        change the units used in the PPAQ.</t>

                    <t> If the newly received PPAQ reduces the amount of allocated quota beyond what
                        is already used then the PPC accepts the new PPAQ and act as it normally
                        would when the quota is used up. For example, if the threshold is reached
                        then is request a quota update.</t>

                </section>

            </section>

            <section anchor="termop" title="Termination Operation">

                <t> The termination phase is initiated when (i) the subscriber logs off, (ii) the
                    subscriber balance is exhausted, or (iii) when the PPC receives a Disconnect
                    Message. </t>

                <t> In case the user logged off, or the PPC receives a Disconnect Message, the PPC
                    sends an Authorize-Only Access-Request message with a PPAQ and Update-Reason
                    attribute set to either "Client Service Termination" or "Remote Forced
                    Disconnect". This message indicates the amount of consumed quota.</t>

                <t> In case the currently allocated quota is exhausted, if the PPAQ contained the
                    Termination-Action subytype, the PPC follows the specified action.</t>

            </section>


            <section anchor="mipop" title="Mobile IP Operations">

                <t> In roaming scenarios with Mobile-IP, the prepaid data session should be
                    maintained transparently if the HA is acting as the access device hosting the
                    PPC. As the subscriber device associates with a new access service device (AP or
                    PDSN that supports PPC capability), this service access device sends a RADIUS
                    Access-Request and the subscriber is re-authenticated and reauthorized. The
                    service access device SHALL include the PPAC attribute in the RADIUS
                    Access-Request. In this manner, the procedure follows the Authentication and
                    Authorization procedure described earlier.</t>

                <t>If the HA was acting as the service access device before handoff, then the
                    prepaid session does not undergo any change after the handoff because the Mobile
                    IP session is anchored at the HA and the user's Home IP address does not change. </t>

                <t>In the case of a wireless access point or PDSN acting as the service access
                    device, it is likely that the user's (care-of) IP address will change. The
                    prepaid session will be affected by this. In this scenario the service access
                    device shall send an Access-Request message which is routed to the home network
                    and SHALL reach the PPS that is serving this session. The PPS correlates the new
                    authorization request with the existing active session and assigns a quota to
                    the new request. Any outstanding quota at the old service access device SHALL be
                    returned to the PPS if the Mobile-IP nodes (HA and FA) support registration
                    revocation (Mobile IPv4 only). Specifically, the quota SHOULD be returned when
                    the service access device sends the Authorize-Only Access-Request with PPAQ
                    Update-Reason set to either "Remote Forced Disconnect" or "Client Service
                    Termination". In order to trigger the sending of this last Authorize-Only
                    Access- Request, the PPS may issue a Disconnect Message [3576] to the service
                    access device.</t>

                <t>Even if the subscriber moves to a service access device that does not have
                    prepaid capabilities can the prepaid data service continue. This can be done by
                    requesting the Home Agent (assuming it has such capabilities) to take over the
                    responsibilities of the service access device (i.e. metering). This scenario
                    will be discussed in detail in a later version of this document. </t>

            </section>


            <section anchor="opcons4mservs" title="Operation Considerations for Multiple Services">

                <t> This section describes the support for multiple prepaid services on a single
                    PPC. Message flows illustrating the various interactions are presented in <xref
                        target="flows"/>. </t>

                <t> A PPC that supports prepaid operations for multi-services SHOULD set the
                    "Multi-Services Supported" bit in the PPAC. When working with multi-services, we
                    need to differentiate between the services. A Service-Id attribute is used in
                    the PPAQ in order to uniquely differentiate between the services. The exact
                    definition of the Service-Id attribute is outside the scope of this document. </t>

                <t> A PPAQ that contains a Service-Id is associated with that service. A PPAQ that
                    contains a Rating-Group-Id is associated with that Rating-Group. A PPAQ MUST NOT
                    contain both a Rating-Group-Id and a Service-Id. A PPAQ that contains neither a
                    Rating-Group-Id nor a Service-Id then the default service is used, i.e., the
                    "Access Service".</t>

                <section anchor="iqr" title="Initial Quota Request">

                    <t> When operations with multiple services is desired then the PPC requests the
                        initial quota by sending a PPAQ containing the Service-Id in an
                        Authorize-Only Access-Request packet for that service. Similarly, if the PPC
                        supports rating groups then it may request a quota for the rating group by
                        sending a PPAQ containing the Rating-Group-Id. In both cases the
                        Update-Reason is set to "Initial-Request". The Authorize-Only Access-Request
                        message MAY contain more than one PPAQ. </t>

                    <t> Upon receiving an Authorize-Only Access-Accept message containing one or
                        more PPAQs, the PPS allocates resources to each PPAQ. Each PPAQ is assigned
                        a unique QID that MUST appear in subsequent PPAQ updates for that service or
                        rating group. Additionally, the PPAQ MUST contain the Service-ID or
                        Rating-Group-Id, unless the PPAQ is the generic "Access Service". </t>
                </section>

                <section anchor="qu" title="Quota Update">
                    <t> Once the services start to utilize their allotted quota they will eventually
                        need to replenish their quotas (either the threshold is reached or no more
                        quota remains). In order to replenish the quota, the PPC sends an
                        Authorize-Only Access-Request message containing one or more PPAQs. Each
                        PPAQ MUST contain the appropriate QID, Service-ID or Rating-Group-Id (or
                        neither the Service-ID or Rating-Group-Id if the quota replenishment is for
                        the "Access Service"). The Update-Reason filed indicates either "Threshold
                        reached"(3), or "Quota reached"(4).</t>
                    <t> Upon receiving an Authorize-Only Access-Request packet with one or more
                        PPAQs the PPS responds with a new PPAQ for that service. The PPAQ contains a
                        new QID, the Service-Id or the Rating-Group-Id, and a new QID. If the PPS
                        does not grant additional quota for the service it MUST include the
                        Termination-Action subfield in the PPAQ that will instruct the PPC to take
                        appropriate actions. </t>
                </section>

                <section anchor="termination" title="Termination">
                    <t> When the allotted quota for a service is exhausted, the PPC shall act in
                        accordance with the flags set in the Termination-Action subtype. If the
                        Termination-Action subtype is absent then the service MUST be terminated. If
                        the service is to be terminated, then the PPC shall send a PPAQ with the
                        appropriate QID, the Service-Id, the used quota, and the Update-Reason set
                        to "Client Service Termination". </t>
                    <t> If the "Access Service" has terminated, then all other services must be
                        terminated as well. In this case the PPC MUST report on all issued quotas
                        for the various services. The Update-Reason field should be set to "Access
                        Service Terminated". </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="dynamicops" title="Dynamic Operations">
                    <t> Dynamic operations for multi-services are similar to dynamic operations
                        described for single service operations. The PPS MAY send a COA message
                        containing a PPAQ for an existing service instance. The PPC matches the PPAQ
                        with the service using the Service-ID or the Rating-Group-Id attribute. The
                        new quota could differ from the previously allocated value.</t>
                    <t> A disconnect message terminates the "Access Service". As such the PPC MUST
                        report all unused quotas by sending an Authorize-Only Access Request message
                        containing a PPAQ for each active service. The Update-Reason MAY indicate
                        that the reason for the update. </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="supp4rpools" title="Support for Resource Pools">
                    <t> If the PPC supports pools as indicated by setting the "Pools supported" bit
                        in the PPAC then the PPS may associate a quota with a Pool by including the
                        Pool-Id and the Pool-Multiplier in the PPAQ. When Resource Pools are used,
                        the PPAQ MUST NOT use the threshold field. </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="onetimecharging" title="One-time Charging">
                    <t> To initiate one-time charging the PPC includes the PPAQ attribute in an
                        Access-Request packet. The Service-ID field of the PPAQ identifies the
                        prepaid service. The amount to be charged is specified using the Resource
                        Quota and Resource Quota overflow subtypes. If the value specified is
                        negative then the resources are credited to the user account. This
                        functionality corresponds to refunding. </t>
                    <t> The QID subtype MUST be set to a unique value and is used by the PPS to
                        detect duplicates. The Update Reason field MUST be set to One-Time Charging.
                        Upon receiving a One-Time charge PPAQ, the RADIUS server authenticates the
                        user and, if successful, passes the PPAQ to the PPS. The PPS locates the
                        account and debits or credits it accordingly. The PPS MUST respond to the
                        PPS with an Access-Accept message if successful, or an Access-Reject message
                        otherwise. </t>
                    <t> In case of a successful operation the HAAA forwards the message to the PPC
                        with an Access Accept message. Since this is a one-time charge the PPC MUST
                        NOT allow the session to continue. Therefore, the RADIUS server SHOULD
                        include in the Access-Accept a Session-Timeout set to 0. Upon receiving an
                        Access-Accept response the PPC SHOULD generate an Accounting Stop message. </t>
                    <t> A PPAQ used for One-Time charging MAY appear in an Authorize-Only Access
                        Request. This is the case when the session already exists. The PPS responds
                        with an Access-Accept to indicate that the user account has been debited or
                        an Access-Reject otherwise. </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="errhand" title="Error Handling">
                    <t> If the PPS receives a PPAQ with an invalid QID it MUST ignore that PPAQ.</t>
                    <t> If the PPS receives a PPAQ containing a Service-Id, or a Rating-Group-Id
                        that it does not recognize, then it MUST ignore that PPAQ. </t>
                    <t> If the PPC receives a PPAQ containing a Service-Id, or a Rating-Group-Id
                        that it does not recognize, then it MUST ignore that PPAQ. </t>
                    <t> If the PPC receives a PPAQ that contains a Pool-Id without a Pool-Multiplier
                        or a Pool-Multiplier without a Pool-Id it MUST ignore that PPAQ. </t>
                </section>

                <section anchor="acccons" title="Accounting Considerations">
                    <t> Although typically generated, accounting messages are not required to
                        deliver a prepaid data service. When generated, accounting messages are used
                        for auditing purposes and for billing. Accounting messages associated with
                        prepaid data sessions should include the PPAQ attribute. </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section anchor="attributes" title="Attributes">
            <t> This section specifies the attributes that implement the RADIUS extensions for
                prepaid.</t>

            <!-- ********************** PPAC ************************ -->

            <section anchor="ppacatt" title="PrePaid Accounting Capability (PPAC) Attribute">
                <t> The PrepaidAccountingCapability (PPAC) attribute is sent in the Access-Request
                    message by a PPC to describe its prepaid capabilities. </t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="ppac" title="PPAC Attribute">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |  Length       |            Vendor-Id
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      Vendor-Id (cont)           | Vendor type   | Vendor length |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |  Continuation | VALUE ...
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                            
   Type: 
                            
     26 for Vendor-Specific
   
   Length: 
                         
     6 + 3 + length of SubTypes 
   
   Vendor-Id:

     The Vendor-Id value for WiMAX is 24757.

   Vendor type:
  
     35 for PPAC

   Vendor length:
  
     3 + length of VALUE
                            
   Continuation:
                            
     The Continuation Field is defined as follows:
                            
     0
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |C|r|r|r|r|r|r|r|
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

     The C-bit of the continuation field indicates 
     if a attribute is being fragmented. When the 
     C-bit is set to one 1 this indicates that 
     the attribute is being fragmented that is
     the next VSA of the same type is to be appended 
     to this attribute. When the C-bit is set to zero 
     '0' this indicates that the next attribute is 
     not a fragment of this attribute.
     An attribute that is not being fragmented will 
     have the C-bit set to '0'. An attribute that is 
     being fragmented will have its C-bit set to '1' 
     for all fragments until the last fragment, which 
     will have its C-bit set to '0' indicating it's 
     the last fragment of the attribute. The r-bits 
     are reserved for future use. They SHALL be set 
     to zero by the sender and SHALL be ignored by 
     the receiver.

     The value of the C-bit MUST be 0.
                            
    VALUE : 
                            
     The content of the AvailableInClient (AiC) SubType fields 
     are encoded using the data type String.  
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t>The AvailableInClient (AiC) SubType is encoding as follows: <figure anchor="aic"
                        title="AvailableInClient (AiC) SubType">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[                            
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       | LENGTH        | AvailableInClient (AiC)      ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   |  AvailableInClient (AiC)      |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
    
   SubType : Value (1)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 4  

   AvailableInClient (AiC): The bitmap is encoded as:

   Value          | Description
   ------------  -+-------------------------------------
    0x00000001    | Volume metering supported
    0x00000010    | Duration metering supported
    0x00000100    | Resource metering supported
    0x00001000    | Pools supported 
    0x00010000    | Rating groups supported
    0x00100000    | Multi-Services supported
    0x01000000    | Tariff Switch supported
    0x10000000    | Reserved
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
            </section>

            <!-- ********************** Session Termination Capability ************************* -->

            <section anchor="statt" title="Session Termination Capability Attribute">
                <t> The Session Termination Capability attribute is included in the RADIUS
                    Access-Request message towards the RADIUS server to indicate whether or not the
                    NAS supports Dynamic Authorization. </t>


                <t>
                    <figure anchor="stermatt" title="Session Termination Capability Attribute">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |  Length       |            Vendor-Id
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      Vendor-Id (cont)           | Vendor type   | Vendor length |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |  Continuation | String ...
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                            
   Type: 
                            
     26 for Vendor-Specific
   
   Length: 
                         
     6 + 3 + 4 
   
   Vendor-Id:

     The Vendor-Id value for WiMAX is 24757.

   Vendor type:
  
     36 for Session Termination Capability

   Vendor length:
  
     3 + 4
                            
   Continuation:
                            
     The Continuation Field is defined as follows:
                            
     0
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |C|r|r|r|r|r|r|r|
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

     The C-bit of the continuation field indicates 
     if a attribute is being fragmented. When the 
     C-bit is set to one 1 this indicates that 
     the attribute is being fragmented that is
     the next VSA of the same type is to be appended 
     to this attribute. When the C-bit is set to zero 
     '0' this indicates that the next attribute is 
     not a fragment of this attribute.
     An attribute that is not being fragmented will 
     have the C-bit set to '0'. An attribute that is 
     being fragmented will have its C-bit set to '1' 
     for all fragments until the last fragment, which 
     will have its C-bit set to '0' indicating it's 
     the last fragment of the attribute. The r-bits 
     are reserved for future use. They SHALL be set 
     to zero by the sender and SHALL be ignored by 
     the receiver.

     The value of the C-bit MUST be 0.

   String: 
                
     This field is encoded as a bitmap. 
    
                
   Value          | Description
   ---------------+-------------------------------------
    0x00000000    | Reserved
    0x00000001    | Dynamic Authorization Extensions 
                  | (RFC 3576) is supported.
    ...           | All further values are reserved. 
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
            </section>

            <!-- ********************** PPAQ ************************* -->

            <section anchor="ppaqAtt" title="Prepaid Accounting Operation (PPAQ) Attribute">
                <t> One or more PPAQ attributes are sent in an Access Request, Authorize-Only
                    Access-Request and Access-Accept message. In an Access Request message, the PPAQ
                    attribute is used to facilitate one-time charging transactions. In
                    Authorize-Only Access-Request messages it is used for one-time charging, report
                    usage and to request further quota. It is also used in order to request prepaid
                    quota for a new service instance. In an Access-Accept message it is used in
                    order to allocate the (initial and subsequent) quotas. </t>
                <t> When multiple services are supported, a PPAQ is associated with a specific
                    service as indicated by the presence of a Service-Id, a Rating-Group-Id, or the
                    "Access Service" (as indicated by the absence of both, the Service-Id and the
                    Rating-Group-Id). </t>
                <t> Note: Either Volume-Quota, Time-Quota, or Resource-Quota SubTypes MUST appear in
                    the PPAQ attribute, except for the price enquiry message exchange where these
                    subtypes MUST be absent. A single PPAQ attribute MUST NOT contain more than one
                    Service-Id, MUST NOT contain more than one Rating-Group-Id, and MUST NOT contain
                    both a Service-Id and a Rating-Group-Id. A PPAQ that does not contain a
                    Service-ID or a Rating-Group-Id refers to the "Access Service". A PPAQ MUST NOT
                    contain more than one Pool-Id. A PPAQ that contains a Pool-Id MUST also contain
                    a Pool-Multiplier SubType. </t>
                <t> The PPAQ attribute, as shown in <xref target="ppaq"/>, has a variable length
                    (greater than 8, encoded into one octet), and consists of a variable number of
                    subtypes. Unused subtypes are omitted from the message.</t>
                <t>The following table summarizes the presence of various SubTypes in the PPAQ
                    attribute carried in the Access-Request and Access-Accept messages.</t>

                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Request             Accept        #  SubType Name

0-1(g)              0-1(m,n)      1  Quota Identifier
0-1(a,g)            0-1(a,k,n)    2  VolumeQuota
 0                  0-1(a,m,n)    3  VolumeThreshold
0-1(b,g)            0-1(b,k,n)    4  DurationQuota                        
 0                  0-1(b,m,n)    5  DurationThreshold
0-1(c,g)            0-1(c,k,n)    6  ResourceQuota
 0                  0-1(c,m,n)    7  ResourceThreshold
0-1(d,g)              0           8  Update-Reason
0-n(e,g)            0-n(e,m,n)    9  PrepaidServer
0-1(g,h,j)          0-1(m,n)     10 Service-ID
0-1(g,h,j)          0-1(m,n)     11 Rating-Group-ID
 0                  0-1(m,n)     12 Termination-Action
 0                  0-1(m,n)     13 Pool-ID
 0                  0-1(f,m,n)   14 Pool-Multiplier
0-1(g)                0          15 Requested-Action
 0                  0-1(k,m,n)   16 Check-Balance-Result
 0                  0-1(n)       17 Cost-Information 
                        ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>None of the above-listed SubTypes appears in the Access-Reject nor in the
                    Access-Challenge.</t>

                <t>Notes: <list style="empty">
                        <t> (a) SHALL be present if volume based charging is used. SHALL NOT be
                            present otherwise. Volume- Threshold is optional. </t>
                        <t>(b) SHALL be present if duration-based charging is used. SHALL NOT be
                            present otherwise. Duration- Threshold is optional. </t>
                        <t>(c) SHALL be present if resource-based charging is used. SHALL NOT be
                            present otherwise. Resource- Threshold is optional.</t>

                        <t>(d) SHALL be present in an Authorize-Only Access-Request. </t>
                        <t>(e) MAY be present in an Access-Accept. If present in Access Accept it
                            SHALL be present in Access- Request (except for the first
                            Access-Request). </t>
                        <t>(f) Pool-Multiplier SHALL be present when Pool-ID is present otherwise
                            Pool-Multiplier SHALL NOT be present in the PPAQ. </t>
                        <t>(g) If Requested-Action is present then Service-ID SHALL also be present
                            and all other attributes SHALL NOT be present. </t>
                        <t>(h) PPAQ SHALL NOT contain both a Service-ID and a Rating-Group-ID. </t>
                        <t>(j) A PPAQ that does not contain a Service-ID or a Rating-Group-Id refers
                            to the "Access Service"(ISF). </t>
                        <t>(k) If Balance-Check-Result is present and set to 0 then either
                            Volume-Quota, Duration-Quota or Resource- Quota SHALL be present. </t>
                        <t>(m) If Balance-Check-Result is present then Service-ID SHALL also be
                            present and other attributes (tagged with m) SHALL NOT be present. </t>
                        <t>(n) The PPAQ in which a Cost-Information occurs SHALL NOT include a
                            Quota-Identifier, because no quota is actually reserved by the PPS. The
                            Service-ID SHALL be present with the Cost-Information for that
                            Service-ID may not be present if the Cost-Information cannot be
                            provided. All other attribute SHALL not appear. </t>
                    </list>
                </t>

                <t>In the following subsections the various subtypes of the PPAQ attribute are
                    specified. </t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="ppaq" title="PPAQ Attribute Encoding Style">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |  Length       |            Vendor-Id
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      Vendor-Id (cont)           | Vendor type   | Vendor length |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |  Continuation | VALUE ...
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                            
   Type: 
                            
     26 for Vendor-Specific
   
   Length: 
                         
     6 + 3 + length of SubTypes 
   
   Vendor-Id:

     The Vendor-Id value for WiMAX is 24757.

   Vendor type:
  
     37 for PPAQ

   Vendor length:
  
     3 + length of SubTypes
                            
   Continuation:
                            
     The Continuation Field is defined as follows:
                            
     0
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |C|r|r|r|r|r|r|r|
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

     The C-bit of the continuation field indicates 
     if a attribute is being fragmented. When the 
     C-bit is set to one 1 this indicates that 
     the attribute is being fragmented that is
     the next VSA of the same type is to be appended 
     to this attribute. When the C-bit is set to zero 
     '0' this indicates that the next attribute is 
     not a fragment of this attribute.
     An attribute that is not being fragmented will 
     have the C-bit set to '0'. An attribute that is 
     being fragmented will have its C-bit set to '1' 
     for all fragments until the last fragment, which 
     will have its C-bit set to '0' indicating it's 
     the last fragment of the attribute. The r-bits 
     are reserved for future use. They SHALL be set 
     to zero by the sender and SHALL be ignored by 
     the receiver.

     The value of the C-bit MAY be 0 or 1. 
                                                                         
   VALUE: 
                            
     Data type String 
     Each SubType is then encoded in the following style: 
                            
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       | LENGTH        | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                
   SubType : 
      
      Contains an 8 bit unsigned integer. 
                            
   LENGTH  :

      Contains an 8 bit unsigned integer.
      The value of the LENGTH field is calculated as the length of the
      VALUE field plus two octets (one octet for the length of the 
      SubType field and another octet for the length of the LENGTH
      field).
                            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="qid" title="Quota Identifier (QID) SubType">
                    <t>The Quota Identifier (QID) is generated by the PPS and subsequently returned
                        in a PPAQ->QID subtype from the PPC to the PPS. This field has the semantic
                        of a transaction identifier and therefore changes with every transaction
                        initiated by the PPS to the PPC.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="Quota Identifier (QID) SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   |  VALUE                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                           
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(1)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + length of VALUE field.  
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>


                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="volumequota" title="VolumeQuota SubType">
                    <t> TVolumeQuota SubType is only present when volume-based charging is used. In
                        a RADIUS Access-Accept message (PPS to PPC direction), it indicates the
                        volume (in octets) allocated for the session by the PPS. In a RADIUS
                        Authorize-Only Access-Request message (PPC to PPS direction), it indicates
                        the totally used volume (in octets) for both inbound and outbound traffic.
                        The Exponent Field, if present, MUST NOT encode a negative number or zero. </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="VolumeQuota SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                   
   SubType : Value(2)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + (8 or 12)  
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field either contains the 
   Value-Digits Field (8 octets long) or the Value-Digits Field 
   plus the Exponent Field (12 octets long).
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="volumeth" title="VolumeThreshold SubType">
                    <t> The value of the type field of the VolumeThreshold SubType is TBD and its
                        length is 10 or 14 octets. This SubType is optionally present if the
                        VolumeQuota is present in a RADIUS Access-Accept message (PPS to PPC
                        direction). It is generated by the PPS and indicates the volume (in octets)
                        that has to be consumed before a new quota is requested. This threshold MUST
                        NOT be larger than the VolumeQuota. The Exponent Field, if present, MUST NOT
                        encode a negative number or zero. </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="VolumeThreshold SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                
   SubType : Value(3)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + (8 or 12)  
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field either contains the 
   Value-Digits Field (8 octets long) or the Value-Digits 
   SubType plus the Exponent Field 12 octets long). 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="durationquota" title="DurationQuota SubType">
                    <t>The optional DurationQuota SubType is only present if duration-based charging
                        is used. In a RADIUS Access-Accept message (PPS to PPC direction), it
                        indicates the duration (in seconds) allocated for the session by the PPS. In
                        a RADIUS Access-Request message (PPC to PPS direction), it indicates the
                        total duration (in seconds) since the start of the accounting session
                        related to the QID subtype of the PPAQ attribute in which it occurs. </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="DurationQuota SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   |  VALUE                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                           

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(4)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 4 
   
   VALUE : Data type string. 
                            
   The content of this field contains a 32-bit unsigned integer
   (with the values 0 to +4,294,967,295).
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="durationth" title="DurationThreshold SubType">
                    <t> The DurationThreshold SubType is optionally present if the DurationQuota is
                        present in a RADIUS Access-Accept message (PPS to PPC direction). It
                        represents the duration (in seconds) after which new quota should be
                        requested. This threshold MUST NOT be larger than the DurationQuota SubType.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="DurationThreshold SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   |  VALUE                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                           
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                   
   SubType : Value(5)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 4  
                                
   VALUE : Data type string. 
                            
   The content of this field contains a 32-bit unsigned integer
   (with the values 0 to +4,294,967,295).
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="ResourceQuota" title="ResourceQuota SubType">
                    <t> The optional ResourceQuota SubType is only present if resource-based or
                        one-time charging is used. In the RADIUS Access-Accept message (PPS to PPC
                        direction) it indicates the resources allocated for the session by the PPS.
                        In RADIUS Authorize-Only Access-Request message (PPC to PPS direction), it
                        indicates the resources used in total, including both incoming and outgoing
                        chargeable traffic. In one-time charging scenarios, the subtype represents
                        the number of units to charge the user. The attribute consists of a
                        Value-Digits Field and optionally an Exponent Field (as indicated by the
                        length field). </t>


                    <t>
                        <figure title="ResourceQuota SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
    
   SubType : Value(6)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + (8 or 12)  
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field either contains the 
   Value-Digits Field (8 octets long) or the Value-Digits Field 
   plus the Exponent Field (12 octets long). 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="resourceth" title="ResourceThreshold SubType">
                    <t> The semantic of the ResourceThreshold SubType follow those of the
                        VolumeThreshold and DurationThreshold SubType.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="ResourceThreshold SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(7)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + (8 or 12)
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field either contains the 
   Value-Digits Field (8 octets long) or the Value-Digits Field 
   plus the Exponent Field (12 octets long). 
    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="updatereason" title="Update-Reason SubType">
                    <t> The Update-Reason SubType is present in a RADIUS Access-Request message (PPC
                        to PPS direction) and indicates the reason for initiating the quota update
                        operation. Update reasons (6), (7), (8) and (9) indicate that the associated
                        resources are released at the PPC side, and that therefore the PPS MUST NOT
                        allocate a new quota in the RADIUS Access-Accept message. </t>


                    <t>
                        <figure title="Update-Reason SubType">

                            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
   0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType         | LENGTH        |      VALUE                  | 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                    
   SubType : Value(8)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 1  
                                
   VALUE : Data type string  
                
   This field contains a byte
   (with the values 0 to 255). 
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The following values for the Update-Reason SubType are defined:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure anchor="updatereason-table" title="Values for Update-Reason SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value        | Description
 -------------+--------------------------------------
   0          | Reserved
   1          | Pre-initialization 
   2          | Initial Request
   3          | Threshold Reached
   4          | Quota Reached
   5          | TITSU Approaching
   6          | Remote Forced Disconnect
   7          | Client Service Termination
   8          | "Access Service" Terminated
   9          | Service not established
  10          | One-Time Charging
  11...255    | **Available for IANA registration**
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="prepaidserver" title="PrepaidServer SubType">
                    <t> The optional PrepaidServer SubType indicates the address of the serving PPS.
                        If present, the Home RADIUS server uses this address to route the message to
                        the serving PPS. Multiple instances of this subtype MAY be present in a
                        single PPAQ attribute.</t>
                    <t> If present in the PrepaidServer SubType of an incoming RADIUS Access-Accept
                        message, the PPC returns this SubType back without modifying it in the
                        subsequent RADIUS Access-Request message. If multiple values are present,
                        the PPC MUST NOT change their order. </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="PrepaidServer SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | Address                      ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                                
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                
   SubType : Value(9)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + (4 or 16)
                                
   Address : Data type String 
                                
   For IPv4, the Address field is 4 octets based on the encoding of 
   the NAS-IP-Address defined in RFC 2138. For IPv6, the Address 
   field is 16 octets long.
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="serviceidavp" title="Service-ID SubType">
                    <t> The Service-ID SubType is handled as an opaque string that uniquely
                        describes the service instance for which prepaid metering should be applied.</t>
                    <t>A Service-Id could be an IP 5-tuple (source address, source port, destination
                        address, destination port, protocol). If a Service-ID SubType is present in
                        the PPAQ, the entire PPAQ attribute refers to that service. If a PPAQ
                        attribute does not contain a Service-Id or Rating-Group-ID, then the PPAQ
                        attribute refers to the "Access Service".</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="Service-ID SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | Service                      ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                
   SubType : Value(10)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + length (Service)  
                                
   Service : Data type String
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section toc="exclude" anchor="ratingroupid" title="Rating-Group-ID SubType">
                    <t> The Rating-Group-ID SubType indicates that this PPAQ attribute is associated
                        with resources allocated to a Rating Group with the corresponding ID. This
                        SubType is encoded as a string. A single PPAQ MUST NOT contain more than one
                        Rating-Group-ID.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="Rating-Group-ID SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   |  VALUE                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                           

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(11)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 4 
                                
   VALUE : Data type string with a length of 4 octets
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="termactavp" title="Termination-Action SubType">
                    <t> The value of the type field of the Termination-Action SubType is TBD. The
                        length of this SubType is 3 octets. This SubType contains an enumeration of
                        the action to take when the PPS does not grant additional quota. Valid
                        actions are as follows.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="Termination-Action SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2       
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3  
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | Action        |               
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(12)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 1   
                                
   Action : Data type string. 
   
   The content is a byte (with the values 0 to +255).
                                
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The following values for the Termination-Action SubType are defined:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure anchor="termactavp-table"
                            title="Values for the Termination-Action SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value        | Description
 -------------+------------------------------------
   0          | Reserved
   1          | Terminate
   2          | Request More Quota
   3          | Redirect/Filter
   4..255     | **Available for IANA registration**
                                ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="poolidavp" title="Pool-ID SubType">
                    <t> The Pool-ID SubType identifies the resource pool. It is encoded as a string.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="Pool-ID SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | Poolid                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(13)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 4 
                                
   Poolid : Data type string with length of 4 octets.   
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="poolmult" title="Pool-Multiplier SubType">
                    <t> The Pool-Multiplier SubType determines the weight of resources when they are
                        inserted into the pool that is identified by the accompanying Pool-ID
                        SubType, and the rate at which resources are taken out of the pool by the
                        relevant Service or Rating-Group. </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="Pool-Multiplier SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(14)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + (8 or 12)  
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field either contains the 
   Value-Digits Field (8 octets long) or the Value-Digits Field 
   plus the Exponent Field (12 octets long). 
                                ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="reqactavp" title="Requested-Action SubType">
                    <t> The Requested-Action SubType is only be present in messages sent from the
                        PPC to the PPS. It indicates that the PPC desires the PPS to perform the
                        indicated action and to return the result. The PPAQ in which a
                        Requested-Action SubType occurs MUST NOT contain a QID, and MUST contain a
                        Service-Identifier or a Rating-Group-Identifer that allows the PPS to
                        uniquely identify the service for which the indicated action is requested.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="Requested-Action SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2       
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3  
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | Action        |               
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(15)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 1  
                                
   Action : Data type string. 
   
   The content is a byte (with the values 0 to +255).
   The values are listed below.
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                    <t>The following values for the Action field of the Requested-Action SubType are
                        defined:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure anchor="reqactavp-table"
                            title="Values for the Requested-Action SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value        | Description
 -------------+-------------------------------------
   0          | Reserved
   1          | Balance Check
   2          | Price Enquiry
   3..255     | **Available for IANA registration**
                                ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="checkbalres" title="Check-Balance-Result SubType">
                    <t> The Check-Balance-Result SubType can only be present in messages sent from
                        the PPS to the PPC. It indicates the balance check decision of the PPS about
                        a previously received Balance Check Request (as indicated in a
                        Requested-Action SubType). The PPAQ attribute in which a
                        Check-Balance-Result occurs MUST NOT include a QID beause no quota is
                        reserved by the PPS. </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="Check-Balance-Result SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2       
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3  
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | Decision      |               
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(16)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 1
                                
   Decision : Data type string. 
   
   The content is a byte (with the values 0 to +255).
   The values are listed below.
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The following values for the Decision field of the Check-Balance-Result
                        SubType are defined:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure anchor="checkbalres-table"
                            title="Values for the Check-Balance-Result SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value        | Description
 -------------+-------------------------------------------
   0          | Success; Sufficient funds available 
              | in the user's prepaid account
   1          | Failure; Insufficient funds available
   2..255     | **Available for IANA registration**
                                ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="costinfo" title="Cost-Information SubType">
                    <t> The Cost-Information SubType is used in order to return the cost information
                        of a service, which the PPC can transfer transparently to the end user. This
                        SubType is sent from the PPS to the PPC as a response to a "Price Enquiry",
                        as indicated by the Requested-Action SubType. </t>


                    <t>
                        <figure title="Cost-Information SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(17)
                            
   LENGTH  : 2 + 12 + 4 + length of the Cost-Unit Field
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field contains (in this order) the 
   Value-Digits Field, Exponent Field, Currency-Code Field 
   and the Cost-Unit Field. 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>For example, the cost of 7.75 Malawi kwacha per hour would be encoded as
                        follows. Value-Digits = 775, Exponent = -2, Currency Code = 454, and
                        Cost-Unit = "hour". </t>
                    <t>The PPAQ that carries a Cost-Information MUST NOT include a QID. </t>
                    <t>The Currency-Code Field is of type Unsigned32 and used inside the
                        Check-Balance-Result SubType and contains a currency code that specifies in
                        which currency the values of AVPs containing monetary units were given. It
                        is specified by using the numeric values defined in the ISO 3166-1 standard. </t>

                    <t>The Cost-Unit Field is used inside the Check-Balance-Result SubType and
                        contains a human readable UTF8 encoded string that can be displayed to the
                        end user. It specifies the applicable unit to the Cost-Information when the
                        service cost is a cost per unit (e.g., cost of the service is $1 per
                        minute). The Cost-Unit can, for example, be minutes, hours, days, kilobytes,
                        megabytes, etc. </t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Fields">
                <section toc="exclude" anchor="valdigts" title="Value-Digits Field">
                    <t> The Value-Digits Field is an Unsigned64 value (with a length of 8 octets)
                        that contains the significant digits of the number. If decimal values are
                        needed to present the number, the scaling MUST be indicated with a related
                        Exponent Field, see <xref target="exponent"/>.</t>
                    <t>For example, the decimal number 0.05 is encoded by a Value-Digits Field set
                        to 5, and a scaling that is indicated with the Exponent Field set to -2. </t>
                    <t>The encoding of this SubType is not done in an TLV format but rather the
                        encoded value is added to existing subtypes. </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="exponent" title="Exponent Field">
                    <t> The Exponent field is a Integer32 value that contains the exponent value
                        that is to be applied to the accompanying Value-Digit Field. </t>
                </section>
            </section>


            <!-- ********************* PTS ******************** -->

            <section anchor="tariffsw" title="Prepaid Tariff Switching (PTS) Attribute">
                <t> This specification defines the PTS attribute, which allows to switch from one
                    rate to another during service provision. Support for tariff switching is
                    optional to implement and to use for the PPC and the PPS. PPCs use the flag
                    "Tariff Switching supported" in the AvailableInClient field of the PPAC
                    attribute in order to indicate support for tariff switching. PPSs employ the PTS
                    attribute in order to announce their support for tariff switching. </t>
                <t> If a RADIUS message contains a PTS attribute, it MUST also contain at least one
                    PPAQ attribute. If a RADIUS Access-Request message contains a PTS attribute or
                    the "Tariff Switching supported" flag in the AvailableInClient field of the PPAC
                    attribute, it MUST also contain an Event-Timestamp RADIUS attribute (see <xref
                        target="RFC2869"/>). </t>
                <t> Every PTS attribute MUST include a QID SubType, as specified in <xref
                        target="qid"/>. In a RADIUS Access-Request message sent from the PPC to the
                    PPS, the QID SubType MUST contain the value of the Quota Identifier SubType that
                    was previously received from the PPS and MUST be the same as the value carried
                    in the QID SubType of one of the PPAQ attributes included the same RADIUS
                    message.</t>
                <t>If multiple services are supported and if the PPAQ is associated with a service
                    as indicated by the Service-ID SubType, then the PTS refers to the tariff switch
                    for that service. If the PPAQ does not have a Service-ID, then the PTS refers to
                    tariff switch for the "Access Service". </t>
                <t> A PPAQ attribute that is transported along with a PTS attribute and has the same
                    value as the QID SubType contained in the PTS attribute in its own QID SubType
                    is referred to as the "accompanying PPAQ attribute". If a PPS receives an
                    Access-Request message from a PPC, it associates a unique value for the QID
                    SubType to this request. </t>

                <t>The following table summarizes the presence of various SubTypes in the PTS
                    attribute carried in the Access-Request and Access-Accept messages.</t>

                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
Request           Accept        #  SubType Name
 1                  1           1  Quota Identifier
 1                  0           2  VolumeUsedAfterTariffSwitch
 0                 0-1          3  TarrifSwitchInterval
 0                 0-1(a)       4  TimeIntervalAfterTarriffSwitchUpdate
                        ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>None of the above-listed SubTypes appears in the Access-Reject nor in the
                    Access-Challenge.</t>

                <t>Notes: <list style="empty">
                        <t> (a) The PPS SHALL include this AVP if there is another tariff switch
                            period after the period that ends as indicated by the TSI attribute.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>
                    <figure anchor="pts" title="PTS Attribute">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |     Type      |  Length       |            Vendor-Id
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      Vendor-Id (cont)           | Vendor type   | Vendor length |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |  Continuation | VALUE ...
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                            
   Type: 
                            
     26 for Vendor-Specific
   
   Length: 
                         
     6 + 3 + length of SubTypes 
   
   Vendor-Id:

     The Vendor-Id value for WiMAX is 24757.

   Vendor type:
  
     38 for PTS

   Vendor length:
  
     3 + length of SubTypes
                            
   Continuation:
                            
     The Continuation Field is defined as follows:
                            
     0
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |C|r|r|r|r|r|r|r|
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

     The C-bit of the continuation field indicates 
     if a attribute is being fragmented. When the 
     C-bit is set to one 1 this indicates that 
     the attribute is being fragmented that is
     the next VSA of the same type is to be appended 
     to this attribute. When the C-bit is set to zero 
     '0' this indicates that the next attribute is 
     not a fragment of this attribute.
     An attribute that is not being fragmented will 
     have the C-bit set to '0'. An attribute that is 
     being fragmented will have its C-bit set to '1' 
     for all fragments until the last fragment, which 
     will have its C-bit set to '0' indicating it's 
     the last fragment of the attribute. The r-bits 
     are reserved for future use. They SHALL be set 
     to zero by the sender and SHALL be ignored by 
     the receiver.

     The value of the C-bit MAY be 0 or 1. 
                                                   
   VALUE : Variable length content of data type String containing 
           one or multiple SubTypes. 

   Each SubType is then encoding in the following style: 
                            
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       | LENGTH        | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
                            
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                
   SubType: 
      
      Contains an 8 bit unsigned integer. 
                            
   LENGTH:

      Contains an 8 bit unsigned integer. 

   VALUE: 
      
      Contains the content of the SubType.
                            
                            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <section toc="exclude" anchor="vuats" title="VolumeUsedAfterTariffSwitch SubType">
                    <t> The optional VolumeUsedAfterTariffSwitch (VUATS) SubType is used in the
                        RADIUS Access-Request messages (PPC to PPS direction). It indicates the
                        volume (in octets) used during a session after the last tariff switch for
                        the service specified via the QID SubType and the accompanying PPAQ
                        attribute.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="VolumeUsedAfterTariffSwitch SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
                    
   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(23)
                            
   LENGTH  : variable (8 or 14)  
                                
   VALUE : Data type String 
                                
   The content of the VALUE field either contains the 
   Value-Digits Field or the Value-Digits Field plus the 
   Exponent Field. The length field indicates whether one or
   both subtypes are included. 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="tsi" title="TariffSwitchInterval SubType">
                    <t> The TariffSwitchInterval (TSI) SubType MUST be present in each PTS attribute
                        that is part of a RADIUS Access-Accept message (PPS to PPC direction). It
                        indicates the interval (in seconds) between the value of Event-Timestamp
                        RADIUS attribute (see <xref target="RFC2869"/>) of the corresponding RADIUS
                        Access-Request message and the next tariff switch condition. </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="TariffSwitchInterval SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   |  VALUE                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                           

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(24)
                            
   LENGTH  : 6  
                                
   VALUE : Data type string  
                                
   This field contains a 16-bit unsigned integer
   (with the values 0 to +65,535). 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="titsu"
                    title="TimeIntervalafterTariffSwitchUpdate SubType">
                    <t> The PPS MUST include TimeIntervalafterTariffSwitchUpdate (TITSU) SubType if
                        there is another tariff switch period after the period that ends as
                        indicated by the TSI SubType. The value of the TITSU SubType contains the
                        number of seconds of the tariff period that begins immediately after the
                        period that ends as indicated by the TSI attribute. If the TITSU SubType is
                        not present, the PPC assumes that the tariff period, which ends as indicated
                        by the TSI SubType, lasts until further notice. If TITSU is specified, the
                        PPC MUST send a quota update before the point in time specified by the TITSU
                        SubType (see <xref target="mtsdiagram"/>). </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure title="TimeIntervalafterTariffSwitchUpdate SubType">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[                             
    0                   1                   2                   3 
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
   | SubType       |    LENGTH     | VALUE                        ...
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    
   |  VALUE                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                           

   The fields have the following meaning and encoding: 
                                  
   SubType : Value(25)
                            
   LENGTH  : 6  
                                
   VALUE : Data type string  
                                
   This field contains a 16-bit unsigned integer
   (with the values 0 to +65,535). 
                    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section title="Diameter RADIUS Interoperability">
            <t> The RADIUS Prepaid extension described in this document may need to interoperate
                with the Diameter Credit Control Application. Two interoperability scenarios exist,
                as follows. Either the AAA server is Diameter based and the AAA client is RADIUS
                based, or the AAA client is Diameter based and the AAA server is RADIUS based. </t>

            <t> The Diameter Credit Control Application <xref target="RFC4006"/> describes how to
                implement a prepaid accounting system using a Diameter based infrastructure. </t>

            <t>A possible procedure for accomplishing the translation of the functionality defined
                in Diameter Credit Control and in the RADIUS Prepaid specification is described in
                    <xref target="translator"/>.</t>

        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section anchor="sec" title="Security Considerations">
            <t> This specification describes the use of RADIUS for purposes of real-time accounting.
                Threats and security issues for this application are described in <xref
                    target="RFC3579"/> and <xref target="RFC3580"/>; security issues encountered in
                roaming are described in <xref target="RFC2607"/>. </t>
            <t> This document specifies new attributes that can be included in existing RADIUS
                packets, which are protected as described in <xref target="RFC3579"/> and <xref
                    target="RFC3576"/>. See those documents for a more detailed description. </t>
            <t> The security mechanisms supported in RADIUS are focused on preventing an attacker
                from spoofing packets or modifying packets in transit. They do not prevent an
                authorized RADIUS/Diameter server or proxy from modifying, inserting, or removing
                attributes with malicious intent. When the attributes defined in this document are
                modified or removed by a RADIUS proxy they may lead to incorrect accounting records
                being delivered to users or wrong resource consumption being collected. </t>
            <t> The described mechanism add the mechanism of capability negotiation, so that a
                RADIUS server can automatically discover whether a NAS supports the real-time
                accounting features described in this document (and even more detailed capabilities
                can be learned by the RADIUS server). These mechanisms are being added to ensure
                that neither the NAS nor the RADIUS server make incorrect assumptions about the
                capabilities of the other party; potentially leading to incorrect accounting and
                improper access to the network or other services. </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->
        <section anchor="table-of-attributes" title="Table of Attributes">
            <t>The following table provides a guide which attributes may be found in which RADIUS
                messages, and in what quantity.</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
Request Accept Reject Challenge Accounting  #  Attribute
                                Request
0-1     0      0      0         0          35  PPAC
0-1     0      0      0         0          36  Session Termination
                                               Capability
0+      0+     0      0         0+         37  PPAQ
0+      0+     0      0         0+         38  PTS
]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>
        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section anchor="iana_cons" title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>This document contains a number of instructions to IANA.</t>

            <section toc="exclude" title="RADIUS Attributes">
                <t>This document does not require IANA to register the following four RADIUS
                    attributes as the code registered by the Wimax Forum is re-used. The Wimax Forum
                    SMI Network Management Private Enterprise Code is 24757. </t>
                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Attribute Name                        |  Attribute Type Value
 --------------------------------------+-----------------------------
 Prepaid-Accounting-Capability (PPAC)  |  35
 Session Termination Capability        |  36
 Prepaid-Accounting-Operation (PPAQ)   |  37
 Prepaid Tariff Switching (PTS)        |  38
                            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: PPAC SubTypes">
                <t><xref target="ppacatt"/> defines the SubTypes used within the PPAC attribute.
                    IANA is asked to create a registry for these SubTypes. Each registry entry
                    consists of a 8 bit number together with a description of the PPAC SubType. This
                    document creates the following PPAC SubTypes for this registry:</t>
                <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value    |  SubType Name
 ---------+-----------------------------
   0      |  Reserved
   1      |  AvailableInClient 
   2..255 |  **Available for IANA registration**
                                                    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure> The semantic of the above-listed SubType is described in <xref
                        target="ppacatt"/>. </t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available SubTypes
                    (i.e., value 0 and values 2-255) with a description of their semantic will be
                    assigned after the expert review process. Updates can be provided based on
                    expert approval only. Based on expert approval it is possible to mark entries as
                    "deprecated". A designated expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
                <t>Each registration must include a number for the SubType and the semantic of the
                    SubType.</t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: PPAQ SubTypes">
                <t><xref target="ppaqAtt"/> defines the SubTypes used within the PPAQ attribute.
                    IANA is asked to create a registry for these SubTypes. Each registry entry
                    consists of a 8 bit number together with a description of the PPAQ SubType. This
                    document creates the following PPAQ SubTypes for this registry:</t>
                <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value    |  SubType Name
 ---------+-----------------------------
   0      |  Reserved
   1      |  Quota Identifier
   2      |  VolumeQuota
   3      |  VolumeThreshold
   4      |  DurationQuota
   5      |  DurationThreshold
   6      |  ResourceQuota
   7      |  ResourceThreshold
   8      |  Update-Reason
   9      |  PrepaidServer
  10      |  Service-ID
  11      |  Rating-Group-ID
  12      |  Termination-Action
  13      |  Pool-ID
  14      |  Pool-Multiplier
  15      |  Requested-Action
  16      |  Check-Balance-Result
  17..255 |  **Available for IANA registration**
                            ]]></artwork>
                    </figure> The semantic of the above-listed SubTypes is described in <xref
                        target="ppaqAtt"/>. </t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available SubTypes
                    (i.e., value 0 and values 22-255) with a description of their semantic will be
                    assigned after the expert review process. Updates can be provided based on
                    expert approval only. Based on expert approval it is possible to mark entries as
                    "deprecated". A designated expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
                <t>Each registration must include a number for the SubType and the semantic of the
                    SubType.</t>
            </section>


            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: PTS SubTypes">
                <t><xref target="tariffsw"/> defines the SubTypes used within the PTS attribute.
                    IANA is asked to create a registry for these SubTypes. Each registry entry
                    consists of a 8 bit number together with a description of the PTS SubType. This
                    document creates the following PTS SubTypes for this registry:</t>
                <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
 Value    |  SubType Name
 ---------+-----------------------------
   0      |  Reserved
   1      |  Quota Identifier
   2      |  VolumeUsedAfterTariffSwitch
   3      |  TariffSwitchInterval
   4      |  TimeIntervalafterTariffSwitchUpdate
   5..255 |  **Available for IANA registration**
                                                    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure> The semantic of the above-listed SubTypes is described in <xref
                        target="tariffsw"/>. </t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available SubTypes
                    (i.e., value 0 and values 5-255) with a description of their semantic will be
                    assigned after the expert review process. Updates can be provided based on
                    expert approval only. Based on expert approval it is possible to mark entries as
                    "deprecated". A designated expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
                <t>Each registration must include a number for the SubType and the semantic of the
                    SubType.</t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: Update-Reason">
                <t><xref target="updatereason"/> defines the Update-Reason SubType. IANA is asked to
                    create a registry for the values contained in the Update-Reason SubType, as
                    shown in <xref target="updatereason-table"/>. Each registry entry consists of a
                    16 bit number together with a description of the update reason.</t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available values
                    together with a description of their semantic will be assigned after the expert
                    review process. Updates can be provided based on expert approval only. Based on
                    expert approval it is possible to mark entries as "deprecated". A designated
                    expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: Termination-Action">
                <t><xref target="termactavp"/> defines the Termination-Action SubType. IANA is asked
                    to create a registry for the values contained in the Termination-Action SubType,
                    as shown in <xref target="termactavp-table"/>. Each registry entry consists of a
                    8 bit number together with a description of the termination action.</t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available values
                    together with a description of their semantic will be assigned after the expert
                    review process. Updates can be provided based on expert approval only. Based on
                    expert approval it is possible to mark entries as "deprecated". A designated
                    expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: Requested-Action">
                <t><xref target="reqactavp"/> defines the Requested-Action SubType. IANA is asked to
                    create a registry for the values contained in the Requested-Action SubType, as
                    shown in <xref target="reqactavp-table"/>. Each registry entry consists of a 8
                    bit number together with a description of the requested reason.</t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available values
                    together with a description of their semantic will be assigned after the expert
                    review process. Updates can be provided based on expert approval only. Based on
                    expert approval it is possible to mark entries as "deprecated". A designated
                    expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" title="New Registry: Check-Balance-Result">
                <t><xref target="checkbalres"/> defines the Check-Balance-Result SubType. IANA is
                    asked to create a registry for the values contained in the Check-Balance-Result
                    SubType, as shown in <xref target="checkbalres-table"/>. Each registry entry
                    consists of a 8 bit number together with a description of the requested reason.</t>
                <t>Following the policies outline in <xref target="RFC3575"/> the available values
                    together with a description of their semantic will be assigned after the expert
                    review process. Updates can be provided based on expert approval only. Based on
                    expert approval it is possible to mark entries as "deprecated". A designated
                    expert will be appointed by the IESG. </t>
            </section>

        </section>

        <!-- ====================================================================== -->

        <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
            <t> The authors would like to thank Bernard Aboba, Christian Guenther, Dirk Kroeselberg
                and John Loughney for their feedback throughout the development of this document.
                Additionally, the authors would like to thank the members of the Wimax Forum and the
                members of 3GPP2 for their help with this specification. </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">

            <reference anchor="RFC2119">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 2119: Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
                    <author initials="S" surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="March" year="1997"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="RFC2865">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 2865: Remote Authentication Dial In User Server (RADIUS)</title>
                    <author initials="C" surname="Rigney" fullname="C. Rigney">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="A" surname="Rubens" fullname="A. Rubens">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="W" surname="Simpson" fullname="W. Simpson">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="S" surname="Willens" fullname="S. Willens">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="June" year="2000"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="RFC3576">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 3576: Dynamic Authorization Extensions to Remote Authentication
                        Dial-In User Service (RADIUS)</title>
                    <author initials="M" surname="Chiba" fullname="M. Chiba">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="G" surname="Dommety" fullname="G. Dommety">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="M" surname="Eklund" fullname="M. Eklund">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="D" surname="Mitton" fullname="D. Mitton">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="B" surname="Adoba" fullname="B. Adoba">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="February" year="2003"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            <reference anchor="RFC2866">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 2866: RADIUS Accounting</title>
                    <author initials="C" surname="Rigney" fullname="C. Rigney">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="June" year="2000"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="RFC2869">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 2869: RADIUS Extensions</title>
                    <author initials="C" surname="Rigney" fullname="C. Rigney">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="W" surname="Willats" fullname="W. Willats">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="P" surname="Calhoun" fullname="P. Calhoun">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="June" year="2000"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="RFC3748">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 3748: Extensible Authentication Protocol</title>
                    <author initials="B" surname="Adoba" fullname="B. Adoba">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="L" surname="Blunk" fullname="L. Blunk">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="J" surname="Vollbrecht" fullname="J. Vollbrecht">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="J" surname="Carlson" fullname="J. Carlson">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="H" surname="Levkowetz" fullname="H. Levkowetz">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="June" year="2004"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="RFC4006">
                <front>
                    <title>RFC 4006: Diameter Credit Control Application</title>
                    <author initials="H" surname="Hakala" fullname="H. Hakala">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="L" surname="Mattila" fullname="L. Mattila">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="J-P" surname="Koskinen" fullname="J-P. Koskinen">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="M" surname="Stura" fullname="M. Stura">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="J" surname="Loughney" fullname="J. Loughney">
                        <organization/>
                    </author>
                    <date month="August" year="2005"/>
                </front>
            </reference> &RFC2284; &RFC4849; &RFC3575; &RFC2607; &RFC3579; &RFC6158;
            &RFC3580; </references>


        <section anchor="flows" title="Example flows">
            <t>Note: This section is informative.</t>
            <t> This section presents certain example flows that involve the RADIUS prepaid
                extensions. By no means is the intent of this section to specify or recommend
                business logic, rating strategies, and application-level behaviour. The intent of
                this section is purely to illustrate some fictive scenarios and the RADIUS prepaid
                message flows that could be associated with these scenarios. The contents of this
                section should be regarded as a collection of informative examples that aim to
                provide guidance to implementors.</t>

            <section anchor="simpleflow" title="A simple flow">

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="simpleflowexample" title="A simple example message flow ">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
   End user          PPC                  PPS                 

   user logs on
   ------(1)--------->
                         Access Request
                         {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                          PPAC=00...00011}
                         -------(2)-------->

                                            [allocates
                                            5MB quota]

                             Access Accept
                            {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                            PPAQ={QID=5, VQ = 5MB,
                            VTH = 4.5 MB}}
                            <-------(3)--------

   service provision/metering
   -------(4)--------->

   4.5 MB consumed

                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=5, VQ=4.5MB,
                       REASON=THRESHOLD REACHED}}
                       -------(5)--------->

                                    [allocates another 7MB
                                   to the access service]

                           Access Accept
                           {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                           PPAQ={QID=8, VQ=12MB,
                           VTH = 11.5 MB}}
                       <----------(6)--------------
     user logs off
   ------(7)-------
                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=8, VQ=7 MB,
                       REASON=ACCESS SERV TERMINATED}}
                       -------(8)--------->

                                     [reimburses
                                     user account]
 
                           AA Accept
                          {RADIUS BASE AVPS}
                         <-------(9)--------                                         
    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t> The user logs on (1). The PPC sends a RADIUS Access Request message to the PPS
                    (2), and includes the prepaid-specific PPAC AVP. This AVP indicates that both
                    duration-based and volume-based metering is supported. However, it also
                    indicated that multiple services, rating groups and resource pools are not
                    supported. Note that, since this is not an "Authorize-Only" message, no PPAQ
                    attribute with Update Reason="initial request" is included (see Section 3.7.1).
                    The PPS then authenticates the user and authorizes the access service, as is
                    usual in RADIUS. Note that the PPAC AVP is appended by the PPC in at least the
                    last message that is sent to the home AAA server during this possibly
                    multiple-round exchange. </t>

                <t> If authentication and authorization is successful (in this example this is
                    assumed), then the PPS identifies the user's prepaid account from the included
                    base RADIUS AVPs, and determines the capabilities of the PPC from the PPAC
                    attribute. Assuming that sufficient funds are available in the user's prepaid
                    account, the PPS reserves some of these and rates the service. In this example,
                    the PPS reserves, say, 2 Euros and determines that the access service is rated
                    at 0.4 Euro per MB. This results in 5 MB of quota being granted. The PPS also
                    determines that the PPC should ask for this quota to be replenished once 4.5 MB
                    have been consumed. Thus, it creates an Access Accept message with a
                    Volume-Threshold indication of 4.5MB. It further associates the QID=5 to this
                    reservation. This identifier can be used to later uniquely identify the prepaid
                    session, user, account, etc. The resulting Access Accept message is sent to the
                    PPC (3). </t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (4), the PPC provides the access service to the user
                    and meters it accordingly. At some point in time, the threshold is reached,
                    i.e., 4.5MB of "access service" have been consumed by the user. At that point,
                    the PPC generates an Authorize-Only Access Request that contains the usual
                    RADIUS attributes and a PPAQ attributes that reports the amount of consumed
                    quota, and the request for replenishment, i.e., the Update-Reason= THRESHOLD
                    REACHED (5). Note that the QID in this message is the same as the one previously
                    received from the PPS.</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (5), the PPS identifies the user and his account from
                    the QID. In also determines that a prepaid session is ongoing, and that enough
                    credit remains in the prepaid account in order for the access service to
                    continue being provided. Since 4.5 MB have been consumed, the PPS subtracts 1.8
                    Euros from the user's prepaid account. The PPS decides to reserve another 2.8
                    euros from the user's account. (This results in 3 euros being reserved in total
                    at this point in time.) As the access service is rated at 0.4 euros per MB, the
                    PPS determines that another 7 MB of quota should be granted. This results in a
                    total cumulative quota allocation of 12 MB for the access service. The PPS
                    further calculates the new threshold value of 11.5 MB. Since this is a new quota
                    reservation, the PPS also allocates a new QID to it, in this example QID=8. The
                    resulting RADIUS message is sent to the PPC (6).</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (6), the PPC updates its records and continues
                    provisioning access to the user. At some point the user logs off (7). The PPC
                    must then report how many resources were consumed, so that the PPC can subtract
                    the appropriate monetary amount from the user's prepaid account. To this end the
                    PPC constructs an Authorize-Only Access Request message with a PPAQ attributes
                    for the access service. In this example, 7 MB were consumed by the access
                    service in total. The PPC reports 7 MB its final message (8). The PPS correlates
                    the report, using the QID, to the previous session state. It determines, from
                    the previous records, that the access service had consumed another 4.5 MB before
                    (as indicated in message (6)). This means that, of the 7 MB, only 3.5 MB have
                    not yet been subtracted from the user's account. Thus, the PPS subtracts another
                    1.4 euros from the user's account and, since the session is to be terminated
                    (REASON=ACCESS SERVICE TERMINATED), releases any reserved monetary amount.</t>

                <t> The PPS responds with an Access Response as required by the RADIUS base
                    specification (9). </t>


            </section>
            <section anchor="ptsflow" title="A flow with prepaid tariff switching">

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="ptsflowexample" title="Example message flow with Tariff Switch">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
End user          PPC                  PPS

   user logs on
   ------(1)--------->
                         Access Request
                         {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                          PPAC=00...00111}
                         -------(2)-------->

                                     [allocates
                                     20MB quota]

                                Access Accept
                             {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                        PPAQ={QID=5, VQ = 20MB,
                           VTH = 18 MB}, PTS={
                         QID=5, PTS{TSI=300sec,
                                TITSU=6000sec}}
                           <-------(3)-------
 
   service provision/metering
   -------(4)--------->

   5900 seconds 
   passed
                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=5, VQ=14MB,
                       REASON=TITSU APPROACH.},
                       TSI={QID=5, VUATS=11MB}}
                       -------(5)--------->

                                
                               [allocates another 10MB
                               to the access service]

                       Access Accept
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=8, VQ=30MB,
                       VTH = 28 MB},PTS={
                       QUD=8, PTS=95 sec}}
                  <----------(6)--------------


     user logs off
   ------(7)-------

                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=8, VQ=17 MB,
                       REASON=ACCESS SERV TERMINATED},
                       PTS={QID=8, VUATS=2.5 MB}
                       -------(8)--------->


                                       [reimburses
                                       user account]

                             AA Accept
                            {RADIUS BASE AVPS}
                           <-------(9)--------                                         
    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t> The user logs on (1). The PPC sends a RADIUS Access Request message to the home
                    AAA server (2), and includes the prepaid-specific PPAC AVP. This AVP indicates
                    that both duration-based and volume-based metering is supported, as well as
                    tariff switching. The home AAA server then may authenticate and user and
                    authorize the access service, as is usual in RADIUS. Note that the PPAC AVP is
                    appended by the PPC in at least the last message that is sent to the PPS during
                    this possibly multiple-round exchange.</t>

                <t> If authentication and authorization is successful (in this example this is
                    assumed), the PPS identifies the user's prepaid account from the included base
                    RADIUS AVPs, and determines the capabilities of the PPC from the PPAC attribute.
                    In this example, it is assumed that a tariff switch is about to occur in 300
                    seconds from the current time. Suppose that the access service is currently
                    rated at 0.5 euros per MB and in the next tariff period it is rated at 0.6 euros
                    per MB. Suppose further that a third tariff period is about to start in 6000
                    seconds from current time and that that access service is rated at 0.8 euros per
                    MB in that period. The PPS then decides to reserve 12 euros from the user's
                    account. Since it is conceivable that the user may consume all allocated quota
                    in the (more expensive) "0.6-euro" period, the PPS reserves 20 MB of quota, and
                    determines a threshold value of 18 MB. It constructs a Radius Access Accept
                    message with a PPAQ attribute that reflects these choices, and carries a Quota
                    Identifier QID=5. It further adds a PTS AVP in the message which is linked to
                    the PPAQ via the common QID value. The PTS AVP contains a TSI attribute
                    indicating that a tariff switch will occur in 300 seconds. It also includes a
                    TITSU attribute with the value of 6000 seconds. This is included in order to
                    make sure that the PPC will report the consumed quota before the "2-euro" tariff
                    period will start. The message is sent to the PPC (3).</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (3), the PPC provides the access service to the user
                    and meters it accordingly (4). It also keeps track of time. That is, it
                    remembers how many octets are consumed before and how many after the tariff
                    switch that will take place in 300 seconds.</t>

                <t> In this example it is assumed that the user consumes the allocated quota rather
                    slowly. In particular, nearly 6000 seconds (the value indicated by TITSU
                    SubType) pass without the threshold of 18 MB being reached. The PPC notices this
                    and must therefore report usage and request the quota to be replenished despite
                    the fact that the threshold has not been reached. In this example, it decides to
                    do so 100 seconds before the 6000 seconds are reached. To this end, it
                    constructs an Authorization Access Request message including a PPAQ that
                    indicates that 14 MB have been consumed up to now. It also includes a PTS
                    attribute in order to indicate, using the VUATS SubType, that 11 MB of these
                    were consumed after the tariff switch. The message is sent to the the PPS (5).</t>

                <t>The PPS can link the message to previous session state via the QID. It now rates
                    the consumed volume as follows. The 11 MB that were consumed after the tariff
                    switch correspond to 11 * 0.6 = 6.6 euros and the remaining 14-11=3 MB to 3 *
                    0.5 = 1.5 euros. Thus, the PPS subtracts the amount of 6.6+1.5=8.1 euros from
                    the user's account, which leads to a remainder of 12 - 8.1 = 3.9 euros being
                    reserved.</t>

                <t> The PPS now determines that message (5) was sent in order to replenish the quota
                    for this prepaid session. This can be deduced from the UPDATE REASON field,
                    which indicates that the PPC sent this message because the time indicated by the
                    TITSU SubType is approacing. The PPS now determines that enough credit remains
                    in the user's prepaid account in order for the access service to continue being
                    provided and decides to reserve another 8.9 euros from the user's account. Since
                    it is conceivable that the user will consume the 6 unused MB of quota from the
                    previous allocation, as well as the entire quota that is to be allocated now,
                    entirely in the "0.8-euro" period, the quota that should now be granted in
                    addition to the previous 20 MB should be 10 MB. This is because 0.9 of the 8.9
                    euros are being reserved in order to "cover the worst case scenario". The fact
                    that 0.9 euros are reserved for this purpose is due to the fact that the unused
                    6 MB from the previous allocation correspond to 4.8 euros (with 0.8 euros per
                    MB). This is 4.8 - 3.9 = 0.9 euros more than the amount of funds that are still
                    "reserved" from the previous allocation. (After this reservation, the total
                    amount of reserved money is 8.9 + 3.9 = 12.8 euros, which corresponds to 16
                    (10+6) MB being consumed in the "0.8-euro" period.)</t>

                <t> Since quotas are encoded in a cumulative way in RADIUS, the PPS includes a
                    VolumeQuota of 30 MB into the Access Accept message (6). The PPS further
                    calculates the new threshold value of 28 MB. Since this is a new quota
                    reservation, the PPS also allocates a new QID to it, in this example QID=8. The
                    resulting RADIUS message is sent to the PPC (6).</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (6), the PPC updates its records and continues
                    providing access to the user. At some point the user logs off (7). The PPC must
                    then report how many resources were consumed, so that the PPC can subtract the
                    appropriate monetary amount from the user's prepaid account. To this end the PPC
                    constructs an Authorize- Only Access Request message with a PPAQ attributes for
                    the access service. In this example, 17 MB were consumed by the access service
                    in total. The PPC reports 17 MB its final message (8). The PPS correlates the
                    report, using the QID, to the previous session state. It determines, from the
                    previous records, that the access service had consumed 14 MB before (as
                    indicated in message (5)). This means that, of the 17 MB, only the monetary
                    equivalent for 3 MB have not yet been subtracted from the user's account. The
                    PPS calculates how much should be deducted from the user's account as follows.
                    Since the VUATS SubType indicates that 2.5MB were consumed after the tariff
                    switch, only 0.5 MB were consumed before that. Thus, the monetary equivalent is
                    0.5 * 0.6 + 2.5 * 0.8 = 3.6 euros. That is, the PPS subtracts 3.6 euros from the
                    user's prepaid account. Since the session has by now be terminated by the PPC
                    (REASON=ACCESS SERVICE TERMINATED), the PPS now releases any reserved monetary
                    amount, in this example 12.8 - 3.6 = 9.2 euros.</t>

                <t> The PPS responds with an Access Response as required by the RADIUS base
                    specification (9).</t>

                <t> Remark: In this example, two tariff switches take place. In other scenarios, of
                    course, only one tariff switch may occur. In such scenarios the TITSU SubType is
                    not used.</t>

            </section>

            <section anchor="rpoolflow" title="Resource pools and Rating Groups">

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="rpoolflowexample"
                        title="Example message flow with resource pools and rating groups">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
   End user          PPC                  PPS

   user logs on
   ------(1)--------->

                         Access Request
                         {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                          PPAC=00...00101111}
                         -------(2)-------->


                                       [allocates
                                       5MB quota]

                         Access Accept
                        {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                        PPAQ={QID=5, VQ = 5MB,
                        poolID=1,mult=1}}
                       <-------(3)--------

   service provision/metering
   -------(4)--------->

   user requests service A
   -------(5)--------->

                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,PPAQ={
                       SID="A", RGROUP=1}}
                        -------(6)-------->

                        [allocates 50 min
                                    quota]

                       Access Accept
                      {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                      PPAQ={QID=7, DQ=3000sec
                      poolID=1,RGROUP=1, SID="A"
                      mult=1747.63}}
                      <---------(7)---------------

   user requests service B
   -------(8)-------->

   Pool 1 close to exhaustion

                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=5, VQ=4MB,
                       REASON=QUOTA REACHED,
                       PoolID=1, mult=1}
                       PPAQ={QID=7, DQ=3300sec
                       REASON=QUOTA REACHED,
                       PoolID=1, mult=1747.63,
                       SID="A",RGROUP=1}}
                       -------(9)--------->

                                    [allocates another
                                    3 MB to access service
                                    and 30 minutes to
                                    service "A"]

                       Access Accept
                      {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                      PPAQ={QID=8, VQ=8MB,
                      PoolID=1, mult=1, RGROUP=1},
                      PPAQ={QID=9, DQ=4800sec
                      PoolID=1, mult=1747.63,
                      SID="A"}}
  \                    <----------(10)--------------

     user logs off
   ------(11)-------
                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=8, VQ=6.5MB,
                       REASON=ACCESS SERV TERMINATED,
                       PoolID=1, mult=1}
                       PPAQ={QID=9, DQ=5400sec
                       REASON=ACCESS SERV TERMINATED,
                       PoolID=1, mult=1747.63,
                       SID="A",RGROUP=1}}
                       -------(12)--------->

                                         [reimburses
                                         user account]

                       AA Accept
                      {RADIUS BASE AVPS
                      <------(13)--------
    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t> The user logs on (1). The PPC sends a RADIUS Access Request message to the PPS
                    (2), and includes the prepaid-specific PPAC AVP, indicating that multiple
                    services, rating groups and resource pools are supported. Note that, since this
                    is not an "Authorize- Only" message, no PPAQ attribute with Update
                    Reason="initial request" is included (see Section 3.7.1). The PPS then may
                    authenticate the user and authorize the access service, as is usual in RADIUS.
                    Note that the PPAC AVP is appended by the PPC in at least the last message that
                    is sent to the PPS during this possibly multiple-round exchange.</t>

                <t> If authentication and authorization is successful (in this example this is
                    assumed), the PPS identifies the user's prepaid account from the included base
                    RADIUS AVPs, and determines the capabilities of the PPC from the PPAC attribute.
                    Assuming that sufficient funds are available in the user's prepaid account, the
                    PPS reserves some of these and rates the service. In this example, the PPS
                    reserves 5 Euros and determines that the access service is rated at 1 Euro per
                    MB. In anticipation that the user requests more chargeable services throughout
                    this prepaid session, and since this is supported by the PPC, the PPS further
                    associates a resource pool with this reservation, in this example PoolID=1. The
                    PPC also specifies the multiplier = 1 for the access service. Note that, since
                    5MB = 5242880 octets, 1 unit in the resource pool corresponds to 5 / 5242880
                    euros, which is about 0.000095367431640625 Eurocents. (However, the PPC does not
                    need to know that.) Moreover, the PPS associates the QID=5 to this reservation.
                    This identifier can be used to later uniquely identify the prepaid session,
                    user, account, etc. The resulting Access Accept message is sent to PPC (3).</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (3), the PPC provides the access service to the user
                    and meters it accordingly (4). That is, for every octet consumed, the PPC
                    subtracts 1 unit (since the multiplier is 1) from the resouce pool with
                    PoolID=1.</t>

                <t> At some point in time, the user requests another chargeable service, namely
                    service A (5). The PPC generates an Authorize-Only Access Request that contains
                    the usual RADIUS attributes and the Service-ID identifying service A (6). The
                    PPC has determined that service A is rated in an identical way as at least one
                    more service. Thus, service A has been configured to belong to a rating group,
                    in this example the group with Rating-Group-ID=1. This identifier is included is
                    message (6).</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (6), the PPS identifies the user and his account from
                    the base RADIUS attributes, the fact that a prepaid session is ongoing, and
                    determines that enough credit remains in the prepaid account in order for
                    service A to be provided. The PPS also determines that service A is rated at
                    0.10 euros per minute. The PPS decides to reserve another 5 euros from the users
                    account; this corresponds to 50 minutes or, as encoded in the DurationQuota
                    SubType, 3000 seconds. As service A draws from the same prepaid account as the
                    access service, the PPS associates this reservation with the same resource pool
                    as the previous reservation (QID=5), namely the pool with PoolID=1. Note that,
                    in order for the abstract units in the pool to be consistent, the multiplier has
                    to be 1747.63. This is because each second corresponds to about 0.10 / 60 =
                    0.00167 euros, which is about 1747.63 times the value of an abstract resource
                    pool unit, as this was determined by the first allocation of quota to the pool
                    (i.e., 0.000095367431640625 Eurocents). Since this is a new quota reservation,
                    the PPS also allocates a new QID to it, in this example QID=7. The resulting
                    RADIUS message is sent to the PPC (7).</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (7), the PPC adjusts the units in resource pool 1.
                    That is, it first determines how much quota had been allocated to service A in
                    the past, and subtracts this from the quota reservation found in the message.
                    Since this is the first quota reservation for service A, there is nothing to
                    subtract. Thus, it adds 3000 * 1747.63 = 5242890 units to the pool and remembers
                    that 3000 seconds have been allocated to service A during this prepaid session.
                    The PPC then provides service A to the user, and meters it against resource pool
                    1. That is, for every second it subtracts 1747.63 units from the pool.</t>

                <t> At some point in time, the user requests service B (8). The PPC determines that
                    service B is rated exactly in the same way as service A, i.e., that they belong
                    to the same rating group, namely the one with Rating-Group-ID=1. Since this
                    rating group has been effectively authorised by the allocation of quota with
                    QID=7, the PPC provides service B to the user immediately. It is rated in the
                    same way as service A, i.e., for every second provided, 1747.63 units are
                    subtracted from credit pool 1.</t>

                <t> At some point in time, resource pool 1 is close to exhaustion. (For example, the
                    PPC may determine that the pool is "close to exhaustion" when has less than 10%
                    its initial amount of units.) At that point, the PPC needs to ask for
                    replenishment for the pool. Suppose that, at that point in time, 4MB of "access
                    service", 45 minutes of "service A", and 10 minutes of "service B" were provided
                    to the user. Note that this corresponds to (4*1048576) + (55*60*1747.63) =
                    4194304 + 5767179 = 9961483 abstract service units from the pool. The PPC
                    constructs an Authorize-Only Access Request message that reports the usage for
                    the "access service" and "service A". This message contains two PPAQ attributeS,
                    is sent to the PPS (9). Note that is the message it appears that "service A" has
                    consumed more than it was allocated (i.e., 55 minutes although only 50 minutes
                    were initially allocated to it). This is not a a problem since the PPS knows
                    that "service A" was drawing from the same pool as the "access service" and that
                    the "access service" did only consume 4 out of the 5 MB it was allocated.</t>

                <t> Upon reception of message (9), the PPS subtracts 4 euros from the user's account
                    for the "access service" and another 5.5 euros for "service A". (This includes
                    the charge incurred by "service B" up to that point in time, although the PPS is
                    not aware of "service B" being provisioned to the user.) The PPS then determines
                    that sufficient funds remain in the prepaid account in order for both services
                    to be continued. The PPS decides to reserve another 3MB for the access service
                    and 30 minutes for "service A". This corresponds to 3+3=6 euros. Since in RADIUS
                    prepaid the quotas are encoded in a cumulative manner, the PPAQ attribute that
                    grants the quota for the "access service" contains a Volume-Quota SubType of 8MB
                    (8388608 octets), which is the 5MB that were initially allocated, plus the 3MB
                    allocated now. The resource pool identifier is, as previously, PoolID=1 and the
                    multiplier is 1. Similarly, the PPAQ that grants quota for "service A" contains
                    4800 seconds (the initial 3000 plus 1800 that correspond to the 30 additional
                    minutes). Again, the PoolID=1 and multiplier=1747.63. The resulting Access
                    Response message is sent to the PPC (10).</t>

                <t> When the PPC received message (10) it checks how much quota has been allocated
                    previously to the "access service". It finds that the answer is 5MB (5242880
                    octets); thus, out of the 8MB (8388608 octets) that are indicated by the PPAQ
                    with QID=8, only 3MB (3145728 octets) have not yet been added to resource pool
                    1. The PPC thus adds 3145728 abstract units to resource pool 1 (since the
                    multiplier is 1). The PPC then acts similarly on the other PPAQ attribute that
                    exists in message (11). That is, the PPC determines that 3000 seconds of quota
                    for "service A" had already been added to the pool. Thus only 1800 out of the
                    4800 should be additionally added to the pool. Since the applicable multiplier
                    here is 1747.63, the PPC adds further 3145734 abstract units to the pool 1.</t>

                <t> The PPC then continues to provide the access service, "service A" and "service
                    B" to the user, and meters them against the pool, as previously.</t>

                <t> At some point the user logs off (11). The PPC must then report how many
                    resources were consumed, so that the PPC can subtract the appropriate monetary
                    amount from the user's prepaid account. To this end the PPC constructs an
                    Authorize-Only Access Request message with two PPAQ attributes; one for the
                    access service and one for "service A". Suppose that, in total, 6.5MB were
                    consumed by the access service, 70 minutes were consumed by "service A" and 20
                    minutes by "service B". The PPC reports 6.5MB (6815744 octets) and 90 minutes
                    (5400 seconds) in its final message (12). The PPS determines, from the previous
                    records, that the access service consumed another 2.5MB (since 4MB out of the
                    6.5MB were already reported in message (9), and that "service A" consumed
                    further 600 seconds. This corresponds to 2.5 + (600/60)*0.1 = 2.5+ 1=3.5 euros.
                    Thus, the PPS only subtracts 2.5 out of the 6 previously reserved euros from the
                    user's prepaid account and responds with an Access Response as required by the
                    RADIUS base specification (13).</t>

            </section>

            <section anchor="ontimecharging" title="One-time charging">

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="onetimeexample"
                        title="Example message flow with one-time charging">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
  End user          PPC                  PPS

   user requests ring tone
   ------(1)--------->


                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={QID=321, SID=X, RQ=650,
                       REASON=10 (ONE-TIME CHARGING}}
                       -------(2)--------->
 
                                [rates 650 abstract units
                                deducts from user's account]

                             Access Accept
                             {RADIUS BASE AVPS}
                   <----------(3)--------------


     ring tone is delivered
   <------(4)-------
    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t> The user requests a chargeable ring tone (1). The PPC sends a RADIUS Access
                    Request message to the PPS (2), and includes a PPAQ attribute with Update
                    Reason="one-time charging" is included (see <xref target="onetimecharging"/>). The
                    Service ID indicates to the PPS that the charging event is connected to a ring
                    tone, so that the PPS can rate the event accordingly. The PPAQ also contains a
                    unique Quota Identifier.</t>

                <t> The PPS then may authenticate the user as is usual in RADIUS. If authentication
                    is successful (in this example this is assumed), the home AAA server forwards
                    the PPC converts the 650 reported abstract units into monetary value, according
                    to the service type, and debit the user's account accordingly. This happens, of
                    course, only if sufficient funds are available in the user's prepaid account.
                    The PPC then responds with an an Access Accept message (3). The PPS adds a
                    "session timeout = 0 AVP" (see <xref target="onetimecharging"/>).</t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="priceenc" title="Price enquiry">

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="priceenqexample"
                        title="Example message flow with price enquiry (advice of charge)">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
   End user          PPC                  PPS

   user requests AoC
   ------(1)--------->


                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={SID=X, VQ=10MB,
                       REQ_ACT=2(PRICE ENQUIRY}}
                       -------(2)--------->

                           [rates 10MB for requested
                                             service]

                        Access Accept
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={SID=X, VQ=10MB,
                COST INFORMATION= 0.6 euros
                       per MB}}
                     <----------(3)--------------

     AoC is delivered
   <------(4)-------

    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>Please refer to <xref target="servpriceenc"/> for an explanation of this message
                    flow.</t>
            </section>


            <section anchor="balancchek" title="Balance check">

                <t>
                    <figure anchor="balancecheckexample"
                        title="Example message flow with balance check">
                        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
End User               PPC                  PPS

                       Access Request
                       {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                       PPAQ={SID=X, VQ=10MB,
                       REQ_ACT=BALANCE CHECK}}
                       -------(2)--------->

                                    [rates requested
                                    Service and checks 
                                    remaining funds]

                       Access Accept
                      {RADIUS BASE AVPS,
                      PPAQ={SID=X, VQ=10MB,
                BALANCE_CHECK_RESULT}}
                 <----------(3)--------------
    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>Please refer to <xref target="bceck"/> for an explanation of this message
                flow.</t>
            </section>
        </section>


        <section anchor="translator"
            title="Translation between RADIUS Prepaid and Diameter Credit Control">

            <t>Note: This section is informative.</t>

            <t> In scenarios where the service metering device uses the "RADIUS prepaid" (RPP)
                protocol for accounting and prepaid charging while the AAA infrastructure uses the
                "Diameter Credit Control" (DCC) protocol, a translation agent that enables the
                interoperation of both systems, is desirable. This also applies vice versa, i.e., in
                scenarios where the AAA infrastructure uses RADIUS and the service metering device
                uses Diameter. </t>

            <t> The idea of such a translation agent would be to convert incoming RPP (resp. DCC)
                messages into outgoing DCC (resp. RPP) messages. It would be, in principle,
                desirable for the translation agent to be stateless. That is, the agent should not
                be required to internally maintain information about each ongoing RADIUS or Diameter
                session. However, under the current specification of RPP and DCC, this appears to be
                impossible due to a number of reasons. These include the following. </t>

            <t>
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t> The transport mechanism for DCC is TCP, which requires per-session state to
                        be maintained at both endpoints of the communication. Note, however, that,
                        in principle, each DCC message could be sent over a dedicated TCP connection
                        which is torn down as soon as the message is sent. This, however, is likely
                        to be unacceptable in terms of efficiency. </t>

                    <t> While RPP messages encode the cumulative amount of consumed/requested
                        resources, DCC messages carry the difference from the previous message. This
                        means that the translation agent has to maintain the current amount of
                        consumed/requested resources in order to be able to calculate the correct
                        amount to be put into an outgoing message. </t>
                </list>
            </t>

            <t> The translator maps each incoming RPP (resp. DCC) message into an outgoing DCC
                (resp. RPP) message, and possibly establishes or updates local state that is
                associated with the session. The translated (i.e., outgoing) message is a function
                of the incoming message as well as existing state that is associated with the
                current session. </t>

            <t> Translation occurs on an attribute-by-attribute basis. Certain attributes are
                translated without consideration of local per-session state. Other attributes,
                namely those that are bound to a particular session, require such consideration. The
                translation agent has to identify the session (and possibly subsession) an incoming
                message belongs to in order to consult the appropriate local per-session state. </t>

            <t> Note that certain DCC attributes cannot be translated due to their semantics not
                being present in RPP, and vice versa. This results in the messages, in which these
                attributes occur, not being delivered to their intended destination. In such cases
                it is desirable to inform the originator about the failure and terminate the
                session.</t>

            <t> In each scenario (i.e., RPP client / DCC AAA infrastructure and DCC client / RPP AAA
                infrastructure), the translator operates in two directions, namely RPP to DCC and
                vice versa. In the following sections, the notation c->s means that the attribute in
                question may occur only in the direction from the client to the server. The notation
                s->c denotes the converse and the notation c&lt;->s denotes that the attribute
                may occur in messages that are directed in either direction. </t>

            <section toc="exclude" anchor="trsid" title="Session Identification">

                <t> The translation agent has to keep per-session state in order to perform its
                    task. A session may be identified based on the RPP identifier or the DCC session
                    identifier. That is, the translation agent should always maintain a pair of
                    (RPP, DCC) session identifiers and maintain the per-session state in association
                    with that pair. This per-session state must be addressable by either of these
                    two identifiers. Moreover, an RPP session identifier must uniquely correspond to
                    a DCC identifier. (If this holds, the converse also holds.) Each subsession
                    identifier within an RPP session must also uniquely correspond to a subsession
                    identifier within its corresponding DCC session. (If this holds the converse
                    also holds.) </t>
            </section>

            <section toc="exclude" anchor="trRPP2DCC"
                title="Translation between RADIUS Prepaid and Diameter Credit Control">
                <t> This section describes the translator in the "RPP client / DCC AAA
                    infrastructure" case. In other words, in this section it is assumed that the
                    client "talks" RPP and the AAA inftrastructure "talks" DCC. The translator is
                    assumed to sit somewhere in the middle and to mediate between client and server.</t>

                <t> For each RPP AVP (i.e., AVPs that are specified in the present document), the
                    transformation into a semantically equivalent DCC AVP (if such an AVP exists),
                    along with what per-session state the translator has to create or consult, is
                    described. For clarity of exposition, each RPP AVP is addressed in a separate
                    subsection. Since in this scenario, the PPC is typically the initiator a
                    session, the focus is on the RPP AVPs.</t>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trppac" title="PPAC (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> A DCC client is assumed to always support Volume metering, Duration
                        metering, Resource metering, Pools, Rating groups, and Tariff Switching.
                        Thus, if a PPAQ that indicates any of the above is sent client->server, the
                        translator does the following: It lets message go through but remembers what
                        exactly the client supports. If the server later requests (servier -> client
                        direction) an unsupported metering to be performed, send failure to server
                        and cause the session to be terminated at the client. </t>

                    <t> If a PPAC indicates support for multiple services (0x00000020), the
                        translator maps this onto a DCC Multiple-Services- Indicator AVP. </t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trstc" title="Service Termination Attribute (c->s)">

                    <t> The Diameter base protocol assumes that the client always supports dynamic
                        session termination. If this AVP is present, the translator does not need to
                        do anything, i.e., there exists no DCC AVP that this AVP can be mapped to.
                        If this AVP is absent, the message in which it appears should either be
                        discarded and originator should be informed of a failure, or the message can
                        be passed on (without this AVP being mapped onto a DCC AVP). However, in the
                        latter case, the translator has to remember that the client does not support
                        dynamic termination. Thus, the translatior has to initiate the normal
                        session termination procedure with the client when (if) dynamic termination
                        is later initiated by the server. </t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trqid"
                    title="Quota Identifier Attribute (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> When quota is allocated for the first time by the DCC server, the translator
                        has to create a QID AVP, as required by this specification. The translator
                        later uses a QID AVP that is sent in the client-to-server direction in order
                        to identify the corresponding DCC session. The QID has to be saved in the
                        translator's per session state.</t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trvq" title="Volume Quota Attribute (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> If this AVP occurs in a message that is sent in the server-to-client
                        direction, it is translated into a Granted-Service-Unit AVP with an embedded
                        CC-Total-Octets AVP.
                        <!-- [editor's note: this sentence belongs to the other
                        translation type, i.e., AAA = RPP and client = DCC.] -->
                    </t>

                    <t> If this AVP occurs in a message that is sent in the client-to-server
                        direction, then it is translated into a Used-Service-Unit AVP with an
                        embedded CC-Total-Octets AVP. Note that only the difference between current
                        cumulative quota for the (sub)session and the quota in incoming messages is
                        indicated in the translated DCC message. Local state is updated with
                        cumulative consumed resources.</t>

                    <t> Conversely, if the server grants quota using the DCC Granted-Service-Unit
                        AVP with an embedded CC-Total-Octets AVP, then the translation agent must
                        translate this into a Volume Quota Attribute. Again, local state must be
                        consulted so that the cumulative amount of octets is indicated in the Volume
                        Quota attribute.</t>

                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trdq" title="Duration Quota Attribute (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> If this AVP occurs in a message that is sent in the server-to-client
                        direction, it is translated into a Granted-Service-Unit AVP with an embedded
                        CC-Time AVP.
                        <!--[editor's note: this sentence belongs to the other translation
                        type, i.e., AAA = RPP and client = DCC.] -->
                    </t>

                    <t> If this AVP occurs in a message that is sent in the client-to-server
                        direction, then it is translated into a Used-Service-Unit AVP with an
                        embedded CC-Time AVP. Note that only the difference between current
                        cumulative quota for the (sub)session and the quota in incoming messages is
                        indicated in the translated DCC message. Local state is updated with
                        cumulative consumed resources (i.e., time).</t>

                    <t> Conversely, if the server grants quota using the DCC Granted-Service-Unit
                        AVP with an embedded CC-Time AVP, then the translation agent must translate
                        this into a Duration Quota attribute. Again, local state must be consulted
                        so that the cumulative amount of seconds is indicated in the Duaration Quota
                        attribute.</t>

                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trrq" title="Resource Quota Attribute (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> If this AVP occurs in a message that is sent in the server-to-client
                        direction, it is translated into a Granted-Service-Unit AVP with an embedded
                        CC-Service-Specific-Units AVP.
                        <!-- [editor's note: this sentence belongs to the
                        other translation type, i.e., AAA = RPP and client = DCC.] -->
                    </t>

                    <t> If this AVP occurs in a message that is sent in the client-to-server
                        direction, then it is translated into a Used-Service-Unit AVP with an
                        embedded CC-Service-Specific-Units AVP. Note that only the difference
                        between current cumulative quota for the (sub)session and the quota in
                        incoming messages is indicated in the translated DCC message. Local state is
                        updated with cumulative consumed resources (i.e., resources).</t>

                    <t> Conversely, if the server grants quota using the DCC Granted-Service-Unit
                        AVP with an embedded CC-Service-Specific-Units AVP, then the translation
                        agent must translate this into a Resource Quota attribute. Again, local
                        state must be consulted so that the cumulative amount of resource units is
                        indicated in the Resource Quota attribute.</t>

                    <t> Note that the "resource" type is application dependent. This means that a
                        DCC application unit corresponds to n RPP application units, where n may be
                        any real number. If n is not 1, then the RPP/DCC translator must be aware of
                        that and translate resource units accordingly. </t>

                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trvd" title="Value Digits Attribute (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> The encoding of this AVP is similar in RPP and DCC, and the value it holds
                        may have to be evaluated in conjunction with an acommpanying "Exponent" AVP.
                        It should be kept in mind that, in RPP the cumulative amount of
                        granted/consumed quota is typically encoded into an AVP of this type, while
                        in DCC only the difference from a previous message. </t>

                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="tre" title="Exponent Attribute (c&lt;->s)">

                    <t> The encoding of this AVP is similar in RPP and DCC, and the value it holds
                        may have to be evaluated in conjunction with an acommpanying "Value Digits"
                        AVP. It should be kept in mind that, in RPP the cumulative amount of
                        granted/consumed quota is typically encoded into a related "Value Digits"
                        and "Exponent" AVP pair, while in DCC only the difference from a previous
                        message is encoded into such a pair. </t>

                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trvth"
                    title="Volume/Duration/Resource Threshold Attributes (s->c)">

                    <t> In DCC the concept of "threshold" does not exist. Instead, the DCC client is
                        assumed to ask for the replenishment of quota in good time. In RPP, on the
                        other hand, the server may optionally include a threshold AVP, as an
                        indication to the PPC about when to ask for quota replenishment. </t>

                    <t> Thus, in this scenario, there is no need for the translator to ever include
                        a threshold attribute into the messages that it sends to the PPC. If,
                        however, there is a need for a threshold attribute to be present in order to
                        avoid a possible service provision</t>

                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trur" title="Update Reason Attribute (c->s)">

                    <t> The DCC AVP that is semantically closer to the Update Reason AVP than any
                        other AVP is the CC-Request-Type AVP. This AVP indicates whether the message
                        is which it appears is intended to indicate an "initial", an "intermediate"
                        or a "final interrogation". Morever, in case of the session being terminated
                        at the client, it indicates the reason for this termination. </t>

                    <t> The following list lists the possible values of an "Update Reason"
                        attribute, along with corresponding values for the CC-Request-Type AVP.</t>

                    <t>
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t> Pre-initialization: No action/value defined. </t>
                            <t> Initial Request: Typically an "intial interrogation" is triggered as
                                a result of the reception of the message that contains this Update
                                Reason AVP. Hence, CC-Request-Type AVP indicates "INITIAL_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> Threshold Reached: The reception of the message containing this
                                Update Reason AVP typically triggers an "intermediate
                                interrogation". Hence, CC-Request-Type AVP indicates
                                "UPDATE_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> Quota Reached: The reception of the message containing this Update
                                Reason AVP typically triggers an "intermediate interrogation".
                                Hence, CC-Request-Type AVP indicates "UPDATE_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> TITSU Approaching: The reception of the message containing this
                                Update Reason AVP typically triggers an "intermediate
                                interrogation". Hence, CC-Request-Type AVP indicates
                                "UPDATE_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> Remote Forced Disconnect: Reception of such an Update Reason
                                indicates that the client has terminated the session. The
                                corresponding value for the CC-Request-Type AVP is
                                "TERMINATION_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> Client Service Termination: Reception of such an Update Reason
                                indicates that the client has terminated the session. The
                                corresponding value for the CC-Request-Type AVP is
                                "TERMINATION_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> "Access Service" Terminated: Reception of such an Update Reason
                                indicates that the client has terminated the session. The
                                corresponding value for the CC-Request-Type AVP is
                                "TERMINATION_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> Service not established: Reception of such an Update Reason
                                indicates that the client has terminated the session. The
                                corresponding value for the CC-Request-Type AVP is
                                "TERMINATION_REQUEST". </t>
                            <t> One-Time Charging: Such an Update Reason indicates that a one-time
                                charging event is initiated by the client. The corresponding value
                                for the CC-Request-Type AVP is "EVENT_REQUEST". Note that a
                                "Requested-Action: AVP MUST also be included in the outgoing DCC
                                message. Typically, this would be of the type "DIRECT_DEBITING", or
                                "REFUND_ACCOUNT", depending on other AVPs present in the
                            message.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>



                </section>


                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trpps" title="PrepaidServer Attribute (s&lt;->c)">

                    <t> The PPC typically never sets the value of a PrepaidServer attribute.
                        Instead, it repeats those values that it receives from the AAA
                        infrastructure, in this scenario from the translator. This attribute is
                        therefore not used in a translation scenario. Nevertheless, the translator
                        must make sure that messages about the same RPP session are forwarded to the
                        same DCC server, throughout the whole session. This may be easy to guarantee
                        since the transport of Diameter is TCP.</t>

                </section>
                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trsrvid" title="Service-ID Attribute (s&lt;->c)">

                    <t> The DCC equivalent of a RPP "Service-ID" AVP is the combination of
                        Service-Context-Id and Service-Identifier AVPs. The translator must keep a
                        static equivalence table of the RPP Service-ID and the corresponding DCC
                        combination in order to correctly translate an RPP service identifier into
                        DCC and back. </t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trrgid"
                    title="Rating-Group-ID Attribute (s&lt;->c)">

                    <t> The DCC equivalent of a RPP "Rating-Group-ID" AVP is also called a
                        "Rating-Group-ID". Depending on the configuration, this AVP may contain the
                        same value on both the RPP and the DCC side of the communication. If,
                        however, static rating groups are configured between the RCC client and the
                        translator, and different rating groups between the DCC server and the
                        translator, then the translator has to maintain a static translation table
                        for the rating group identifier. In any case, the translation of a rating
                        group AVP, is not a function of the translator's local per-session state.</t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trtac" title="Termination-Action Attribute (s->c)">

                    <t> The DCC equivalent of the "Termination-Action" AVP is called the
                        "Final-Unit-Action" AVP. In this scenario (RPP client and DCC AAA
                        infrastructure), a DCC "Final-Unit-Action" AVP is translated into a
                        "Termination-Action" AVP. The following list contains the possible
                        "Final-Unit-Action" values along with their "Termination-Action" equivalent.</t>

                    <t>
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t> TERMINATE (DCC): This value has a direct equivalent in RPP, also
                                called "Terminate".</t>
                            <t> REDIRECT (DCC): If this value appears in a "Final-Unit-Action" AVP,
                                then a "Redirect-Server-Address" AVP must also appear in the same
                                DCC message. The translator translates these two AVPs into a
                                "Termination-Action" with value "Redirect/Filter" and an eqiovalent
                                NAS-Filter-Rule attribute (specified in
                                http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-radext-ieee802-00.txt). </t>

                            <t> RESTRICT_ACCESS (DCC): If this value appears in a
                                "Final-Unit-Action" AVP, then a "Restriction-Filter-Rule" AVP must
                                also appear in the same DCC message. The translator translates these
                                two AVPs into a "Termination-Action" with value "Redirect/Filter"
                                and an eqiovalent Filter-ID attribute (specified in
                                http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-radext-ieee802-00.txt). </t>

                            <t> In the absence of a "Final-Unit-Action" AVP, the DCC server assumes
                                that the DCC client will ask for replenishment of quota at some
                                suitable time. In RPP, this is explicitly conveyed via a
                                "Termination-Action" AVP with the value "Request More Quota". Thus,
                                in the absence of a "Final-Unit-Action" AVP, the translator in this
                                scenario appends such an AVP into the outgoing RPP message.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trpid" title="Pool-ID Attribute (s&lt;->c)">

                    <t> The DCC equivalent of a RPP "Pool-ID" AVP is also called a "Pool-ID".
                        Typically, no translation needs to be done to the "Pool-ID" attribute.</t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trmlp" title="Multiplier Attribute (s&lt;->c)">

                    <t> The multiplier attribute, which is a pair of "Value-Digits" and "Exponent"
                        AVPs, typically needs no translation, since the value it carries (inside a
                        "Value-Digits" and an "Exponent" AVP) represents the rating of the service
                        or rating group to which it refers, with respect to abstract units. As such,
                        the same multiplier value would typically applyt be conveyed from a DCC
                        server to an PPC, and vice versa.</t>

                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trrac" title="Requested-Action Attribute (c->s)">

                    <t> The "Requested Action" AVP can be directly translated into its DCC
                        equivalent, which carries the same name.</t>

                    <t>
                        <list style="numbers">
                            <t> Balance Check (PCC): CHECK_BALANCE (DCC)</t>
                            <t> Price Enquiry (PCC): PRICE_ENQUIRY (DCC)</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>


                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trcbr" title="Check-Balance-Result Attribute (s->c)">

                    <t> This attribute carries only a binary value. Hence, its translation is
                        straightforward.</t>


                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trci" title="Cost-Information Attribute (s->c)">
                    <t> This attribute consists of a Value-Digits AVP, an Exponent AVP, a Currency
                        Code AVP, and a Cost-Unit AVP. All these AVPs do likewise exist in DCC, and
                        carry identical semantics in the context of the "Cost-Information" AVP.
                        Thus, the translation of this attribute is straightforward.</t>
                </section>

                <section toc="exclude" anchor="trvuats"
                    title="VolumeUsedAfterTariffSwitch attribute (c->s)">

                    <t> This attribute carries the amount of octets that were consumed after a
                        tariff change. It always appears in a message with an accompanying PPAQ
                        attribute in which the total amount of octets (i.e., those that were
                        consumed both before and after the tariff switch) is reported. Thus, the
                        translation agent can compute the amount of octets that were consumed before
                        the tariff change. </t>

                    <t> In DCC, the two amounts, i.e., the octets that were consumed before a tariff
                        change and those that were consumed afterwards, are reported in separate
                        Used-Service-Unit AVPs. The two Used-Service-Unit AVPs have an embedded
                        CC-Total-Octets AVP that indicates the appropriate amount of octets.
                        Furthermore, the Used-Service-Unit AVP that carries the amount that was
                        consumed before the tariff switch also carries an embedded
                        Tariff-Change-Usage AVP with the value UNIT_BEFORE_TARIFF_CHANGE (0).
                        Similarly, the Used-Service-Unit AVP that carries the amount that was
                        consumed after the tariff switch also carries an embedded
                        Tariff-Change-Usage AVP with the value UNIT_AFTER_TARIFF_CHANGE (1). </t>
                </section>



            </section>

        </section>



    </back>


</rfc>
