<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119   PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5222 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5222.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5627 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5627.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5626 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5626.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.patel-ecrit-sos-parameter PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.patel-ecrit-sos-parameter.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6442 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6442.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-geopriv-res-gw-lis-discovery PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-res-gw-lis-discovery.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6155 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6155.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-psap-callback PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-psap-callback.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3841 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3841.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5031 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6197 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6197.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.rosen-ecrit-premature-disconnect-rqmts PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.rosen-ecrit-premature-disconnect-rqmts.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3969 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3969.xml">
]>

<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-winterbottom-ecrit-direct-02.txt">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ECRIT Direct">ECRIT Direct Emergency Calling</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Winterbottom" fullname="James Winterbottom">
      <organization>CommScope</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Suit 1, Level 2</street>
          <street>iC Enterprise 1, Innovation Campus</street>
          <street>Squires Way</street>
          <city>North Wollongong</city>
          <region>NSW</region>
          <code>2500</code>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+61 242 212938</phone>
        <email>james.winterbottom@commscope.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <region/>
          <code>02 600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2012"/>
    <area>RAI</area>
    <workgroup>ECRIT</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>The specified IETF emergency services architecture puts a strong emphasis on emergency call
        and emergency messaging via the Voice Service Provider (VSP) / Application Service Provider
        (ASP). There are two reasons for this design decision: The call routing via the VSP/ASP is
        more natural as it follows the standard communication pattern and transition deployments
        assume non-updated end hosts.</t>
      <t>As the deployment of the Location-to-Service Translation protocol progresses there are
        possibilities for upgraded end devices to directly communicate with the IP-based emergency
        services network without the need to interact with a VSP/ASP, which simplifies the task of
        regulators as the involved parties are within the same jurisdiction. </t>
      <t> This memo describes the procedures and operations of a generic emergency calling client
        utilizing the available building blocks. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The description of the IETF emergency services architecture, found in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> and in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework"/>,
        focuses on devices where emergency calls are routed primarily through the subscriber's home
        VSP and the direct signaling communication between the end host and the Public Safety
        Answering Point (PSAP) that contains the IP-based PSAP is only an exception. This is a
        convenient assumption if one considers the regular communication patterns of the device and
        the potential proprietary protocol implementations used between the end host and the VSP and
        the ability to move the interoperability challenges away from the end device and closer to
        VSPs. There are, however, challenges for regulators to enforce emergency services
        functionality when the VSP is located in a different jurisdiction. Inclusion of a VSP
        introduces unnecessary elements into the emergency call path making the overall solution
        more cumbersome.</t>
      <t>With the help of the Location-to-Service Translation protocol a PSAP URI is discovered that
        allows the end device to directly send SIP communication requests towards the PSAP. </t>
      <t> Note that the information returned by LoST may not necessarily be the address of the PSAP
        itself but might rather be an entity that gets the emergency call closer to the PSAP by
        returning the address of an Emergency Services Routing Proxy (ESRP). </t>
      <t>The intent of this client is that it will be able to use the available ECRIT building
        blocks to allow any IP enabled device with access to the Internet to make an emergency call
        without requiring the signaling interaction with the VSP. In fact, there is no assumption or
        requirement for a VSP subscription to exist. The interacting entities are shown in <xref
          target="network"/>. </t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="network" title="Network Configuration">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                   ....   ....
                 ,'    ','    ',
                ;               ;
 +--------+    ;                 ;      +------+
 | Device |--->:       ISP       :----->| ESRP |
 +--------+    ;                 ;      +------+
                `,     ,',     ,'
                  ,   ,   ,   ,
                   ````    ````
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t> Furthermore, a means for call-back in the event of a dropped call is also described. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="The Jurisdictional Problem">
      <t>The jurisdictional problem is illustrated with <xref target="juris"/> that highlights that
        provided the data in the Location Information Server (LIS) and the LoST server are correct,
        that the caller and the PSAP are assured of being in the same regulatory jurisdiction. This
        is important, because it shows that it is the access component of the network and not the
        service component against which reguatory obligations can be imposed with any hope of
        enforcement. Regulation without the possibility of enforcement is challenging as there is
        very little coordination between regulators world wide in this area, consequently any
        emergency calling procedure should ensure that all nodes against which the procedures apply
        fall within the same regulatory boundary. </t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="juris" title="Jurisdictional Boundaries in Internet Emergency Calling">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                           +-----+        
                           | VSP |
                           |  #  |
                           +-----+
                    
     o-------------o----------------------o-------------o
   /                                                      \
  /   +---------+                          +--------+      \
 /    |  Access  \                        /  ESINet  \      \
o     |  Network  \                      /            \      o
|     +            +                    +      O       +     |
|     /    O       |                   /      <P\      |     |
|    +    <C\      o   REGULATORY     +       /'\      +     |
|    |    /'\     /                   |      PSAP      /     o
o    +   Caller   +    JURISDICTION   +    +-------+  +     /
 \    \ __________|                    \ /          \/     /
  \                                                       /
   o--------------o----------------------o---------------o
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="ESRP Route Determination">
      <t>The ESRP is discovered by the emergency client obtaing its location from a LIS, for
        example, using HELD, and then using LoST to resolve the location and 'urn:services.sos'
        Service URN to the ESRP URI. </t>
      <t> When the emergency client is started the device needs to perform LIS and LoST server
        discovery, as described in Section 7 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>. </t>
      <t>The emergency client MUST support location acquisition and the LCPs described in Section
        6.5 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>. The description in Section 6.5 and 6.6 of
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> regarding the interaction between the device and
        the LIS applies to this document. </t>

      <t> The emergency client MUST use LoST <xref target="RFC5222"/> to obtain an ESRP URI. The
        exact timing of individual LoST lookups may vary based on a number of factors, including the
        design of the user interface. For example, a hypothetical user interface may offer an
        emergency call button that triggers a &lt;listServicesByLocation&gt; interaction to
        learn about the available emergency services (potentially using the serviceListBoundary
        extension defined in <xref target="RFC6197"/>). The service
        options may be presented to the emergency caller in a graphical fashion and once a specific
        service is selected a LoST query would be initiated (unless a cached mapping is available
        that makes this request obsolete). The LoST &lt;findService&gt; query to obtain the
        ESRP URI for the selected service is in this example initiated at the time the emergency
        call setup is performed. It is recommended that ESRP discovery occurs at call time. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Emergency Client Registration">
      <t>Emergency registration is only necessary when an emergency call procedure is initiated.
        Immediately prior to making an emergency call, the emergency client performs a SIP emergency
        registration with the registrar in the ESRP, the ESRP-registrar. The emergency registration
        is a SIP registration with specific options and headers which are required in order to guard
        the emergency network and ensure callback should it be required. </t>

      <t>Each emergency client MUST provide an instance-id, as defined in <xref
          target="RFC5626"/>, this allows the ESRP-registrar to generate a GRUU <xref
          target="RFC5627"/> that can be used as a callback identifier. A GRUU is necessary as the
        callback identifier because the emergency client does not provide a longer-term contact
        address to the ESRP-registrar prior to registration, and the GRUU provides a handle by which
        the PSAP can identify the calling emergency client. To simplify the emergency client and
        ESRP-registrar implementations, only public GRUUs are provided by the ESRP-registrar. The
        public GRUU is guaranteed to be the same for a device regardless of re-registration with a
        different call-id, which may occur if the device unexpectedly reboots. This is not true for
        temporary GRUUs, which makes temporary GRUUs undesriable in the scope of this application
        space. </t>
      <t> The PSAP is able to define and mandate the time over which callback is possible. This
        needs to be a reasonable period of time, nominally 10s of minutes, as the device may well be
        transient with regards to network attachment. The ESRP-registrar reflects the regulatory
        callback period in the expiry value of emergency registration responses. Emergency clients
        claiming compliance to this specification MUST honour the value in the registration response
        from the ESRP-registrar, up to a maximum of 60 minutes. An emergency client SHOULD respect a
        registration expiry of longer than 60 minutes, but MAY terminate its registration with and
        ESRP-registrar at 60 minutes if the expiry value provided by the ESRP-registrar was longer. </t>
      <t> In the event that a registration is lost by the emergency client prior to reaching
        registration expiry then the emergency client MUST re-register with the ESRP-registrar and
        SHOULD use the same call-id. In this circumstance the ESRP-registrar SHOULD match the
        instance-id and the call-id to recognize that it is a re-registration for a dropped
        connection, and expiry time in the registration response SHOULD be set to the time remaining
        when the original registration occurred. </t>
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC5626"/> requires a device to support at least 2 registrations
        to different proxies. The emergency client requirements in this memo relax this requirement
        down to one registration, but more than one is allowed. There are several reasons for
        relaxing the connection redundancy requirement. Firstly, ESRPs are expected to have inbuilt
        redundancy, so if a connection is dropped due to a failed proxy in the ESRP, then a new
        connection or registration will automatically be directed to an active proxy in the ESRP
        cluster. If the connection dropped because of some other failure along the path from the
        emergency client to the ESRP, then multiple SIP registrations are unlikely to provide any
        measurable reliability improvements since single points of failure in this path are
        inherently likely. Secondly, re-registrations only occur immediately prior to call
        placement, so any outbound failure will also likely result in the call dropping. If this
        occurs then the emergency client MUST re-register with the ESRP-registrar, and since
        instance-id and public GRUU will remain unchanged as a result of this, the emergency client
        can either receive a callback from the PSAP, or it can initiate a new call to the emergency
        network. </t>
      <t> Location information is critical to emergency calling. Providing location information to
        the calling-entity with sufficient granularity to allow ESRP route determination is crucial.
        Since this must occur prior to the emergency client registering with the ESRP-registrar, the
        emergency client must have access to a certain amount of location information (and the
        amount varies depending on the specific emergency services deployment architecture). </t>
      <t> The device SHOULD include all the location information it has when registering with the
        ERSP-registrar. Inclusion of location information in SIP REGISTER messages is specified in
          <xref target="RFC6442"/>. There are three possible execution
        paths for the ESRP-registrar when receiving a REGISTER message: <list style="numbers">
          <t> If the REGISTER message does not include location information the ESRP-registrar MUST
            use HELD identity <xref target="RFC6155"/> to obtain
            the location of the device as both a location value and reference. In order to contact
            the LIS the ESRP-registrar SHOULD determine the LIS address using the mechanism
            described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-res-gw-lis-discovery"/>. The
            ESRP-registrar MAY use other methods for LIS determination where available.</t>
          <t>If the REGISTER message contains a location URI then the ESRP-registrar MUST
            dereference it so that it has a location available to route the impending emergency
            call. The ESRP-registrar MAY validate the LIS address in the location URI with that of
            the LIS serving the network from which the REGISTER message originated.
            <!--  LIS determination MAY be performed
            using the methods described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-res-gw-lis-discovery"/>. -->
          </t>
          <t>The REGISTER message contains location information by value. Any actions performed by
            the ESRP-registrar to valid this information are specific to the jurisdiction in which
            the ESRP operates and are out of the scope of this document.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Where location conveyance is used confidentiality protection SHOULD be provided using
        Transport Layer Security (TLS).</t>

      <t><xref target="reg-flow"/> show the registration message exchange graphically.</t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="reg-flow" title="Example Registration Message Flow">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
    +--------+               +-----+            +------+       +------+
    | Device |               | LIS |            | LoST |       | ESRP |
    +--------+               +-----+            +------+       +------+
        |                       |                   |             |
        +<----LIS Discovery---->+                   |             |
        |                       |                   |             |
        +----locationRequest--->+                   |             |
        |                       |                   |             |
        +<---locationResponse---|                   |             |
        |                       |                   |             |
        +------------------findService------------->+             |
        |                       |                   |             |
        +<--------------findServiceResponse---------+             |
        |                       |                   |             |
        +------------------------REGISTER------------------------>+
        |                       |                   |             |
        |                       +<------locationRequest-----------+
        |                       |                   |             |
        |                       +-------locationResponse--------->+
        |                       |                   |             |
        +<-------------------------200 OK ------------------------+
        |                       |                   |             |
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="reg-msg" title="Sample REGISTER message">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   REGISTER sip:sos.example.com SIP/2.0
   Via: SIP/2.0/TCP 192.0.2.2;branch=z9hG4bKnashds7
   Max-Forwards: 70
   From: anon <sip:anon@sos.example.com>;tag=7F94778B653B
   To: anon <sip:anon@sos.example.com>
   Call-ID: 16CB75F21C70
   CSeq: 1 REGISTER
   Geolocation: <https://lis.access.example.com:9192/suXweu838737d72>
     ;inserted-by="anon@192.0.2.2"
     ;routing-allowed=yes
   Geolocation: <cid:target123@192.0.2.2>
     ;inserted-by="anon@192.0.2.2"
     ;routing-allowed=no
   Require: gruu, geolocation
   Supported: outbound, gruu
      Contact: <sip:anon@192.0.2.2;transport=tcp>
    ;+sip.instance="<urn:uuid:00000000-0000-1000-8000-AABBCCDDEEFF>"
   Content-Type: multipart/mixed; boundary=boundary1
   Content-Length: ...
 ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>Since the emergency client does not have a domain, it MUST register in the same domain as
        the ESRP. This is illustrated in the example REGISTER message show in <xref target="reg-msg"
        />. </t>
    </section>




    <section title="Emergency Client Call Initiation">

      <t> Immediately subsequent to the registration a SIP INVITE request is sent to the ESRP in the
        following form: <list style="numbers">

          <t>The Request URI MUST be the service URN <xref target="RFC5031"/> in the "sos" tree. </t>
          <t>The To header MUST be a service URN in the "sos" tree. </t>
          <t>The From header MUST be present and MUST be the public GRUU returned from the
            registration with the ESRP-registrar.</t>
          <t>A Route header MUST be present with an ESRP URI, obtained from LoST.</t>
          <t>A Contact header MUST be present and contain the public GRUU <xref target="RFC5627"/>,
            and be valid for several minutes following the termination of the call, provided that
            the UAC remains registered with the same registrar, to permit an immediate call-back to
            the specific device which placed the emergency call. </t>
          <t>A SDP offer MUST be included in the INVITE. If voice is supported the offer MUST
            include the G.711 codec, see Section 14 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>. </t>
          <t> SIP Caller Preferences <xref target="RFC3841"/> SHOULD be used to signal how the PSAP
            should handle the call. For example, a language preference expressed in an
            Accept-Language header may be used as a hint to cause the PSAP to route the call to a
            call taker who speaks the requested language. SIP Caller Preferences may also be used to
            indicate a need to invoke a relay service for communication with people with
            disabilities in the call. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

<!-- 
    <section title="Call Termination Control">
      <t> The description in <xref target="I-D.rosen-ecrit-premature-disconnect-rqmts"/> is relevant
        for this document. </t>
    </section>
--> 

    <section title="SIP Feature Restrictions">
      <t> The functionality defined in Section 9.3 in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>
        regarding disabling of certain features is relevant for this document and an emergency
        client MUST NOT implement the the features listed in ED-70, and ED-71. </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Testing">
      <t> The description in Section 15 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> regarding
        emergency call testing is used by this specification. Since this specification mandates a
        registration with the ESRP-registrar a similar tagging URI to that described in <xref
          target="I-D.patel-ecrit-sos-parameter"/> is used to indicate a test registration.</t>
      <t>Test registrations SHALL be of short durations, but MUST be long enough to allow completion
        of a &quot;test call&quot; as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>. </t>

      <section title="Test Registration">
        <t>When the emergency client sends a REGISTER request for emergency test registration, the
          "sos.test" URI parameter MUST be appended to the URI in the Contact header. This indicates
          to the ESRP-registrar that the request is for emergency test registration. </t>
        <t>
          <figure anchor="test-reg" title="Test REGISTER Message Fragment">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
   ...
      Contact: <sip:anon@192.0.2.2;transport=tcp;sos.test>
    ;+sip.instance="<urn:uuid:00000000-0000-1000-8000-AABBCCDDEEFF>"
   Content-Type: multipart/mixed; boundary=boundary1
   Content-Length: ...
 ]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t> Only one Contact header field SHOULD be included in the emergency REGISTER test request.
          If more than one Contact header is included then the presence of the
          &quot;sos.test&quot; URI in any of the Contact fields SHALL result in the
          ESRP-registrar treating the registration as a test registration. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Format">
        <t>The following syntax specification uses the augmented Backus-Naur Form (BNF) as described
          in <xref target="RFC5234"/>. </t>
        <t> The &quot;sos.test&quot; URI parameter is a &quot;uri-parameter&quot;,
          as defined by <xref target="RFC3261"/>. </t>
        <t>uri-parameter =/ sos-param-test</t>
        <t>sos-param-test = &quot;sos.test&quot;</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="PSAP Callback">
      <t>PSAP callback occurs as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-psap-callback"
      />.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification defines one new SIP URI parameter, as per the registry created by <xref
          target="RFC3969"/>.</t>

      <t>Parameter Name: sos.test</t>

      <t>Predefined Values: none</t>

      <t>Reference: [RFCXXXX]</t>

      <t>[NOTE TO IANA: Please replace XXXX with the RFC number of this specification.] </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Elaine Quah for being a sounding board. </t>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; &RFC5222; &RFC3261;
      &I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp; &RFC5627; &RFC5626;
      &RFC6442; &I-D.ietf-geopriv-res-gw-lis-discovery;
      &RFC6155; &I-D.ietf-ecrit-psap-callback;
      &RFC3841; &RFC5031; &RFC5234; &RFC3969;</references>

    <references title="Informative References"> &I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework;
      &I-D.patel-ecrit-sos-parameter; &RFC6197;
  </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
