<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2141 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2141.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3406 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3406.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-lumbreras-ees-urn-00.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="URN EES Namespace">Uniform Resource Name (URN) Namespace for the European Emergency Services</title>
 
 <author initials="C." surname="Lumbreras" fullname="Cristina Lumbreras">
      <organization>European Emergency Number Association (EENA)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
	
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <code></code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2012"/>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>EES URN</keyword>
    <keyword>Emergeny Services</keyword>
	<keyword>European Emergency Number Association (EESR)</keyword>
	<keyword>European Emergency Number Association (EENA)</keyword>

    <abstract>
   <t> This document describes the Namespace Identifier (NID) "eena" for
   Uniform Resource Name (URN) resources published by the European
   Emergency Number Association (EENA).  EENA defines and manages
   resources that utilize this URN model.  Management activities for
   these and other resource types are provided by the European Emergency Services Registry (EESR).</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

  <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
	
<t> The European Emergency Number Association (EENA) is currently in the
   process of setting standards, processes, and procedures for the use
   of an IP-based Emergency Services IP Network (ESInet) for all public
   safety entities in Europe.  Some of the solutions being
   developed by EENA require namespaces that are managed so that
   they are unique and persistent.  To assure that the uniqueness is
   absolute, the registration of a specific Uniform Resource Name (URN)
   <xref target="RFC2141"/> Namespace ID (NID) for use by EENA is required.  This
   document defines and registers such a namespace in accordance with the procedures in
   <xref target="RFC3406"/>.</t>

</section>

  <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

<section title="URN Specification for 'ees' NID">

<t>
<list style="empty">
<t>Namespace ID: ees</t>

<t>Registration information:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

   <list style="empty">

     <t>Registration version number: 1</t>

     <t>Registration date: 2012-09-26</t>
   </list>
   </t>
   
 <t>Declared registrant of the namespace:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      <list style="empty">
	  <t>Registering organization</t>
      <t>Name: European Emergency Number Association (EENA)</t>
      <t>Address:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  <list style="empty">
	    <t>Avenue de la Toison d'Or 79,</t>
        <t>1060 Brussels</t>
        <t>Belgium</t>
      </list>
	  </t>
     </list>
   </t>

   <t>Designated contact:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

     <list style="empty">
	   <t>Role:    European Emergency Services Registry Administrator</t>
       <t>Email:   eesr-admin@eena.org</t>
     </list>
   </t>
   
   <t>Declaration of syntactic structure:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      The Namespace Specific String (NSS) of all URNs that use the
      "eena" NID will have the following structure:
         {EESclass}:{ClassSpecificString}
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The "EESclass" conforms to the URN syntax requirements <xref target="RFC2141"/> and
   defines a specific class of resource type.  Each class will have a
   specific labeling scheme that is covered by "ClassSpecificString",
   which also conforms to the naming requirements of <xref target="RFC2141"/>.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   EENA maintains a naming authority, the European Emergency Service Registry  (EESR), that will manage the
   assignment of "EESclass" and the specific registration values
   assigned for each class.  Other EENA standards documents will define
   the "ClassSpecificStrings" for a given "EESclass".
   </t>

   <t>Relevant ancillary documentation:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The European Emergency Service Registry (EESR)
      provides information on the registered resources and the
      registrations for each.  More information about the EESR and the
      registration activities and procedures to be followed are defined
      in "EENA Registry System Standard",  TBD,
      which is available at http://www.eena.org/.
	</t>

   <t>Identifier uniqueness considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      The EESR will manage resources using the "ees" NID and will be the
      authority for managing the resources and subsequent strings
      associated.  The EESR shall ensure the uniqueness of all ees URNs
      by checking such names against the list of existing namespace
      names, as documented in TBD.
   </t>

   <t>Identifier persistence considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      
      The EESR will provide clear documentation of the registered uses of
      the "ees" NID.  The EESR will establish a registry for
      "EESclass", as defined in TBD.  Each
      "EESclass" will have a separate description in the registry and
      may have its own sub-registry.  In particular, new "EESclass"
      registry entries will require a full EENA Technical Standard
      document.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   
   The EESR will maintain a website at a stable address that provides XML
   and text renderings of the urn:ees registry.
   </t>

   <t>Process of identifier assignment:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      The EESR processes and procedures for identifier assignment are
      documented in TBD.  The registry that will
      control the urn:ees namespace is defined in TBD.  In particular, assignments to the "EESclass"
      registry will require a EENA Technical Standard document.
      Subregistries for particular "EENAclasses" may be established by
      such technical standards.  Subregistries may be defined to have
      more liberal management policies as defined in TBD, but must be EESR managed and will not be permitted to be delegated to any other organization or registry.  Thus, the EESR
      will manage the entire urn:ees tree.
   </t>
   
   <t>Process for identifier resolution:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      The namespace is not currently listed with a Resolution Discovery
      System (RDS), but nothing about the namespace prohibits the future
      definition of appropriate resolution methods or listing with
      an RDS.
   </t>

   <t>Rules for lexical equivalence:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      No special considerations; the rules for lexical equivalence of
      <xref target="RFC2141"/> apply.
   </t>
   
   <t>Conformance with URN syntax:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      No special considerations.
   </t>
   
   <t>Validation mechanism:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      None specified.  URN assignment will be handled by procedures
      implemented in support of EENA activities.
   </t>
   
   <t>Scope:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Global
   </t>
   </list>
   </t>
   
</section> 



    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->


 <section anchor="examples" title="Examples">

   <t>The following examples are representative URNs that could be assigned
   by the ERS.  They may not be the actual strings that would be
   assigned.</t>

   <t>Resource "psaproute"</t>
   <t>Syntax: "urn:ees:emergencyresponders:&lt;responder name&gt;"</t>
   <t>ResourceSpecificString: simple string with name of responder,
                           defined in a subregistry</t>
   <t>Use: Defines the URN to be used for queries to an NG112 Emergency
   Call Routing Function that provides URIs for responding agencies.</t>

   <t>Examples:</t>

   <t>urn:ees:emergencyresponders:ambulance</t>
   <t>urn:ees:emergencyresponders:fire</t>
   <t>urn:ees:emergencyresponders:police</t>
   <t>urn:ees:emergencyresponders:poison</t>
   <t>urn:ees:emergencyresponders:coastguard</t>
   <t>urn:ees:emergencyresponders:marine</t>
	
</section>
	
	

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->


 <section title="Namespace Considerations">

<t>The European Emergency Number Association is a Brussels-based NGO set up in 1999 dedicated to promoting high-quality emergency services reached by the number 112 throughout the EU. EENA serves as a discussion platform for emergency services, public authorities, decision makers, associations and solution providers in view of improving emergency response in accordance with citizens' requirements. EENA is also promoting the establishment of an efficient system for alerting citizens about imminent or developing emergencies.</t>

<t>The EENA memberships include about 655 emergency services representatives from 43 European countries, 56 solution providers, 9 international associations/organisations as well as 26 Members of the European Parliament.</t>

<t>EENA members do their work in committees, which also includes a technical committee that develops a variety of applications and services using Internet
   protocols built upon IETF standards.  Some of these services require
   that supporting information (e.g., data descriptions, attributes,
   etc.) be fully specified.  For proper operation, descriptions of the
   needed supporting information must exist and be available in a
   unique, reliable, and persistent manner.  These dependencies provide
   the basis of the need for namespaces, in one form or another, and
   will enable EENA to define URNs that are to assign cleaner, more
   general, more permanent, more reliable, and more controllable
   namespace names related to EENA standards, while keeping URNs defined
   by EENA properly separate from the IETF-defined URNs.</t>

<t>As the European Emergency Number Association work is ongoing and
   covers many technical areas, the possibility of binding to various
   other namespace repositories has been deemed impractical.  Each
   object or description, as defined in EENA, could possibly be related
   to multiple different namespaces, so further conflicts of association
   could occur.  Thus, the intent is to utilize the European Emergency Services Registry, operated by EENA, as the naming
   authority for EENA-defined objects and descriptions.
</t>

</section>


    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->


 <section title="Community Considerations">

<t>The European public safety organizations will benefit from
   publication of this namespace by having permanent and reliable URNs
   to be used with protocols defined by EENA.  The objects and
   descriptions required for services defined by EENA are generally
   available for use by other organizations.  The European Emergency
   Number Association will provide access and support for name requests
   by these organizations within the constraints of the defined ERS
   processes and the specific urn:eena registry and subregistries.  This
   support can be enabled in a timely and responsive fashion as new
   objects and descriptions are produced.  These will be enabled in a
   fashion similar to current IANA processes, as documented in
   TBD.
</t>

<t>
   The EESR establishes registries when called for in a EENA Technical
   Standard.  Such standards must provide clear and concise
   instructions on creating and maintaining such registries.  Defined
   management policies include "EENA Technical Standard Required", "EENA
   Document Required", "Expert Review", and "First Come First Served",
   which correspond to similar IANA management policies.  EENA is
   establishing a website that provides controlled entry of new
   registries and entries in registries, and automatically produces HTML
   and XML descriptions of registry contents that are used by vendors
   and other consumers of the content.
</t>
</section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="sec-cons" title="Security Considerations">
   
<t>There are no additional security considerations other than those
   normally associated with the use and resolution of URNs in general.</t>

    </section> 

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
	
<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document adds a new entry in the URN Namespaces registry.  The
   namespace is "eena".  The defining document is this RFC.  The entry
   can be found in the Uniform Resource Names (URN) Namespaces registry
   available from http://www.iana.org and any associated mirrors.</t>

</section> 

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
   
<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>We would like to thank Brian Rosen for his work on RFC 6061. We have re-used his writeup since it aims to accomplish the same goal. His work was focused on the National Emergency Number Association, a partner organization of EENA.</t>
</section> 

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
  </middle>

  <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997"/>
        </front>
        <format octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>
      &RFC2141;
	  &RFC3406;
    </references>
<!--    <references title="Informative References">

    </references>
-->
  </back>
</rfc>
