<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-ecrit-additional-data-03.txt">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc compact="no" ?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Additional Call Data">Additional Data related to an Emergency Call</title>
    <author fullname="Brian Rosen" initials="B.R" surname="Rosen">
      <organization>NeuStar</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>470 Conrad Dr.</street>
          <city>Mars</city>
          <region>PA</region>
          <code>16046</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 724 382 1051</phone>
        <email>br@brianrosen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
       <author initials="R." surname="Marshall" fullname="Roger Marshall">
      <organization>TeleCommunication Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2401 Elliott Avenue</street>
          <city>Seattle</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98121</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 206 792 2424</phone>
        <email>rmarshall@telecomsys.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.telecomsys.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2012"/>
    <area>RAI</area>
    <workgroup>ECRIT</workgroup>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>Additional Call Data</keyword>
    <keyword>Emergency Services</keyword>
    <keyword>Call Information</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>When an emergency call is sent to a Public Safety Answering Point (PSAP), 
      the device that sends it, as well as any service
      provider in the path of the call, or access network through which the call 
      originated may have information about the call which the PSAP may be
      able to use. This document describes an XML data structure to contains such data 
      and a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) for conveying the data to the PSAP.  
      The URI may point to either an external resource, or the body of the SIP message.
      </t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
    
   <t>This document extends the basic signaling of an emergency call as described in <xref target="RFC6443"/> and 
   <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/> in
   order to carry additional data which may be useful to an entity
   handling the call.  This data is "additional" to the basic
   signaling used in processing the call.  Four general categories of
   such data are defined, for the caller, the location, the call, and
   the PSAP.  An XML data structure is defined for such data, and a
   means of conveying the data by including a Uniform Resource
   Identifier (URI) in the SIP signaling which resolves to the data.
   The data itself may reside on an external resource, or may be
   contained within the BODY of the SIP message.
   </t>
   
   <t>In general, there are three types of data exchanged:
   
   <list style="hanging"> 
   <t hangText="Data Associated with a Call:">While information is carried in the call setup procedure itself (as part of the SIP headers as well as in the body of the SIP message), there is additional data known by the device making the call, or a service provider in the path of the call including contact data, subscriber data, service data and device data. </t>
   <t hangText="Data Associated with a Location:">There may be data that is specific to the location not available in the location data structure (PIDF-LO <xref target="RFC4119"/>) itself, such as floor plan, tenant and building owner contact data, HVAC status, etc.</t>
   <t hangText="Data Associated with a Caller:">This is personal data about a caller, such as medical information and emergency contact data.</t>
   </list> 
   </t>
   
      <t>When an emergency call is sent to a PSAP, while there is a rich set of data in the SIP message used for the call setup,
      the device, as well as any service provider in the path may have even
        more information that may be useful for a PSAP. This information may include the identity
        and contact information of the service provider, subscriber identity and contact
        information, the type of service the provider offers, what kind of device is being used, etc. Some data is device or service dependent data. For
        example, a car telematics system or service may have crash information. A medical monitoring
        device may have sensor data. While the details of the information may vary by device or
        service, there needs to be a common way to send such data to a PSAP. </t>
        
      <t>This document focuses only four types of additional data associated with an emergent call
   and a mechanism for transporting it in an existing SIP header field,
   the Call-Info header, which is specified in Section 20.9 of <xref target="RFC3261"/>. 
   For this purpose a new token, namely
   'emergencyCallData' is defined to be carried in the "purpose"
   parameter.  If the "purpose" parameter is set to 'emergencyCallData'
   then the Call-Info header contains a HTTPS URL that points to a service and data
   structure with information about the call or is a CID that allows the
   data structure itself to be placed in the body of the message. <xref target="example"/> shows a SIP INVITE example 
   containing such a Call-Info header using the purpose parameter. 
   </t>
   <t>Besides a service provider in the path of a call, the access network (which in the IETF emergency call
   architecture provides location in the form of a PIDF-LO <xref target="RFC4119"/>) also has similar information
   that may be valuable to the PSAP.  This information is not specific to the location itsef, but rather would provide descriptive information having to do with the
   immediate circumstances about the provision of the location (who the access network is, how to contact that entity, 
   what kind of service the access network provides, possibly subscriber data, etc.).  This data is similar in nearly every
   respect with the data known by services providers in the path of the call.  For this reason,
   this document describes a "provided-by" namespace per <xref target="RFC4119"/> for
   passing information known to the access network.</t>

   <t>The data is defined as a series of "blocks" that represent a class of
   information.  Each of the blocks is a MIME type, and an extensible
   set of these types constitute the data structure.  A registry is
   defined to list the block types that may be included.
   </t>
      <t>The data structure contains an element which itself is a URI that has device or service
        dependent data. Thus the common Additional Data about a Call defined by this document
        contains a 'hook', in the form of a URI, for a device or service dependent data structure.</t>

    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD
        NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
   <t>In the data block definitions, the "Use:" values are specified as one of:
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Mandatory"> which means they MUST be present in the data structure.</t>
<t hangText="Conditional"> which means they MUST be present unless the specified condition is met, in which case the they MAY be present.</t>
<t hangText="Optional"> which means they MAY be present.</t>
</list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->


    <section title="Call-Info Specification">
    
   <t>The Additional Data about a Call is information specific to a call
   known by the device that sends it or a service provider in the path
   of a call or in the access network the call originates in.  The
   Additional Data about a Call is a set of information blocks.  Each
   block is a MIME type, and any set of blocks may be included in the
   set.</t>

   <t>Two mechanisms are provided to transport the data set, namely
   <list style="numbers"> 
   <t>A URI to
   the data set MAY be inserted in a SIP INVITE or MESSAGE transaction
   with a Call-Info header containing a purpose of "emergencyCallData".
   The Call-info header with purpose='emergencyCallData' MUST only be sent on an emergency
        call, which can be ascertained by the presence of an emergency service urn in a Route header
        of a SIP message.  If the data is provided by reference, it may be retrieved with an
   HTTPS Get from the URI.  The URI MUST specify an HTTPS scheme, and
   TLS protection for the data MUST be negotiated.</t>

   <t>The data may be supplied by value in a SIP INVITE or MESSAGE message.
   In this case, Content Indirection (CID) <xref target="RFC2392"/> is used, with the CID URL
   pointing to the body of the message.</t>
   </list> 
   </t>
   
   <t> More than one Call-Info header with an emergencyCallData purpose can be expected, but at least one MUST be provided. 
The device MUST provide one if no service provider is in the path of the call.  The
        device MAY insert one if it uses a service provider. Any service provider in the path of the call MUST insert its own. For example, a device, a telematics service provider in the call path, as well as the mobile carrier handling
        the call will each provide one.  There may be circumstances where there is a service provider who is unaware that the call is an emergency call and cannot reasonably be expected to determine that it is an emergency call.  In that case, that service provider is not expected to provide emergencyCallData.</t>
        
  <t>Note: The access network MAY supply additional data as well. For this
   purpose, this document defines a namespace and adds the namespace to
   the "provided-by" registry defined by PIDF-LO <xref target="RFC4119"/>.</t>
   <t>In regions where callers can elect to suppress certain personally identifying information, the network or PSAP functionality can inspect privacy flags within the SIP headers to determine what information may be passed, stored, or displayed to comply with local policy or law.</t>

   <t>Additional data about a call is defined as a series of MIME objects, each with an XML data 
   structure contained inside.  MIME-multipart is used to enclose the XML documents and the
   sections below define them.  When additional data is passed by value, the CID URL points one block.  Multiple URIs must be used within a Call-Info header to point to each of the blocks.  When additional data is provided by reference, the data is retrieved with an HTTP Get operation, which returns a multi-part MIME header and a set of MIME blocks defined by this document.  A registry of allowed types is created by this document.  Every block MUST be one of the types in the registry.</t>
   
  </section> 
  
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
  
      <section title="Data Provider Information">
      <t>This block is intended to be provided by any service provider in the
   path of the call or the access network provider.  It includes
   identification and contact information.  This block SHOULD be
   provided for every service provider in the path of the call, and the
   access network provider.  Devices MAY use this block to provide
   identifying information.  The MIME type is "addDataProviderInfo+xml".</t>
   
      <section title="Data Provider String"> 
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Data Provider String<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;DataProviderString&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">This is a plain language string suitable for displaying the
              name of the service provider that created the additional data structure. If the device
              created the structure the value is identical to the contact header in the SIP INVITE.
              <!-- This data is required and should reflect the contact information of the owner of the
                device. --> <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:"> Inform the call taker of the identity of the entity
              providing the additional call data structure.</t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Allows the call taker to interpret the data in
              this structure. The source of the information often influences how the information is
              used, believed or verified. </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Data Provider ID">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Data Provider ID<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional. Must be provided if the service provider is located in a jurisdiction that maintains such ids.  Devices are not required to provide it.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;ProviderID&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">A jurisdiction specific code for the provider shown in the
              &lt;DataProvidedBy&gt; element that created the structure of the call. <!-- NOTE:
              In the US, the NENA Company ID must appear here. Additional information may be found
              at http://www.nena.org/nena-company-id. The NENA Company ID shall be in the form of
              any URI for example: urn:nena:companyid:&lt;NENA Company ID&gt;. --> This data SHOULD be provided if 
              the local jurisdiction maintains such an ID list.  For example, in North America, this would be
              a "NENA Company ID".  Devices SHOULD NOT use this element.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Inform the call taker of the identity of the entity
              providing the additional call data structure.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Where jurisdictions have lists of providers the
              Data Provider ID can be useful.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Data Provider ID Series">
        <t>  
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Data Provider ID Series<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional.  If Data Provider ID is provided, Data Provider ID Series is required.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;ProviderIDSeries&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Identifies the issuer of the
              the ProviderId. A registry will reflect the following valid
              entries: <list style="symbols">
               <t>NENA</t>
               <t>EENA</t>
             </list>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Identifies how to interpret the Data Provider ID.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Determines which provider ID registry to consult for more information</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Type of Data Provider">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Type of Data Provider ID<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional.  If Data Provider ID is provided, Type of Data Provider ID is required.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;TypeOfProviderID&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Identifies the type of data provider id being supplied in
              the ProviderId data element. A registry will reflect the following valid
              entries: <list style="symbols">
                <t>Access Infrastructure Provider</t>
		<t>Service Provider</t>
		<t>Service Provider Subcontractor</t>
               <t>Telematics Provider</t>
               <t>Relay Provider</t>
                <t> Other</t>
              </list>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Identifies what kind of data provider this is.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">To decide who to contact when further information is needed</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
        <section title="Data Provider Contact URI">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Data Provider Contact URI<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;ContactURI&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">For a service provider the contact SHOULD be a contact
              URI. This MUST be a SIP URI. If a telephone number is the contact
              address it should be provided in the form of
              sip:telephonenumber@serviceprovider:user=phone. If the call is from a device, this
              would reflect the contact information of the owner of the
                device.  When provided by a service provider, this would be a URI to a 24/7 support organization tasked to provide PSAP support
                for this emergency call.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Additional data providers may need to be contacted for
              error or other unusual circumstances.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">To contact the supplier of the additional data for assistance in handling the call.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Data Provider Languages(s) Supported">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Data Provider Language(s) supported<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;Language&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">The language used by the entity at the Data Provider Contact URI as an alpha 2-character code as defined in ISO
              639-1:2002 (http://www.iso.org/iso/catalogue_detail?csnumber=22109) Codes for the
              representation of names of languages -- Part 1: Alpha-2 code Multiple instances of
              this element may occur. Order is significant; preferred language should appear first.
              This data is required if a Data Provider Contact URI is provided.  The content must reflect the languages
              supported at the contact URI.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Information needed to determine if emergency service authority can
              communicate with the service provider or if an interpreter will be needed.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">If call taker cannot speak language(s) supported
              by the service provider, a translation service will need to be added to the conversation.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="xCard of Data Provider">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">xCard of Data Provider<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;DataProviderContact&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">There are many fields in the xCARD and the creator of the data
              structure is encouraged to provide as much information as they have available. N, ORG, ADR, TEL, EMAIL are suggested at a minimum.  N should contain name of support group or device owner as appropriate.  If more than one TEL property is provided, a parameter from the vCard Property Value registry MUST be specified on each TEL.  For encoding of the xCard this specification uses the XML-based encoding specified in <xref target="RFC6351"/>.<vspace blankLines="1"/> and is hereinafter referred to as "xCard"</t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Information needed to determine additional contact
                information.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Assists call taker by providing additional contact
              information that may not be included in the SIP invite or the PIDF-LO.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
     <section title="Subcontractor Principal"> 
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Subcontractor Principal<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;SubcontratorPrincipal&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">If the data provider is a subcontractor to another
                    provider such as an access infrastructure provider or 
                    telematics provider, this element contains the DataProviderString of the  
                    service provider to indicate which provider the subcontractor is working for.  
                    This data is required if the Data Provider type is subcontractor. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:"> Identify the entity the subcontractor works for.</t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Allows the call taker to understand what the relationship 
                         between data providers and the service providers in the path of the call are. </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
     <section title="Subcontractor Priority"> 
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Subcontractor Priority<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;SubcontractorPriority&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">If the subcontractor should be contacted first, this element should have a "sub" value.  If the access or origination service provider should be contacted first, this element should have a "main" value.
              This data is required if the Data Provider type is "subcontractor". <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:"> Inform the call taker whether the network operator or the subcontractor should be contacted first if support is needed.</t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">To decide which entity to contact first if assistance is needed.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="addDataProviderInfo XML Schema"> 
        <figure anchor="addDataProviderInfo" title="addDataProviderInfo XML Schema">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xs:schema
     targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataProviderInfo"
     xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:ad="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataProviderInfo"
     xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
     xmlns:xc="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:vcard-4.0"
     elementFormDefault="qualified" attributeFormDefault="unqualified">

     <xs:import namespace="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
                schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml.xsd"/>

     <xs:simpleType name="iso3166a2">
       <xs:restriction base="xs:token">
         <xs:pattern value="[A-Z]{2}"/>
       </xs:restriction>
     </xs:simpleType>

    <xs:element name="addDataProviderInfo">
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence>
                <xs:element name="DataProviderString" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="ProviderID" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="ProviderIdSeries" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="TypeOfProvider" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="ContactURI" type="xs:anyURI"
                    minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="Language" type="ad:iso3166a2" 
                    minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded" />
                <xs:element name="DataProviderContact" 
                    type="xc:vcard" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
            </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
</xs:schema>
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

      </section> 
      
    </section> 


    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

      <section title="Service Information">
      
      <t>This block describes the service that the service provider provides	
			to the caller. It SHOULD be included by all SPs in the path of the	
			call. The mime type is "addCallSvcInfo+xml".</t>
			
        <section title="Service Environment"> 
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Service Environment<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;SvcEnvironment&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">This element defines whether a call is from a business or
              residence caller. Currently, the only valid entries are 'Business' or 'Residence'.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">To assist in determining equipment and manpower
                requirements.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Information may be used to assist in determining equipment and
              manpower requirements for emergency responders.  As the information is not always available, and the registry is not all encompassing, this is at best advisory information, but since it mimics a similar capability in some current emergency calling systems, it is known to be valuable.  The service provider uses it's best information (such as a rate plan, facilities used to deliver service or service description) to determine the information and is not responsible for determining the actual characteristics of the location where the call originates from.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Service Delivered by Provider to End User">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Service Delivered by Provider to End User<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;SvcDelByProvider&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">This defines the type of service the end user has 
              subscribed to.  The implied mobility of this service can not be relied upon.
              A registry will reflect the following initial valid entries: 
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Wireless Telephone Service: Includes Satellite, CDMA, GSM, Wi-Fi, WiMAX, LTE (Long
                  Term Evolution) </t>
                <t>Fixed Public Pay/Coin telephones: Any coin or credit card operated device. </t>
                <t> One way outbound service </t>
                <t>Inmate call/service </t>
                <t>Soft dialtone/quick service/warm disconnect/suspended </t>
                <t>Multi-line telephone system (MLTS): Includes all PBX, Centrex, key systems,
                  Shared Tenant Service. </t>
                <t>Sensor, unattended: Includes devices that generate DATA ONLY. This is one-way
                  information exchange and there will be no other form of communication. </t>
                <t> Sensor, attended: Includes devices that are supported by a monitoring service
                  provider or automatically open a two-way communication path. </t>
                <t> Wireline: Plain Old Telephone Service (POTS). </t>
                <t> VoIP Telephone Service: A type of service that offers communication over
                  internet protocol, such as Fixed, Nomadic, Mobile, Unknown </t>
                <t> Relay Service: a type of service where there is a human 3rd party agent who provides some kind of additional assistance to the caller.  Includes sign language relay and telematics services which provide a service assistant on the call.</t>
                <t> Remote (off premise extension) </t> 
              </list>
              There can be more than one value returned.  For example, a VoIP inmate telephone service is a
              reasonable combination.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Knowing the type of service may assist the PSAP with the
              handling of the call.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Call takers often use this information to determine what kinds of questions
            to ask callers, and how much to rely on supportive information.  An emergency call from a prison is treated differently
            that a call from a sensor device.  As the information is not always available, and the registry is not all encompassing, this is at best advisory information, but since it mimics a similar capability in some current emergency calling systems, it is known to be valuable.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
       </section>
      <section title="Service Mobility Environment">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Service Mobility Environment<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;SvcMobility&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">This provides the service providers view of the mobility of the caller.  As the service provider may not know the characteristics of the actual access network used, the value not be relied upon.
              A registry will reflect the following initial valid entries: 
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>Mobile: the device should be able to move at any time </t>
                <t>Fixed: the device is not expected to move unless the service is relocated </t>
                <t>Nomadic: the device is not expected to move while on a call, but may move between calls</t>
               </list>
               <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Knowing the service provider's belief of mobility may assist the PSAP with the
              handling of the call.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">To determine whether to assume the location of the caller might change.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
       </section>       
       <section title="addCallSvcInfo XML Schema">
       
        <figure anchor="addCallSvcInfo" title="addCallSvcInfo XML Schema">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xs:schema
     targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSvcInfo"
     xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:svc="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSvcInfo"
     xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
     elementFormDefault="qualified" attributeFormDefault="unqualified">

     <xs:import namespace="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
                schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml.xsd"/>

    <xs:element name="addCallSvcInfo">
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence>
                <xs:element name="SvcEnvironment" 
                  type="xs:string" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="SvcDelByProvider" 
                  type="xs:string" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="SvcMobility"
                  type="xs:string" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="Link" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
            </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
</xs:schema>
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
       </section> 
       
      </section> 
      
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

      <section title="Device Information">

       <t>	This block provides information about the device used to place the	
			call. It should be provided by any service provider that knows what	
			device is being used, and by the device itself. The mime type is	
			"addDataDevInfo+xml".
			</t> 
			
 		<section title="Device Classification">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Device Classification<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;DeviceClassification&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">This data element defines the kind of device making
                the emergency call. If the device provides the data structure, the device 
                information SHOULD be provided.  If the service provider provides the  
                structure and it knows what the device is, the service provider SHOULD 
                provide the device information.  Often the carrier does not know what the 
                device is.  It is possible to receive two Additional Data Associated with a 
                Call data structures, one created by the device and one created by the 
                service provider.  This information describes the the device, not 
                how it is being used.  This data element defines the kind of device making 
                the emergency call.  A registry will reflect the following valid entries:
                <list style="symbols">
                <t>Cordless handset</t>
                <t>Fixed phone</t>
                <t>Mobile handset</t>
                <t>ATA (analog terminal adapter)</t>
                <t>Satellite phone</t>
                <t>Stationary computing device (alarm system, data sensor)</t>
                <t>Guardian devices</t>
                <t>Desktop PC</t>
                <t>Laptop computing device</t>
                <t>Tablet computing device</t>
                <t>Alarm system</t>
                <t>Data sensor</t>
                <t>Personal beacons (spot)</t>
                <t>Auto telematics (indicates VEDS data set)</t>
                <t>Trucking telematics</t>
                <t>Farm equipment telematics</t>
                <t>Marine telematics</t>
                <t>PDA (personal digital assistant)</t>
                <t>PND (personal navigation device)</t>
                <t>Smart phone</t>
                <t>Internet tablet</t>
                <t>Gaming console</t>
                <t>Video phone</t>
                <t>Other text device</t>
                <t>Not Available</t>
              </list>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">The device classification implies the 
               capability of the calling device and assists in identifying the meaning of
               the emergency call location information that is being presented.  For 
               example, does the device require human intervention to initiate a call or 
               is this call the result of programmed instructions?  Does the calling 
               device have the ability to update location or condition changes?  
               Is this device interactive or a one-way reporting device?<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">May assist with location of caller. For example, a
              cordless handset may be outside or next door. May provide calltaker some context about
              the caller, the capabilities of the device used for the call or the environment the device is being used in.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Device Manufacturer">

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Device Manufacturer<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;DeviceMfgr&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">The plain language name of the manufacturer of the device.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Used by PSAP management for post-mortem
                investigation/resolution.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Probably not used by calltaker, but by PSAP
              management.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Device Model Number">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Device Model Number<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;DeviceModelNr&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Model number of the device.<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Used by PSAP management for after action
                investigation/resolution.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Probably not used by calltaker, but by PSAP
              management.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Unique Device Identifier">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Unique Device Identifier<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;UniqueDeviceID&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">String that identifies the specific device making the call
              or creating an event.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Uniquely identifies the device as opposed to any signaling
            identifiers encountered in the call signaling stream.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Probably not used by calltaker they would need to
              refer to management for investigation.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Type of Device Identifier">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Type of Device Identifier<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional: must be provided if DeviceID is provided<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;TypeOfDeviceID&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Identifies the type of device identifier being generated in
              the unique device identifier data element. A registry will reflect the following valid
              entries: <list style="symbols">
                <t>MEID (CDMA)</t>
                <t>ESN (Electronic Serial Number -- superseded by MEID) </t>
                <t> MAC (Media Access Control) Address --  IEEE-delegated address of any of the interfaces of the device with a MAC address (e.g., Ethernet, WiFi) </t>
                <t> WiMAX device certificate subject unique identifier</t>
                <t> IMEI (International Mobile Equipment Identifier - GSM) </t>
                <t> Unique Device Identifier (UDI) assigned by US FD for medical devices </t>
                <t> RFID (Radio Frequency Identification) </t>
                <t> Sensors (types to be identified in a future document version) </t>
                <t> Manufacturer Serial Number </t>
                <t> Other</t>
              </list>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Identifies how to interpret the Unique Device Identifier.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Additional information that may be used to assist
              with call handling.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Device/Service Specific Additional Data Structure">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Device/service specific additional data structure<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;devicespecificSchema&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">A URI representing additional data whose schema is specific
              to the device or service which created it. An example is the VEDs structure for a
              vehicle telematics device. The URI, when dereferenced, MUST yield a data structure 
              defined by the Device/service specific additional data type value.
              Different data may be created by each
                  classification; e.g., telematics creates VEDS data set.  
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Provides device/service specific data that may be used by the
            call taker and/or responders.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Provide information to guide call takers to select appropriate responders,
            give appropriate pre-arrival instructions to callers, and advise responders of what to be prepared for.  May
            be used by responders to guide assistance provided.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Device/Service Specific Additional Data Structure Type">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Type of Device/service specific additional data structure<vspace
                blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional.  MUST be provided when Device/service specific additional URI is provided
            <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;devicespecificType&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Value from a registry defined by this document to describe the type of data 
            that can be retrieved from the Device/service specific additional data structure.  Initial values are:               
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>IEEE 1512 - USDOT Model for traffic incidents </t>
                <t>VEDS</t>
              </list>
               <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">This data element allows identification of
              externally defined schemas, which may have additional data that may assist in
              emergency response.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">This data element allows the end user
              (calltaker or first responder) to know what type of additional data may be available
              to aid in providing the needed emergency services.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Note:">Information which is specific to a location or a caller (person) should not be placed in this section.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>     
      <section title="addDataDevInfo XML Schema">
      
        <figure anchor="addDataDevInfo" title="addDataDevInfo XML Schema">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xs:schema
     targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataDevInfo"
     xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:svc="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataDevInfo"
     xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
     elementFormDefault="qualified" attributeFormDefault="unqualified">

     <xs:import namespace="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
                schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml.xsd"/>

    <xs:element name="addDataDevInfo">
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence>
                <xs:element name="DeviceClassification" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="DeviceMfgr" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="DeviceModelNr" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="UniqueDeviceID" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xs:element name="TypeOfDeviceID" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
               <xsd:element name="devicespecificType" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
                <xsd:element name="devicespecificSchema" 
                    type="xsd:anyURI" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1"/>
            </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
</xs:schema>
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

      </section> 
      
     </section>
    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

<!-- 
      <section title="Telephone Number Privacy Indicator">
   <t>In regions where callers can elect to suppress certain personally identifying information, the network or PSAP functionality can inspect privacy flags within the identity header to drive what information is passed, stored, or displayed to comply with local policy or law.</t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Telephone Number Privacy Indicator<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Required<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;TNPrivacyIndicator&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Some state and country regulations require that the caller's
              name remains anonymous to all including emergency service authorities. Where this regulation is in place, the
              callers name must be hidden using extensions defined for SIP.”<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Some State regulations require that Non-Published
              subscriber name remains private to all including emergency calls. Where this
              regulation is in place, the end user’s name must be overlaid with blanks or the
              verbiage, “Non-Published Number”.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">This is not beneficial to PSAPs; however, they
              must follow state regulations. This indicator will allow for coding that overlays the
              non-published subscriber name with the verbiage “Non-Published Number.”</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

--> 

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
      
      <section title="Owner/Subscriber Information"> 
				
	 <t>This block describes the owner of the device (if provided by the	
			device) or the subscriber information, if provided by a service	
			provider. The contact location is not necessarily the location of	
			the caller or incident, but is rather the nominal contact address.	
			The mime type is "addCallSub+xml".</t>
			
      <section title="xCard for Subscriber’s Data">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">xCARD for Subscriber’s Data<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Conditional: Some services (e.g. prepaid phones, initialized phones, etc.) may not have this information.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;SubscriberData&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Information known by the service provider or device about the
              subscriber; e.g., Name, Address, Individual Telephone Number, Main Telephone Number and any
              other data.  N, ORG (if appropriate), ADR, TEL, EMAIL are suggested at a minimum.  If more than one TEL property is provided, a parameter from the vCard Property Value registry MUST be specified on each TEL.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">When the caller is unable to provide information, this data may be used to obtain it<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">Obtaining critical information about the caller and possibly the location when it is not able to be obtained otherwise.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="addCallSub XML Schema">
      
       <figure anchor="addCallSub" title="addCallSub XML Schema">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xs:schema
     targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSub"
     xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:sub="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSub"
     xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
     xmlns:xc="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:vcard-4.0"
     elementFormDefault="qualified" attributeFormDefault="unqualified">

     <xs:import namespace="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
                schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml.xsd"/>

    <xs:element name="addCallSub">
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence>
                <xs:element name="SubscriberData" 
                    type="xc:vcard" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
           </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
</xs:schema>
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
 
      </section> 
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

      <section title="Comment"> 
				
	 <t>This block Provides a mechanism for the data provider to supply extra, human readable information to the PSAP.  It is not intended for a general purpose extension mechanism</t>
			
      <section title="Comment">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Data Element:">Comment<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Use:">Optional<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="XML Element:">&lt;Comment&gt;<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Description:">Human readable text providing additional information to the PSAP.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="Reason for Need:">Explanatory information for values in the data structure <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
            <t hangText="How Used by Call Taker:">To interpret the data provided</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Comment XML Schema">
      
        <figure anchor="addCallComment" title="Comment XML Schema">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xs:schema
     targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallComment"
     xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
     xmlns:sub="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallComment"
     xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
     elementFormDefault="qualified" attributeFormDefault="unqualified">

     <xs:import namespace="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace"
                schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml.xsd"/>

    <xs:element name="addCallComment">
        <xs:complexType>
            <xs:sequence>
                <xs:element name="Comment" 
                    type="xs:string" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
           </xs:sequence>
        </xs:complexType>
    </xs:element>
</xs:schema>
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
 
      </section> 
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->
<section anchor="example" title="Example"> 


        <figure title="Example: Attaching Additional Data via CID to a SIP INVITE">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   INVITE sips:bob@biloxi.example.com SIP/2.0
   Via: SIPS/2.0/TLS pc33.atlanta.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK74bf9
   Max-Forwards: 70
   To: Bob <sips:bob@biloxi.example.com>
   From: Alice <sips:alice@atlanta.example.com>;tag=9fxced76sl
   Call-ID: 3848276298220188511@atlanta.example.com
   Call-Info: <http://wwww.example.com/alice/photo.jpg> ;purpose=icon,
     <http://www.example.com/alice/> ;purpose=info, 
     <cid:1234567890@atlanta.example.com> ;purpose=emergencyCallData
   Geolocation: <cid:target123@atlanta.example.com>
   Geolocation-Routing: no
   Accept: application/sdp, application/pidf+xml, 
      application/addDataProviderinfo+xml
   CSeq: 31862 INVITE
   Contact: <sips:alice@atlanta.example.com>
   Content-Type: multipart/mixed; boundary=boundary1

   Content-Length: ...

   --boundary1

   Content-Type: application/sdp

   ...SDP goes here

   --boundary1

   Content-Type: application/pidf+xml
   Content-ID: <target123@atlanta.example.com>

   …PIDF-LO goes here

   --boundary1--

   Content-Type: application/addDataProviderinfo+xml
   Content-ID: <1234567890@atlanta.example.com>

   …Additional Data goes here

   --boundary1--
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

    </section> 


    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

    <section anchor="mainTel" title="Main Telephone Number">
    <t>In a xCard, used extensively in this document, there is no way to specify a "Main" telephone number.  These numbers are useful to emergency responders who are called to a large enterprise.  This document adds a new Property Value to the "tel" property of the TYPE parameter called "main".  It can be used in any xCard in additional data.</t>
    </section> 


    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>The information in this data structure will usually be considered private. HTTPS is
        specified to require the provider of the information to validate the credentials of the
        requester. While the creation of a PKI that has global scope may be difficult, the
        alternatives to creating devices and services that can provide critical information securely
        are more daunting.  The provider may enforce any policy it wishes to use, but PSAPs and responder agencies should deploy a PKI so that providers of additional data can check the certificate of the client and decide the appropriate policy to enforce based on that certificate.</t>
      
      <t>Ideally, the PSAP and emergency responders will be given credentials signed by an authority trusted by the data provider.  In most circumstances, nationally recognized credentials would be sufficient, and if the emergency services arranges a PKI, data providers could be provisioned with the root CA public key for a given nation.  Some nations are developing a PKI for this, and related, purposes.  Since calls could be made from devices where the device and/or the service provider(w) are not local to the emergency authorities, globally recognized credentials are useful.  This might be accomplished by extending the notion of the "forest guide" described in <xref target="RFC5222"/> to allow the forest guide to provide the credential of the PKI root for areas that it has coverage information for, but standards for such a mechanism are not yet available.  In its absence, the data provider will need to obtain the root CA credentials for any areas it is willing to provide additional data by out of band means. With the credential of the root CA for a national emergency services PKI, the data provider server can validate the credentials of an entity requesting additional data by reference.</t>
      <t>The data provider also needs a credential that can be verified by the emergency services to know that it is receiving data from the right server.  The emergency authorities could provide credentials, distinguishable from credentials it provides to emergency responders and PSAPs, which could be used to validate data providers.  This would be extensible to global credential validation using the forest guide as above.  In the absence of such credentials, the emergency authorities could maintain a list of local data providers' credentials provided to it out of band.  At a minimum, the emergency authorities could obtain a credential from the DNS entry of the domain in the Addional Data URI to at least validate that the server is known to the domain providing the URI.</t>
      <t>Data provided by devices by reference have similar credential validation issues to service providers, and the solutions are the same.</t>
      
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations"> 
      <t>There is much private data in this information. Local regulations	
			may govern what data must be provided in emergency calls, but in	
			general, the emergency call system is often aided by the kinds of	
			information described in this document. There is a tradeoff between	
			the privacy considerations and the utility of the data. Certainly,	
			if the data cannot be protected, due to failure to establish (by TLS) a secure connection to the data provider, data SHOULD NOT be sent unless specifically required by regulation.
		</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
   <section title="Registry creation">
     <t>This document creates a new registry called 'Emergency Call Additional Data'.  The following subregistries are created in Emergency Call Additional Data:</t>
   <section title="Additional Call Data Blocks Registry">
      <t>This document creates a new subregistry called ’Provider ID Series’.  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
   operates under "Expert Review" rules.  The expert should determine that the entity requesting a new value is a legitimate issuer of service provider IDs suitable for use in Additional Call Data.</t>
<t>The content of this registry includes:</t>

<t>Name: The identifier which will be used in the ProviderIDSeries element</t>

<t>Source: The full name of the organization issuing the identifiers</t>
<t>URL: A URL to the organization for further information</t>

<t>The values defined are:</t>
<figure><artwork>
   +-----------+-----------+--------------+--------------+
   | Name      | Source                   |     URL      |
   +-----------+--------------------------+--------------+
   | NENA      | North American Emergency | www.nena.org |
   |           | Number Association       |              |
   | EENA      | European Emergency       | www.eena.org |
   |           | Number Association       |              |
   +-----------+--------------------------+--------------+
RFC Editor Note:
   replace XXXX in the table above with this documents RFC number
</artwork></figure>   
    </section>   
   <section title="Service Provider Type">
      <t>This document creates a new subregistry called ’Service Provider Type’.  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
   operates under "Expert Review".  The expert should determine that the proposed new value is distinct from existing values and appropriate for use in the TypeOfServicerProvider element</t>
<t>The content of this registry includes:</t>

<t>Name: Value to be used in TypeOfServiceProvider.</t>

<t>Description: A short description of the type of service provider</t>

<t>The values defined are:</t>
<figure><artwork>
   +------------------------------+------------------------------------+
   | Name                         | Description                        |
   +------------------------------+------------------------------------+
   |Access Infrastructure Provider| Access network service provider    |
   |Service Provider              | Calling or Origination telecom SP  |
   |Service Provider Subcontractor| A contractor to another kind of SP |
   |Telematics Provider           | A sensor based SP, especially      |
   |                              | vehicle based                      |
   |Relay Provider                | A interpretation SP, for example,  | 
   |                              | video relay for sign language      |
   |                              | interpretors                       |
   |Other                         | Any other type of service provider |
   +------------------------------+------------------------------------+
RFC Editor Note:
   replace XXXX in the table above with this documents RFC number
</artwork></figure>   
    </section>   
   <section title="Additional Call Data Blocks Registry">
      <t>This document creates a new subregistry called ’Additional Call Data Blocks’.  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
   operates under "Expert Review" and "Specification Required" rules.</t>
<t>The content of this registry includes:</t>

<t>Name: Element Name of enclosing block.</t>

<t>Reference: The document that describes the block</t>

<t>The values defined are:</t>
<figure><artwork>
   +---------------------+-----------+
   | Name                | Reference |
   +---------------------+-----------+
   | addDataProviderInfo | RFCXXXX   |
   | addCallSvcInfo      | RFCXXXX   |
   | addCallSvcInfo      | RFCXXXX   |
   | addCallSub          | RFCXXXX   |
   | addCallComment      | RFCXXXX   |
   +---------------------+-----------+
RFC Editor Note:
   replace XXXX in the table above with this documents RFC number
</artwork></figure>   
    </section>   
   <section title="Additional Call Data Service Delivered Registry">
      <t>This document creates a new registry called ’Additional Call Data Service Delivered’.  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
   operates under "Expert Review" rules.</t>
<t>The content of this registry includes:</t>

<t>Name: enumeration token of the service.</t>

<t>Description:  Short description identifying the service.</t>

<t>The values defined are:</t>
<figure><artwork>
   +--------+----------------------------------------+
   | Name   | description                            |
   +--------+-------+--------------------------------+
   | Wrless | Wireless Telephone Service: Includes     |
   |        |   Satellite, CDMA, GSM, Wi-Fi, WiMAX,  | 
   |        |   LTE (Long Term Evolution)            |
   | Coin   | Fixed Public Pay/Coin telephones: Any  |
   |        |   coin or credit card operated device  |
   | 1way   | One way outbound service               |
   | Prison | Inmate call/service                    |
   | Temp   | Soft dialtone/quick service/warm       |
   |        |   disconnect/suspended                 |
   | MLTS   | Multi-line telephone system: Includes  |
   |        |   all PBX, Centrex, key systems,       |
   |        |   Shared Tenant Service                |
   | SenseU | Sensor, unattended: Includes devices   |
   |        |   that generate DATA ONLY. This is     |
   |        |   one-way information exchange and     |
   |        |   there will be no other form of       |
   |        |   communication                        |
   | SenseA | Sensor, attended: Includes devices     |
   |        |   that are supported by a monitoring   |
   |        |   service provider or automatically    |
   |        |   open a two-way communication path    |
   | POTS   | Wireline: Plain Old Telephone Service  |
   | VOIP   | VoIP Telephone Service: A type of      |
   |        |   service that offers communication    |
   |        |   over internet protocol, such as Fixed|
   |        |   Nomadic, Mobile, ...                 |
   +--------+-------+--------------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
   
    </section>
   <section title="Additional Call Data Device Classification Registry">
      <t>This document creates a new registry called ’Additional Call Data Device Classification’.  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
   operates under "Expert Review" rules.</t>
<t>The content of this registry includes:</t>

<t>Name: enumeration token of the device classification.</t>

<t>Description:  Short description identifying the device type.</t>

<t>The values defined are:</t>
<figure><artwork>
   +--------+----------------------------------------+
   | Name   | description                            |
   +--------+-------+--------------------------------+
   |Cordless| Cordless handset                       |
   | Fixed  | Fixed phone                            |
   | Mobile | Mobile handset                         |
   | ATA    | analog terminal adapter                |
   |Satphone| Satellite phone                        |
   | FSense | Stationary computing device (alarm     |
   |        |   system, data sensor)                 |
   | Guard  | Guardian devices                       |
   | Desktop| Desktop PC                             |
   | Laptop | Laptop computing device                |
   | Tablet | Tablet computing device                |
   | Alarm  | Alarm system                           |
   | MSense | Mobile Data sensor                     |
   | Beacon | Personal beacons (spot)                |
   | Auto   | Auto telematics                        |
   | Truck  | Truck telematics                       |
   | Farm   | Farm equipment telematics              |
   | Marine | Marine telematics                      |
   | PDA    | Personal digital assistant             |
   | PND    | Personal navigation device)            |
   | SmrtPhn| Smart phone                            |
   | Itab   | Internet tablet                        |
   | Game   | Gaming console                         |
   | Video  | Video phone                            |
   | Text   | Other text device                      |
   | NA     | Not Available                          |
   +--------+----------------------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
   
    </section>

   <section title="Additional Call Data Device ID Type Registry">
      <t>This document creates a new registry called ’Additional Call Data Device ID Type’.  As defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>, this registry
   operates under "Expert Review" rules.</t>
<t>The content of this registry includes:</t>

<t>Name: enumeration token of the device id type.</t>

<t>Description:  Short description identifying the type of device id.</t>

<t>The values defined are:</t>
<figure><artwork>
   +--------+----------------------------------------+
   | Name   | description                            |
   +--------+-------+--------------------------------+
   | MEID   | Mobile Equipment Identifier  (CDMA)    |
   | ESN    | Electronic Serial Number(GSM)          |
   | MAC    | Media Access Control Address (IEEE)    |
   | WiMAX  | device certificate unique id           |
   | IMEI   | International Mobile Equipment ID (GSM)|
   | UDI    | Unique Device Identifier (medical)     |
   | RFID   | Radio Frequency Identification         |
   | Sense  | Sensors (types to be identified )      |
   | SN     | Manufacturer Serial Number             |
   | Other  | Other                                  |
   +--------+----------------------------------------+
</artwork></figure>
   
    </section>

</section>

     
      <section title="'emergencyCallData' Purpose Parameter Value">
        <t> This document defines the 'emergencyCallData' value for the "purpose" parameter of the
          Call-Info header field. The Call-Info header and the corresponding registry for the 'purpose' parameter 
          was established with RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/>. </t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
   Header       Parameter   New
   Field        Name        Value               Reference
   ----------   ---------   -----------------   ---------
   Call-Info    purpose     emergencyCallData   [This RFC]
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>

      </section>

	  <section title="URN Sub-Namespace Registration for provided-by Registry Entry">
	  
	  <t>This section registers the namespace specified in ??? in the	
			provided-by registry established by RFC 4119.</t>
      </section>
				
	  <section title="MIME Registrations">
 
  <section title="MIME Content-type Registration for 'application/addDataProviderInfo+xml'">

   <t>This specification requests the registration of a new MIME type
   according to the procedures of RFC 4288 <xref target="RFC4288"/> and guidelines in RFC
   3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.</t>
   <t>
   <list style="empty"> 
   <t>MIME media type name:  application</t>

   <t>MIME subtype name:  addDataProviderInfo+xml</t>

   <t>Mandatory parameters:  none</t>

   <t>Optional parameters:  charset<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Indicates the character encoding of enclosed XML.
   </t>

   <t>Encoding considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Uses XML, which can employ 8-bit characters, depending on the
      character encoding used.  
      See Section 3.2 of RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.
   </t>
   
   <t>Security considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   
      This content type is designed to carry the data provider 
      information, which is a sub-category of additional 
      data about an emergency call. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Since this data contains personal information appropriate precautions 
      have to be taken to limit unauthorized access, inappropriate disclosure
      to third parties, and eavesdropping of this information.  Please refer 
      to <xref target="security"/> and <xref target="privacy"/> for more 
      information.</t>

   <t>Interoperability considerations:  None</t>

   <t>Published specification: [TBD: This specification]</t>

   <t>Applications which use this media type:

      Emergency Services
   </t>
   
   <t>Additional information:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Magic Number:  None<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      File Extension:  .xml<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Macintosh file type code:  'TEXT'<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   
   <t>Person and email address for further information:
      Hannes Tschofenig, Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net
   </t>
   
   <t>Intended usage:  LIMITED USE</t>

   <t>Author:

      This specification is a work item of the IETF ECRIT working
      group, with mailing list address &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;.
   </t>
   
   <t>Change controller:

      The IESG &lt;ietf@ietf.org&gt;
   </t>
   
  </list>
  </t>
</section> 


  <section title="MIME Content-type Registration for 'application/addCallSvcInfo+xml'">

   <t>This specification requests the registration of a new MIME type
   according to the procedures of RFC 4288 <xref target="RFC4288"/> and guidelines in RFC
   3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.</t>
   <t>
   <list style="empty"> 
   <t>MIME media type name:  application</t>

   <t>MIME subtype name:  addCallSvcInfo+xml</t>

   <t>Mandatory parameters:  none</t>

   <t>Optional parameters:  charset<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Indicates the character encoding of enclosed XML.
   </t>

   <t>Encoding considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Uses XML, which can employ 8-bit characters, depending on the
      character encoding used.  
      See Section 3.2 of RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.
   </t>
   
   <t>Security considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   
      This content type is designed to carry the service information, which is a sub-category of additional 
      data about an emergency call. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Since this data contains personal information appropriate precautions 
      have to be taken to limit unauthorized access, inappropriate disclosure
      to third parties, and eavesdropping of this information.  Please refer 
      to <xref target="security"/> and <xref target="privacy"/> for more 
      information.</t>

   <t>Interoperability considerations:  None</t>

   <t>Published specification:  [TBD: This specification]</t>

   <t>Applications which use this media type:

      Emergency Services
   </t>
   
   <t>Additional information:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Magic Number:  None<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      File Extension:  .xml<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Macintosh file type code:  'TEXT'<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   
   <t>Person and email address for further information:
      Hannes Tschofenig, Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net
   </t>
   
   <t>Intended usage:  LIMITED USE</t>

   <t>Author:

      This specification is a work item of the IETF ECRIT working
      group, with mailing list address &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;.
   </t>
   
   <t>Change controller:

      The IESG &lt;ietf@ietf.org&gt;
   </t>
   
  </list>
  </t>
</section> 


  <section title="MIME Content-type Registration for 'application/addDataDevInfo+xml'">

   <t>This specification requests the registration of a new MIME type
   according to the procedures of RFC 4288 <xref target="RFC4288"/> and guidelines in RFC
   3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.</t>
   <t>
   <list style="empty"> 
   <t>MIME media type name:  application</t>

   <t>MIME subtype name:  addDataDevInfo+xml</t>

   <t>Mandatory parameters:  none</t>

   <t>Optional parameters:  charset<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Indicates the character encoding of enclosed XML.
   </t>

   <t>Encoding considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Uses XML, which can employ 8-bit characters, depending on the
      character encoding used.  
      See Section 3.2 of RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.
   </t>
   
   <t>Security considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   
      This content type is designed to carry the device information 
      information, which is a sub-category of additional 
      data about an emergency call. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Since this data contains personal information appropriate precautions 
      have to be taken to limit unauthorized access, inappropriate disclosure
      to third parties, and eavesdropping of this information.  Please refer 
      to <xref target="security"/> and <xref target="privacy"/> for more 
      information.</t>

   <t>Interoperability considerations:  None</t>

   <t>Published specification: [TBD: This specification]</t>

   <t>Applications which use this media type:

      Emergency Services
   </t>
   
   <t>Additional information:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Magic Number:  None<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      File Extension:  .xml<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Macintosh file type code:  'TEXT'<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   
   <t>Person and email address for further information:
      Hannes Tschofenig, Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net
   </t>
   
   <t>Intended usage:  LIMITED USE</t>

   <t>Author:

      This specification is a work item of the IETF ECRIT working
      group, with mailing list address &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;.
   </t>
   
   <t>Change controller:

      The IESG &lt;ietf@ietf.org&gt;
   </t>
   
  </list>
  </t>
</section> 


  <section title="MIME Content-type Registration for 'application/addCallSub+xml'">

   <t>This specification requests the registration of a new MIME type
   according to the procedures of RFC 4288 <xref target="RFC4288"/> and guidelines in RFC
   3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.</t>
   <t>
   <list style="empty"> 
   <t>MIME media type name:  application</t>

   <t>MIME subtype name:  addCallSub+xml</t>

   <t>Mandatory parameters:  none</t>

   <t>Optional parameters:  charset<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Indicates the character encoding of enclosed XML.
   </t>

   <t>Encoding considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Uses XML, which can employ 8-bit characters, depending on the
      character encoding used.  
      See Section 3.2 of RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.
   </t>
   
   <t>Security considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   
      This content type is designed to carry owner/subscriber information, 
      which is a sub-category of additional 
      data about an emergency call. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Since this data contains personal information appropriate precautions 
      have to be taken to limit unauthorized access, inappropriate disclosure
      to third parties, and eavesdropping of this information.  Please refer 
      to <xref target="security"/> and <xref target="privacy"/> for more 
      information.</t>

   <t>Interoperability considerations:  None</t>

   <t>Published specification: [TBD: This specification]</t>

   <t>Applications which use this media type:

      Emergency Services
   </t>
   
   <t>Additional information:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Magic Number:  None<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      File Extension:  .xml<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Macintosh file type code:  'TEXT'<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   
   <t>Person and email address for further information:
      Hannes Tschofenig, Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net
   </t>
   
   <t>Intended usage:  LIMITED USE</t>

   <t>Author:

      This specification is a work item of the IETF ECRIT working
      group, with mailing list address &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;.
   </t>
   
   <t>Change controller:

      The IESG &lt;ietf@ietf.org&gt;
   </t>
   
  </list>
  </t>
</section> 

  <section title="MIME Content-type Registration for 'application/addCallComment+xml'">

   <t>This specification requests the registration of a new MIME type
   according to the procedures of RFC 4288 <xref target="RFC4288"/> and guidelines in RFC
   3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.</t>
   <t>
   <list style="empty"> 
   <t>MIME media type name:  application</t>

   <t>MIME subtype name:  addCallComment+xml</t>

   <t>Mandatory parameters:  none</t>

   <t>Optional parameters:  charset<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Indicates the character encoding of enclosed XML.
   </t>

   <t>Encoding considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Uses XML, which can employ 8-bit characters, depending on the
      character encoding used.  
      See Section 3.2 of RFC 3023 <xref target="RFC3023"/>.
   </t>
   
   <t>Security considerations:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   
      This content type is designed to carry a comment, 
      which is a sub-category of additional 
      data about an emergency call. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
      This data may contain personal information. Appropriate precautions 
      may have to be taken to limit unauthorized access, inappropriate disclosure
      to third parties, and eavesdropping of this information.  Please refer 
      to <xref target="security"/> and <xref target="privacy"/> for more 
      information.</t>

   <t>Interoperability considerations:  None</t>

   <t>Published specification: [TBD: This specification]</t>

   <t>Applications which use this media type:

      Emergency Services
   </t>
   
   <t>Additional information:<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Magic Number:  None<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      File Extension:  .xml<vspace blankLines="1"/>

      Macintosh file type code:  'TEXT'<vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   
   <t>Person and email address for further information:
      Hannes Tschofenig, Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net
   </t>
   
   <t>Intended usage:  LIMITED USE</t>

   <t>Author:

      This specification is a work item of the IETF ECRIT working
      group, with mailing list address &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;.
   </t>
   
   <t>Change controller:

      The IESG &lt;ietf@ietf.org&gt;
   </t>
   
  </list>
  </t>
</section> 

      </section>
      
      <section title="URN Sub-Namespace Registration"> 

                  <section title="Registration for urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataProviderInfo">
        <t> This section registers a new XML namespace, as per the guidelines in RFC 3688 <xref
            target="RFC3688"/>. </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataProviderInfo</t>
            <t hangText="Registrant Contact:"> IETF, ECRIT working group,
              &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;, as delegated by the IESG
              &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;. </t>
            <t hangText="XML:">
              <figure>
                <artwork>
                  <![CDATA[
   BEGIN
   <?xml version="1.0"?>
   <!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML Basic 1.0//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-basic/xhtml-basic10.dtd">
   <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <head>
     <meta http-equiv="content-type"
           content="text/html;charset=iso-8859-1"/>
     <title>Namespace for Additional Emergency Call Data: 
            Data Provider Information</title>
   </head>
   <body>
     <h1>Namespace for Additional Data related to an Emergency Call</h1>
     <h2>Data Provider Information</h2>
   <p>See [TBD: This document].</p>
   </body>
   </html>
   END
   ]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      
                  <section title="Registration for urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSvcInfo">
        <t> This section registers a new XML namespace, as per the guidelines in RFC 3688 <xref
            target="RFC3688"/>. </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSvcInfo</t>
            <t hangText="Registrant Contact:"> IETF, ECRIT working group,
              &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;, as delegated by the IESG
              &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;. </t>
            <t hangText="XML:">
              <figure>
                <artwork>
                  <![CDATA[
   BEGIN
   <?xml version="1.0"?>
   <!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML Basic 1.0//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-basic/xhtml-basic10.dtd">
   <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <head>
     <meta http-equiv="content-type"
           content="text/html;charset=iso-8859-1"/>
     <title>Namespace for Additional Emergency Call Data: 
            Service Information</title>
   </head>
   <body>
     <h1>Namespace for Additional Data related to an Emergency Call</h1>
     <h2>Service Information</h2>
   <p>See [TBD: This document].</p>
   </body>
   </html>
   END
   ]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>


            <section title="Registration for urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataDevInfo">
        <t> This section registers a new XML namespace, as per the guidelines in RFC 3688 <xref
            target="RFC3688"/>. </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addDataDevInfo</t>
            <t hangText="Registrant Contact:"> IETF, ECRIT working group,
              &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;, as delegated by the IESG
              &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;. </t>
            <t hangText="XML:">
              <figure>
                <artwork>
                  <![CDATA[
   BEGIN
   <?xml version="1.0"?>
   <!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML Basic 1.0//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-basic/xhtml-basic10.dtd">
   <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <head>
     <meta http-equiv="content-type"
           content="text/html;charset=iso-8859-1"/>
     <title>Namespace for Additional Emergency Call Data: 
            Device Information</title>
   </head>
   <body>
     <h1>Namespace for Additional Data related to an Emergency Call</h1>
     <h2>Device Information</h2>
   <p>See [TBD: This document].</p>
   </body>
   </html>
   END
   ]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      
      <section title="Registration for urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSub">
        <t> This section registers a new XML namespace, as per the guidelines in RFC 3688 <xref
            target="RFC3688"/>. </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallSub</t>
            <t hangText="Registrant Contact:"> IETF, ECRIT working group,
              &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;, as delegated by the IESG
              &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;. </t>
            <t hangText="XML:">
              <figure>
                <artwork>
                  <![CDATA[
   BEGIN
   <?xml version="1.0"?>
   <!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML Basic 1.0//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-basic/xhtml-basic10.dtd">
   <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <head>
     <meta http-equiv="content-type"
           content="text/html;charset=iso-8859-1"/>
     <title>Namespace for Additional Emergency Call Data: 
            Owner/Subscriber Information</title>
   </head>
   <body>
     <h1>Namespace for Additional Data related to an Emergency Call</h1>
     <h2> Owner/Subscriber Information</h2>
   <p>See [TBD: This document].</p>
   </body>
   </html>
   END
   ]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Registration for urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallComment">
        <t> This section registers a new XML namespace, as per the guidelines in RFC 3688 <xref
            target="RFC3688"/>. </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="URI:">urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:addCallComment</t>
            <t hangText="Registrant Contact:"> IETF, ECRIT working group,
              &lt;ecrit@ietf.org&gt;, as delegated by the IESG
              &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;. </t>
            <t hangText="XML:">
              <figure>
                <artwork>
                  <![CDATA[
   BEGIN
   <?xml version="1.0"?>
   <!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML Basic 1.0//EN"
     "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-basic/xhtml-basic10.dtd">
   <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <head>
     <meta http-equiv="content-type"
           content="text/html;charset=iso-8859-1"/>
     <title>Namespace for Additional Emergency Call Data:Comment</title>
   </head>
   <body>
     <h1>Namespace for Additional Data related to an Emergency Call</h1>
     <h2> Comment</h2>
   <p>See [TBD: This document].</p>
   </body>
   </html>
   END
   ]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

  </section> 
  
      <section title="Schema Registrations">
        <t>This specification registers five schemas, as per the guidelines in RFC 3688 <xref target="RFC3688"/>.</t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:additional-data:addDataProviderInfo</t>
            <t>Registrant Contact: IETF, ECRIT Working Group (ecrit@ietf.org), as delegated by the
              IESG (iesg@ietf.org).</t>
            <t>XML: The XML schema can be found in <xref target="addDataProviderInfo"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:additional-data:addCallSvcInfo</t>
            <t>Registrant Contact: IETF, ECRIT Working Group (ectit@ietf.org), as delegated by the
              IESG (iesg@ietf.org).</t>
            <t>XML: The XML schema can be found in <xref target="addCallSvcInfo"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:additional-data:addDataDevInfo</t>
            <t>Registrant Contact: IETF, ECRIT Working Group (ecrit@ietf.org), as delegated by the
              IESG (iesg@ietf.org).</t>
            <t>XML: The XML schema can be found in <xref target="addDataDevInfo"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:additional-data:addCallSub</t>
            <t>Registrant Contact: IETF, ECRIT Working Group (ecrit@ietf.org), as delegated by the
              IESG (iesg@ietf.org).</t>
            <t>XML: The XML schema can be found in <xref target="addCallSub"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:schema:additional-data:addCallComment</t>
            <t>Registrant Contact: IETF, ECRIT Working Group (ecrit@ietf.org), as delegated by the
              IESG (iesg@ietf.org).</t>
            <t>XML: The XML schema can be found in <xref target="addCallComment"/>.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="VCard Parameter Value Registration">
      <t>This document registers a new value in the vCARD Parameter Values registry as defined by <xref target="RFC6350"/> with the following template:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
         <t hangText="Value:">main</t>
         <t hangText="Purpose:">The main telephone number, typically of an enterprise, as opposed to a direct dial number of an individual employee</t>
         <t hangText="Conformance:">This value can be used with the "TYPE" parameter
      applied on the "TEL" property.</t>
         <t hangText="Example(s):">TEL;VALUE=uri;TYPE=&quot;main,voice&quot;;PREF=1:tel:+1-418-656-9000</t>

      </list>
     </t>
    </section>
  </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>This work was originally started in NENA and has benefitted from a large number of participants in NENA standardization efforts, originally in the Long Term Definition Working Group, the Data Technical Committee and most recently the Additional Data working group.  The authors are grateful for the initial work and extended comments provided by the many NENA participants.</t>
    </section>


    <!-- ******************************************************************************* -->

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3688" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2392"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3023"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4288"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6350"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6351"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informational References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5222"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6443"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.iab-privacy-considerations"?>      
    </references>
   </back>
</rfc>
