<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--
vim:et:ts=2:sw=2:spell:spelllang=en:tw=80
-->
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-avtcore-rtp-circuit-breakers SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-avtcore-rtp-circuit-breakers.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.irtf-iccrg-multfrc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-iccrg-multfrc.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.schulzrinne-lmap-requirements SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.schulzrinne-lmap-requirements.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.nichols-tsvwg-codel SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nichols-tsvwg-codel.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5405 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5405.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2914 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2914.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4585 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4585.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5348 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5348.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6817 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6817.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2309 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2309.xml">
	]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="mp"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-tschofenig-cc-workshop-report-01.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->
  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->
    <title abbrev="Congestion Control Workshop Report">Report from the IAB/IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication</title>

    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H.T."
            surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
        <city>Espoo</city>
        <region></region>
        <code>02600</code>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
      <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
      <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
	
	 <author fullname="Lars Eggert" initials="L.E."
            surname="Eggert">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Sonnenallee 1</street>
        <city>Kirchheim</city>
        <region></region>
        <code>85551</code>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+49 151 12055791</phone>
      <email>lars@netapp.com</email>
      <uri>http://eggert.org/</uri>
      <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
	 <author fullname="Zaheduzzaman Sarker" initials="Z.S."
            surname="Sarker">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city>Lulea</city>
        <region></region>
        <code>SE-971 28</code>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+46 10 717 37 43</phone>
      <email>zaheduzzaman.sarker@ericsson.com</email>
      <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
	
	<!-- 
		 <author fullname="Bill Ver Steeg" initials="B.V.S."
            surname="Ver Steeg">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city></city>
        <region></region>
        <code></code>
        <country></country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>versteb@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
--> 
	
    <date year="2013" />
<!--    <area>
    Security
    </area>-->
    <keyword>Congestion Control</keyword> <keyword>RTCWeb</keyword> <keyword>Workshop</keyword> <keyword>Real-Time Communication</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a summary of the IAB/IRTF Workshop on 'Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication', which took place in Vancouver, Canada, on July 28, 2012. The main goal of the workshop was to foster a discussion on congestion control mechanisms for interactive real-time communication. This report summarizes the discussions and lists the conclusions and recommendations to the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) community. The views and positions in this report are those of the workshop participants and do not necessarily reflect the views and positions of the authors, the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) or the Internet Research Task Force (IRTF).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Any application that sends significant amounts of data over the Internet is expected to implement reasonable congestion control behavior. Although the specific mechanisms depend on the application or protocol, the motivations for congestion control are well understood and documented in RFC 2914 <xref target="RFC2914"/> and RFC 5405  <xref target="RFC5405"/>. The goals are:
<list style="numbers">
<t>Preventing congestion collapse.</t>
<t>Allowing multiple flows to share the network fairly.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
The Internet has been used for interactive real-time communication for decades, most of which is being transmitted using RTP over UDP, often over provisioned capacity and/or using only rudimentary congestion control mechanisms.</t>

<t>The development and upcoming widespread deployment of web-based real-time media communication - where RTP is used to and from web browsers to transmit audio, video and data - will likely result in substantial new Internet traffic. Due to the projected volume of this traffic, as well as the fact that it is more likely to use unprovisioned capacity, it is essential that it is transmitted with robust and effective congestion control mechanisms.</t>

<t>Designing congestion control mechanisms that perform well under a wide variety of traffic mixes and over network paths with widely varying characteristics is not easy. Prevention of congestion collapse can be achieved through "circuit breaker" mechanisms, but for media flows that are supposed to coexist with a user's other ongoing communication sessions, a congestion control mechanism that shares capacity fairly in the presence of a mix of TCP, UDP and other protocol flows is needed.</t>

<t>Many additional complications arise. Here are some examples:
<list style="numbers">
<t>Real-time interactive media sessions require low latencies, whereas streaming media can use large play-out buffers.</t>
<t>RTCP feedback about an RTP session typically arrives much less frequently than, for example, TCP ACKs for a given TCP connection. The RTP/RTCP control loop can lead to a longer reaction time.</t>
<t>Media codecs can usually only adjust their output rates in a much more coarse-grained fashion than, for example, TCP, and user experience suffers if encoding rates are switched too frequently. Codecs typically have a minimum sending rate as well.</t>
<t>Some bits of an encoded media stream are more important than others. For example, losing or dropping an I-frame of a video stream is more problematic than dropping a P-frame.</t>
<t>Ramping up the transmission rate can be problematic. Simply increasing the output rate of the codec without knowledge whether the network path can sustain transmission at the increased rate runs the danger of incurring a significant amount of packet loss that can cause playback artifacts.</t>
<t>A congestion control scheme for interactive media needs to handle bundles of interrelated flows (audio, video, data), in a way that accommodates the preferences of the application in the event of congestion.</t>
<t>The desire to provide a congestion control mechanism that can be efficiently implemented inside an application (e.g., a web server and a browser) imposes additional restrictions.</t>
<t>There are explicit congestion signals (such as ECN), and there are indirect indications of congestion (such as packet delay and loss). However, congestion is not the only source of these indirect signals. Care must be taken to account for each of these signals, particularly if various applications react on the same signals.</t>
<t>Network elements and end device operating systems often create buffers to better support TCP-based applications. These buffers introduce additional communication delay, which harms the small delay budget available for real-time applications.</t>
</list> 
</t>

      <t>Note that this document is a report on the proceedings of the workshop.
        The views and positions documented in this report are those of the workshop
        participants and do not necessarily reflect the views of the
        authors.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="History and Current Status">
<t>The currently deployed RTP-based RTC systems use congestion control schemes that are ad hoc at best. As the Internet moves towards an RTCWeb standard for interoperable audio/video conferencing, it needs a standardized and most importantly effective mechanism for congestion control.</t>

<t>The most immediate need is for a control mechanism that balances a real-time flow
fairly among other competing traffic. For instance, under congested conditions, it
would be inappropriate to use far more bandwidth than flows from other applications
are using, particularly lasting gross over-utilization of
the network.  Simple "circuit breaker" -style control mechanisms can prevent congestion collapse by
disabling a circuit that far exceeds a fair share and making the circuit remain disabled for some time.
But does not in any way enable concurrent flows to share available network capacity sensibly.</t>

<!-- 
<t>The most immediate need is for a circuit breaker mechanism that stops a flow when serious anomalies are detected, i.e., when it is using an order of magnitude more bandwidth than a TCP flow would use over the given path <xref target="I-D.ietf-avtcore-rtp-circuit-breakers"/>. This prevents the RTCWeb flows from causing long lasting gross over-utilization of the network. Circuit breakers can prevent congestion collapse if used correctly, i.e., if the circuit remains disabled for some time after the breaker triggers, but does not in any way enable concurrent flows to share available network capacity sensibly.</t>
--> 

<t>Therefore, in addition to circuit breakers, more complete methods for media congestion control are needed. The focus of the workshop was on discussing ideas for these more complete congestion control methods. Note that the primary focus of the workshop is RTCWeb-style audio/video flows. The assumed underlying flows (in most attendees minds) were digital audio/video data encapsulated in RTP over UDP over IP. Most of the concepts presented at the workshop could be used with different media types over different transports, but this was the generally assumed baseline for discussions.</t>
    </section>
	
	<section title="Workshop Structure">
	<t>The IETF has a long history in the work on congestion control mechanisms but with the ongoing 
	standardization work on real-time interactive communication on the Web new challenges emerged and 
	existing work got revisited. The participants contributed 32 papers as input to the one-day workshop.  
	To get the discussion focused the workshop was structured into diverse sessions starting with a keynote speech of Mark Handley describing the history of the work on congestion control for real-time media followed with his views of the problems.</t>
	
	<t>A summary of the discussions and the identified issues are captured in the subsections below.</t>
   
    <section title="History and Challenges"> 

    <t>The primary goal of congestion control is to avoid congestion collapse - to make the network work. The second important goal is to guarantee some sort of fairness so that all users get some service. RFC 2914 <xref target="RFC2914"/> discusses these two aspects in detail and references earlier work, such as <xref target="FF99"/> regarding historic incidents, such as congestion collapse due to unnecessarily-retransmitted, undelivered, and fragmented packets.</t>
				
	<t>Mark argues that since 1988, the Internet has remained functional despite exponential growth, routers that are sometimes buggy or misconfigured, rapidly changing applications and usage patterns, and flash crowds. This is largely because most applications use TCP, and TCP implements end-to-end congestion control.</t>
	
	<t>TCP's congestion control adapts the window to fit the capacity available in the network and accomplishes approximate fairness between two competing flows over a period of time. Mark indicates that the provided level of fairness is not necessarily what we want: The 1/round-trip-time relationship in TCP is not wonderful since it means that network operators can packet loss by adding big buffers (which leads to buffer bloat problems). The 1/sqrt(packet drop rate) relationship is also not necessarily desireable since TCP did not work particularly well for high-speed flows (which had been subject for a lot of additional TCP research work).</t>

	<t>TCP controls the congestion window in bytes. For bulk transfer, usually this results in controlling the number of 1500 byte packets per second sent. Real-time media is, however, different since it has it's own time constraints. For audio we want to send, for example, one packet per 20ms and for video 30 frames per second. We therefore want to avoid additional delay.</t>

    <t>As an example, videos have a natural frame rate around 25 to 30 frames per second. To relieve congestion one has to reduce the number of packets per seconds transmission rate that than transmitting smaller packets since at higher bitrates on WiFi the time it takes to send a packet is almost negligible compared to the time that is spent with MAC layer operations. Reducing the packet size makes little difference to the available capacity. For a serial line it does not matter how long the packets are.</t>

	<t>Mark believes that the primary goals of congestion control (from a network point of view) therefore are:
	<list style="numbers"> 
	<t>Avoid congestion collapse</t>
    <t>Avoid starvation
	<list style="symbols"> 
	  <t>Of TCP flows</t>
      <t>Of real-time flows</t>
      <t>TCP causing starvation of real-time flows when they share the same FIFO queue</t>
	</list> 
	</t>
	</list> 
	</t>
	
    <t>The applications have different requirements: 
	<list style="numbers"> 
	<t>Robust behavior. One wants to have good quality when network is working well and it still works when network is working poorly.</t>
	<t>Predictable behavior because it matters from a userability behavior. Variable quality is bad for users.</t>
	<t>Low latency. With large buffers along the end-to-end path the latency will increase when interactive real-time flows compete with TCP flows since TCP will fill up the buffers and the increased buffering leads to additional delays for the delivery of the interactive real-time media. </t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>Attempts for providing congestion control for interactive real-time media were already done much earlier in the IETF, for example, with the work on TCP-Friendly Rate Control (TFRC) <xref target="RFC5348"/>. It illustrates the challenges quite well. TFRC tries to accomplish the same throughput as TCP, but with smoother transmission rate. It measures the loss and the round-trip trip but follows a similar model as TCP to determine the sending rate.</t> 
	
	<t>In a link with low statistical multiplexing TCP can bad to bad oscillations. The sending rate hits the maximum rate of a bottleneck link, a lot of loss occurs, and then the sending rate peaks again. For very small buffers the result is acceptable but bigger buffers lead to oscillations. The result is bad for both network and applications. To deal with large buffers on these links a short-term rate adaptation based on RTT is utilized in TRFC but this requires good short-term RTT measurements.</t>

    <t>TRFC works pretty well but unfortunately only in theory. TFRC assumes network is in charge of codec and that codec can produce data at demanded rate. Video is inheritent variable based on the content and it is hard to produce data at exactly a demanded rate without excessive buffering or ugly quality changes.</t>
	
	<t>What if we put the codec in charge instead of the network? The network tells the codec the mean rate but it does not worry about what happens in short time scales and the codec matches the mean rate does not worry whether it is over or under the rate for a relatively short time scale. This again leads to the low statistical multiplexing problem and this leads to oscillations.</t>
	
	<t>The congestion control mechanism we know of work well if they can respond fast to changes and if they do not  bump into the low statistical multiplexing problem.</t>
	
	<t>We only know how to do congestion control well if the application is under the control of the congestion control algorithm but we do not know how to do the video streaming / video encoding part well if the codec is in charge. Trying to match the two together is where the problems are. We would like to have the codec and the network to be in charge. They cannot be both in charge at the same time.</t>
	
	<t>To avoid the low statistical multiplexing problem techniques for inferring linkspeed are needed and the work from Van Jacobson's pathchar (and successors) serve as valuable input. The idea is to send short packet trains, to measure timing accurately, and to infer the linkspeed from the relative delay. If you know the linkspeed, you can avoid exceeding it. Congestion control can give you an approximate rate, but you must not exceed linkspeed. This is a hybrid between codec being in charge (most of the time), and network being in charge. These work well for some links and not others where the wireless link speed can change in less than a single RTT because of fading, bitrate adaption, etc.</t>

	<t>Regarding RTP and RTCP Mark is not sure whether they are good for congestion control. RTCP gives feedback, but it cannot send it often enough to avoid bumping into linkspeed. Circuit breakers on the other hand do not help to give good performance on an uncongested path. With circuit breakers the sender measures the loss rate and RTT, and runs with a loose "cap".</t> 

    <t>As a conclusion, Mark Handely claims that we know how to do good congestion control, but only if congestion control is in charge, and that's not acceptable for real-time applications. We only know how to do good congestion control if we change packet/sec rate and not packet size.</t>

	</section> 
	
	<section title="Simulations and Measurements"> 
	<t>This second part of the workshop was focused on the presentation and the discussion of data gathered from simulations and real-world measurements.</t>
	
	<t>Keith Winstein started the discussion with his presentation of measurements performed in cellular operator networks in the US <xref target="Keith"/>. The measurements indicate that the analysed cellular networks showed varying RTT with transient latency spikes to hundreds of ms, link speed that varies by a factor of 10 in a short time scale, and buffers that do not drop packets until they contain 5 - 10 seconds of data at bottleneck link speed.</t>
	
	<t>Zaheduzzaman Sarker <xref target="Zahed"/> presented results from real-time voice communication in an LTE simulator utilizing ECN-based packet marking and adaptation using implicit methods like packet loss and delay. ECN marking provides ways for the network to explicitly signal congestion but the audience raised concerns regarding the deployment status of ECN.</t>
	
	<t>Mo Zahaty <xref target="Mo"/> discussed TFRC <xref target="RFC5348"/> and TFRC with weighted fairness (MulTFRC) <xref target="I-D.irtf-iccrg-multfrc"/>, which tunes TFRC to consider multiple flows, and showed the impact of RTT and loss rates on the type of video quality that can be achieved under those conditions. TFRC requires frequent feedback, which RTCP does not provide even when considering RFC 4585 <xref target="RFC4585"/>. Mo argued that application-specified weighted fairness is important but while MulTFRC provides better performance than TFRC it is not clear whether the added complexity over NxTFRC is indeed worth the effort.</t>
	
	<t>Markku Kojo presented the analysis of how audio is affected by concurrent TCP flows. In the experiments shown in Figure 2 of <xref target="Markku"/> a real-time interactive audio stream had to compete against one concurrent TCP flow, as well as against six TCP fllows. With one concurrent TCP flow voice is impacted on startup and six TCP flows destroy quality of call. Two types of losses were analysed, namely losses that result from a packet being dropped in the network (e.g., due to congestion or link errors) and losses that result from the delayed arrival of the packet (due to buffering) when the audio packet misses the deadline for the codec to decode and play the transmitted content. Consequently, even a moderate number of TCP flows typically used by browsers to retrieve content on Web pages in parallel causes irreparable harm for audio transfers. The size of the initial window also impacts interactive real-time communication since a larger TCP initial window size (e.g., IW(10) with ten segments instead of IW(3)) leads to a bigger burst of packets because of the initial window transmission.</t>
	
	<t>Cullen Jennings <xref target="Cullen"/> presented measurement results showing interactions between RTP and TCP flows for several widely deployed video communication products, i.e., Apple Facetime, Google Hangout, Cisco Movi, and Microsoft Skype. While all tested products implemented some form of congestion control protocol none of the applications did additive increase and multiplicative decrease. In general, it was observable that video adapts slower to changes of the available bandwidth to improve the user's experience.</t>
	
	 <t>Stefan Holmer <xref target="Stefan"/> investigated the difference between loss-based, receiver-side delay-based and sender-side delay-based congestion control. 
	 The suitability of loss-based congestion control schemes for interactive real-time communication systems heavily depends on buffer sizes and the deployment of active queue management mechanisms. If most routers are using tail-drop queueing, then loss-based congestion control cannot fulfill the requirements of interactive real-time applications since those flows will effectively increase the bitrate until a loss event is identified, which only happens when the bottleneck queue is full.</t>
	</section> 
	
	
	<!--
	
	Active queue management
(AQM) and its most prominent representative Random Early
Detection (RED) [FJ93] is often proposed as a solution to the
bufferbloat but that is challenging to realize in practice. The
access network devices that are typically bottlenecks lack
support for AQM/RED, and even if available, RED does not
work with the default settings as it is “too gentle to handle
fast changes due to TCP slow start when the aggregate traffic
is limited” [JDNK12]. As tuning of the RED parameters
requires modifications on the intermediate network nodes, it
is not deployable in the short run on large scale even when
RED itself is supported by the devices.

   -->

   <section title="Constraints">
   
   <t>This part of the workshop tried to identify constraints that impact the solution space. The discussions in this session started with a presentation by Jim Gettys about problems related to Bufferbloat <xref target="Jim"/><xref target="GN2012"/>. Bufferbloat is "a phenomenon in a packet-switched computer network whereby excess buffering of packets inside the network causes high latency and jitter, as well as reducing the overall network throughput." <xref target="Bufferbloat"/>. While a certain amount of buffering is helpful to improve the efficiency not dropping packets in the event of congestion leads to increasing delays for interactive real-time communication.</t>

<t>Packets may get buffered at various places along the end-to-end path including in the operating system/device drivers, customer premise equipment (such as cable modem and DSL routers), base stations, and routers. While the understanding of too large buffers has improved over the last few years the participants were still concerned that many equipment manufactures and network operators do not yet acknowledge the existence of the problem. This lack of understanding is existing network performance measurements that are focused on throughput and do not take latency into account. Only recently the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) has added latency tests to their test suites [REF missing].</t>

<t>Active queue management (AQM) aims to prevent queues from growing too large. This is accomplished by monitoring queue length and by informing the sender to slow their transmission rate by dropping or marking packets. Random Early Detection (RED) <xref target="RFC2309"/> is one such AQM algorithm but it has not been widely deployed in routers largely because of challenges to configure it correctly <xref target="Feng"/>. Accoring to <xref target="JDNK12"/> , RED does not work with the default settings as it is "too gentle to handle fast changes due to TCP slow start when the aggregate traffic is limited". There may also be a lack of incentives to deploy AQM algorithms. Participants speculated about the time it takes to update network equipment with different noted the different expected update cycles of these devices. Measurement tools that allow an end user to determine the performance of their network is seen as a promising approach. The  how bad your network sucks and complain to your ISP. This will create market force. While the intent of the IETF IP Performance Metrics (ippm) working group <xref target="ippm"/> was to develop such metrics to qualify networks it may have started to early. A recent effort that has gotten a lot of attention of attention is <xref target="I-D.schulzrinne-lmap-requirements"/>.</t>

<t>In face of bufferbloat the question was raised whether the development of a congestion control algorithm for interactive real-time applications provides any benefits. What can be done that will help now or whether network updates are needed to fix excessive queuing first? It was noted that current interactive voice usage over the Internet works most of the time satisfactory. To explain this situation various suggestions were provided, such as the usage of LEDBAT <xref target="RFC6817"/> for the download of software updates, the small percentage of voice traffic of the overall Internet traffic, and human protocols to avoid having other family members interfere during the time of conference call.</t>
 
<t>Matt Mathis argued that the traffic of throughput-maximizing and delay-minimizing applications need to be in separate queues, i.e. that segregated queuing is applied. Others agreed with him.  Quality of Service signaling is a way to deploy segregated queuing but there are several simpler alternatives, such as Stochastic Fair Queuing and the Controlled Delay (CoDel) <xref target="I-D.nichols-tsvwg-codel"/>.</t>

<t>Cullen Jennings raised a concern that not providing a solid congestion control mechanism for interactive video, as it was done with interactive voice, could have substantial impact due to the potential uptake in deployment triggered by the work on RTCWeb. He phrased it as "I'm worried about the approach that says 'Let us do the minimal' and that is what we did with voice -- nothing. If we do the same with video, we're going to be in trouble. In the class of space where voice is currently working, that's where I'm worried about video failing."</t>
 
<t>Bill Ver Steeg suggested to consider three different deployment environments, namely
<list style="numbers">
<t>Flows competing with flows from the host ("self-inflicted queuing delay")</t>
<t>Flows competing with flows in the same sub-network (e.g. home network)</t>
<t>Flows competing with flows from other networks (e.g., traffic from different households that utilize the same DSL provider)</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>The narrowest problem domain that makes sense is to avoid self-inflicted queuing delay. This requires an information exchange inside a browser (or even beyond, as Michael Welzl suggested in <xref target="Michael"/>) to control and synchronize the exchange of audio, video, and data. John Leslie <xref target="John"/> also noted: "We're acting as if we believe congestion will magically be solved by a new transport algorithm. It won't." Instead, an interaction between the network layer, transport layer, and the application layer is needed whereby the application layer is the only practical place to balance what piece(s) to constrain to lower bandwidths. All flows relating to a user session should have a common congestion controller. For many applications, audio is much more critical than video. In those cases the video may back off, but the audio transmission remains unchanged.</t>



   </section> 
   
	</section> 
	
	<section title="Recommendations">
	<t>The participants suggested to explore two complementary solution tracks, as described in the two sub-sections below.</t>
	
	<section title="Changes to Network Infrastructure"> 

	<t>Like for all other traffic on the network, better data plane infrastructure improves the perceived quality of the best-effort service the Internet provides for RTCWeb flows. The IETF has already deeloped several technologies that would be of immediate usefulness, if they were deployed. The workshop participants expressed the hope that due to the volume and importance of RTCWeb traffic, some of these technologies might finally see widespread use.</t>
	
	<t>The first and by far most important improvement is traffic segregation, i.e., the ability to use different queues for different traffic types. Specifically jitter/delay sensitive and throughput maximizing protocols need to be in different queues. It is not possible for a single queue/AQM to be optimal for both.</t>

    <t>Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) allows routers along the end-to-end path to signal the onset of congestion and allows applications to respond early, avoiding losses and keep queue sizes short and therefore end-to-end delay low. ECN is implemented on some end system stacks and routers, but frequently not enabled.</t>

    <t>Different mechanisms have been developed to facilitate traffic segregation. Differentiated services are one possibility in this space if applications start to mark outgoing traffic appropriately and routers would segregate traffic accordingly, browsers could more directly control the relative importance of their various flows, and avoid self-competition. Compared to ECN, however, DiffServ is far more difficult to deploy meaningfully end-to-end, especially given that DSCPs have no defined end-to-end meaning and packets can be re-marked. Quality-of-service (QoS) signaling together with resource reservation facilities would enable a fine-grained and flexible way to indicate resource needs to network elements but it is also by far the most heavyweight proposal, and unlikely to be viable in the global Internet.</t>

    <t>However, any change to network infrastructure will take time particularly if the interest of the involved stakeholders is not aligned (as it is the case for network operators and over-the-top application providers). It is therefore imperative that RTCWeb congestion control provides adequate improvement in the absence of any of the aforementioned schemes.</t>
	</section> 
	
	
	<section title="Avoiding Self-Inflicted Queuing"> 
	<t>This approach tries to ensure that the network does not get congested by focusing on the traffic sent by a single host independent of any changes to networks, as mentioned in the earlier chapter. A single congestion manager within the end host or the browser could already help to coordinate various congestion control activities and to ensure a more coordinated approach between different applications, and different flows.</t>
	
	<t>The following activities were suggested during the workshop.</t>
	
	<t>	<list style="hanging">
	
	<t hangText="Reacting to all Congestion Signals:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
   To initiate the congestion control process it is important to detect
   congestion in the communication path.  Congestion in the
   comminication can be detected using either an explicit mechanism or
   an implicit mechanism.  The explicit mechanism involves direct
   congestion signaling usually from the congested network node, such as
   ECN. The ECN bits are set in the IP header by the network node
   before it starts to drop the packets and gives end hosts to react to
   the congestion.  In case of implicite mechanism, a particular
   characteristics or event in the network traffic can be inferred as a
   congestion signal.  For example, packet loss events or observed
   delay increase or jitter in the communication path can be taken as an
   implicit congestion signals. These measurements can also be made available 
   in a variety of different protocols, such as RTCP reports or transport 
   protocols. Communication endpoints can trigger congestion
   control on the event of these phenomena.  It is also possible to
   correlate these events to detect congestion in the communication
   path.  The implicit and explicit signals can come in any sequence and
   at any time during the ongoing media session. It is recommended to
   react to all the possible implicit congestion signals, ideally from all 
   applications at the end host,  to avoid self-
   inflicted queues.</t>
   
   <t hangText="Delay- and Loss-based Algorithms:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The main goal of designing a congestion control algorithm for
   real-time conversational media is to achieve low latency.  An
   explicit signaling based congestion control algorithm perhaps is the
   best fit for this purpose as the network nodes are directly involved
   in the process.  However, in case of absence of ECN support in the
   end-to-end communication path delay based algorithms are needed where
   the increased delay in the communication path is taken into account
   as implicit congestion signal. While it is difficult to design
   algorithms based on delay since many wireless networks show a wide delay
   variation even in a non-congested network. The workshop participants 
   recommended that more research should be done to better understand 
   non-congestion related delay variation in the network. General consensus 
   among the workshop participants was that when latency-based techniques 
   were competing against loss-based techniques, the loss-based techniques 
   got all the bandwidth.</t>
 
   <t hangText="Algorithm Evaluation:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The Internet consists of heterogeneous networks, which also includes 
   misconfigured, and unmanaged network nodes. Bandwidth and latency varies 
   a lot. Not only this, different services deployed using RTP/UDP have 
   different requirements in terms of media quality. A congestion control 
   algorithm needs to perform well not only in simulators but also in 
   today's Internet.  To achieve this it is recommended to test the 
   algorithms with real-world loss and delay figures to be sure that the 
   desired audio/video rates are attainable using the proposed algorithms 
   for the desired services.</t>
   
   <t hangText="Media Characteristics in Focus:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
   Interactive real-time voice and video data is inherently variable.  
   Usually the content of the media and service requirements dictate the 
   media coding.  The codec may be bursty and not all frames are equally 
   important (e.g., I-frames are more important than P-frames). Thus, 
   codecs have limited room for adaptation. Congestion control for audio 
   and video codecs is therefore different to congestion control applied 
   for bulk transfers. The latter are allows buffering of media irrespective 
   to their content and more fine-grained control for a congestion control 
   algorithm.  In the workshop these limitations were brought up and 
   the workshop participants recommended that a congestion controller needs
   to be aware of these constraints. However, further investigation is 
   needed to decide what information needs to be exchanged between a codec 
   and the congestion manager.</t>
  
  <t hangText="Startup Behaviour:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The startup media quality is very important for real-time interactive
   application and for user-perceived application performance. The startup
   behavior of these is also different to other traffic. By nature the 
   real-time interactive communication applications want to provide a 
   smooth user experience and maintain best media quality to ease the 
   interaction. While it may be desirable from a user experience point of 
   view to immediately start streaming video with high-definition quality 
   and audio of a wideband codec this will have impacts on the bandwidth of 
   the already ongoing flows. As such, it would be ideal to start slow enough 
   to avoid excessive congestion to other flows but fast enough to offer a 
   good user experience. The sweetspot, however, yet has to be found.</t>
 </list> 
 </t>
 
	<t>In addition, there were some discussions on how to make RTCWeb-style 
	flows fair to other RTCWeb-style flows, other TCP based flows, LEDBAT 
	flows, and other flows. This is a much more difficult problem than simply 
	making RTCWeb flows avoid congestion. Changing the way TCP is used in browsers 
	or other HTTP-based applications would already help, for example, by avoid 
    opening too many concurrent TCP connections, and improved interworking 
    with video streaming and file sharing software. The work on HTTP 2.0 
    with SPDY is already the step in the right direction since SPDY makes 
	makes use of a more aggressive form of multiplexing instead of opening 
	a larger number of TCP connections.</t>
    
	</section>
	
	</section> 
	
    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>We would like to thank the participants and the paper authors of the position
        papers for their input.</t>
		
      <t>Additionally, we would like to thank the following persons for their review comments: Michael Welzl, John Leslie, Mirja Kuehlewind, Matt Mathis, Mary Barnes</t>
    </section>
    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>While two position papers focused on security congestion control security itself was not on the agenda of the workshop. As such, nothing beyond the material contained in those position papers can be reported.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->
  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->
    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->
    <references title="Normative References"> 
	&RFC5405;
    &RFC2914; 
    </references>
	
    <references title="Informative References"> 
	&I-D.ietf-avtcore-rtp-circuit-breakers;
	&I-D.irtf-iccrg-multfrc;
	&RFC4585;
	&I-D.nichols-tsvwg-codel; 
	&I-D.schulzrinne-lmap-requirements;
	&RFC6817;
	&RFC2309; 
	&RFC5348;
	
	          <reference anchor="FF99">
		        <front>
		          <title>Promoting the Use of End-to-End Congestion Control in the Internet</title>
                    <author fullname="Sally Floyd" initials="S." surname="Floyd">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Kevin Fall" initials="K." surname="Fall">
					</author>
					
		          <date month="Aug" year="1999"/>
		        </front>
				   <seriesInfo
			          name="IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking,"
			          value="URL: http://www.aciri.org/floyd/end2end-paper.html"/>
			        <format target="http://www.aciri.org/floyd/end2end-paper.html" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			  <reference anchor="Mo">
		        <front>
		          <title>Fairness Considerations for Congestion Control</title>
                    <author fullname="Mo Zanaty" initials="M." surname="Zanaty">
					</author>
					
		          <date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
				   <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			  <reference anchor="Zahed">
		        <front>
		          <title>Improving the Interactive Real-Time Video Communication with Network Provided Congestion Notification</title>
                    <author fullname="Zaheduzzaman Sarker" initials="Z." surname="Sarker">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Ingemar Johansson" initials="I." surname="Johansson">
					</author>
					
		          <date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
				   <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			 <reference anchor="Keith">
		        <front>
		          <title>Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Flows on Today's Internet</title>
                    <author fullname="Keith Winstein" initials="K." surname="Winstein">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Anirudh Sivaraman" initials="A." surname="Sivaraman">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Hari Balakrishnan" initials="H." surname="Balakrishnan">
					</author>
					
		          <date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
				   <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>


              <reference anchor="JDNK12">
		        <front>
		          <title>Harsh RED: Improving RED for Limited Aggregate Traffic</title>
                    <author fullname="Ilpo Jarvinen" initials="I." surname="Jarvinen">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Aaron Yi Ding" initials="A." surname="Ding">
					</author>
					<author fullname="A. Nyrhinen" initials="A." surname="Nyrhinen">
					</author>	
                    <author fullname="Markku Kojo" initials="M." surname="Kojo">
					</author>	
					
					<date month="March" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="In Proceedings of the 26th IEEE International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications (AINA 2012)"
			          value=""/>
		      </reference>
 
              <reference anchor="Markku">
		        <front>
		          <title>Impact of TCP on Interactive Real-Time Communication</title>
                    <author fullname="Ilpo Jarvinen" initials="I." surname="Jarvinen">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Binoy Chemmagate" initials="B." surname="Chemmagate">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Laila Daniel" initials="L." surname="Daniel">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Aaron Yi Ding" initials="A." surname="Ding">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Markku Kojo" initials="M." surname="Kojo">
					</author>					
                    <author fullname="Markus Isomaki" initials="M." surname="Isomaki">
					</author>		
					<date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
 
              <reference anchor="Cullen">
		        <front>
		          <title>Vendors Considered Harmfull</title>
                    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
					</author>
					<author fullname="Suhas Nandakumar" initials="S." surname="Nandakumar">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Hein Phan" initials="H." surname="Phan">
					</author>
					<date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			   <reference anchor="Michael">
		        <front>
		          <title>One control to rule them all</title>
                    <author fullname="Michael Welzl" initials="M." surname="Welzl">
					</author>
					<date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
		  
			   <reference anchor="John">
		        <front>
		          <title>There is No Magic Transport Wand</title>
                    <author fullname="John Leslie" initials="J." surname="Leslie">
					</author>
					<date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			  <reference anchor="Matt">
		        <front>
		          <title>Position paper on CC for Interactive RT</title>
                    <author fullname="Matt Mathis" initials="M." surname="Mathis">
					</author>
					<date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			  <reference anchor="Jim">
		        <front>
		          <title>Bufferbloat: Dark Buffers in the Internet</title>
                    <author fullname="Jim Gettys" initials="J." surname="Gettys">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Jim Gettys" initials="J." surname="Gettys">
					</author>
					
					<date month="May/June" year="2011"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IEEE Internet Computing, 15, pp. 95 - 96"
			          value=""/>
		      </reference>
			  
			  <reference anchor="Feng">
		        <front>
		          <title>The BLUE Active Queue Management Algorithm</title>
                    <author fullname="Wu-Chang Feng" initials="W." surname="Feng">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Kang G. Shin" initials="K." surname="Shin">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Dilip D. Kandlur" initials="D." surname="Kandlur">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Debanjan Saha" initials="D." surname="Saha">
					</author>
					
					<date month="August" year="2002"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="In IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking, 10(4), pp. 513 - 528"
			          value=""/>
		      </reference>
			  
			  
			  
			  <reference anchor="ippm">
		        <front>
		          <title>IETF IP Performance Metrics (ippm) Working Group</title>
                    <author fullname="IETF" initials="" surname="IETF">
					</author>
					<date month="Jan." year="2012"/>
		        </front>
				
				<format target="http://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/ippm/charter/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
			   <reference anchor="GN2012">
		        <front>
		          <title>Bufferbloat: Dark Buffers in the Internet</title>
                    <author fullname="Jim Gettys" initials="J." surname="Gettys">
					</author>
                    <author fullname="Kathleen Nichols" initials="K." surname="Nichols">
					</author>
					
					<date month="Jan." year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="Communications of the ACM, Vol. 55 No. 1, Pages 57 - 65, "
			          value="URL: http://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2012/1/144810-bufferbloat/"/>
				<format target="http://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2012/1/144810-bufferbloat/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
		      <reference anchor="Bufferbloat">
		        <front>
		          <title>Bufferbloat</title>
                    <author fullname="Wikipedia" initials="" surname="Wikipedia">
					</author>
					<date month="Jan." year="2012"/>
		        </front>
				
				<format target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bufferbloat" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
              <reference anchor="Stefan">
		        <front>
		          <title>On Fairness, Delay and Signaling of Different Approaches to Real-time Congestion Control</title>
                    <author fullname="Stefan Holmer" initials="S." surname="Holmer">
					</author>
					<date day="28" month="July" year="2012"/>
		        </front>
					 <seriesInfo
			          name="IAB / IRTF Workshop on Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication,"
			          value="URL: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/"/>
			        <format target="http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/" type="HTML"/>
		      </reference>
			  
	</references>
    <section anchor="app-program" title="Program Committee">
      <t>This workshop was organized by Harald Alvestrand, Bernard Aboba, Mary Barnes, Gonzalo Camarillo, Spencer Dawkins, Lars Eggert, Matthew Ford, Randell Jesup, Cullen Jennings, Jon Peterson, Robert Sparks, and Hannes Tschofenig.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="app-material" title="Workshop Material">
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Main Workshop Page: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/</t>
          <t>Position Papers: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/papers/</t>
          <t>Slides: http://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/cc-workshop/slides/</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="app-papers" title="Accepted Position Papers">
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>"One control to rule them all" by Michael Welzl</t>
		  <t>"Congestion Avoidance Through Deterministic" by Pier Luca Montessoro, Riccardo Bernardini, Franco Blanchini, Daniele Casagrande, Mirko Loghi, and Stefan Wieser</t>
		  <t>"Congestion Control in Real Time Media - Context" by Harald Alvestrand</t>
          <t>"Improving the Interactive Real-Time Video Communication with Network Provided Congestion Notification" by ANM Zaheduzzaman Sarker, Ingemar Johansson</t>
		  <t>"Multiparty Requirements in Congestion Control for Real-Time Interactive Media" by Magnus Westerlund</t>
		  <t>"On Fairness, Delay and Signaling of Different Approaches to Real-time Congestion Control" by Stefan Holmer</t>
		  <t>"RTP Congestion Control and RTCWeb Application Feedback" by Ted Hardie</t>
		  <t>"Issues with Using Packet Delays and Inter-arrival Times for Inference of Internet Congestion" by Wesley M. Eddy</t>
		  <t>"Impact of TCP on Interactive Real-Time Communication" by Ilpo Jarvinen, Binoy Chemmagate, Laila Daniel, Aaron Yi Ding, Markku Kojo, and Markus Isomaki</t>
		  <t>"Security Concerns For RTCWeb Congestion Control" by Dan York</t>
		  <t>"Vendors Considered Harmfull" by Cullen Jennings, Suhas Nandakumar, and Hein Phan</t>
		  <t>"Network-Assisted Dynamic Adaptation" by Xiaoqing Zhu and Rong Pan</t>
		  <t>"Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Applications" by Sanjeev Mehrotra, and Jin Li</t>
		  <t>"There is No Magic Transport Wand" by John Leslie</t>
		  <t>"Towards Adaptive Congestion Management for Interactive Real-Time Communications" by Dirk Kutscher, and Miriam Kuehlewind</t>
		  <t>"Enlarge the pre-congestion spectrum usage?" by Xavier Marjou, and Emile Stephan</t>
		  <t>"Congestion control for users who don't have first-class internet access" by Maire Reavy</t>
		  <t>"Realtime Congestion Challenges" by Randell Jesup</t>
		  <t>"Congestion Control for Interactive Media: Control Loops &amp; APIs" by Varun Singh, Joerg Ott, and Colin Perkins</t>
		  <t>"Some Notes on Threat Modelling Congestion Management" by Eric Rescorla</t>
		  <t>"Timely Detection of Lost Packets" by Ali C. Begen</t>
		  <t>"Congestion Control Considerations for Data Channels" by Michael Tuexen</t>
		  <t>"Position paper on CC for Interactive RT" by Matt Mathis</t>
		  <t>"Overall Considerations for Congestion Control" by M. Zanaty, B. VerSteeg, B. Christensen, D. Benham, A. Romanow</t>
		  <t>"Fairness Considerations for Congestion Control" by Mo Zanaty</t>
		  <t>"Media is not Data: The Meaning of Fairness for Competing Multimedia Flows" by Timothy B. Terriberry</t>
		  <t>"Thoughts on Real-Time Congestion Control" by Murari Sridharan</t>
          <t>"Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Flows on Today's Internet" by Keith Winstein, Anirudh Sivaraman, and Hari Balakrishnan</t>
		  <t>"Congestion Control Principles for CoAP" by Carsten Bormann, Klaus Hartke</t> 
		  <t>"Erasure Coding and Congestion Control for Interactive Real-Time Communication" by Pierre-Ugo Tournoux, Tuan Tran Thai, Emmanuel Lochin, Jerome Lacan, Vincent Roca</t>
		  <t>"Video Conferencing Specific Considerations for RTP Congestion Control" by Stephen Botzko and Mary Barnes</t>
		  <t>"The Internet is Broken, and How to Fix It" by Jim Gettys</t>
		  <t>"Deployment Considerations for Congestion Control in Real-Time Interactive Media Systems" by Jari Arkko</t>
		  </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="app-participants" title="Workshop Participants">
      <t>We would like to thank the following workshop participants for attending the workshop:
        <list style="symbols">
<t>Mat Ford</t>
<t>Bernard Aboba</t>
<t>Alissa Cooper</t>
<t>Mary Barnes</t>
<t>Lars Eggert</t>
<t>Harald Alvestrand</t>
<t>Gonzalo Camarillo</t>
<t>Robert Sparks</t>
<t>Cullen Jennings</t>
<t>Dirk Kutscher</t>
<t>Carsten Bormann</t>
<t>Michael Welzl</t>
<t>Magnus Westerlund</t>
<t>Colin Perkins</t>
<t>Murari Sridharan</t>
<t>Klaus Hartke</t>
<t>Pier Luca Montessoro</t>
<t>Xavier Marjou</t>
<t>Vincent Roca</t>
<t>Wes Eddy</t>
<t>Ali C. Begen</t>
<t>Mo Zanaty</t>
<t>Jin Li</t>
<t>Dave Thaler</t>
<t>Bob Briscoe</t>
<t>Barry Leiba</t>
<t>Jari Arkko</t>
<t>Stewart Bryant</t>
<t>Martin Stiemerling</t>
<t>Russ Housley</t>
<t>Marc Blanchet</t>
<t>Zaheduzzaman Sarker</t>
<t>Xiaoqing Zhu</t>
<t>Randell Jesup</t>
<t>Eric Rescorla</t>
<t>Suhas Nandakumar</t>
<t>Hannes Tschofenig</t>
<t>Bill VerSteeg</t>
<t>Sean Turner</t>
<t>Keith Winstein</t>
<t>Jon Peterson</t>
<t>Maire Reavy</t>
<t>Michael Tuexen</t>
<t>Stefan Holmer</t>
<t>Joerg Ott</t>
<t>Timothy Terriberry</t>
<t>Benoit Claise</t>
<t>Ted Hardie</t>
<t>Stephen Botzko</t>
<t>Matt Mathis</t>
<t>David Benham</t>
<t>Jim Gettys</t>
<t>Spencer Dawkins</t>
<t>Sanjeev Mehrotra</t>
<t>Adrian Farrel</t>
<t>Greg White</t>
<t>Markku Kojo</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>We also had remote participants, namely
<list style="symbols">
<t>Emmanuel Lochin</t>
<t>Mark Handley</t>
<t>Anirudh Sivaraman</t>
<t>John Leslie</t>
<t>Varun Singh</t>
</list>
</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
