<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<rfc category='std' ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac-03'>
  <?rfc strict='yes' ?>
  <?rfc toc='yes' ?>
  <?rfc tocdepth='3' ?>
  <?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
  <?rfc compact='yes' ?>
  <?rfc subcompact='yes' ?>

  <front>
   <title abbrev="OAuth 2.0 MAC Tokens">OAuth 2.0 Message Authentication Code (MAC) Tokens</title>

   <author  fullname="Justin Richer" initials="J" 
            surname="Richer">
      <organization>The MITRE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>jricher@mitre.org</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="William Mills" initials="W." surname="Mills">
      <organization>Yahoo! Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <code/>
          <region/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>wmills@yahoo-inc.com </email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author role="editor" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year='2013'/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This specification describes how to use MAC Tokens in HTTP requests to access OAuth 2.0 protected resources.  An OAuth client willing to access a protected resource needs to demonstrate possession of a crytographic key by using it with a keyed message digest function to the request.</t>

      <t>The document also defines a key distribution protocol for obtaining a fresh session key.</t>
  </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
   <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  
  
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t>This specification describes how to use MAC Tokens in HTTP requests and responses to access protected resources via the OAuth 2.0 protocol <xref target='RFC6749' />. An OAuth client willing to access a protected resource needs to demonstrate possession of a symmetric key by using it with a keyed message digest function to the request. The keyed message digest function is computed over a flexible set of parameters from the HTTP message.</t>
     <!-- <t>
        Similar to the HTTP Basic access authentication scheme <xref target='RFC2617' />, the MAC
        scheme utilizes a set of client credentials which include an identifier and key. However,
        in contrast with the Basic scheme, the key is never included in authenticated requests but
        is used to calculate the request MAC value which is included instead.
      </t>
     --> 
	 
      <t>The MAC Token mechanism requires the establishment of a shared symmetric key between the client and the resource server. This specification defines a three party key distribution protocol to dynamically distribute this session key from the authorization server to the client and the resource server.</t>
      <t>The design goal for this mechanism is to support the requirements outlined in <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-oauth-security"/>. In particular, when a server uses this mechanism, a passive attacker will be unable to use an eavesdropped access token exchanged between the client and the resource server. In addition, this mechanism helps secure the access token against leakage when sent over a secure channel to the wrong resource server if the client provided information about the resource server it wants to interact with in the request to the authorization server.</t>
	  
	  <t>Since a keyed message digest only provides integrity protection and data-origin authentication confidentiality protection can only be added by the usage of Transport Layer Security (TLS). This specification provides a mechanism for channel binding is included to ensure that a TLS channel is not terminated prematurely and indeed covers the entire end-to-end communication.</t>
	  
	  </section>
	  
   <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

      <section title='Terminology'>
        <t>
          The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL', 'SHALL NOT', 'SHOULD',
          'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this specification are to be
          interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
        </t>
        <t>
          This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) notation of
          <xref target='I-D.ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging' />. Additionally, the following rules
          are included from <xref target="RFC2617"/>: auth-param.
        </t>
		
		<t><list style="hanging">
		
		<t hangText="Session Key:">The terms mac key, session key, and symmetric key are used interchangably and refer to the cryptographic keying material established between the client and the resource server. This temporary key used between the client and the resource server, with a
      lifetime limited to the lifetime of the access token. This session key is generated by the authorization server.</t>
	  
	  <t hangText="Authenticator:">
      A record containing information that can be shown to have been
      recently generated using the session key known only by the client
      and the resource server.</t>
	  
	  <t hangText="Message Authentication Code (MAC):">
	  Message authentication codes (MACs) are hash functions that take two distinct inputs, a message and a secret key, and produce a ﬁxed-size output. The design goal is that it is practically infeasible to produce the same output without knowledge of the key. The terms keyed message digest functions and MACs are used interchangably.</t>
      </list>
	  </t>
      </section>

	  <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  
	  
<section title="Architecture"> 
    
<t>The architecture of the proposal described in this document assumes that the authorization server acts as a trusted third party that provides session keys to clients and to resource servers. These session keys are used by the client and the resource server as input to a MAC. In order to obtain the session key the client interacts with the authorization server as part of the a normal grant exchange. This is shown in an abstract way in <xref target="architecture-1"/>. Together with the access token the authorization server returns a session key (in the mac_key parameter) and several other parameters. The resource server obtains the session key via the access token. Both of these two key distribution steps are described in more detail in <xref target="key-distribution"/>.</t>

<t>
<figure anchor="architecture-1" title="Architecture: Interaction between the Client and the Authorization Server.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[
                     +---------------+
                    ^|               | AS-RS Key
                  // | Authorization |<*******  
                 /   | Server        |       *  
               //    |               |       *
              /      |               |       *
       (I)  //      /+---------------+       *
 Access    /      //                         *
 Token    /      /                           *
 Request//     //  (II) Access Token         *
       /      /         +Session Key (SK)    *
     //     //                               *
    /      v                                 v
  +-----------+                       +------------+
  |           |                       |            |
  |           |                       | Resource   |
  | Client    |                       | Server     |
  |           |                       |            |
  |           |                       |            |
  +-----------+                       +------------+
  
  ****: Out-of-Band Long-Term Key Establishment
  ----: Dynamic Session Key Distribution
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

<t>Once the client has obtained the necessary access token and the session key (including parameters) it can start to interact with the resource server. To demonstrate possession of the session key it computes a MAC and adds various fields to the outgoing request message. We call this structure the "Authenticator". The server evaluates the request, includes an Authenticator and returns a response back to the client. Since the access token is valid for a period of time the resource server may decide to cache it so that it does not need to be provided in every request from the client. This interaction is shown in <xref target="architecture-2"/>.

<figure anchor="architecture-2" title="Architecture: Interaction between the Client and the Resource Server.">
<artwork>
<![CDATA[
                   +---------------+
                   |               |
                   | Authorization |
                   | Server        |
                   |               |
                   |               |
                   +---------------+






+-----------+  Authenticator (a)    +------------+
|           |---------------------->|            |
|           |  [+Access Token]      | Resource   |
| Client    |                       | Server     |
|           |  Authenticator (b)    |            |
|           |<----------------------|            |
+-----------+                       +------------+

     ^                                    ^
     |                                    |
     |                                    |
    SK                                   SK
    +param                               +param
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

	  </section> 
	  
 
	<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  
	
	    <section title='Key Distribution' anchor='key-distribution'>
	  
	  <t>For this scheme to function a session key must be available to the client and the resource server, which is then used as a parameter in the keyed message digest function. This document describes the key distribution mechanism that uses the authorization server as a trusted third party, which ensures that the session key is transported 
	  from the authorization server to the client and the resource server.</t>
	  
<!--      <t>
        This specification does not define methods for the client to specifically request a
        MAC-type token from the authorization server. Additionally, it does not include any
        discovery facilities for identifying which HMAC algorithms are supported by a resource
        server, or how the client may go about obtaining MAC access tokens for any given protected
        resource.
      </t>
--> 

      <section anchor="transport-to-client" title='Session Key Transport to Client'>
        <t>
          Authorization servers issue MAC Tokens based on requests from clients. The request MUST include the audience parameter defined in <xref target="I-D.tschofenig-oauth-audience"/>, which indicates the resource server the client wants to interact with. This specification assumes use of the 'Authorization Code' grant. If the request is processed successfully by the authorization server it MUST return at least the following parameters to the client:</t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='kid'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The name of the key (key id), which is an identifier generated by the resource server. It is RECOMMENDED that the authorization server generates this key id by computing a hash over the access_token, for example using SHA-1, and to encode it in a base64 format.  
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
			<t hangText='access_token'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The OAuth 2.0 access token. 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
            <t hangText='mac_key'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The session key generated by the authorization server. Note that the lifetime of the session key is equal to the lifetime of the access token.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
            <t hangText='mac_algorithm'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The MAC algorithm used to calculate the request MAC. The value MUST be one
              of <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-1</spanx>, <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-256</spanx>, or
              a registered extension algorithm name as described in <xref target='registry' />. The authorization server is assumed to know the set of algorithms supported by the client and the resource server. It selects an algorithm that meets the  security policies and is supported by both nodes.
            </t>
          </list>
		</t>
		<t>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            For example:
          </preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: application/json
  Cache-Control: no-store

  {
    "access_token":
"eyJhbGciOiJSU0ExXzUiLCJlbmMiOiJBMTI4Q0JDK0hTMjU2In0.
pwaFh7yJPivLjjPkzC-GeAyHuy7AinGcS51AZ7TXnwkC80Ow1aW47kcT_UV54ubo
nONbeArwOVuR7shveXnwPmucwrk_3OCcHrCbE1HR-Jfme2mF_WR3zUMcwqmU0RlH
kwx9txo_sKRasjlXc8RYP-evLCmT1XRXKjtY5l44Gnh0A84hGvVfMxMfCWXh38hi
2h8JMjQHGQ3mivVui5lbf-zzb3qXXxNO1ZYoWgs5tP1-T54QYc9Bi9wodFPWNPKB
kY-BgewG-Vmc59JqFeprk1O08qhKQeOGCWc0WPC_n_LIpGWH6spRm7KGuYdgDMkQ
bd4uuB0uPPLx_euVCdrVrA.
AxY8DCtDaGlsbGljb3RoZQ.
7MI2lRCaoyYx1HclVXkr8DhmDoikTmOp3IdEmm4qgBThFkqFqOs3ivXLJTku4M0f
laMAbGG_X6K8_B-0E-7ak-Olm_-_V03oBUUGTAc-F0A.
OwWNxnC-BMEie-GkFHzVWiNiaV3zUHf6fCOGTwbRckU",
    "token_type":"mac",
    "expires_in":3600,
    "refresh_token":"8xLOxBtZp8",
    "kid":"22BIjxU93h/IgwEb4zCRu5WF37s=",
    "mac_key":"adijq39jdlaska9asud",
    "mac_algorithm":"hmac-sha-256"
  }
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
	  </t>
      </section>

	   <section anchor="transport-to-rs" title='Session Key Transport to Resource Server'>
       <t>The transport of the mac_key from the authorization server to the resource server
	   is accomplished by conveying the encrypting mac_key inside the access token. At the time of writing only one standardized format for carrying the access token is defined: the JSON Web Token (JWT) <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-json-web-token"/>. Note that the header of the JSON Web Encryption (JWE) structure <xref target="I-D.ietf-jose-json-web-encryption"/>, which is a JWT with encrypted content, MUST contain a key id (kid) in the header to allow the resource server to select the appropriate keying material for decryption. This keying material is a symmetric or an asymmetric long-term key established between the resource server and the authorization server, as shown in <xref target="architecture-1"/> as AS-RS key. The establishment of this long-term key is outside the scope of this specification.</t>
	   
	   <t>This document defines two new claims to be carried in the JWT: mac_key, kid. These two parameters match the content of the mac_key and the kid conveyed to the client, as shown in <xref target="transport-to-client"/>.</t>
	   
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='kid'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The name of the key (key id), which is an identifier generated by the resource server.  
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
            <t hangText='mac_key'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The session key generated by the authorization server.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
          </list>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            This example shows a JWT claim set without header and without encryption:
          </preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
{"iss":"authorization-server.example.com",
"exp":1300819380,
"kid":"22BIjxU93h/IgwEb4zCRu5WF37s=",
"mac_key":"adijq39jdlaska9asud",
"aud":"apps.example.com"
}
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
	  </t>

	  <t><list style="empty">
	  <t>QUESTIONS: An alternative to the use of a JWT to convey the access token with the encrypted mac_key is use the token introspect <xref target="I-D.richer-oauth-introspection"/>. What mechanism should be described? What should be mandatory to implement?</t>
      <t>QUESTIONS: The above description assumes that the entire access token is encrypted but it would be possible to only encrypt the session key and to only apply integrity protection to other fields. Is this desireable?</t>
	  </list>
	  </t>
       </section>
 
    </section>
	
	<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

    <section title='The Authenticator' anchor='requests'>
      <t>To access a protected resource the client must be in the possession of a valid set of session key
        provided by the authorization server. The client constructs the authenticator, as described in 
		<xref target='authz_header' />.
      </t>

      <section title='The Authenticator' anchor='authz_header'>
        <t>The client constructs the authenticator and adds the resulting fields to the HTTP request using the
        <spanx style='verb'>Authorization</spanx> request header field. 
		
          The <spanx style='verb'>Authorization</spanx> request header field uses the framework
          defined by <xref target='RFC2617' />. To include the authenticator in a subsequent response from the authorization 
		  server to the client the WWW-Authenticate header is used. For further exchanges a new, yet-to-be-defined header 
		  will be used. </t>
		  
	    <t> 
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  authenticator  = "MAC" 1*SP #params
  
  params         = id / ts / seq-nr / access_token / mac / h / cb

  kid            = "kid" "=" string-value
  ts             = "ts" "=" ( <"> timestamp <"> ) / timestamp
  seq-nr         = "seq-nr" "=" string-value
  access_token   = "access_token" "=" b64token
  mac            = "mac" "=" string-value
  cb             = "cb" "=" token
  h              = "h" "=" h-tag
  h-tag          = %x68 [FWS] "=" [FWS] hdr-name
                   *( [FWS] ":" [FWS] hdr-name )
  hdr-name       = token
	  
  timestamp      = 1*DIGIT
  string-value   = ( <"> plain-string <"> ) / plain-string
  plain-string   = 1*( %x20-21 / %x23-5B / %x5D-7E )
  
  b64token       = 1*( ALPHA / DIGIT /
                       "-" / "." / "_" / "~" / "+" / "/" ) *"="
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
	
        <t>
          The header attributes are set as follows:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='kid'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              REQUIRED. The key identifier.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
            <t hangText='ts'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              REQUIRED. The timestamp. The value MUST be a positive integer set by the
              client when making each request to the number of milliseconds since 1 January 1970.
			  <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
			  The JavaScript getTime() function or the Java System.currentTimeMillis() function, for example, produce such a timestamp.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
            <t hangText='seq-nr'>
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              OPTIONAL.
      This optional field includes the initial sequence number to be
      used by the messages exchange between the client and the server when the replay protection 
	  provided by the timestamp is not sufficient enough replay protection. This
      field specifies the initial sequence number for messages from the
      client to the server.  When included in the response message, the
      initial sequence number is that for messages from the server to
      the client. Sequence numbers fall in the range 0 through 2^64 - 1 and wrap to zero following
      the value 2^64 - 1. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	  The initial sequence number SHOULD be random and
      uniformly distributed across the full space of possible sequence
      numbers, so that it cannot be guessed by an attacker and so that
      it and the successive sequence numbers do not repeat other
      sequences. In the event that more than 2^64 messages are to be generated in a series of messages, 
	  rekeying MUST be performed before sequence numbers are reused. Rekeying requires a new access token to be requested.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
            <t hangText='access_token'>
               <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              CONDITIONAL. The access_token MUST be included in the first request from the client to the server but MUST NOT be included in a subsequent response and in a further protocol exchange. 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
			
            <t hangText='mac'>
               <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              REQUIRED. The result of the keyed message digest computation, as described in <xref target='mac' />.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> </t>
			
			<t hangText='cb'> 
			 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
			OPTIONAL. This field carries the channel binding value from RFC 5929 <xref target="RFC5929"/> in the following format: cb= channel-binding-type ":" channel-binding-content. RFC 5929 offers two types of channel bindings for TLS. First, there is the 'tls-server-end-point' channel binding, which uses a hash of the TLS server's certificate as it
   appears, octet for octet, in the server's Certificate message. The second channel binding is 'tls-unique', which uses the first TLS Finished message sent (note: the Finished struct, not the TLS record layer message containing it) in the most
   recent TLS handshake of the TLS connection being bound to. As an example, the cb field may contain cb=tls-unique:9382c93673d814579ed1610d3</t>
           		
			<t hangText='h'>
               <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              OPTIONAL.  This field contains a colon-separated list of header field names that identify the
      header fields presented to the keyed message digest algorithm. If the 'h' header field is absent then the following value is set by default: h="host". The field MUST
      contain the complete list of header fields in the order presented
      to the keyed message digest algorithm.  The field MAY contain names of header
      fields that do not exist at the time of computing the keyed message digest; nonexistent header fields do
      not contribute to the keyed message digest computation (that is, they are
      treated as the null input, including the header field name, the
      separating colon, the header field value, and any CRLF
      terminator).  
	  
	  By including header fields that do not
         actually exist in the keyed message digest computation, the client can allow the resource server to detect
         insertion of those header fields by intermediaries.  However, since
         the client cannot possibly know what header fields might be
         defined in the future, this mechanism cannot be used to prevent
         the addition of any possible unknown header fields.
		 
	  The field MAY contain multiple instances of a header
      field name, meaning multiple occurrences of the corresponding
      header field are included in the header hash.  The field MUST NOT
      include the mac header field.  Folding whitespace (FWS) MAY be
      included on either side of the colon separator.  Header field
      names MUST be compared against actual header field names in a
      case-insensitive manner.  This list MUST NOT be empty.  See
      <xref target="Security"/> for a discussion of choosing header fields.
            </t>
			
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Attributes MUST NOT appear more than once. Attribute values are limited to a subset of
          ASCII, which does not require escaping, as defined by the plain-string ABNF.
        </t>
      </section>
		
      <section title='MAC Input String' anchor='base_string'>
         
          <t>An HTTP message can either be a request from client to server or a
   response from server to client.  Syntactically, the two types of
   message differ only in the start-line, which is either a request-line
   (for requests) or a status-line (for responses).</t>
   
          <t>Two parameters serve as input to a keyed message digest function: a key and an input string. 
			 Depending on the communication direction either the request-line or the status-line is used as the first 
		     value followed by the HTTP header fields listed in the 'h' parameter. Then, the timestamp field and  
			 the seq-nr field (if present) is concatenated.</t>
		
<!-- 			<t>
            <list style='numbers'>
              <t>
                The HTTP request method in upper case. For example:
                <spanx style='verb'>HEAD</spanx>, <spanx style='verb'>GET</spanx>,
                <spanx style='verb'>POST</spanx>, etc.
              </t>
              <t>
                The HTTP request-URI as defined by <xref target='RFC2616' /> section 5.1.2.
              </t>
              <t>
                The hostname included in the HTTP request using the
                <spanx style='verb'>Host</spanx> request header field in lower case.
              </t>
              <t>
                The port as included in the HTTP request using the
                <spanx style='verb'>Host</spanx> request header field. If the header field does not
                include a port, the default value for the scheme MUST be used (e.g., 80 for HTTP and
                443 for HTTPS).
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
		  --> 
		  <t>As an example, consider the HTTP request with the new line separator character 
		  represented by <spanx style='verb'>\n</spanx> for editorial purposes only.
		  The h parameter is set to h=host, the kid is 314906b0-7c55, and the timstamp is 1361471629.
          <figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
POST /request?b5=%3D%253D&a3=a&c%40=&a2=r%20b&c2&a3=2+q HTTP/1.1
Host: example.com

Hello World!
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
</t>		  
		  	
<t>The resulting string is:
          <figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
POST /request?b5=%3D%253D&a3=a&c%40=&a2=r%20b&c2&a3=2+q HTTP/1.1\n
1361471629\n
example.com\n
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
		  </t> 
		  
        </section>

		
      <section title='Keyed Message Digest Algorithms' anchor='mac'>
        <t>
          The client uses a cryptographic algorithm together with a session key to calculate a keyed message digest. This
          specification defines two algorithms: <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-1</spanx> and
          <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-256</spanx>, and provides an extension registry for
          additional algorithms.
        </t>

        <section title='hmac-sha-1'>
          <t>
            <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-1</spanx> uses the HMAC-SHA1 algorithm, as defined in
            <xref target='RFC2104' />:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
  mac = HMAC-SHA1 (key, text)
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Where:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
              <t hangText='text'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                is set to the value of the input string as described in
                <xref target='base_string' />,
              </t>
              <t hangText='key'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                is set to the session key provided by the authorization server, and
              </t>
              <t hangText='mac'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                is used to set the value of the <spanx style='verb'>mac</spanx> attribute,
                after the result string is base64-encoded per Section 6.8 of <xref target='RFC2045' />.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title='hmac-sha-256'>
          <t>
            <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-256</spanx> uses the HMAC algorithm, as defined in
            <xref target='RFC2104' />, with the SHA-256 hash function, defined in
            <xref target='NIST-FIPS-180-3' />:
          </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
              <![CDATA[
  mac = HMAC-SHA256 (key, text)
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Where:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
              <t hangText='text'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                is set to the value of the input string as described in
                <xref target='base_string' />,
              </t>
              <t hangText='key'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                is set to the session key provided by the authorization server, and
              </t>
              <t hangText='mac'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                is used to set the value of the <spanx style='verb'>mac</spanx> attribute,
                after the result string is base64-encoded per Section 6.8 of <xref target='RFC2045' />.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

    </section>

 <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

    <section title='Verifying the Authenticator'>
      <t>
        When receiving a message with an authenticator the following steps are performed:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style='numbers'>
		  <t>When the authorization server receives a message with a new access token (and consequently a new session key) then it obtains the session key by retrieving the content of the access token (which requires decryption of the session key contained inside the token).
          The content of the access token, in particular the audience field and the scope, MUST be verified as described in  
		  Alternatively, the kid parameter is used to look-up a cached session key from a previous exchange. </t>
          <t>
            Recalculate the keyed message digest, as described in <xref target='mac' />, and compare the
            request MAC to the value received from the client via the <spanx style='verb'>mac</spanx> attribute.
          </t>
          <t>
            Verify that no replay took place by comparing the value of the ts (timestamp) header with the local time. 
			The processing of authenticators with stale timestamps is described in <xref target='ts' />.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Error handling is described in <xref target="error-handling"/>.</t>
	  
      <section title='Timestamp Verification' anchor='ts'>
        <t>
          The timestamp field enables the server to detect replay attacks. Without replay protection, an
          attacker can use an eavesdropped request to gain access to a protected resource. The following 
		  procedure is used to detect replays:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='symbols'>
            <t>
              At the time the first request is received from the client for each key
              identifier, calculate the difference (in seconds) between the request timestamp and
              the local clock. The difference is stored locally for later use.
            </t>
            <t>
              For each subsequent request, apply the request time delta to the timestamp included in the message
              to calculate the adjusted request time.
            </t>
            <t>
              Verify that the adjusted request time is within the allowed time period defined by
              the authorization server.
			  If the local time and the calculated time based in the request differ by more than the 
			  allowable clock skew (e.g., 5 minutes) a replay has to be assumed. 
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

	  <section title='Error Handling' anchor='error-handling'>
	  <t>TBD: Error handling goes in here.</t>
	  
	  <t>
          If the protected resource request does not include an access token, lacks the keyed message digest, contains
          an invalid key identifier, or is malformed, the server SHOULD return a 401 (Unauthorized) HTTP status code.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            For example:
          </preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
  WWW-Authenticate: MAC
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          The <spanx style='verb'>WWW-Authenticate</spanx> request header field uses the framework
          defined by <xref target='RFC2617' /> as follows:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  challenge   = "MAC" [ 1*SP #param ]
  param       = error / auth-param
  error       = "error" "=" ( token / quoted-string)
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
		 
        <t>
          Each attribute MUST NOT appear more than once.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the protected resource request included a MAC
          <spanx style='verb'>Authorization</spanx> request header field and failed authentication,
          the server MAY include the <spanx style='verb'>error</spanx> attribute to provide the
          client with a human-readable explanation why the access request was declined to assist
          the client developer in identifying the problem.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <preamble>
            For example:
          </preamble>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
  WWW-Authenticate: MAC error="The MAC credentials expired"
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
	
	</section> 

		<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

	     <section title='Example'>
		  <t>[Editor's Note: Full example goes in here.]</t>
		  
		 <!-- 
        <t>
          The client attempts to access a protected resource without authentication, making the
          following HTTP request to the resource server:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  GET /resource/1?b=1&a=2 HTTP/1.1
  Host: example.com
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The resource server returns the following authentication challenge:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
  WWW-Authenticate: MAC
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The client has previously obtained a set of MAC credentials for accessing resources on
          the <spanx style='verb'>http://example.com/</spanx> server. The MAC credentials
          issued to the client include the following attributes:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='MAC key identifier:'>h480djs93hd8</t>
            <t hangText='MAC key:'>489dks293j39</t>
            <t hangText='MAC algorithm:'>hmac-sha-1</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The client constructs the authentication header by calculating a timestamp (e.g. the
          number of seconds since January 1, 1970 00:00:00 GMT).
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style='hanging' hangIndent='6'>
            <t hangText='Timestamp:'>1336363200</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The client constructs the normalized request string (the new line separator character is
          represented by <spanx style='verb'>\n</spanx> for display purposes only; the trailing
          new line separator signify that no extension value is included with the request,
          explained below):
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  1336363200\n
  dj83hs9s\n
  GET\n
  /resource/1?b=1&a=2\n
  example.com\n
  80\n
  \n
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The request MAC is calculated using the specified MAC algorithm
          <spanx style='verb'>hmac-sha-1</spanx> and the MAC key over the normalized request
          string. The result is base64-encoded to produce the request MAC:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  bhCQXTVyfj5cmA9uKkPFx1zeOXM=
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The client includes the MAC key identifier, nonce, and request MAC with the request
          using the <spanx style='verb'>Authorization</spanx> request header field:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
  GET /resource/1?b=1&a=2 HTTP/1.1
  Host: example.com
  Authorization: MAC id="h480djs93hd8",
                     ts="1336363200",
                     nonce="dj83hs9s",
                     mac="bhCQXTVyfj5cmA9uKkPFx1zeOXM="
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The server validates the request by calculating the request MAC again based on the
          request received and verifies the validity and scope of the MAC credentials. If valid,
          the server responds with the requested resource representation.
        </t>
		--> 
      </section>

	<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

    <section title='Security Considerations' anchor='Security'>
      <t>
        As stated in <xref target='RFC2617' />, the greatest sources of risks are usually found not
        in the core protocol itself but in policies and procedures surrounding its use.
        Implementers are strongly encouraged to assess how this protocol addresses their security
        requirements and the security threats they want to mitigate. 
      </t>

      <section title='Key Distribution'>
        <t>
          This specification describes a key distribution mechanism for providing the session key (and parameters) from the authorization server to the client. The interaction between the client and the authorization server requires Transport Layer Security (TLS) with a ciphersuite offering confidentiality protection. The session key MUST NOT be transmitted in clear since this would completely destroy the security benefits of the proposed scheme. Furthermore, the obtained session key MUST be stored so that only the client instance has access to it. Storing the session key, for example, in a cookie allows other parties to gain access to this confidential information and compromises the security of the protocol. 
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Offering Confidentiality Protection for Access to Protected Resources'>
        <t>This specification can be used with and without Transport Layer Security (TLS).</t> 
		
		<t>Without TLS this protocol provides a mechanism for verifying the integrity of requests and responses, it
          provides no confidentiality protection. Consequently, eavesdroppers will have full access to request content and further messages exchanged between the client and the resource server. This could be problematic when data is exchanged that requires care, such as personal data.
        </t>
		
		<t>When TLS is used then confidentiality can be ensured and with the use of the TLS channel binding feature it ensures that the TLS channel is cryptographically bound to the used MAC token. TLS in combination with channel bindings bound to the MAC token provide security superiour to the OAuth Bearer Token.</t> 
		
		<t>The use of TLS in combination with the MAC token is highly recommended to ensure the confidentiality of the user's data.</t>
      </section>

      <section title='Authentication of Resource Servers'>
        <t>This protocol allows clients to verify the authenticity of resource servers in two ways: 
		  
		  <list style="numbers"> 
		  <t>The resource server demonstrates possession of the session key by computing a keyed message digest function over a number of HTTP fields in the response to the request from the client.</t>

		  <t>When TLS is used the resource server is authenticated as part of the TLS handshake.</t>
		  </list> 
	   </t> 
		  
      </section>

      <section title='Plaintext Storage of Credentials'>
        <t>
          The MAC key works in the same way passwords do in traditional authentication systems. In
          order to compute the keyed message digest, the client and the resource server must have access to the MAC key in plaintext form.
        </t>
        <t>
          If an attacker were to gain access to these MAC keys - or worse, to the resource server's or the authorization server's database
          of all such MAC keys - he or she would be able to perform any action on behalf of any
          client.</t> 
		  
		  <t>It is therefore paramount to the security of the protocol that these session keys are protected from 
          unauthorized access.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Entropy of Session Keys'>
        <t>
          Unless TLS is used between the client and the resource server, eavesdroppers will have full access
          to requests sent by the client. They will thus be able to mount offline
          brute-force attacks to recover the session key used to compute the keyed message digest. Authorization servers should be careful to generate fresh and unique session keys with sufficient entrophy to resist such attacks for at least the
          length of time that the session keys are valid.
        </t>
        <t>
          For example, if a session key is valid for one day, authorization servers must ensure that
          it is not possible to mount a brute force attack that recovers the session key in less than
          one day. Of course, servers are urged to err on the side of caution, and use the
          longest session key reasonable.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is equally important that the pseudo-random number generator (PRNG) used to generate
          these session keys be of sufficiently high quality. Many PRNG implementations generate number
          sequences that may appear to be random, but which nevertheless exhibit patterns, which make cryptanalysis easier. Implementers are advised to follow the guidance on random number generation in <xref target="RFC4086"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Denial of Service / Resource Exhaustion Attacks'>
        <t>This specification includes a number of features which may make resource exhaustion
          attacks against resource servers possible. For example, a resource server may need to need to 
		  consult backend databases and the authorization server to verify an incoming request including an access token 
		  before granting access to the protected resource.</t> 
		<t>An attacker may exploit this to perform a denial of service attack by
          sending a large number of invalid requests to the server. The computational overhead of verifying the 
		  keyed message digest alone is, however, not sufficient to mount a denial of service attack since keyed message digest functions belong to the computationally fastest cryptographic algorithms. The usage of TLS does, however, require 
		  additional computational capabity to perform the asymmetric cryptographic operations. For a brief discussion about 
		  denial of service vulnerabilities of TLS please consult Appendix F.5 of RFC 5246 <xref target="RFC5246"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Timing Attacks'>
        <t>
          This specification makes use of HMACs, for which a signature verification involves
          comparing the received MAC string to the expected one. If the string comparison operator
          operates in observably different times depending on inputs, e.g. because it compares the
          strings character by character and returns a negative result as soon as two characters
          fail to match, then it may be possible to use this timing information to determine the
          expected MAC, character by character.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementers are encouraged to use fixed-time string comparators for MAC
          verification. This means that the comparison operation is not terminated once a mismatch is found. 
		</t>
      </section>

      <section title='CSRF Attacks'>
        <t>
          A Cross-Site Request Forgery attack occurs when a site, evil.com, initiates within the
          victim's browser the loading of a URL from or the posting of a form to a web site where a
          side-effect will occur, e.g. transfer of money, change of status message, etc. To prevent
          this kind of attack, web sites may use various techniques to determine that the
          originator of the request is indeed the site itself, rather than a third party. The
          classic approach is to include, in the set of URL parameters or form content, a nonce
          generated by the server and tied to the user's session, which indicates that only the
          server could have triggered the action.
        </t>
        <t>
          Recently, the Origin HTTP header has been proposed and deployed in some browsers. This
          header indicates the scheme, host, and port of the originator of a request. Some web
          applications may use this Origin header as a defense against CSRF.
        </t>
        <t>
          To keep this specification simple, HTTP headers are not part of the string to be MAC'ed.
          As a result, MAC authentication cannot defend against header spoofing, and a web site
          that uses the Host header to defend against CSRF attacks cannot use MAC authentication to
          defend against active network attackers. Sites that want the full protection of MAC
          Authentication should use traditional, cookie-tied CSRF defenses.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Protecting HTTP Header Fields'>
        <t>This specification provides flexibility for selectively protecting header fields and even the body 
		of the message. At a minimum the following fields are included in the keyed message digest. 
		</t>
		
		
<!--		
          The normalized request string has been designed to support the authentication methods
          defined in this specification. Those designing additional methods, should evaluated the
          compatibility of the normalized request string with their security requirements.
          Since the normalized request string does not cover the entire HTTP request, servers
          should employ additional mechanisms to protect such elements.
        </t>
        <t>
          The request MAC does not cover entity-header fields which can often affect how the
          request body is interpreted by the server (i.e., Content-Type). If the server behavior is
          influenced by the presence or value of such header fields, an attacker can manipulate the
          request header without being detected.
        </t>
--> 		
      </section>

    </section>
	
	<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

    <section title='IANA Considerations' anchor='IANA'>

	<section title="JSON Web Token Claims">
	<t>This document adds the following claims to the JSON Web Token Claims registry established with <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-json-web-token"/>:
	
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Claim Name: "kid"</t>
     <t>Change Controller: IETF</t>
     <t>Specification Document(s): [[ this document ]]</t>
    </list>
	
	<list style="symbols">
     <t>Claim Name: "mac_key"</t>
     <t>Change Controller: IETF</t>
     <t>Specification Document(s): [[ this document ]]</t>
    </list>
	</t>
	
    </section>    
	
      <section title='MAC Token Algorithm Registry' anchor='registry'>
        <t>
          This specification establishes the MAC Token Algorithm registry.
        </t>
        <t>
          Additional keyed message digest algorithms are registered on the advice of one or more Designated Experts
          (appointed by the IESG or their delegate), with a Specification Required (using
          terminology from <xref target='RFC5226' />). However, to allow for the allocation of
          values prior to publication, the Designated Expert(s) may approve registration once they
          are satisfied that such a specification will be published.
        </t>
        <t>
          Registration requests should be sent to the [TBD]@ietf.org mailing list for review and
          comment, with an appropriate subject (e.g., "Request for MAC Algorithm: example").
          [[ Note to RFC-EDITOR: The name of the mailing list should be determined in consultation
          with the IESG and IANA. Suggested name: http-mac-ext-review. ]]
        </t>
        <t>
          Within at most 14 days of the request, the Designated Expert(s) will either approve or
          deny the registration request, communicating this decision to the review list and IANA.
          Denials should include an explanation and, if applicable, suggestions as to how to make
          the request successful.
        </t>
        <t>
          Decisions (or lack thereof) made by the Designated Expert can be first appealed to
          Application Area Directors (contactable using app-ads@tools.ietf.org email address or
          directly by looking up their email addresses on http://www.iesg.org/ website) and, if the
          appellant is not satisfied with the response, to the full IESG (using the iesg@iesg.org
          mailing list).
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA should only accept registry updates from the Designated Expert(s), and should direct
          all requests for registration to the review mailing list.
        </t>

        <section title='Registration Template'>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging'>
              <t hangText='Algorithm name:'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                The name requested (e.g., "example").
              </t>
              <t hangText='Change controller:'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                For standards-track RFCs, state "IETF". For others, give the name of the
                responsible party. Other details (e.g., postal address, e-mail address, home page
                URI) may also be included.
              </t>
              <t hangText='Specification document(s):'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Reference to document that specifies the algorithm, preferably including a URI that
                can be used to retrieve a copy of the document. An indication of the relevant
                sections may also be included, but is not required.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title='Initial Registry Contents'>
          <t>
            The HTTP MAC authentication scheme algorithm registry's initial contents are:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Algorithm name: hmac-sha-1
              </t>
              <t>
                Change controller: IETF
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification document(s): [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style='symbols'>
              <t>
                Algorithm name: hmac-sha-256
              </t>
              <t>
                Change controller: IETF
              </t>
              <t>
                Specification document(s): [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section title='OAuth Access Token Type Registration'>
        <t>
          This specification registers the following access token type in the OAuth Access Token
          Type Registry.
        </t>

        <section title='The "mac" OAuth Access Token Type'>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging'>
              <t hangText='Type name:'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                mac
              </t>
              <t hangText='Additional Token Endpoint Response Parameters:'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                secret, algorithm
              </t>
              <t hangText='HTTP Authentication Scheme(s):'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                MAC
              </t>
              <t hangText='Change controller:'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                IETF
              </t>
              <t hangText='Specification document(s):'>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                [[ this document ]]
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section title='OAuth Parameters Registration'>
        <t>
          This specification registers the following parameters in the OAuth Parameters Registry
          established by <xref target='RFC6749' />.
        </t>

        <section title='The "mac_key" OAuth Parameter'>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging'>
              <t hangText='Parameter name:'>
                mac_key
              </t>
              <t hangText='Parameter usage location:'>
                authorization response, token response
              </t>
              <t hangText='Change controller:'>
                IETF
              </t>
              <t hangText='Specification document(s):'>
                [[ this document ]]
              </t>
              <t hangText='Related information:'>
                None
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title='The "mac_algorithm" OAuth Parameter'>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging'>
              <t hangText='Parameter name:'>
                mac_algorithm
              </t>
              <t hangText='Parameter usage location:'>
                authorization response, token response
              </t>
              <t hangText='Change controller:'>
                IETF
              </t>
              <t hangText='Specification document(s):'>
                [[ this document ]]
              </t>
              <t hangText='Related information:'>
                None
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
		
		  <section title='The "kid" OAuth Parameter'>
          <t>
            <list style='hanging'>
              <t hangText='Parameter name:'>
                kid
              </t>
              <t hangText='Parameter usage location:'>
                authorization response, token response
              </t>
              <t hangText='Change controller:'>
                IETF
              </t>
              <t hangText='Specification document(s):'>
                [[ this document ]]
              </t>
              <t hangText='Related information:'>
                None
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

    </section>

	</section> 
	
	<!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

    <section title='Acknowledgments'>
	  
	     <t>This document is based on OAuth 1.0 and we would like to thank Eran Hammer-Lahav for his work on incorporating the ideas into OAuth 2.0. As part of this initial work the following persons provided feedback: Ben Adida, Adam Barth, Phil Hunt, Rasmus Lerdorf, James Manger, William Mills, Scott Renfro, Justin Richer, Toby White, Peter Wolanin, and Skylar Woodward</t>
		 
	  <t>Further work in this document was done as part of OAuth working group conference calls late 2012/early 2013 and in design team conference calls February 2013. The following persons (in addition to the OAuth WG chairs, Hannes Tschofenig, and Derek Atkins) provided their input during these calls: Bill Mills, Justin Richer, Phil Hunt, Prateek Mishra, Mike Jones, George Fletcher, John Bradley, Tony Nadalin, Thomas Hardjono, Brian Campbell</t>
	  
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************************** -->  

		
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6265.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-p1-messaging.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.tschofenig-oauth-audience.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-json-web-token.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.richer-oauth-introspection.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-jose-json-web-encryption.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-html401-19991224.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4086.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5929.xml' ?>
      <reference anchor='NIST-FIPS-180-3'>
        <front>
          <title>Secure Hash Standard (SHS). FIPS PUB 180-3, October 2008</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <format type='pdf' target='http://www.nist.gov/itl/upload/fips180-3_final.pdf' />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.tschofenig-oauth-security.xml' ?>

    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>


