<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>


<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-mills-kitten-sasl-oauth-04.txt" category="std">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="A SASL/GSS-API Mechanism for OAuth">A SASL and GSS-API Mechanism for OAuth</title>
    <author fullname="William Mills" initials="W." surname="Mills">
      <organization>Yahoo! Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <code/>
          <region/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>wmills@yahoo-inc.com </email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Tim Showalter" initials="T." surname="Showalter">
      <organization>Yahoo! Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <code/>
          <region/>
          <country/>
          </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>timshow@yahoo-inc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2011"/>
    <workgroup>KITTEN</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        OAuth enables a third-party
   application to obtain limited access to a protected resource, either on
   behalf of a resource owner by orchestrating an approval interaction, or by allowing the
   third-party application to obtain access on its own behalf.
   </t>
      <t>This document defines how an application client uses OAuth over the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) or the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API) to access a protected resource at a resource serve, and additionally defines
	authorization and token issuing endpoint discovery. Thereby, it enables
	schemes defined within the OAuth framework for non-HTTP-based application protocols.
      </t> 
      <t>Clients typically store the user's long term credential. This does, however, lead to 
      significant security vulnerabilities, for example, when such a credential leaks. A significant benefit of OAuth for usage in those clients is that the password is replaced by a token. Tokens typically provided limited access rights and can be managed and
        revoked separately from the user's long-term credential (password).
	</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

    <section title="Introduction">

<t>OAuth <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> enables a third-party
   application to obtain limited access to a protected resource, either on
   behalf of a resource owner by orchestrating an approval interaction, or by allowing the
   third-party application to obtain access on its own behalf. The core OAuth
        specification <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> does not define the interaction between the 
        client and the resource server with the access to a protected resource using an Access Token. 
        This functionality is described in two separate specifications, namely <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-bearer"/>, and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac"/>, whereby the focus is on an HTTP-based environment only.
    </t> 
          
      <t><xref target="oauth-exchange"/> shows the abstract message flow as shown in Figure 1 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/>.</t>
       
      <t>
        <figure anchor="oauth-exchange" title="Abstract OAuth 2.0 Protocol Flow">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
     +--------+                               +---------------+
     |        |--(A)- Authorization Request ->|   Resource    |
     |        |                               |     Owner     |
     |        |<-(B)-- Authorization Grant ---|               |
     |        |                               +---------------+
     |        |
     |        |                               +---------------+
     |        |--(C)-- Authorization Grant -->| Authorization |
     | Client |                               |     Server    |
     |        |<-(D)----- Access Token -------|               |
     |        |                               +---------------+
     |        |
     |        |                               +---------------+
     |        |--(E)----- Access Token ------>|    Resource   |
     |        |                               |     Server    |
     |        |<-(F)--- Protected Resource ---|               |
     +--------+                               +---------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

  <t>This document  takes
        advantage of the OAuth protocol and its deployment base to provide a way to use 
        SASL <xref target="RFC4422"/> as well as the GSS-API <xref target="RFC2743"/> to gain access to resources when using non-HTTP-based protocols,
        such as the Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) <xref target="RFC3501"/>, which is what this memo uses in the examples.</t>

<t>The Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) is a framework
   for providing authentication and data security services in
   connection-oriented protocols via replaceable mechanisms.  It
   provides a structured interface between protocols and mechanisms.
   The resulting framework allows new protocols to reuse existing
   mechanisms and allows old protocols to make use of new mechanisms.
   The framework also provides a protocol for securing subsequent
   protocol exchanges within a data security layer.</t>
   
<t>
The Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API)
   <xref target="RFC2743"/> provides a framework for applications to support multiple
   authentication mechanisms through a unified interface. </t>

<t>
 This document
  defines a SASL mechanism for OAuth, but it conforms to the new
   bridge between SASL and the GSS-API called GS2 <xref target="RFC5801"/>.  This means
   that this document defines both a SASL mechanism and a GSS-API
   mechanism.  Implementers may be interested in 
either the SASL, the GSS-API, or even both mechanisms. To
   faciliate these two variants, the description has been split into two
   parts, one part that provides normative references for those interested in the SASL OAuth mechanism (see <xref target="SASL-OAUTH"/>), and a second part for those implementers that wish to implement the GSS-API portion (see <xref target="GSSAPI-OAUTH"/>).
</t>

<t>When OAuth is integrated into SASL and the GSS-API the high-level steps are as follows:
<list style="empty"> 
<t>  (A)  The client requests authorization from the resource owner.  The
        authorization request can be made directly to the resource owner
        (as shown), or preferably indirectly via the authorization
        server as an intermediary.</t>
<t>   (B)  The client receives an authorization grant which is a credential
        representing the resource owner's authorization, expressed using
        one of four grant types defined in this specification or using
        an extension grant type.  The authorization grant type depends
        on the method used by the client to request authorization and
        the types supported by the authorization server.</t>
<t>   (C)  The client requests an access token by authenticating with the
        authorization server and presenting the authorization grant.</t>
<t>   (D)  The authorization server authenticates the client and validates
        the authorization grant, and if valid issues an access token.</t>
<t>   (E)  The client requests the protected resource from the resource
        server and authenticates by presenting the access token.</t>
<t>   (F)  The resource server validates the access token, and if valid,
        serves the request.</t>
</list> 
</t>

    <t>Steps (E) and (F) are not defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> and are the main functionality specified within this document. 
       Additionally, an optional discovery exchange is defined. Consequently, the message exchange shown in <xref target="overview"/> is the result of this specification.
      (1) and (2) denote the optional discovery exchange steps that may happen before the OAuth 2.0 protocol 
      exchange messages in steps (A)-(D) are executed. Steps (E) and (F) also defined in this specification. 
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="overview" title="OAuth SASL Architecture">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                                              ----+
   +--------+                                  +---------------+  |
   |        |--(A)-- Authorization Request --->|   Resource    |  |
   |        |                                  |     Owner     |  |Plain
   |        |<-(B)------ Access Grant ---------|               |  |OAuth
   |        |                                  +---------------+  |2.0
   |        |                                                     | 
   |        |         Client Credentials &     +---------------+  |
   |        |--(C)------ Access Grant -------->| Authorization |  |
   | Client |                                  |     Server    |  |
   |        |<-(D)------ Access Token ---------|               |  |
   |        |      (w/ Optional Refresh Token) +---------------+  |
   |        |                                                 ----+
   |        |
   |        |                                                 ----+
   |        |        (Optional discovery)      +---------------+  |
   |        |--(1)------- User Name  --------->|               |  |
   | Client |                                  |               |  |
   |        |<-(2)------ Authentication -------|               |  |
   |        |          endpoint information    |    Resource   |  |OAuth
   |        |                                  |     Server    |  |over
   |        |--(E)------ Access Token -------->|               |  |SASL/
   |        |                                  |               |  |GSS-
   |        |<-(F)---- Protected Resource -----|               |  |API
   +--------+                                  +---------------+  |
                                                              ----+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Note: The discovery procedure in OAuth is still work in progress. Hence, the discovery
            components described in this document should be considered incomplete and a tentative
            proposal. In general, there is a trade off between a generic, externally available
            defined discovery mechanisms (such as Webfinger using host-meta <xref
              target="I-D.hammer-hostmeta"/>,or <xref target="I-D.jones-simple-web-discovery"/>) and configuration information exchanged in-band between
            the SASL communciation endpoints. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
            <t>It is worthwhile to note that this specification is also compatible with OAuth 1.0a <xref
        target="RFC5849"/>.</t>

    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
	<xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      <t>The reader is assumed to be familiar with the terms used in the OAuth 2.0 specification <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/>.</t>
      <t>In examples, "C:" and "S:" indicate lines sent by the client and server respectively. Line
        breaks have been inserted for readability.</t>
      <t>Note that the IMAP SASL specification requires base64 encoding message, not this memo.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

    <section anchor="SASL-OAUTH" title="OAuth SASL Mechanism Specification">

      <t>SASL is used as a generalized authentication method in a variety of application layer protocols. This
        document defines two SASL mechanisms for usage with OAuth: "OAUTH" and "OAUTH-PLUS". The "OAUTH" SASL
        mechanism provides bearer token alike semantic for SASL while "OAUTH-PLUS" provides a semantic similar to 
        OAuth MAC authentication by utilizing a channel binding mechanism <xref target="RFC5056"/> .</t>


      <section title="Channel Binding">
	
	<t>If the specification for the underlying
        authorization scheme requires a security layer, such as TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/>, the server 
	SHOULD only offer a mechanism where channel binding can be enabled.</t>

	  <t>The channel binding data is computed by the client based on it's choice of
	  preferred channel binding type.   As specified in <xref target="RFC5056"/>, the
	  channel binding information MUST start with the channel binding unique prefix, followed
	  by a colon (ASCII 0x3A), followed by a base64 encoded channel binding
	  payload.  The channel binding payload is the raw data from the channel binding
	  type if the raw channel binding data is less than 500 bytes. If the raw channel binding data is 500 bytes or
	  larger then a SHA-1 <xref target="RFC3174"/> hash of
	  the raw channel binding data is computed.</t>

	    <t>If the client is using tls-unique for a channel binding then the raw channel
	    binding data equals the first TLS finished message.  This is under the 500 byte
	    limit, so the channel binding payload sent to the server would be the base64
	    encoded first TLS finished message.</t>
	    
	    <t>In the case where the client has chosen tls-endpoint, the raw channel binding
	    data is the certificate of the server the client connected to, which will
	    frequently be 500 bytes or more. If it is then the channel binding payload
	    is the base64 encoded SHA-1 hash of the server certificate.</t>
      </section>


      <section title="Initial Client Response">
        <t>The SASL client response is formatted as an HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/> request.  The HTTP request is limited in
        that the path MUST be "/".  In the OAUTH mechanism no query string is allowed.  The following  header lines are
        defined in the client response: 
	<list><t>
	  <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="User (OPTIONAL):">Contains the user identifier being authenticated, and is
              provided to allow correct discovery information to be returned.</t>
            <t hangText="Host (REQUIRED):">Contains the host name to which the client connected.</t>
            <t hangText="Authorization (REQUIRED):">An HTTP Authorization header.</t>
          </list>
        </t></list>
        </t>
        <t> The user name is provided by the client to allow the discovery information to be
        customized for the user, a given server could allow multiple authenticators and it needs to
        return the correct one. For instance, a large ISP could provide mail service for 
          several domains who manage their own user information. For instance, users at foo-example.com
          could be authenticated by an OAuth service at https://oauth.foo-example.com/, and users at
          bar-example.com could be authenticated by https://oauth.bar-example.com, but both could be served
          by a hypothetical IMAP server running at a third domain, imap.example.net. </t>

	  <section title="Query String in OAUTH-PLUS">
	    <t> In the OAUTH-PLUS mechanism the channel binding information is carried in
	    the query string.  OAUTH-PLUS defines following query parameter(s):
	      <list><t>
		<list style="hanging">
		  <t hangText="cbdata (REQUIRED):">Contains the
		  base64 encoded channel binding data, properly 
		  escaped as an HTML query parameter value.</t>
		</list>
	      </t></list>
	    </t>
	  </section>


      </section>

      <section title="Server's Response">
        <t>The server validates the response per the specification for the authorization
        scheme used. If the authorization scheme used includes signing of the request
        parameters the client must provide a complete HTTP style request that satisfies
	the data requirements for the scheme in use.  
	</t>
	<t>In the OAUTH-PLUS mechanism the server examines the channel binding data,
        extracts the channel binding unique prefix, and extracts the raw channel biding
        data based on the channel binding type used.  It then computes it's own copy of
        the channel binding payload and compares that to the payload sent by the client in
        the query parameters of the tunneled HTTP request.  Those two must be equal for
        channel binding to succeed.
	</t>
        <t> The server responds to a successfully verified client message by completing the SASL
          negotiation. The authentication scheme MUST carry the user ID to be used as the 
	  authorization identity (identity to act as). The server
          MUST use that ID as the user being authorized, that is the user assertion
          we accept and not other information such as from the URL or
          "User:" header. </t>
        <t> The server responds to failed authentication by sending discovery information
          in an HTTP style response with the HTTP status code set to 401, and then
	  failing the authentication.   
	</t>
	<t>If channel binding is in use and the channel
	  binding fails the server responds with a minimal HTTP response without discovery
          information and the HTTP status code set to 412 to indicate that the channel
	  binding precondition failed.  If the authentication scheme in use does not include
	  signing the server SHOULD revoke the presented credential and the client SHOULD
          discard that credential.
	</t>
 </section>
 
	 <section title="Mapping to SASL Identities">
	     <t> Some OAuth mechanisms can provide both an authorization identity and an  
	     authentication identity.  An example of this is OAuth 1.0a <xref target="RFC5849"/> where 
	     the consumer key (oauth_consumer_key) identifies the entity using to token which equates to the 
	     SASL authentication identity, and is authenticated using the shared secret.  The 
	     authorization identity in the OAuth 1.0a case is carried in the token (per the requirement 
	     above), which SHOULD validated independently.  The server MAY use a consumer key or
	     other comparable identity in the OAuth authorization scheme as the SASL authentication identity.
	     If an appropriate authentication identity is not available the server MUST use the 
	     identity asserted in the token.</t>
        
      </section>

      <section title="Discovery Information">
        <t>The server MUST send discovery information in response to a failed authentication 
          exchange or a request with an empty Authorization header. If discovery information is
          returned it MUST include an authentication
          endpoint appropriate for the user. If the "User" header is present the discovery
          information MUST be for that user. Discovery information is provided by the server to the
	  client to allow a client to discover the appropriate OAuth authentication and token
	  endpoints. The client then uses that information to obtain the access token needed for
	  OAuth authentication. The client SHOULD cache and re-use the user specific discovery
	  information for service endpoints. </t>
	<t>Discovery information makes use of both the WWW-Authenticate header as defined
        in HTTP Authentication: Basic and Digest Access Authentication  <xref target="RFC2617"/> and Link headers as
        defined in <xref target="RFC5988"/>.  The following elements are defined for discovery information:  
	    <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="WWW-Authenticate"> A WWW-Authenticate header for each authentication scheme
	      supported by the server.  Authentication scheme names are case
	      insensitive. The following <xref target="RFC2617"/> authentication
	      parameters are defined:
	      	    <list style="hanging">
		    <t hangText="realm">REQUIRED -- (as defined by RFC2617)</t>
		    <t hangText="scope">OPTIONAL -- A quoted string.  This provides the
		        client an OAuth 2 scope known to be valid for the resource.</t>
		    </list>
	    </t>
            <t hangText="oauth2-authenticator"> An <xref target="RFC5988"/> Link header specifying
	        the <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> authentication endpoint.  This link has an
		OPTIONAL link-extension "scheme", if included this link applies ONLY to the
		specified scheme.
	    </t>
            <t hangText="oauth2-token"> An <xref target="RFC5988"/> Link header specifying
	        the <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> token endpoint.  This link has an
		OPTIONAL link-extension "scheme", if included this link applies ONLY to the
		specified scheme.
	    </t>
            <t hangText="oauth-initiate"> (Optional) An <xref target="RFC5988"/> Link header specifying
	        the Oauth 1.0a <xref target="RFC5849"/> initiation endpoint.  The server MUST send this if
		"OAuth"  is included in the supported list of HTTP authentication schemes for the
		server. 
	    </t>
            <t hangText="oauth-authorize"> (Optional) An <xref target="RFC5988"/> Link header specifying
	        the Oauth 1.0a <xref target="RFC5849"/> authentication endpoint.  The server MUST send this if
		"OAuth"  is included in the supported list of HTTP authentication schemes for the
		server. 
	    </t>
            <t hangText="oauth-token"> (Optional) An <xref target="RFC5988"/> Link header specifying
	        the Oauth 1.0a <xref target="RFC5849"/> token endpoint.  The server MUST send this if
                "OAuth"  is included in the supported list of HTTP authentication schemes for the
		server.  This link type has one link-extension "grant-types" which is a space
		separated list of the the OAuth 2.0 grant types that can be used at the token
		endpoint to obtain a token.
	    </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Usage of the URLs provided in the discovery information is defined in the relevant 
          specifications. If the server supports multiple authenticators the discovery information
          returned for unknown users MUST be consistent with the discovery information for known
          users to prevent user enumeration. The OAuth 2.0 specification <xref
	  target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> supports multiple types of authentication schemes and the server
	  MUST specify at least one supported authentication scheme in the discovery information. The server
          MAY support multiple schemes and MAY support schemes not listed in the discovery
          information.</t>
	<t>If the resource server provides a scope the client SHOULD always request scoped
	tokens from the token endpoint.  The client MAY use a scope other than the one
	provided by the resource server.  Scopes other than those advertised by the
	resource server must be defined by the resource owner and provided in service
	documentation (which is beyond the scope of this memo).
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of Signature Type Authorization">
        <t>This mechanism  supports authorization using signatures, which requires that both client and
          server construct the string to be signed. OAuth 2 is designed for
          authentication/authorization to access specific URIs. SASL is designed for user authentication,
          and has no facility for being more specific. In this mechanism we require an HTTP style
          format specifically to support signature type authentication, but this is extremely
          limited. The HTTP style request is limited to a path of "/". This 
	  mechanism is in the SASL model, but is
          designed so that no changes are needed if there is a revision of SASL which supports more
          specific resource authorization, e.g. IMAP access to a specific folder or FTP access
          limited to a specific directory. </t>
        <t> Using the example in the MAC specification <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac"/>
        as a starting point, on an IMAP server running on port 143 and given
        the MAC style authorization request (with long lines wrapped for readability) below: 
<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET / HTTP/1.1 
Host: server.example.com 
User: user@example.com
Authorization: MAC token="h480djs93hd8",timestamp="137131200",
               nonce="dj83hs9s",signature="YTVjyNSujYs1WsDurFnvFi4JK6o="

]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>

        <t>The normalized request string would be constructed per the MAC specifcation <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac" />. In this example the normalized
            request string with the new line separator character is represented by
	    "\n" for display purposes only would be:<figure> 
            <artwork><![CDATA[
h480djs93hi8\n
137131200\n
dj83hs9s\n
\n
GET\n
server.example.com\n
143\n
/\n
\n
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      
           
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

<section anchor="GSSAPI-OAUTH" title="GSS-API OAuth Mechanism Specification"> 

<t>Note: The normative references in this section are informational for SASL
   implementors, but they are normative for GSS-API implementors.</t>

<t>The SASL OAuth mechanism is also a GSS-API mechanism and the messages 
   described in <xref target="SASL-OAUTH"/> are the same, but
   <list style="numbers"> 
   <t>the GS2 header on the client's
   first message is excluded when OAUTH is used as a GSS-API
   mechanism, and</t>
   <t>initial context token
   header is prefixed to the client's first authentication message
   (context token), as described in Section 3.1 of RFC 2743,
   </t>
   </list> 
   </t>

   <t>The GSS-API mechanism OID for OAuth is [[TBD: IANA]].</t>

   <t>OAuth security contexts always have the mutual_state flag
   (GSS_C_MUTUAL_FLAG) set to TRUE.  OAuth supports credential
   delegation, therefore security contexts may have the
   deleg_state flag (GSS_C_DELEG_FLAG) set to either TRUE or FALSE.
   </t>

   <t>The mutual authentication property of this mechanism relies on
   successfully comparing the TLS server identity with the negotiated
   target name.  Since the TLS channel is managed by the application
   outside of the GSS-API mechanism, the mechanism itself is unable to
   confirm the name while the application is able to perform this
   comparison for the mechanism.  For this reason, applications MUST
   match the TLS server identity with the target name, as discussed in
   <xref target="RFC6125"/>.</t>

   <t>The OAuth mechanism does not support per-message tokens or
   GSS_Pseudo_random.</t>

   <t>OAuth supports a standard generic name syntax for acceptors, such as
   GSS_C_NT_HOSTBASED_SERVICE (see <xref target="RFC2743"/>, Section 4.1).  
   These
   service names MUST be associated with the  "entityID" claimed by
   the RP.

   OAuth supports only a single name type for initiators:
   GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME.  GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME is the default name type.

   The query, display, and exported name syntaxes for OAuth principal
   names are all the same.  There is no OAuth-specific name syntax;
   applications SHOULD use generic GSS-API name types, such as
   GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME and GSS_C_NT_HOSTBASED_SERVICE (see <xref target="RFC2743"/>,

   Section 4).  The exported name token does, of course, conform to
   <xref target="RFC2743"/>, Section 3.2, but the "NAME" part of the token should be
   treated as a potential input string to the OAuth name normalization
   rules.
</t>

</section> 


    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->


    <section title="Examples">
      <t>These example illustrate exchanges between an IMAP client and an IMAP server.</t>

      <section title="Successful Bearer Token Exchange">

        <t>This example shows a successful OAuth 2.0 bearer token exchange with an initial client
          response. Note that line breaks are inserted for readability.</t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
S: * IMAP4rev1 Server Ready 
C: t0 CAPABILITY 
S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 AUTH=OAUTH
S: t0 OK Completed
C: t1 AUTHENTICATE OAUTH R0VUIC8gSFRUUC8xLjENCkhvc3Q6IGltYXAuZXhhbXBs
      ZS5jb20NCkF1dGhvcml6YXRpb246IEJFQVJFUiAidkY5ZGZ0NHFtVGMyTnZiM1J
      sY2tCaGJIUmhkbWx6ZEdFdVkyOXRDZz09Ig0KDQo=
S: +
S: t1 OK SASL authentication succeeded
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>As required by IMAP <xref target="RFC3501"/>, the payloads are base64-encoded. The
          decoded initial client response is: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET / HTTP/1.1 
Host: imap.example.com 
Authorization: BEARER "vF9dft4qmTc2Nvb3RlckBhbHRhdmlzdGEuY29tCg=="
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>The line containing just a "+" and a space is an empty response from the server. This response contains
          discovery information, and in the success case no discovery information is necessary so the
          response is empty. Like other messages, and in accordance with the IMAP SASL binding, the
          empty response is base64-encoded. </t>
      </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
      <section title="MAC Authentication with Channel Binding">
        <t>This example shows a channel binding failure.  The example sends the same
        request as above, but in the context of an OAUTH-PLUS exchange the channel binding
	information is missing. Note that line breaks are inserted for
        readability.</t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 AUTH=OAUTH SASL-IR IMAP4rev1 Server Ready 
S: t0 OK Completed 
C: t1 AUTHENTICATE MAC R0VUIC8/Y2JkYXRhPSJTRzkzSUdKcFp5QnBjeUJoSUZSTVV5Q
   m1hVzVoYkNCdFpYTnpZV2RsUHdvPSIgSFRUUC8xLjENCkhvc3Q6IHNlcnZlci5leGFtcG
   xlLmNvbQ0KVXNlcjogdXNlckBleGFtcGxlLmNvbQ0KQXV0aG9yaXphdGlvbjogTUFDIHR
   va2VuPSJoNDgwZGpzOTNoZDgiLHRpbWVzdGFtcD0iMTM3MTMxMjAwIixub25jZT0iZGo4
   M2hzOXMiLHNpZ25hdHVyZT0iV1c5MUlHMTFjM1FnWW1VZ1ltOXlaV1F1SUFvPSINCg0K
S: +
S: t1 OK SASL authentication succeeded
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>As required by IMAP <xref target="RFC3501"/>, the payloads are
      base64-encoded. The
          decoded initial client response is: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /?cbdata="SG93IGJpZyBpcyBhIFRMUyBmaW5hbCBtZXNzYWdlPwo=" HTTP/1.1
Host: server.example.com
User: user@example.com
Authorization: MAC token="h480djs93hd8",timestamp="137131200",
               nonce="dj83hs9s",signature="WW91IG11c3QgYmUgYm9yZWQuIAo="
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>The line conaining just a "+" and a space is an empty response from the server. This response contains
          discovery information, and in the success case no discovery information is necessary so the
          response is empty. Like other messages, and in accordance with the IMAP SASL binding, the
          empty response is base64-encoded.
        </t>
      </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

      <section title="Failed Exchange">
        <t>This example shows a failed exchange because of the empty Authorization header, which is
          how a client can query for discovery information. Note that line breaks are inserted for
          readability.</t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 AUTH=OAUTH SASL-IR IMAP4rev1 Server Ready 
S: t0 OK Completed 
C: t1 AUTHENTICATE OAUTH R0VUIC8gSFRUUC8xLjENClVzZXI6IHNjb290ZXJAYW
   x0YXZpc3RhLmNvbQ0KSG9zdDogaW1hcC55YWhvby5jb20NCkF1dGhlbnRpY2F0ZT
   ogDQoNCg==
S: + SFRUUC8xLjEgNDAxIFVuYXV0aG9yaXplZA0KV1dXLUF1dGhlbnRpY2F0ZTogQk
   VBUkVSIHJlYWxtPSJleGFtcGxlLmNvbSINCkxpbms6IDxodHRwczovL2xvZ2luLn
   lhaG9vLmNvbS9vYXV0aD4gcmVsPSJvYXV0aDItYXV0aGVudGljYXRvciIgIA0KTG
   luazogPGh0dHBzOi8vbG9naW4ueWFob28uY29tL29hdXRoPiByZWw9Im91YXRoMi
   10b2tlbiINCg0K
S: t1 NO SASL authentication failed
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t> The decoded initial client response is: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET / HTTP/1.1 
User: alice@example.com 
Host: imap.example.com 
Authorization: 
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t> The decoded server discovery response is: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 401 Unauthorized
WWW-Authenticate: BEARER realm="example.com"
Link: <https://login.example.com/oauth> rel="oauth2-authenticator"
Link: <https://login.example.com/oauth> rel="oauth2-token"
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->
      <section title="Failed Channel Binding">
        <t>This example shows a channel binding failure in a discovery request. 
        The channel binding information is empty.  Note that line breaks are inserted for
        readability.</t>
        <t>
          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 AUTH=OAUTH SASL-IR IMAP4rev1 Server Ready 
S: t0 OK Completed 
C: t1 AUTHENTICATE OAUTH R0VUIC8/Y2JkYXRhPSIiIEhUVFAvMS4xDQpVc2VyOi
   BhbGljZUBleGFtcGxlLmNvbQ0KSG9zdDogaW1hcC5leGFtcGxlLmNvbQ0KQXV0aG
   9yaXphdGlvbjoNCg0K
S: + SFRUUC8xLjEgNDEyIFByZWNvbmRpdGlvbiBGYWlsZWQNCg0KDQo=
S: t1 NO SASL authentication failed
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t> The decoded initial client response is: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
GET /?cbdata="" HTTP/1.1 
User: alice@example.com 
Host: imap.example.com 
Authorization: 
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t> The decoded server response is: <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 412 Precondition Failed
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->


    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This mechanism does not provide a security layer, but does provide a provision for
        channel binding. The OAuth 2 specification <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-oauth-v2"/> allows for a variety of usages, and the security properties
        of these profiles vary. The usage of bearer tokens, for example, provide security features
        similar to cookies. Applications using this mechanism SHOULD exercise the same level of care
        using this mechanism as they would in using the SASL PLAIN mechanism. In
        particular, TLS 1.2 or an equivalent secure channel MUST be implemented and its
        usage is RECOMMENDED. 
	</t>
      <t> Channel binding in this mechanism has different properties based on the authentication
        scheme used.  Channel binding to TLS with a
	bearer token provides only a binding to the TLS layer.  Authentication schemes like MAC 
	tokens have a signature over the channel binding information. These provide additional
        protection against a man in the middle attacks, and the MAC authorization header is bound to the
	channel and only valid in that context.  
	</t>
      <t> It is possible that SASL will be authenticating a connection and the life of that 
        connection may outlast the life of the token used to authenticate
        it. This is a common problem in application protocols where connections are long-lived, and
        not a problem with this mechanism per se.  Servers MAY unilaterally disconnect
        clients in accordance with the application protocol.
	</t>
      <t>An OAuth credential is not equivalent to the password or primary account
        credential. There are protocols like  XMPP that allow actions like change
        password.  The server SHOULD ensure that actions taken in the authenticated
        channel are appropriate to the strength of the presented credential.
        </t>
      <t> It is possible for an application server running on Evil.example.com to tell a client to
        request a token from Good.example.org. A client following these instructions will pass a
        token from Good to Evil. This is by design, since it is possible that Good and Evil are
        merely names, not descriptive, and that this is an innocuous activity between cooperating
        two servers in different domains. For instance, a site might operate their authentication
        service in-house, but outsource their mail systems to an external entity. </t>
        
          <t>Tokens have a lifetime associated with them. Reducing both the lifetime of a token provides security benefits in case that tokens leak. In addition a previously obtained
        token MAY be revoked or rendered invalid at any time. The client MAY request a new access token for each
        connection to a resource server, but it SHOULD cache and re-use access credentials that appear
        to be valid.</t>

    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
     <section title="SASL Registration">
      <t> The IANA is requested to register the following SASL profile: <list style="empty">
          <t>SASL mechanism profile: OAUTH</t>
          <t>Security Considerations: See this document</t>
          <t>Published Specification: See this document</t>
          <t>For further information: Contact the authors of this document.</t>
          <t>Owner/Change controller: the IETF</t>
          <t>Note: None</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> The IANA is requested to register the following SASL profile: <list style="empty">
          <t>SASL mechanism profile: OAUTH-PLUS</t>
          <t>Security Considerations: See this document</t>
          <t>Published Specification: See this document</t>
          <t>For further information: Contact the authors of this document.</t>
          <t>Owner/Change controller: the IETF</t>
          <t>Note: None</t>
        </list>
      </t>
     </section>
     <section title="GSS-API Registration">
        <t>IANA is further requested to assign an OID for this GSS mechanism
   in the SMI numbers registry, with the prefix of
   iso.org.dod.internet.security.mechanisms (1.3.6.1.5.5) and to
   reference this specification in the registry.</t>
    </section> 

     <section title="Link Type Registration">
      <t> Pursuant to <xref target="RFC5988"/> The following link type registrations 
      [[will be]] registered by mail to link-relations@ietf.org.
      </t>

      <section title="OAuth 2 Authentication Endpoint">
      <t>
      <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
	      Relation Name: oauth2-authenticator
          </t>
          <t>
	      Description: An OAuth 2.0 authentication endpoint. 
          </t>
          <t>
	      Reference:
          </t>
          <t>
	      Notes: This link type indicates an OAuth 2.0 authentication endpoint
	      that can be used for user authentication/authorization for the endpoint
	      providing the link.
          </t>
          <t>
	      Application Data: [optional]
          </t>
	</list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="OAuth 2 Token Endpoint">
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Relation Name: oauth2-token</t>
          <t>
	      Description: The OAuth token endpoint used to get tokens for access.
          </t>
          <t>
	      Reference:
          </t>
          <t>
	      Notes: The OAuth 2.0 token endpoint to be used for obtaining tokens
	      to access the endpoint providing the link.
          </t>
          <t>
	      Application Data: This link type has one link-extension "grant-types",
	      which is the OAuth 2.0 grant types that can be used at the token endpoint
	      to obtain a token.  This is not an exclusive list, it provides a hint
	      to the application of what SHOULD be valid.  A token endpoint MAY support
	      additional grant types not advertised by a resource endpoint.
          </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      </section>
      <section title="OAuth 1.0a Request Initiation Endpoint">
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Relation Name: oauth-initiate</t>
          <t>
	      Description: The OAuth 1.0a request initiation endpoint used to get tokens for access.
          </t>
          <t>Reference: </t>
          <t>
	      Notes: The OAuth 1.0a  endpoint used to initiate the sequence, this temporary
	      request is what the user approves to grant access to the resource.
          </t>
          <t>Application Data: </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      </section>
      <section title="OAuth 1.0a Authorization Endpoint">
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Relation Name: oauth-authorize</t>
          <t>
	      Description: The OAuth 1.0a authorization endpoint used to approve an access request.
          </t>
          <t>Reference: </t>
          <t>
	      Notes: 
          </t>
          <t>Application Data: </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      </section>
      <section title="OAuth 1.0a Token Endpoint">
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>Relation Name: oauth-token</t>
          <t>
	      Description: The OAuth 1.0a token endpoint used to get tokens for access.
          </t>
          <t>Reference: </t>
          <t>
	      Notes: 
          </t>
          <t>Application Data: </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      </section>
     </section>

    </section>



    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->


    <section  title='Appendix A -- Document History'>
      <t>
        [[ to be removed by RFC editor before publication as an RFC ]]
      </t>

      <t>
        -04
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
	  Editorial clean-up and text in introduction improved.
          </t>
	  <t>
Added GSS-API support	  
</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        -03
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
	  Fixing channel binding, not tls-unique specific.  Also defining how the CB data is
	  properly generated.
          </t>
	  <t>
	  Various small editorial changes and embarassing spelling fixes.
	  </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        -02
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
	  Filling out Channel Binding
          </t>
          <t>
	  Added text clarifying how to bind to the 2 kinds of SASL identities.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        -01
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
	      Bringing this into line with draft 12 of the core spec, the 
	      bearer token spec, and references the MAC token spec
          </t>
          <t>
	      Changing discovery over to using the Link header construct from RFC5988.
          </t>
          <t>
	      Added the seeds of channel binding.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        -00
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>
            Initial revision
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ******************************************************************** -->

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3174.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5056.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5849.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5929.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2743.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5801.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6125.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-v2.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-bearer.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-v2-http-mac.xml' ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3501.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hammer-hostmeta.xml' ?>
      <?rfc include='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.jones-simple-web-discovery.xml' ?>      
      
    </references>


  </back>
</rfc>
