<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4101 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4101.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5598 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5598.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4962 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4962.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4858 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4858.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2804 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2804.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4017 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4017.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4282 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2778 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2778.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3859 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3859.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3261 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3922 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3922.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5025 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5025.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4079 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4079.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4745 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4745.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2779 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2779.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3265 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3265.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3856 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3856.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3903 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3903.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-geopriv-arch PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-arch.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-geopriv-policy PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-policy.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-morris-privacy-considerations-00.txt">
  <front>
  <title abbrev="Privacy Considerations">Privacy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>   
    
   <author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="Bernard Aboba">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bernarda@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author initials="J." surname="Morris" fullname="John B. Morris, Jr.">
      <organization abbrev="CDT">Center for Democracy and Technology</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1634 I Street NW, Suite 1100</street>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <region>DC</region>
          <code>20006</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jmorris@cdt.org</email>
        <uri>http://www.cdt.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

        <author initials="J." surname="Peterson" fullname="Jon Peterson">
            <organization abbrev="NeuStar, Inc.">NeuStar, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1800 Sutter St Suite 570</street>
                    <city>Concord</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>94520</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>jon.peterson@neustar.biz</email>
            </address>
        </author>

		  
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2010"/>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>Privacy</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document aims to make protocol designers aware of the privacy-related design choices and offers guidance for writing privacy considerations in IETF documents. Similiar to other design aspects the IETF influence on the actual deployment is limited. We discuss these limitations but are convinced that protocol architects have indeed a role to play in a privacy friendly design by making more conscious decision, and by documenting those.  
</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

 <t>The IETF is known for its contributions to the design of the Internet and the specifications IETF participants produce belong to different categories, such as technical specification, best current practice descriptions, and architectural documentations. While these documents do not mandate a specific type of implementation they are often, if not always, impacted by different architectural design decisions. These decision decisions are influenced by technical aspects, expectations about deployment incentives of the involved entities, operational considerations,  security frameworks, etc. </t>
 
 <t>
This document aims to make protocol designers aware of the privacy-related design choices and offers guidance for writing privacy considerations in IETF documents. Similiar to other design aspects there is only a certain degree of influence a protocol designer working in a standards developing organization has on the final deployment outcome. We discuss these limitations in <xref target="scope"/>. Nevertheless, we believe that the IETF community overall has indeed a role to play in making  specifications more privacy friendly: Being aware of how design decisions impact privacy, by reflecting them in the protocol design, and by documenting the chosen design choices and potential challenges when deploying a single protocol or an entire suite of protcols.  
</t>

<t>
From the activities in the industry one can observe three schools of thought in the work on privacy, namely
<list style="hanging"> 

<t hangText="Privacy by Technology:">
This approach builds on the observation that considering privacy in the design of a protocol as a technical mechanism. One approach is to approach a specific application problem by sharing fewer data items with other parties (i.e. data minimization). Limiting data sharing also avoids the need for evaluation on how consent is obtained, to define policies around how to protect data, etc. The main idea therefore is that different architectural designs lead to different results with respect to privacy. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
Examples in the area of location privacy can be found in <xref target="EFF-Privacy"/>. These solution approaches often make heavy use of cryptographic techniques, such as threshold cryptography and secret sharing schemes. 
</t>
<t hangText="Privacy by Policy:">
With this approach it is assumed that privacy protection happens to a large degree a matter of getting the consent of the user in the form of privacy policies. Hence, protection of the customers privacy is therefore largely a responsibility of the company collecting, processing, and storing personal data. Notice and choice are offered to the customer and backed-up by an appropriate legal framework. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
An example in the area of location-based services is a recent publication by CTIA <xref target="CTIA"/>. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
</t>
<t hangText="Policy/Technology Hybrid:">
This approach presents a middle-ground where some privacy enhancing features can be provided by technology, and made transparent to those who implement (via explicit recommendations for implementation, configuration and deployment best current practices or implicitly by raising awareness via a discussion about privacy in technical specifications) but other aspects can only be provided and enforced by the parties who decide about the deployment. For deployments often a certain expectation about the existence of an appropriate legal framework is required. 
</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>
The authors believe that the policy/technology hybrid approach is the most practical one and therefore suggest it to be the leading paradigm in privacy investigations within the IETF.</t>

<t>
This document is structured as follows: First, we provide a brief introduction to the privacy history in <xref target="background"/>. In <xref target="scope"/> we illustrate what is in scope of the IETF work and where the responsibility of the IETF ends. In <xref target="threatmodel"/> we discuss the main threat model for privacy investigations. In <xref target="guidelines"/> we propose guidelines for investing privacy within IETF specifications and in Section VII we discuss privacy characteristics of a few IETF protocols and explain what privacy features have been provided until now. 
</t>

</section> 

      <!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="background" title="Historical Background"> 

<t>The "right to be let alone" is a phrase coined by Warren and Brandeis in their seminal Harvard Law Review article on privacy <xref target="Warren"/>. They were the first scholars to recognize that a right to privacy had evolved in the 19th century to embrace not only physical privacy but also a potential "injury of the feelings", which could, for example, result from the public disclosure of embarrassing private facts.</t>

<t>In 1967 Westin <xref target="Westin"/> described privacy as a "personal adjustment process" in which individuals balance "the desire for privacy with the desire for disclosure
and communication" in the context of social norms and their environment. Privacy thus requires that an individual has a means to exercise selective control of access to the self and is aware of the potential consequences of exercising that control <xref target="Altman"/>.</t>


<t>Efforts to define and analyze the privacy concept evolved considerably in the 20th century. In 1975, Altman conceptualized privacy as a "boundary regulation process whereby people optimize their accessibility along a spectrum of 'openness' and 'closedness' depending on context" <xref target="Altman"/>. "Privacy is the claim of individuals, groups, or institutions to determine for themselves when, how, and to what extent information about them is communicated to others. Viewed in terms of the relation of the individual to social participation, privacy is the voluntary and temporary withdrawal of a person from the general society through physical or psychological means, either in a state of solitude or small-group intimacy or, when among larger groups, in a condition of anonymity or reserve." <xref target="Westin"/>.
</t>

<t>
Note: Altman and Westin were referring to nonelectronic environments, where privacy intrusion was typically based on fresh information, referring to one particular person only, and stemming from traceable human sources. The scope of possible privacy breaches was therefore rather limited. Today, in contrast, details about an individual's activities are typically stored over a longer period of time, collected from many different sources, and information about almost every activity in life is available electronically. 
</t>

<t>
In 1980, the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) published eight Guidelines on the Protection of Privacy and Trans-Border Flows of Personal
Data <xref target="OECD"/>, which are often referred to as Fair Information Practices (FIPs). Fair information practices include the following principles: 
   <list style="hanging">
   <t hangText="Notice and Consent:"> Before the collection of data, the data 
   subject should be provided: notice of what information is being 
   collected and for what purpose and an opportunity to choose whether 
   to accept the data collection and use. In Europe, data collection 
   cannot proceed unless data subject has unambiguously given his 
   consent (with exceptions). <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   <t hangText="Collection Limitation:">Data should be collected for specified, 
   explicit and legitimate purposes. The data collected should be 
   adequate, relevant and not excessive in relation to the purposes for 
   which they are collected. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   <t  hangText="Use/Disclosure Limitation:"> Data should be used only for the 
   purpose for which it was collected and should not be used or 
   disclosed in any way incompatible with those purposes. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   <t hangText="Retention Limitation:">Data should be kept in a form that 
   permits identification of the data subject no longer than is 
   necessary for the purposes for which the data were collected. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   <t hangText="Accuracy:">The party collecting and storing data is obligated to 
   ensure its accuracy and, where necessary, keep it up to date; every 
   reasonable step must be taken to ensure that data which are 
   inaccurate or incomplete are corrected or deleted. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   <t hangText="Access:">A data subject should have access to data about 
   himself, in order to verify its accuracy and to determine how it is 
   being used. <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   </t>
   <t hangText="Security:">Those holding data about others must take steps to 
   protect its confidentiality. 
   </t>
   </list> 
   </t>
<t>The OECD guidelines and also recent onces, like the Madrid resolution <xref target="Madrid"/> or the Granada Charter of Privacy in a Digital World <xref target="Granada"/>, provide a useful understanding of how to provide privacy protection but these guidelines quite naturally stay on a higher level. As such, they do not aim to evaluate the tradeoffs in addressing privacy protection in the different stages of the development process, as illustrated in <xref target="fig-arch"/>.</t>
<t>
US regulatory and self-regulatory efforts supported by the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) have focused on a subset of these principles, namely to notice, choice, access, and security rather than minimizing data collection or use limitation. Hence, they are sometimes labeled as the "notice and choice" approach to privacy. From a practical point of view it became evident that companies are reluctant to stop collecting and using data but individuals expect to remain in control about its usage. Today, the effectiveness to deal with privacy violations using the "notice and choice" approach is heavily criticized <xref target="limits"/>.
</t>
<t>
Among these considers (although often implicit) are assumptions on how information is exchanged between different parties and for certain protocols this information may help to identify entities, and potentially humans behind them.  Without doubt the information exchanged is not always equal. The terms 'personal data' <xref target="DPD95"/> and Personally Identifiable Information (PII) <xref target="SP800-122"/> have become common language in the vocabulary of privacy experts. It seems therefore understandable that regulators around the globe have focused on the type of data being exchanged and have provided laws according to the level of sensitivity. Medical data is treated differently in many juristictions than blog comments. For an initial investigation it is intuitive and helpful to determine whether specific protocol or application may be privacy sensitive. The ever increasing ability for parties on the Internet to collect, aggregate, and to reason about information collected from a wide range of sources requires to apply further thinking about potential other privacy sensitive items. The recent example of browser fingerprinting <xref target="browser-fingerprinting"/> shows how many information items combined can lead to a privacy threat. 
</t>
<t>
The following list contains examples of information that may be considered personal data: 
<list style="symbols"> 
<t>Name</t>
<t>Address information</t>
<t>Phone numbers, email addresses, SIP/XMPP URIs, other identifiers</t>
<t>IP and MAC addresses or other
host-specific persistent identifiers that consistently links to a particular person or small, well-defined
group of people</t>
<t>Information identifying personally owned property, such as vehicle registration number</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>
Data minimization means that first of all, the possibility to collect personal data about others should be minimized. Next, within the remaining possibilities, collecting personal data should be minimized. Finally, the time how long collected personal data is stored should be minimized.
</t>
<t>As stated in <xref target="I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology"/>, "If we exclude providing misinformation (inaccurate or erroneous information, provided usually without conscious effort at misleading, deceiving, or persuading one way or another) or disinformation (deliberately false or distorted information given out in order to mislead or deceive), data minimization is the only generic strategy to enable anonymity, since all correct personal data help to identify.".
</t>
<t>Early papers from the 1980ies about privacy by data minimization already deal with anonymity, unlinkability, unobservability, and pseudonymity. <xref target="I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology"/> provides a compilation of terms.</t>


</section> 

      <!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="scope" title="Scope"> 

<t>
The IETF at large produces specifications that typically fall into the following categories: 
<list style="symbols"> 
<t>Process specifications (e.g. WG shepherding guidelines described in RFC 4858 <xref target="RFC4858"/>)
  These documents aim to document and to improve the work style within the IETF. 
</t>
<t>Building blocks (e.g. cryptographic algorithms, MIME types registrations). These specifications are meant to be used with other protocols one or several communication paradigms.
</t>
<t>Architectural descriptions (for example, on IP-based emergency services <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework"/>, Internet Mail <xref target="RFC5598"/>)
</t>
<t>Best current practices (e.g. Guidance for Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting (AAA) Key Management <xref target="RFC4962"/>)</t>

<t>Policy statements (e.g. IETF Policy on Wiretapping <xref target="RFC2804"/>)</t>
</list> 
</t>

<t>
Often, the architectural description is compiled some time after the deployment has long been ongoing and therefore those who implement and those who deploy have to make their own determination of which protocols they would like to glue together to a complete system. This type of work style has the advantage that protocol designers are encouraged to write their specifications in a flexible way so that they can be used in multiple contexts with different deployment scenarios without a huge amount of interdependency between the components. <xref target="Tussle"/> highlights the importance of such an approach and <xref target="I-D.morris-policy-cons"/> offers a more detailed discussion.
</t> 
<t>
This work style has an important consequence for the scope of privacy work in the IETF, namely
<list style="symbols">
<t>the standardization work focuses on those parts where interoperability is really essentially rather than describing a specific instantiation of an architecture and therefore leaving a lot of choices for deployments. </t>
<t>application internal functionality, such as API, and details about databases are outside the scope of the IETF</t>
<t>regulatory requirements of different juristictions are not part of the IETF work either. </t> 
</list> 
</t>

<t>
Here is an example that aims to illustrate the boundaries of the IETF work: Imagine a social networking site that allows user registration, requires user authentication prior to usage, and offers its functionality for Web browser users via HTTP, real-time messaging functionality via XMPP, and email notifications. Additionally, support for data sharing with other Internet service providers is provided by OAuth. </t>

<t>
While HTTP, XMPP, Email, and OAuth are IETF specifications they only define how the protocol behavior on the wire looks like. They certainly have an architectural spirit that has enormous impact on the protocol mechanisms and the set of specifications that are required. However, IETF specifications would not go into details of how the user has to register, what type of data he has to provide to this social networking site, how long transaction data is kept, how requirements for lawful intercept are met, how authorization policies are designed to let users know more about data they share with other Internet services, how the user's data is secured against authorized access, whether the HTTP communication exchange between the browser and the social networking site is using TLS or not, what data is uploaded by the user, how the privacy policy of the social networking site should look like, etc. 
</t>

<t>
Another example is the usage of HTTP for the Web. HTTP is published in RFC 2616 and was designed to allow the exchange of arbitrary data. An analysis of potential privacy problems would consider what type of data is exchanged, how this data is stored and processed. Hence, the analysis for a static webpage by a company would different than the usage of HTTP for exchanging health records. A protocol designer working on HTTP extensions (such as WebDAV) it would therefore be difficult to describe all possible privacy considersations given that the space of possible usage is essentially unlimited.
</t>

<t>
      <figure anchor="fig-arch" title="Development Process">
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
+--------+
|Building|-------+
|Blocks  |       |
+--------+       |
          +------v-----+
          |            |----+
          |Architecture|    |
          +------------+    |
                        +---v--+
                        |System|--------+
                        |Design|        |
                        +------+        |
                                +-------v------+
                                |              |------+
                                |Implementation|      |
                                +--------------+      |
                                                +-----v----+
                                                |          |
                                                |Deployment|
                                                +----------+
]]></artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t><xref target="fig-arch"/> shows a typical development process. IETF work often starts with identifying building blocks that ccan then be used in different architectural variants useful for a wide range of usage scenarios. Before implementation activities start a software architecture needs to evaluable which components to integrate, how to provide proper performance characteristics, etc. Finally, the implemented work needs to be deployed. Privacy considerations play a role along the entire process. <list style="empty"> 
<t>To pick an example from the security field consider the NIST Framework for Designing Cryptographic Key Management Systems <xref target="SP800-130"/>, NIST SP 800-130. SP 800-130 provides a number of recommendations that can be addressed largely during the system design phase as well as in the implementation phase of product development. The cryptographic building blocks and the underlying architecture is assumed to be sound. Even with well-design cryptographic components there are plenty of possibilities to introduce security vulnerabilities in the later stage of the development cycle.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Similiar to the work on security the impact of work in standards developing organizations is limited. Neverthelesss, discussing potential privacy problems and considering privacy in the design of an IETF protocol can offer system architects and those deploying systems additional insights. The rest of this document is focused on illustrating how protocol designers can consider privacy in their design decisions, as they do factors like security, congestion control, scalability, operations and management, etc.
</t>
</section> 

      <!-- ====================================================================== -->


<section anchor="threatmodel" title="Threat Model"> 

<t>
To consider privacy in protocol design it useful to think about the overall communication architecture and what the different actors could do. This analysis is similar to a threat analysis found in security consideration sections of IETF documents. See also RFC 4101 <xref target="RFC4101"/> for an illustration on how to write protocol models. In <xref target="arch"/> we show a communication model found in many of today's protocols where a sender wants to establish communication with some recipient and thereby uses some form of intermediary (referred as relay in <xref target="arch"/>. In some cases this intermediary stays in the communication path for the entire duration of the communication and sometimes it is only used for communication establishment, for either inbound or outbound communication. In rare cases they may even be a series of relays that are traversed. 
</t>

<t>
      <figure anchor="arch" title="Example Instantiation of involved Entities">
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
                                   +-----------+
                                   |           |
                                  >| Recipient |
                                 / |           |
                               ,'  +-----------+
+--------+        )-------(  ,'    +-----------+
|        |        |       | -      |           |
| Sender |<------>|Relay  |<------>| Recipient |
|        |        |       |`.      |           |
+--------+        )-------(  \     +-----------+
    ˆ                         `.   +-----------+
    :                           \  |           |
    :                            `>| Recipient |
    ..............................>|           |
                                   +-----------+	 
                                   
Legend:

<....> End-to-End Communication
<----> Hop-by-Hop Communication
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
We can distinguish between three types of adversaries:
<list style="hanging"> 

<t hangText="Eavesdropper:">

RFC 4949 describes the act of 'eavesdropping' as <list style="empty">
<t>"Passive wiretapping done secretly, i.e., without the knowledge of the originator or the intended recipients of the communication."
</t>
</list> 
Eavesdropping is often considered by IETF protocols in the context of a security analysis to deal with a range of attacks by offering confidentiality protection. 
<vspace blankLines="1"/> 
RFC 3552 provides guidance on how to write security considerations
      for IETF documents and already demands the confidentiality
      security services to be considered.  While IETF protocols offer
      guidance on how to secure communication against eavesdroppers
      deployments sometimes choose not to enable its usage.
</t> 
<t hangText="Middleman:">
Many protocols developed today show a more complex communication pattern than just client and server communication, as motivated in <xref target="arch"/>. Store-and-forward protocols are examples where entities participate in the message delivery even though they are not the final recipients. Often, these intermediaries only need to see a small amount of information necessary for message routing and security and/or protocol mechanisms should ensure that end-to-end information is made inaccessible for these entities. Unfortunately, the difficulty to deploy end-to-end security proceduces, the additional messaging, the computational overhead, and other business / legal requirements often slow down or prevent the deployment of these end-to-end security mechanisms giving these intermediaries more exposure to communication patters and communication payloads than necessary. 
</t> 
<t hangText="Recipient:">
It may seem strange to put the recipient as an adversary in this list since the entire purpose of the communication interaction is to provide information to it. However, the degree of familiarity and the type of information that needs to be shared with such an entity may vary from context to context and also between application scenarios. Often enough, the sender has no strong familiarity with the other communication endpoint. While it seems to be advisable to utilize access control before disclosing  information with such an entity reality in Internet communication is not so simple. As such, a sender may still want to limit the amount of information disclosed to the recipient some mutual understanding of how this data is treated my need to be created, e.g. how long it is kept (retention), whether re-distribution is permitted.
</t> 
</list> 
</t>
</section> 

      <!-- ====================================================================== -->



<section anchor="guidelines" title="Guidelines"> 
<t>A pre-condition for reasoning about the impact of a protocol or an architecture is to look at the high level protocol model, as described in <xref target="RFC4101"/>. This step helps to identify actors and their relationship. The protocol specification (or the set of specifications then allows a deep dive into the data that is exchanged.</t>
<t>The answers to these questions provide insight into the potential privacy impact: 
<list style="numbers"> 
  <t>What entities collect and use data?
     <list style="hanging"> 
       <t hangText="1.a:">How many entities collect and use data? 
       <list style="empty">
       <t>Note that this question aims to raise the question of what is possible for various entities to inspect (or potentially modify). In architectures with intermediaries, the question can be stated as “What data is exposed to intermediaries that they do not need to know to do their job?”. </t>
       </list>
       </t>
       <t hangText="1.b:">For each entity, what type of entity is it?
          <list style="symbols"> 
            <t>The first-party site or application</t>
            <t>Other sites or applications whose data collection and use is in some way controlled by the first party</t> 
            <t>Third parties that may use the data they collect for other purposes</t>
          </list> 
       </t>
     </list> 
  </t>
  <t>For each entity, think about the relationship between the entity and the user.
     <list style="hanging"> 
       <t hangText="2.a:">What is the user’s familiarity or degree of relationship with the entity in other contexts?</t>
       <t hangText="2.b:">What is the user’s reasonable expectation of the entity’s involvement?</t>
     </list> 
  </t>	 
  <t>What data about the user is likely needed to be collected?</t>
  <t>What is the identification level of the data? (identified, pseudonymous, anonymous, see <xref target="I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology"/>)</t>
</list> 
</t>
<!-- <t>In <xref target="example"/> we will provide examples to illustrate how these guidelines are applied to IETF protocols.</t> --> 
</section> 

      <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="example" title="Example">
	<t>This section allows us to illustrate how privacy was deal within certain IETF protocols. We will start the description with AAA for network access and expand it to other protocols in a future version of this draft.</t>
	
	<section title="Presence">
<t>A presence service, as defined in the abstract in RFC 2778 <xref target="RFC2778"/>, allows users of a communications service to monitor one another’s availability and disposition in order to make de- cisions about communicating. Presence information is highly dynamic, and generally characterizes whether a user is online or offline, busy or idle, away from communications devices or nearby, and the like. Necessarily, this information has certain privacy implications, and from the start the IETF approached this work with the aim to provide users with the controls to determine how their presence information would be shared.The Common Profile for Presence (CPP) <xref target="RFC3859"/> defines a set of logical operations for delivery of presence information. This abstract model is applicable to multiple presence systems. The SIP-based SIMPLE presence system <xref target="RFC3261"/> uses CPP as its baseline architecture, and the presence operations in the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) have also been mapped to CPP <xref target="RFC3922"/>.
</t>

<t>SIMPLE <xref target="RFC3261"/>, the application of the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) to instant messaging and presence, has native support for subscriptions and notifications (with its event framework <xref target="RFC3265"/>) and has added an event package <xref target="RFC3856"/> for pres- ence in order to satisfy the requirements of CPP. Other event packages were defined later to allow additional information to be exchanged. With the help of the PUBLISH method <xref target="RFC3903"/>. clients are able to install presence information on a server, so that the server can apply access-control policies before sharing presence information with other entities.The integration of an explicit authorization mechanism into the presence architecture has been a major improvement in terms of involving the end users in the decision making pro- cess before sharing information. Nearly all presence systems deployed today provide such a mechanism, typically through a reciprocal authorization system by which a pair of users, when they agree to be ”buddies,” consent to divulge their presence information to one another.
</t>
<t>
One important extension for presence was to enable the support for location sharing. With the desire to standardize protocols for systems sharing geolocation IETF work was started in the GEOPRIV working group. During the initial requirements and privacy threat analysis in the process of chartering the working group, it became clear that the system would an underlying communication mechanism supporting user consent to share location information. The resemblance of these requirements to the presence framework was quickly recognized, and this design decision was documented in RFC 4079 <xref target="RFC4079"/>.
</t>
<t>While presence systems exerted influence on location pri- vacy, the location privacy work also influenced ongoing IETF work on presence by triggering the standardization of a general access control policy language called the Common Policy (defined in RFC 4745 <xref target="RFC4745"/>) framework. This language allows one to express ways to control the distribution of information as simple conditions, actions, and transformations rules expressed in an XML format. Common Policy itself is anabstract format which needs to be instantiated: two examples can be found with the Presence Authorization Rules <xref target="RFC5025"/> and the Geolocation Policy <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-policy"/>. The former provides additional expressiveness for presence based systems, while the latter defines syntax and semantic for location based conditions and transformations.
</t>
<t>As a component of the prior work on the presence architecture, a format for presence information, called Presence Information Data Format (PIDF), had been developed. For the purposes of conveying location information an extension was developed, the PIDF Location Object (PIDF-LO). With the aim to meet the privacy requirements defined in RFC 2779 <xref target="RFC2779"/> a set of usage indications (such as whether retransmission is allowed or when the retention period expires) in the form of the following policies have been added that always travel with location information itself.We believe that the standardization of these meta-rules that travel with location information has been a unique contribution to privacy on the Internet, recognizing the need for users to express their preferences when information travels through the Internet, from website to website. This approach very much follows the spirit of Creative Commons <xref target="CC"/>, namely the usage of a limited number of conditions (such as ’Share Alike’ <xref target="CC-SA"/>). Unlike Creative Commons, the GEOPRIV working group did not, however, initiate work to produce legal language nor to de- sign graphical icons since this would fall outside the scope of the IETF. In particular, the GEOPRIV rules state a preference on the retention and retransmission of location information; while GEOPRIV cannot force any entity receiving a PIDF-LO object to abide by those preferences, if users lack the ability to express them at all, we can guarantee their preferences will not be honored.
</t>
<t>While these retention and retransmission meta-data elements could have been devised to accompany information elements in other IETF protocols, the decision was made to introduce these elements for geolocation initially because of the sensitivity of location information.
</t>
<t>
The GEOPRIV working group had decided to clarify the architecture to make it more accessible to those outside the IETF, and also provides a more generic description applicable beyond the context of presence. <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-arch"/> shows the work-in-progress writeup.
</t>
</section>

<section title="AAA for Network Access"> 

<t>On a high-level, AAA for network access uses the communication model shown in <xref target="network-access"/>. When an end host requests access to the network it has to interact with a Network Access Server (NAS) using some front-end protocol (often at the link layer, such as IEEE 802.1X). When asked by the NAS, the end host presents a Network Access Identifier (NAI), an email alike identifier that consists of a username and a domain part. This NAI is then used to discover the AAA server authorized for the users' domain and an initial access request is forwarded to it. To deal with various security, accounting and fraud prevention aspects an end-to-end authentication procedure, run between the end host (the peer) and a separate component within the AAA server (the server) is executed using the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP). After a successful authentication protocol	exchange the user may get authorized to access the network and keying material is provided to the NAS to enable link layer security over the air interface.</t>

<t>From a privacy point of view, the entities participating in this eco-system are the user, an end host, the NAS, a range of different intermediaries, and the AAA server. The user will most likely have some form of contractual relationship with the entity operating the AAA server since credential provisioning had to happen someone but, in certain deployments like coffee shops, this is not guaranteed. In many deployment during this initial registration process the subscriber is provided with credentials after showing some form of identification information (e.g. a passport) and consequently the NAI together with credentials can be used to linked to a specific subscriber, often a single person. 
</t>

<t>The username part of the NAI is data provided by the end host provides during network access authentication that intermediaries do not need to fulfill their role in AAA message routing. Hiding the user's identity is, as discussed in RFC 4282 <xref target="RFC4282"/>, possible only when NAIs are used together with a separate authentication method that can transfer the username in a secure manner. Such EAP methods have been designed and requirements for offering such functionality have have become recommended design criteria, see <xref target="RFC4017"/>.
</t>

<t>More than just identity information is exchanged during the network access authentication is exchanged. The NAS provides information about the user's point of attachment towards the AAA server and the AAA server in response provides data related to the authorization decision back. While the need to exchange data is motivated by the service usage itself there are still a number of questions that could be asked, such as 
<list style="symbols"> 
<t>What mechanisms can be utilized to offer users ways to authorize sharing of information (considering that the ability for protocol interaction is limited without sucessful network access connectivity)?</t>
<t>What are the best current practices for a privacy-sensitive operation of intermediaries? Since end hosts are not interacting with intermediaries explicitly and users have no relationship with those who operate them it is quite likely their practices are less widely known.</t>
<t>Are there alternative approaches to trust establishment between the NAS and the AAA server so that the involvement of intermediaries can be limited or avoided? 
</t>
</list> 
</t>	
	     <t>
        <figure title="Network Access Authentication Architecture" anchor="network-access">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                +--------------+
                                |  AAA Server  |
                                +-^----------^-+
                                  * EAP      | RADIUS/
                                  *          | Diameter
                                --v----------v--
                             ///                \\\
                           //     AAA Proxies,     \\   ***
                          |       Relays, and        |  back-
                          |       Redirect Agents    |  end
                           \\                      //   ***
                             \\\                ///
                                --^----------^--
                                  * EAP      | RADIUS/
                                  *          | Diameter
  +----------+  Data            +-v----------v-- +
  |          |<---------------->|                |
  | End Host |  EAP/EAP Method  | Network Access |
  |          |<****************>| Server         |
  +----------+                  +--------------- +
              *** front-end ***
Legend: 

 <****>: End-to-end exchange
 <---->: Hop-by-hop exchange
                                             ]]></artwork>
        </figure> 
      </t>

    </section>

<section title="SIP for Internet Telephony">
<t>[Editor's Note: Jon/Bernard to add a little bit of text here.]</t>
</section> 

</section> 

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="SecurityConsiderations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
This document describes aspects a protocol designer would considered in the area of privacy in addition to the regular security analysis.</t>
</section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>
This document does not require actions by IANA. </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
	
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Add your name here. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  <back>
  

    <references title="Normative References"> 
	     
      
       <reference anchor="OECD">
        <front>
          <title>OECD Guidelines on the Protection of Privacy and Transborder Flows of Personal Data</title>
          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1980"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="available at (September 2010)"
          value=", http://www.oecd.org/EN/document/0,,EN-document-0-nodirectorate-no-24-10255-0,00.html"/>
        <format target="http://www.oecd.org/EN/document/0,,EN-document-0-nodirectorate-no-24-10255-0,00.html" type="HTML"/>
      </reference>
	  
	  &I-D.hansen-privacy-terminology; 
	  
	</references>
    
	<references title="Informative References"> 
	
	  <reference anchor="browser-fingerprinting">
        <front>
          <title>How Unique Is Your Browser?</title>
          <author fullname="Peter Eckersley" initials="P." surname="Eckersley">
            <organization>EFF</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Springer Lecture Notes in Computer Science" value=", Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS 2010)"/>
        <format type="PDF"
          target="https://panopticlick.eff.org/browser-uniqueness.pdf"/>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor="CTIA">
        <front>
          <title>Best Practices and Guidelines for Location-Based Services</title>
          <author>
            <organization>CTIA</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2010"/>
        </front>
       <seriesInfo name="" value=""/>

        <format type="PDF"
          target="http://files.ctia.org/pdf/CTIA_LBS_Best_Practices_Adopted_03_10.pdf"/>
      </reference>
	  
	  <reference anchor="DPD95">
        <front>
          <title>Directive 95/46/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 October 1995
            on the protection of individuals with regard to the processing of personal data and on
            the free movement of such data</title>
          <author>
            <organization>European Commission</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Official Journal L 281" value=", 23/11/1995 P. 0031 - 0050"/>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:31995L0046:EN:HTML"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="limits">
        <front>
          <title>The Limits of Notice and Choice</title>
           <author fullname="Fred H. Cate" initials="F." surname="Cate">
            <organization>Indiana University School of Law</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Computer Society" value=", IEEE Security and Privacy, pg. 59-62"/>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/MSP.2010.84"/>
      </reference>	  
	  
      <reference anchor="EFF-Privacy">
        <front>
          <title>On Locational Privacy, and How to Avoid Losing it Forever</title>
           <author fullname="Andrew J. Blumberg" initials="A." surname="Blumberg">
            <organization>EFF</organization>
          </author>
           <author fullname="Peter Eckersley" initials="P." surname="Eckersley">
            <organization>EFF</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML"
          target="http://www.eff.org/wp/locational-privacy"/>
      </reference>	  
	 
	   <reference anchor="Granada">
        <front>
          <title>The Granada Charter of Privacy in a Digital World, Granada (Spain)</title>
           <author>
            <organization>International Working Group on Data Protection in Telecommunications</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <format type="PDF"
          target="http://www.datenschutz-berlin.de/attachments/696/Granada_Charter.pdf?1278642745"/>
      </reference>	  
      
       <reference anchor="Madrid">
        <front>
          <title>The Madrid Resolution, International Standards on the Protection of Personal Data and Privacy</title>
           <author>
            <organization>Data Protection Authorities and Privacy Regulators</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Conference of Data Protection and Privacy Commissioners" value=", 31st International Meeting"/>
        <format type="PDF"
          target="http://www.gov.im/lib/docs/odps//madridresolutionnov09.pdf"/>
      </reference>	  
      
      <reference anchor="Altman">
        <front>
          <title>The Environment and Social Behavior: Privacy, Personal Space, Territory, Crowding</title>
          <author fullname="I. Altman" initials="I." surname="Altman"> </author>
          <date year="1975"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Brooks/Cole" value=""/>
      </reference>
	 
      <reference anchor="Westin">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy and Freedom</title>
          <author fullname="Alan F. Westin" initials="A." surname="Westin"> </author>
          <date year="1967"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Atheneum, New York" value=""/>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor='I-D.morris-policy-cons'>
<front>
<title>Public Policy Considerations for Internet Protocols</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Morris' fullname='John Morris'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='B' surname='Aboba' fullname='Bernard Aboba'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Peterson' fullname='Jon Peterson'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='H' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='Hannes Tschofenig'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='October' year='2010' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-morris-policy-cons-00' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-morris-policy-cons-00.txt' />
</reference>


      <reference anchor="Warren">
        <front>
          <title>The Right to Privacy</title>
          <author fullname="D. Warren" initials="D." surname="Warren"> </author>
		  <author fullname="L. Brandeis" initials="L." surname="Brandeis"> </author>
          <date year="1890"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Harvard Law Rev." value=", vol. 45"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CC">
        <front>
          <title>Creative Commons</title>
          <author> 
            <organization></organization> 
          </author>
          <date month="June"year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
        target='http://creativecommons.org' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CC-SA">
        <front>
          <title>Creative Commons - Licenses</title>
          <author> 
            <organization></organization> 
          </author>
          <date month="June"year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <format type='HTML'
        target='http://creativecommons.org/about/licenses.' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SP800-122">
        <front>
          <title>Guide to Protecting the Confidentiality of Personally Identifiable Information (PII)</title>
		  <author fullname="Erika McCallister" initials="E." surname="McCallister">
            <organization>NIST</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Tim Grance" initials="T." surname="Grance">
            <organization>NIST</organization>
          </author>
	      <author fullname="Karen Scarfone" initials="K." surname="Scarfone">
            <organization>NIST</organization>
          </author>	
		  <date month="April" year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="NIST Special Publication (SP)" value=", 800-122"/>
      </reference>
	  
	         <reference anchor="Tussle">
        <front>
          <title>Tussle in Cyberspace: Defining Tomorrow's Internet</title>
          <author fullname="David Clark" initials="D." surname="Clark">
          </author>
                    <author fullname="John Wroslawski" initials="J." surname="Wroslawski">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Karen Sollins" initials="K." surname="Sollins">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Robert Braden" initials="R." surname="Braden">
          </author>

          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="In Proc. ACM SIGCOMM"
          value=", http://www.acm.org/sigcomm/sigcomm2002/papers/tussle.html"/>
        <format target="http://www.acm.org/sigcomm/sigcomm2002/papers/tussle.html" type="HTML"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="SP800-130">
        <front>
          <title>DRAFT: A Framework for Designing Cryptographic Key Management Systems</title>
          <author fullname="Elaine Barker" initials="E." surname="Barker">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Dennis Branstad" initials="D." surname="Branstad">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Santosh Chokhani" initials="S." surname="Chokhani">
          </author>
          <author fullname="Miles Smid" initials="M." surname="Smid">
          </author>
          <date month="June"year="2010"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo
          name="NIST Special Publication (SP)"
          value=", 800-130"/>
        <format target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/PubsDrafts.html#SP-800-130" type="HTML"/>
      </reference>

&RFC2778;
&RFC2779;
&RFC2804;
&RFC3261;
&RFC3265;
&RFC3856;
&RFC3859;
&RFC3903;
&RFC3922;
&RFC4017;
&RFC4079;
&RFC4101;
&RFC4282;
&RFC4745;
&RFC4858;
&RFC4962; 
&RFC5025;
&RFC5598;	
&I-D.ietf-ecrit-framework;   
&I-D.ietf-geopriv-arch;
&I-D.ietf-geopriv-policy;
	</references>
  </back>
</rfc>
